-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
pro hockey sticks.
bronzed baby shoes.
treadmills.
and handheld computers.
today's cutting-edge hockey sticks
are made primarily of graphite,
a strong yet lightweight material woven from carbon.
professional hockey players
have their graphite sticks custom-made.
each player has the curve and angle of the blade tailored
to precise specifications
that he believes enhance his performance on the ice.
to construct the stick's hollow shaft,
workers layer 15 sheets of graphite,
each in a different direction to
make the shaft uniformly rigid.
heat-activated resin molds the layers together.
this machine, called a flex tester,
measures how much force it takes
to bend the shaft one inch.
if the force is within a certain range,
the shaft has the correct degree
of stiffness for that model.
the blade starts with the plastic core.
in the center,
there's a piece of hard foam wrapped in graphite.
it absorbs the impact of the puck.
later, they'll mold the core to the shaft,
but for now, they glue and clamp them together.
when the glue dries,
they cover the core in a graphite sock.
the sock fibers run diagonally.
the fibers of subsequent layers
run in other directions,
building a combination of crisscross fibers
that creates uniform stiffness throughout the blade.
now the core goes into a glue applicator.
this heat-activated plastic resin permeates the graphite.
once it cures, it will fortify the material.
on the next two layers of graphite are strips.
on one, the fibers run vertically.
on the other, they run diagonally.
they're stiffer because they've
already had a resin application.
they run through the glue applicator
and go onto the core.
this is how the factory builds its graphite blades,
whether mass producing amateur sticks
or making a few special-order sticks for a pro player.
at this point,
retail sticks head into large-scale
automated production.
workers continue making pro sticks by hand.
initially, they produce a customized wooden mold
for each player's stick
and give it an identification number to prevent mix-ups.
they install this two-piece mold
on a press.
the press shapes the blade
to the player's precise specifications,
for the face, or vertical angle,
and the curve.
this molding process also compresses the graphite layers
into a single unit
and bonds the blade to the shaft permanently.
the plastic bag over the blade
prevents excess resin from oozing all over the press.
using a router, they profile the blade to a specific shape.
each pro player orders his own personal template.
it can be any shape, provided it abides by nhl regulations.
maximum curve -- half an inch, maximum height -- 3 inches,
maximum length -- 12 1/2 inches.
now, a good sanding.
and a thorough buffing.
they dip the blades in urethane,
a colorless coating that fills in tiny imperfections
on the surface.
once that dries,
a machine sprays silver paint at the base of the shaft.
finally, another coat of urethane
to seal and protect the paint.
for the retail market,
this company mass produces six
models of graphite hockey sticks
in a right-handed and left-handed version.
they all have the same blade shape,
but different curves.
you can peel off the removable model-name decal
and write your own name on the shaft instead.
not nearly as personalized as a made-to-order pro stick,
but at least you won't leave the arena
with someone else's hockey stick by mistake.
narrator: the pitter-patter of little footsteps
is a welcome sound in any household.
but children grow by leaps and bounds.
bronzing baby shoes is one way to preserve the memory
of those first steps.
the tradition was started back in the 1930s.
in these shoes,
a child learned to stand on his or her own two feet.
the baby shoes have joined a pile of others.
they're all about to be preserved forever.
they record information about the shoes' owners
including personal details for engraving.
they assign a tracking number to each pair.
without it, some shoes might not
find their way back
to their owners.
they stamp that number onto insoles.
there's a special coating on the insoles
that will prevent the metal plating from sticking to them,
so this number will be visible throughout processing.
they staple down the insoles
and then dip the shoes in a special formula.
it chemically seals them
and will also help stiffen them
as they dry later.
but first they hang them to
allow excess liquid to drip off.
they stuff each shoe with plastic
to give it some shape.
they push a rolled plastic form
into each shoe
to complete the shaping.
they tie the laces,
positioning the bows flat against the shoes
so they won't break off during the rest of the process.
as an extra precaution,
they wrap a rubber band around each bow and then glue it down.
with the shaping plastic removed
and the shoes dried and stiffened,
they drill holes into the bottoms of the soles.
this will allow them to be hung
on prongs during plating later.
but before that happens,
they stir up a mix of water, copper, and other ingredients.
they carefully submerge a rack full of baby shoes
into the coppery liquid.
this isn't the final coating. it's a key preparation step.
it makes the shoes electrically conductive
so that they can be electroplated.
they hang the shoes to dry
and dribble a little more of the liquid onto them
to cover any bare spots.
they allow the finish to dry for a couple of days.
then a worker lowers them into the electroplating tank.
an electrical current runs through to the shoes,
attracting copper in the tank to plate them.
using a special polishing wheel,
they lightly scratch the bright
copper finish on the shoes.
this prepares them for the next step.
they spray a black finish onto the shoes.
and then wipe it off,
rubbing some into the crevices
to give them an antique appearance.
next, they spray them with a protective lacquer.
you can still see the identification number clearly
on the insole, so they haven't lost track of the owner.
they attach the engraving plate
onto a wood base
and screw the shoes onto it.
now they won't be going anywhere,
except down memory lane.
and it seems there's no end to the bronze keepsakes
that can also take you there,
from cowboy boots to burgers on a bun.
narrator: treadmills were invented back in the 1800s
for the farm team.
farmers put animals on treadmills
to power butter churns and threshing machines.
it wasn't until the middle of the 20th century
that people started working out
on treadmills,
and as a fitness concept, it's been a success.
in these high-tech treadmills,
computer processors access your level of fitness
and plot your workout program.
to make one, they punch holes in aluminum-frame side pieces.
these holes will be used to attach other parts.
but first, they weld joints to the side pieces.
and they weld brackets onto the platform
that will hold the treadmill's motor.
they position the platform
between two aluminum side pieces
and screw it into place to complete the frame.
next, they attach the elevation mechanism.
this piece will raise the treadmill belt.
they fasten wheels to the frame
that will allow the treadmill to be rolled away for storage.
they turn over the treadmill
frame and work on the underside.
they attach brackets for the rollers
that go inside the belt.
then they position the belt and deck over the frame.
they slide in the steel rollers...
and attach the drive belt.
they bolt a big shock absorber to the drive motor
to dampen its vibration.
they install a strobe disk
and then place an optical sensor over it.
with the help of this sensor,
the strobe will monitor the motor speed
16 times per second.
they mount the drive motor for the treadmill belt
on the special platform and bolt it into place.
at this point, they attach one of the computer boards.
it receives information from the optical sensor
about the treadmill's speed
and relays it to the computer in the control panel.
this will ensure that everything
is in sync.
here, they slide a protective casing over the framework.
they cap the ends,
then turn over the machine once more
to install the mechanism that allows the treadmill
to be folded up when the workout is over.
they screw a plastic cover onto it to protect the bottom.
and it's over to the control system.
they stick the control membrane
onto the plastic housing
and attach a safety switch to the back.
then they install the
treadmill's other computer board
in this housing.
they plug a lead wire into the safety switch
and install a receiver to pick up the runner's heart rate.
they secure the handlebar assembly to the control housing
and plug in the upper circuit board.
now they close the back of the control system,
and it's time for the two assemblies to come together.
they connect the upper and lower computer boards
so they can communicate.
and then they give the treadmill
a little test run
to make sure it's in top form.
they put it through a range of elevations
and check the belt to determine
if it's running in the middle.
they adjust the belt to center it a little better.
and now this treadmill has passed inspection.
so they wipe away their footprints
and press the brand label onto the hood.
they lower the hood onto the motor.
and now, this treadmill is ready
to give you a good workout.
narrator: handhelds, as they're called,
are rugged computers designed for workers on the move.
you see them on delivery trucks,
police cruisers,
forklift trucks, and in large warehouses.
they process data in virtually any condition,
from bad weather to rough roads.
so even though you're in the field,
you're still plugged in.
from scanning bar codes to reading parking meters,
handhelds provide information on location.
they start with the keyboard electronics panel.
they test each contact for conductivity.
then they transfer the tracking number
from the electronics panel to the inner casing,
so it will be visible if it needs servicing.
they glue the electronics panel
to the casing with silicone
for a waterproof seal.
the rubber keypad goes on next.
then they glue a protective plastic plate over it.
next, they cut a silicone liner
to the size of the computer screen.
it will help seal the unit,
preventing water and dust from getting in.
they place the liner in a bracket behind the screen
and then use this jig to align the screen
to the computer casing.
a dab of threadlocker glue to the screws
helps to hold it all together.
the top casing for this handheld
computer is now assembled.
they move on to the back casing
and install a speaker.
they apply a layer of silicone to a circuit board assembly,
again, to resist water and dust
from seeping into it.
this circuit board assembly goes
into a hole in the back casing.
it will allow the unit
to communicate with a central computer.
in the next step,
they wire the speakers to the circuit board,
and now the handheld has a sound system.
more silicone on these connections.
then they install triggers to the scanner,
one on each side.
they install a liner on the door
for the memory card compartment.
then they run the top assemblies
for three hours
in extreme temperatures.
once the inner workings have been completely installed,
they attach the top assemblies to the bottom ones.
they tuck the battery pack into its compartment
and install the end cap.
it has an antenna for wireless communication.
now they install a smartcard reader,
because this particular handheld computer will be used
for security checks on personal i.d. cards.
they test the laser scanner,
then activate security software
which reads fingerprints,
allowing this handheld computer
to do security
or criminal checks on the spot.
when an unregistered person presses a finger
onto the print reader, this is what happens.
of course, mobile computers are designed
to return to a home base,
where they upload information to a main computer.
but first, randomly selected units get roughed up
in a series of tests.
they toss this unit into a tumbler
and it gets thrown around.
then they drop it from a height
of 6 1/2 feet.
they plunge it into a tank of water.
in the real world, things can be even tougher.
this computer ended up in a fire.
and this one was run over.
but even when it seems
that they've been completely destroyed,
information can still be salvaged.
here, they transfer the memory board
from one of the wrecked units to an undamaged one.
they hook it up to a central computer
and retrieve the information.
these are tough computers for those on the go.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...