narrator: today on "how it's made"...
handcuffs...
...caulking and joint compound...
...propane tanks...
...and forensic facial reconstruction.
when a crime is committed,
a slap on the wrist usually isn't enough.
it's time to handcuff them.
the need for some restraint goes back centuries,
but the handcuff's design was really improved in 1862
when adjustable ratchets were added.
they allow the cuffs to snugly grip the suspect's wrist.
when they put the handcuffs on you,
you know you may be in trouble.
handcuffs start with a roll of steel.
a machine pulls it through a straightener
and then through a die
that punches out a handcuff frame part.
a revolving barrel cage sifts out the waste
and kicks the frames into a bin.
here, a worker stacks "u"-shaped
steel parts on a fixture,
which he then clamps onto a machine.
a cutter makes ratchet teeth in the parts.
coolant keeps the tool
from heating up and getting too soft to do the job.
each set of handcuffs
will have two of these ratchets.
next, they load steel rods into a slowly revolving device.
it moves the rods through a series of cutters.
this is how they make swivels for the handcuffs.
they round the tips of the rods
and then carve necks below.
this tool slices the swivel to the proper length.
and then the partially finished
swivel falls into a basket.
next, a drill works on the rounded tip,
scooping out the center.
and now you have a finished swivel.
they take two chain links and two swivels.
they make a small chain --
two links with swivels on the ends.
they lock the links and the swivels together.
and now the swivel-link assembly
is complete.
the swivels will provide some rotational freedom
between the cuffs.
but if they don't weld the links together,
the prisoner could have total freedom.
it's time to assemble the handcuffs.
they install studs in the outer framework
and attach the ratchets to them.
the swivel link fits into the
little grooves in the framework.
they hammer the inner frame on
and then lift the top and bottom
assemblies together.
a tap with a hammer holds them loosely together.
then a press bears down to make a tight seal.
these cuffs look complete,
but they aren't quite ready for a life of crime.
they need to be toughened up.
so they spend 25 minutes in a furnace,
and the searing heat hardens the seal.
this is the pawl,
a spring-loaded bar that will
engage the teeth of the ratchet.
they lock the pawl and spring in place.
a press pushes pins into the assembly
to hold everything in position.
then they stamp serial numbers onto each set of handcuffs
so that the police can keep track of them.
now the handcuffs shake in a vibrating bin full of stones.
this polishes the rough edges.
it's time for the ultimate test.
they activate a 500-pound pull,
and the handcuffs remain strong.
they also tap each set to make sure the ratchets drop freely.
handcuffs are temporary restraints,
and most can be opened with the universal key.
they pack two with each set,
along with the instructions.
there's no doubt they'll have a captive market
because there's always someone who needs to be locked up.
but then again, there are also
those who deserve their freedom.
narrator: the need to seal windows and cracks
in walls and floors has been around since antiquity.
lucky for us, we no longer have to stuff rags
or smelly fish glue into these crevices.
today's caulking and drywall compounds
form durable synthetic seals that also blend into the decor.
this company's caulking comes
in two types, latex and acrylic,
both good for indoor and outdoor use.
to make acrylic caulking, they blend water with chemicals
that prevent mold and help the
caulking withstand cold weather.
everything blends for about one minute.
the batch then goes into another mixer
containing 1,500 pounds of synthetic resin.
they add a plasticizer
that keeps the caulking flexible
over time.
a combination of colorants tints the caulking --
in this case, a shade of brown called sandalwood.
after 15 minutes of blending, the caulking is ready.
to test the batch,
they cure a sample at 77 degrees
fahrenheit for one week...
then check its flexibility.
if the batch gets the okay, it goes into this machine,
which lines up plastic caulking tubes.
piston pumps lift four tubes at a time,
and the nozzles fill each tube with 10 ounces of caulking.
the machine can fill up to 1,000 tubes per hour.
the machine then seals the bottom end of the tubes
with plastic covers.
the top ends have closed nozzles
with replaceable caps.
thanks to the resins and plasticizers,
this company's products last up to 30 years.
that's the tough side of caulking,
but there's also a gentler, craftier side.
start by drawing a pattern on a piece of paper.
then lay glass on top and run caulking along the pattern.
after 48 hours,
the caulking hardens into a delicate lattice.
then fill in the spaces with clear silicone
for a frosted look.
use a small steel brush and rubber gloves
to spread it and create texture.
perfect for a door or a bathroom window.
this factory also makes joint compound.
use this product to cover cracks, holes, and seams
in drywall.
to make it, they mix 185 gallons of water
with chemicals that prevent mold
and a type of clay that makes the compound more spreadable.
now for the main ingredient -- 440 pounds of chalk.
it's what remains on the wall when the compound dries.
next, they add mica,
a mineral whose tiny plates slide over each other
to make the compound flexible and help prevent cracking.
they test the thickness with a device
that gauges how much pressure it takes to stir the compound.
next, they take a sample from every batch
and measure the ph level.
it should have a reading of 8.8,
quite high because of the chalk.
this is what's called a sandability test.
technicians first let a precise
amount of compound harden
on a piece of drywall.
this machine then sands it down,
applying 100 strokes in 2 minutes.
technicians then remeasure the combined weight
of the compound and drywall,
registering how much has been lost.
maximum weight loss should be 4%.
if the batch passes the test, they feed it into this machine.
it pumps compound into either small-size, 6.6-pound
or large-size, 15.5-pound plastic buckets.
then using a hydraulic press,
a worker seals the containers with plastic covers.
to open the bucket, you break a small plastic tab
and lift off the cover.
joint compound also has its crafty uses.
with a stencil,
you can apply small amounts in intricate patterns
to decorate a picture frame or a mirror.
now, that is some fancy filler.
narrator: compressing propane
allows you to sell it by the bottle.
when you compress it,
propane gas turns into a liquid,
and as a liquid, it's much more compact,
which means you can pack a lot of energy
into a small container.
opening the valve converts it back to gas,
giving you energy that you can put to good use.
bottling energy means you can always have fuel on hand.
to make these tanks, they start
with this big coil of steel.
a press punches out 3 disks 19 inches in diameter
with each swoop.
a second press clamps the disk
as a cylinder-shaped die thrusts upward,
transforming it into a shell.
each shell is 1/2 of a barbecue tank.
next, suctioning devices
carry the tank shells over to a trimmer,
where a blade gives it a neat edge.
workers then insert flanges
into prepunched holes in the top shells.
the top and bottom halves of the barbecue tanks
now move in separate directions.
the tops head into an automated welding station
where the flanges are fused to them.
the weld has to be perfect
so it can take the pressure of compressed fuel
without exploding.
this die simultaneously bends steel strips into rings
and punches holes in them.
these rings will be used as pedestals,
and the holes can be used to mount the tank to a barbecue.
next, a machine welds the rings
to the bottoms of the tank shells.
the top and bottom tank shells converge.
and a pusher device nudges the tops onto the bottoms.
they load each freshly assembled
tank onto a welding lathe.
the lathe turns as an automated welding gun
follows the seam precisely,
melting and bonding the two pieces together.
but this processing has hardened the steel...
not a good thing
because these tanks will need to expand and contract
to accommodate pressurized fuel.
so they temper the tanks in a furnace.
they do random tests of the welded seam.
they cut out a piece of the tank
and grind it on both sides
to expose the weld.
then they use a jack
to bend the sample right at the seam.
it doesn't split and passes the test.
in another test, they lower
a tank into a water-filled drum.
they pump water into the tank,
causing pressure inside the drum
to rise,
proving the tank will indeed expand with pressure changes.
the tanks then travel down a row
of paint guns,
which spray them
with electrostatically charged powder paint.
the tanks journey about a half mile to an inspection station.
here, workers check for contaminants.
then they drop valves into the flanged openings
and place the barbecue cylinder
in a special machine
that screws the valve on very tightly.
in one final test, they submerge
air-filled tanks in water.
if the water doesn't bubble up,
it means the valve isn't leaking.
and after all that,
these barbecue tanks should be
able to take plenty of grilling.
narrator: when the usual ways of
identifying human remains fail
and the investigation stalls,
police sometimes need a little image building,
as in facial reconstruction.
using the skull, they re-create
the face of the deceased
in hopes that it will jog someone's memory.
it's a high-tech way to solve a mystery.
to reconstruct a face,
the specialist uses resin to make an exact replica
of the unidentified man's cranium.
he attaches it to the rest of the skull cast.
and now he has an exact copy of the man's skull.
next he measures rubber pegs to different lengths
that are equivalent to the various thicknesses
of facial skin.
the short one is placed on the
forehead where the skin is thin.
then he installs actual
prosthetic eyes made of plastic.
those are suction cups protruding from them now.
they help him to align the eyes.
he shines a light into them
to confirm that they're looking
straight ahead.
next he cuts out muscle shapes from rolled clay.
this piece simulates the area around the mouth.
the man's muscles have left tension marks on his skull.
those marks combined with the knowledge of facial anatomy
help him decide where to build up muscle.
he makes the face expressionless
because expressions are unique
and impossible to extrapolate from a skull.
next he sculpts muscle around the prosthetic eyes.
there are no clues about the
actual shape of this man's eyes,
so he gives them a generic look.
the skull does divulge
the length and width of the nose
as well as the location of the nostrils.
now he builds up smiling muscles
followed by fat and a salivary gland.
he uses different-colored clay
so he can see them more clearly.
he maps out a location for the ears
but doesn't yet attach them.
he shapes muscles in the neck,
working from measurements
and photos from the crime scene.
next he gives the model skin.
as he applies this layer of clay,
he uses the protruding pegs as thickness guides.
and after much sculpting, the model has come to life.
but he needs one more clay ear.
the skull offers some hints about the ears' size
but not their shape, so he keeps that generic.
now he sponges the clay to give it some texture
so it looks more like real skin.
the artist snaps his picture with a digital camera
and then downloads the image onto a computer.
using photo-editing software,
he transfers some hair to the shot of the clay model.
he knows from evidence on the scene
that the man's hair was styled in dreadlocks
and that he had a beard.
he borrows brows from another photo.
he paints in the brows with a stylus,
which is a kind of computer mouse.
using the same technique,
he gives the image facial hair.
this digital artistry takes a couple of days,
and the skull mold and clay model
take 12 days to complete...
time well spent
because once the pictures and information
are posted on police sites like this one,
it may finally help them put a name to this face.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
if you have any comments about the show
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...