-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: tiny motion sensors known as accelerometers
are at the heart of much of today's technology.
built into a smartphone,
for example, the sensor detects both movement
and the angle at which the phone
is being held
to trigger the rotation of the screen.
this little chip is
why a smartphone knows when it has moved.
these motion sensors are tiny,
but smart, because they can detect every move.
they start with silicon disks called wafers.
each wafer will be used to make
thousands of motion sensors.
a technician aligns the disks in a cassette,
using the flat part of each one
as a reference point.
once properly aligned,
a mechanism lowers the silicon wafers onto a carrier
made of quartz, which can withstand intense heat.
the technician loads the wafers
into the furnace.
inside, the 2,000-degree heat and steam cause an oxide
to form on the surface of each wafer.
it'll act as an electrical insulator.
then it goes into what's known as a sputter system.
here, inert gas ions bombard aluminum,
causing it to sputter onto the wafer
until an even layer accumulates.
this aluminum layer will serve as a conductor of electricity.
the next machine deposits a light-sensitive chemical
onto the wafer.
the wafer spins,
allowing the chemical to flow evenly across the surface.
this all happens under the glow
of yellow light
to prevent the untimely activation of the chemical,
which reacts to bright light
just like an unexposed photographic negative would.
they're now ready for that bright light.
u.v. light beams through tiny patterns on a glass plate
to activate the light-sensitive chemical.
the patterns transfer to the wafer's surface,
forming an outline
for thousands of motion sensors.
another chemical then flows onto the silicon wafer
to further develop these miniscule images.
next, lasers locate the wafer's flat edge,
signaling a chuck
to spin into its proper position
for plasma etching.
the etching creates thousands of free-moving 3-d structures.
each one is a motion sensor.
after etching,
a sprayer blasts the surface with carbon dioxide.
it's the only way to clean it without damaging
the now-movable sensors.
at the next station,
a robotic arm flips the wafer into position.
a tray moves under the robot and places the wafer on it.
the tray retracts and loads the wafer
into a clamping system.
it then collects a second silicon wafer
and places it on the first one in the clamp.
the second wafer acts as a lid
to protect the individual sensors.
held in the clamp, a machine heat-seals the two wafers,
and the bond is complete.
next, a computerized saw cuts
grooves into the top wafer only,
while a steady stream of water keeps the dust down.
the saw exposes the aluminum layer on the bottom wafer,
something that will allow each sensor
to make an electrical connection.
a platform now moves the wafer a millimeter at a time
so that a probe can test each sensor
and confirm it performs correctly.
this continues until every sensor on the wafer
has been tested.
from a plain silicon wafer
to a unit that contains thousands of motion sensors --
this process takes three weeks.
after the individual sensors
have been cut and encased in plastic,
they're ready for a final test.
a robot loads each sensor into a test socket.
the socket both tests the sensor's performance
and programs it to customer specifications.
a robot packages the sensors for shipping.
and once installed in phones, tablets,
and computers,
these motion sensors will be ready for action.
narrator: if you've been to an airport,
you've seen mobile belt loaders
on the tarmac.
they drive from the terminal to the aircraft,
align their built-in conveyor belt
with the entrance to the cargo hold,
then load baggage or cargo on board.
when an aircraft arrives,
they do all that in reverse to unload baggage or cargo.
a turn of the control handle
adjusts the height
of the front of the belt loader,
enabling it to reach the cargo hold
of even the tallest aircraft.
the rear height is also adjustable
so the airport baggage handlers
can set it at a level comfortable for loading.
the vehicle and the conveyor belt are separate units.
in this part of the factory,
workers construct the conveyor's steel frame.
they weld together all the steel parts
then grind all the weld seams flat
so that the belt will move over the frame smoothly.
workers install a crossmember
just past the midpoint of the frame.
it will connect with two sets of lift arms
installed in the vehicle --
one which raises and lowers the front of the conveyor,
the other which raises and lowers the rear.
workers insert alignment pins
to position the crossmember on the frame correctly,
then weld it into place.
the vehicle's chassis is also made of welded steel.
workers blast the chassis
and conveyor frame with a metal abrasive.
this removes rust and other debris,
prepping the surface for paint to adhere properly.
the caulk all the unwelded seams
to prevent corrosion,
then spray a coat of primer
followed by a coat of industrial-grade paint
in the color the customer requested.
once the paint dries, assembly can resume.
on the conveyor frame,
they install the motor, which drives the belt.
there are two options available --
this hydraulic motor powered by the vehicle's engine
or an electric motor
powered by battery.
the motor rotates two large metal rollers --
one at the front of the frame,
the other at the rear.
the belt wraps around these rollers so that,
when they turn, the belt moves.
between the end rollers,
running the entire length of the conveyor,
workers install 58 smaller metal
rollers.
these form the floor of the conveyor
and can support up to a ton of cargo.
the motor runs these rollers forward or in reverse,
depending on whether the belt is loading
or unloading the aircraft.
the belt itself is made of high-strength tire-grade rubber
with an antiskid texture on the surface.
to be long enough to loop
around the 25-foot-long conveyor
plus the end rollers,
the belt is 50 feet in length.
the ends have teeth which fit into each other like a zipper
and fasten with a metal pin.
elsewhere in the factory,
technicians install components on the vehicle chassis.
first, the front and rear axles...
...then on each axle, two wheels
with tires specifically designed
for long life on the airport tarmac.
at the rear of the chassis, they
install the hydraulic cylinder,
which raises and lowers the rear
lift arms,
then the vehicle's engine,
which can be either gas, diesel, propane,
or electric powered.
the vehicle drives at a maximum speed
of just 25 miles per hour,
but that's more than sufficient
for traveling between the terminal and the aircraft.
after installing the power-steering system,
technicians run wiring
for the lights
and other electrical components,
run hydraulic hoses for the brakes and lift cylinders,
and install the controls for the conveyor.
they install the hydraulic cylinder,
which raises the front lift arms,
then connect the fluid hoses to the hydraulic pump.
next, they install the front and rear lift arms
along with a safety brace underneath
to use when mechanics are working beneath the conveyor.
they attach the lift arms
to the front and rear cylinders,
which expand to raise the arms and retract to lower them.
now workers hoist the conveyor over the vehicle
and bolt the front and rear lift
arms to the crossmember
on the conveyor's underside.
the two units are now one mobile belt loader,
ready to roll off the line and hit the tarmac.
narrator: the pheasant is one of
the most sought-after game birds
in north america,
but populations in the wild have dwindled.
to replenish them
and also supply a market for pheasant meat,
farmers raise breeding stock and incubate their eggs
to make it more likely they'll yield chicks.
with stunning plumage and an ability to both run and fly,
no wonder the pheasant struts around.
each pheasant lays approximately four eggs weekly,
april through to july.
farm workers collect the eggs daily
before the pheasants have an opportunity to nest.
with their intervention,
the hatch rate will get a big boost.
it will go from 40% to at least 75%.
the farmer washes the eggs in water and special soap
to remove dirt and bacteria
that could infiltrate the shells
and harm the growing chicks.
she inspects the eggs
and rejects any cracked or very large ones
that would contain a double yolk.
eggs with cracks or double yolks won't hatch.
one last dip,
and she sets the eggs aside to drip dry.
once dry, she taps eggs together
systematically and listens.
if the tap sounds like fine china clinking together,
they're suitable for hatching.
but if the tap sounds dull, there's likely a crack.
by listening, she finds one or two cracked eggs
she missed with the visual inspection.
she places the eggs in an incubator rack
and transfers it to a cooling room.
the pheasant eggs chill here for a few days.
the cooling slows down cell division
until the farmer is ready to put
the eggs in the incubator.
chick production is timed for two hatches weekly.
when the time is right,
she transfers the eggs to the incubator.
the incubator is a toasty 100 degrees fahrenheit
to mimic the warmth of a hen's body.
she latches the racks onto an automated system
that gently rocks the long cradles back and forth
to turn the pheasant eggs.
turning the eggs routinely is something
that nesting hens do naturally,
and it's important.
without it, the developing
embryo could stick to the shell,
causing abnormal growth.
the farmer monitors the incubator temperature
and humidity several times daily.
three weeks later,
she removes the rack
and places it on a tray lined with cheesecloth.
she opens each cradle,
and the eggs spill softly onto the tray.
at this point,
there are tiny pits on the shells
caused by the chicks' beaks as they attempt to break through.
once on the tray,
she arranges them close together
in a figure-eight configuration.
this way, the chicks can feel each other moving,
cuing them to break out of their shells.
she pumps water onto the tiers of the hatcher now.
the hatcher is warmer than the incubator.
she covers the trays with screens to keep the chicks
from jumping onto other trays.
as the water heats up, the humidity increases.
this causes the shells to weaken,
making it easier for the pheasant chicks
to break out of their shells.
after a couple of days,
the eggs have hatched.
after drying off, the chicks are fluffy and lively.
the farmer packs them in ventilated cardboard boxes.
freshly hatched,
they'll survive 60 hours
without food, giving the breeder
enough time to ship them anywhere in the world.
that's why pheasants are easier to ship
when they're chicks.
some customers prefer more mature birds,
so the farmer raises some chicks
in wire frames for a week,
until their legs become stronger.
then they move those chicks to other heated buildings
until they're ready to thrive outdoors.
some will be kept as breeding stock.
others will be sold as food.
the rest will be introduced
into the wild and just fly away.
today's diving helmets
are produced primarily for history buffs
and divers performing underwater work,
such as welding the submerged parts of bridges.
unlike a scuba tank,
which carries a limited amount of oxygen,
a helmet connects to an air pump
at the surface,
providing an unlimited air supply.
a diving helmet is completely watertight
so the diver doesn't need a mouthpiece to breathe
and can speak to people at the surface
via a built-in transceiver.
this helmet is the design the u.s. navy used
from 1916 until 1984.
at the factory, they make the helmet's head portion,
called the bonnet, from a copper sheet
about a millimeter and a half thick
that's been spun on a lathe into a dome.
they buff it smooth, then, using a template,
mark where to cut openings for the various components.
it takes a good month and a half
for the factory to machine all those components
and assemble the helmet.
with a hammer and punch,
they dimple the copper at the marked spots.
this will give the saw
a foothold on the otherwise slippery surface.
then they apply cutting oil to prevent the saw
from overheating as it bores through the metal.
the first cut is a 6-inch-wide hole at the front
for the bonnet's hinged faceplate.
they saw eight openings for the bonnet's other components,
including three windows.
next, with tin-and-lead solder,
they fuse a threaded neck ring to the bottom edge.
this ring attaches the bonnet to the helmet's breastplate,
which bolts to the collar of the diver's dry suit.
then they solder a base to the faceplate opening.
like all the helmet's components,
it's made of red brass,
which is more durable
than standard brass due to its higher copper content.
next, through a template, they drill holes
into a banana-shaped brass exhaust tube.
it enables the diver's exhaled air to exit the helmet.
they solder the exhaust to the bonnet,
positioning the non-perforated end
over a hole near the diver's mouth
and the perforated end at the rear.
this directs air bubbles behind the diver
so as not to obstruct the view.
then they solder on the remaining components,
including three window bases.
just as one does when installing
a window in a building,
they apply glazing to the faceplate and window bases
to seal the three-inch thick acrylic pane against leaks.
for underwater safety,
they screw a brass guard to the base.
this prevents the pane from popping out
should too much air pressure build up inside the helmet.
now they install the transceiver
and feed its wires through a brass elbow,
which will ultimately
attach to a communications cable
running to the surface.
with the bonnet complete,
it's time to shape the helmet's breastplate.
they lay a copper sheet
onto a breastplate-shaped mandrel,
clamp on a breastplate-shaped form,
heat the copper with a torch to make it malleable,
then, with a wooden mallet soaked in brine
to keep it from splitting,
pound the copper for about 45 minutes,
until it assumes the shape.
then they chisel out the neck opening.
once the copper has cooled,
they transfer the breastplate to a form
and begin reinforcing the bottom
with a brass strap.
after clamping the strap in position,
they hammer the copper around and over its outer edge.
then they remove the clamps
and solder the copper to the strap.
once the soldering's done, they grind the surface smooth
and drill 12 holes into the strap
for the custom-made bolts
that connect the helmet to the collar of the diver's dry suit.
then, after flipping the breastplate upside down,
they wrap solder around the bolts,
drop them in the holes, and melt
the solder to lock them in.
they polish the metal
and solder on the last breastplate components --
a threaded neck ring for connecting the bonnet
and, at the front, a pair of brass eyes
for lashing the air- and communication hoses
off to the side
so they won't get in the diver's way underwater.