-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: the first fireplaces were strictly functional
for heating the home, cooking meals,
and warming water for bathing.
over time, fireplaces appeared in other rooms of the house
and acquired ascetic features such as wood,
stone, or tile work.
this ceramic fireplace is a heritage model
inspired by fireplaces of the late 19th
and early 20th century.
certain tiles
are exact replicas of originals.
at the ceramic factory they mix water with clay,
feldspar, and silica in a pugmill.
together, these formulate a clay blend.
once the mix is the right consistency,
the operator presses a button,
and the mill switches to extrusion mode.
this forces the clay blend through a mantel shaped die
and produces a 10- to 15-inch long extruded mantel piece.
they trim the piece with a cutting wire
to the precise length required.
they use this extrusion method for making longer pieces.
if they need shorter ones
they often cast them individually in a mold.
when casting they add significantly more water
to the clay blend to produce a liquid clay called slip.
they pour the slip into a plaster mold.
the porous plaster gradually absorbs most of the water,
leaving a layer of clay about 6 millimeters thick
on the walls of the mantel-shaped cavity.
after a few hours, they pour out the excess slip
and open the mold to extract the cast mantel piece.
once the clay becomes firm enough to handle
they carefully trim off the excess
around the opening in the mold.
then they gently smooth down the seam
along the junction between the two halves of the mold.
on the opposite side of the pour hole,
they cut out a matching hole.
this will help the clay dry faster
by enabling air to flow through
the inside of the piece.
to compensate for shrinkage,
the molds and extrusion dies are designed 11% larger
than the size of the finished piece.
clay shrinks as it dries.
to make the fireplace's ceramic tiles,
they produce a rubber mold of two adjoining tiles
and place it inside a metal casing.
they also include a release system to help with extraction.
they fill the casing
with an exceptionally strong type of plaster.
it sets in about half an hour,
taking on the shape of the rubber mold.
this plaster casting
is the die they'll now use to produce the tiles.
they mount the die on what's known as a ram press
because it literally rams a block of clay in the die
and compresses it with 30 tons of pressure.
the tile die is also 11% larger
than the final size
to compensate for shrinkage during drying and firing.
they remove excess clay
and send it back to the pugmill
to be recycled.
then they position a board under the die
and activate the release system,
which extracts the clay with a blast of compressed air.
they trim off the excess clay.
once dry,
the tiles and mantel pieces are ready to be glazed.
glaze is a chemical formula
containing finely ground silica
combined with different combinations
of metallic elements to produce specific colors.
they use a spray gun
to apply glaze to the mantels and a tube tip applicator
to glaze the tiles.
the tiles design has raised borders between its components.
these are called cuenca lines.
they prevent the different colored glazes
from flowing into each other.
the glazed mantel piece and tiles
now go into a gas-fired kiln for 12 to 14 hours.
the high temperature, 2,100 degrees fahrenheit,
triggers chemical reactions
which harden and strengthen the pieces.
the clay's mineral composition transforms
into a completely new configuration
of crystals and glass.
as for the glaze, its precise
formulation of metallic elements
produces a specific color,
and the silica melts into a glass surface.
the ceramics are now smooth and shiny
and ready to transform an otherwise ordinary fireplace
into a work of art.
narrator: many winemakers choose to seal their bottles
with synthetic closures instead
of natural cork from tree bark.
this prevents cork taint,
which happens when natural cork
gets contaminated by the tca molecule.
cork taint is completely harmless to humans,
but spoils the taste of the wine.
this engineered cork is entirely synthetic
and therefore resistant to tca contamination.
it's made of a food-grade polyethylene foam core
encased in elasticized polymer skin.
both materials contract
to squeeze inside the bottleneck
but then regain their original shape
to seal the opening.
to make the foam core,
they mix talc with pellets of low density polyethylene,
a pliable type of plastic.
then they add pellets
of dark brown and beige colorant
to mimic the wood grain look of natural cork.
for each customer's order of corks,
a computerized system automatically releases
the right amount of each ingredient
into an industrial blender.
the blender feeds a specially
designed dual extrusion machine.
the machine melts the foam mix to a liquid state
then injects carbon dioxide.
this produces bubbles,
which create the cellular structure of the foam.
the liquid foam enters the machine's horizontal extruder,
while elasticized polymer enters
the machine's angled extruder.
both extruders
squeeze their materials through the same shaping die,
which outputs a continuous rod of skin-encased foam.
the foam core immediately expands.
the elastic skin stretches with it.
a water bath cools the rod,
halting this expansion at a specific diameter.
then, an underwater ultrasonic gauge
measures the thickness of the outer skin
to make sure it meets specifications.
the rod exits the water bath
and continues cooling and shrinking as it drip dries.
a laser gauge then verifies that the rod is perfectly round
and measures a specific diameter
by this point.
when any of the measuring gauges
detects an area that doesn't meet specifications,
that part of the rod is flagged in the system
and is discarded at the end of the production line.
the rod now enters the final cooling phase.
it travels in several loops past
nozzles spraying cold water.
as the rod cools, it shrinks to its final size,
a diameter of between 22 and 23 millimeters.
it's designed to fit snugly
inside the standard 18.5-millimeter bottle opening.
they had to calculate exactly how wide to extrude the rod
so that after expansion then shrinkage,
it would end up at this precise diameter.
the rod now enters a cutter.
the blade is so sharp that a safety cover is mandatory.
it's removed here only for the camera.
the winery placing the order specifies the cork length.
air jets automatically blow off
any corks
cut from areas the measuring gauges flagged
as being problematic.
the cutter slices about 10 standard-length corks
per second.
all the good corks land on the conveyor belt
and travel to the end of the line,
where computer sensors count them
as they drop into a collection bin.
additional machines print on the winery's name and logo,
and lubricate the surface with silicone
so the corks will glide in
and out of the bottle with ease.
the factory's on-site lab tests samples from every order.
sensory specialists sniff each cork
and compare it to a control sample.
there must be no discernible odor
that might affect the aroma or flavor of the wine.
if there is, the entire order of corks fails inspection.
while natural cork is designed by mother nature,
a synthetic cork manufacturer can engineer the closure
to fit more or less snugly according to the amount of air
the particular wine needs to develop correctly.
narrator: multi-tiered parking garages
have become an urban phenomenon.
with each floor added to the garage
the number of parking spaces increases.
in crowded cities where land is limited,
garages like these are a necessity.
they build parking garages one concrete slab at a time.
these slabs are known as double-t's
because the two support beams
are in a double-t configuration.
double-t's are often factory made
and transported to the construction site later.
they are designed to hold up under very heavy loads.
they make these slabs outdoors.
wind blows dirt onto the molds,
so they sweep it clean.
this mold is about 500 feet long
and will be used to make several slabs.
they spray an oil-based release agent onto it.
the release agent will allow
the slabs to be easily extracted
when complete, preventing cracking.
they spread it more evenly using mops.
this release agent bonds to the metal quickly
and won't wash off easily if it happens to rain.
they're now ready to assemble
the floor slab's elaborate support structure.
they prop up the ends of each slab
with galvanized steel stirrups.
they place l-shaped bearing plates
in strategic locations along the mold.
then they insert wooden blocks in the mold.
these blocks will form notches in the cast concrete
that will be used to join the slabs during construction.
next, workers thread high-strength steel cables
called tendons throughout the beam sections of the mold.
they pull the ends through holes
to the outside of the mold
and clamp them.
a worker tucks another wood block between two tendons
to complete the notch part of the mold
and hold the tendons in place.
the team threads more tendons throughout the mold,
weaving a strategic support structure.
to separate each cast slab, they insert wooden dividers
with slots that accommodate the tendons.
they adjust the location of each of the stirrups
so that they sit at a specific spot near the dividers.
with the final tendons in place,
they bring in a hydraulic jack.
the worker attaches it to one
of the protruding steel tendons.
he activates the jack, and it pulls the tendon
until it's stretched tight like a rubber band.
he pulls the rest of the tendons
with the jack
and checks the tension to confirm
that it's exactly the same for each one.
pulled tight and later released,
the cables will hold the concrete under compression,
adding strength to it.
without it, the concrete slabs
would never be able to support the weight of many vehicles.
the next worker ties a plastic bracket to the stirrups
to set them at the right height.
he inserts metal mesh into the mold
where each slab will end.
this will help disperse
some of the concentrated bearing stresses.
he stabilizes the mesh,
and reinforces it with the support structure.
the team places plastic pockets
along the tops of the beam sections of the mold.
these pockets will be used to chain the slab to the truck
during transport.
they'll also act as entry points
for electrical wiring
and hold controls for parking space counting equipment.
coming up next,
the deck section gets plenty of extra support,
and then it's set in concrete.
narrator: the average car weighs well over 2,000 pounds,
so each parking garage floor
must hold up many times that weight.
double-t concrete slabs make this possible.
each slab has two reinforcing beams,
and each beam has a tense steel skeleton
that compresses the concrete, making it stronger.
with the steel tendons
stretched through the beam parts
of the mold,
workers now lay metal mesh across the deck.
this mesh is known as welded wire fabric,
and it will reinforce
the surface of the parking slab.
they tie the welded wire together
for full coverage across the deck.
they use plastic clips to prop up the wire
so that when they pour the concrete,
it will envelop both sides.
they insert handles
that will protrude from the ends
of the completed slab
to allow it to be lifted for transport and installation.
there are four double handles in each parking floor slab.
they enmesh the prongs of weld plates in the steel grid.
the plates are strategically positioned
for the welding of the slab to other pieces of concrete.
all the prep work is finally done,
and they pour the concrete.
the concrete flows into the beam
sections of the mold first,
and then workers spread the overflow across the deck.
this is a high-performance formula
that's known in the industry as self-consolidating concrete.
it flows evenly into tight spaces
and compacts better without the need for much vibrating.
this leveler vibrates the surface of the concrete
only slightly as it evens it out.
they then rake the surface of the slab
to allow another layer of concrete to adhere to it
later during construction.
they now insert arced metal bars
into slots on the sides of the mold
to form a ribbed framework down the length of it.
this serves as a support structure for a tent.
they unroll the tarp from a huge spool
and drape it over the ribbing.
they secure the canvas to the sides of the mold
with hooks.
the tent will shelter the concrete
from the wind and rain as it cures.
along with an additional plastic layer,
it will contain the hot and
humid conditions created inside.
the heat accelerates the curing
of the concrete,
and the humidity prevents cracking.
the cure takes 16 hours, and then they roll up the tarp.
using a torch, they cut the steel tendons
and place the concrete under compression.
the cuts also separate the slabs.
a driver now parks his crane over one of the slabs.
workers attach the hooks of the crane
to the protruding handles at the ends of the slab.
they signal the crane operator,
and he activates the lift.
thanks to the release agent applied earlier,
the concrete slab easily dislodges from the mold.
it's a heavy load.
each slab weighs 40,000 pounds.
the crane sets it down
and the team inspects the slab for defects.
satisfied that the slab is free of flaws,
a worker trims the protruding steel tendons
flush to the concrete.
another worker spreads a concrete-like paste
on the exposed ends of the severed steel
to seal it from the elements.
then a worker glues rubber pads
to the bearing plates.
they'll act as cushions
when the slab sits on another concrete beam.
he wraps some tape around them while the adhesive sets.
this parking garage floor slab is now ready to join the rest.
side-by-side,
the slabs will form one large parking surface
to create even more spaces.