narrator: the folding kayak
is a seaworthy vessel
that can be disassembled
and stuffed into a duffel bag.
this boat-in-a-bag concept
was developed in germany
a century ago.
it's a good fit for
the modern traveler's
lifestyle
because it can be stowed
in a car trunk,
checked on to a plane,
or stashed in the condo
closet.
history has shown
that when going gets rough,
the folding kayak
doesn't fall apart.
adventurers have crossed
oceans
in them,
and today its story
continues to unfold.
the kayak frame
starts with parts cut from
solid ash and laminated birch.
for waterproofing,
they dip them in marine-grade
varnish three times,
drying them for 24 hours
between dips.
a worker then rivets
metal fittings
to a varnished section
of the keel board.
it's these fittings
that enable the folding kayak
to move with the sea
instead of against it.
that's because they're made
of an aluminum-copper alloy,
a metal with
a certain amount of give.
he fastens more aluminum-alloy
fittings on the cross ribs.
there will be a total
of seven cross ribs
in this two-seater
folding kayak.
the center three
will carry most of the load,
so they're made of nine layers
of laminated birch.
it's super strong
because unlike solid wood,
it has few knots
or imperfections.
he applies a label with
the production's serial number
to a boomerang-shaped piece
of the frame.
this is how the kayak owner
would actually assemble the
boat
on-site.
he locks two sections
of the keel board together
with the flexible fitting
we saw installed earlier.
he snaps the bow piece
to the front
and hooks rods into fittings
installed on the bow.
he fastens a couple of ribs
to the keel board.
the gunnels, which are the top
sides of the boat, are next.
he attaches one end to the bow
and the other
to one of the ribs.
the bow and stern parts
are color-coded
with red-painted fittings
for the bow
and blue ones for the stern.
all the parts fit together
like a toy model.
with both gunnels now
attached,
he's ready to install
more ribs --
the laminated birch ones
that form the cockpit.
he completes
the assembly of rods.
all these rods will give
the kayak directional
stability.
he unfolds part
of the kayak deck assembly,
known as the coaming,
and arranges it to surround
the cockpit.
he attaches it to the gunnels
using metal clamps and
fittings.
he slides the two seats
into place on the keel board.
and he attaches the back rest
to the gunnels.
the frame of this folding
kayak
is now complete and ready
for its custom-made skin.
over in the sewing department,
the seamstress traces
the patterns for the kayak
deck
onto cotton-hemp material and
cuts along the penciled lines.
this natural fabric will allow
the deck to breathe
and yet keep it water-tight.
it's now time to piece
together
all of the parts,
including two long sleeves
for inserting inflatable
tubes.
deflated, the tubes
will create slack,
making it easier to fit
the frame into the skin.
inflated, they make the kayak
virtually unsinkable.
once the thick layers
have been stitched together,
she's ready to insert
the inflatable tubes.
they were pumped full of air
to be examined for holes,
so she deflates them.
she uses a long pole
to extend her reach
and push the inflatable tube
into the sleeve.
with a synthetic rubber hull
now stitched to the deck
fabric,
the skin is complete and ready
for the kayak's wooden frame.
this particular model
has been painted black.
if the fit is even slightly
off,
the kayak won't perform
properly.
the skin fits like a glove.
he brushes glue onto the tips
of the bow and stern
and then presses molded rubber
bumpers onto those areas.
the bumpers will protect
the ends of the hull casing,
which takes
a lot of hard knocks.
in total, it takes
about 50 person-hours
to make a folding kayak.
it should take the owner
about 15 minutes
to disassemble or assemble
one.
for some, it will become
a traveling essential,
part of the luggage on any
trip.
narrator: the piata is
a colorful paper-mache object
typically filled
with candy or small toys,
then suspended high
from a string.
blindfolded partiers take
turns
trying to hit the piata
with a stick to break it open
and release a shower of
goodies.
from popular cartoon
characters
to colorful, glittery shapes,
today's piatas are a big hit
at kid's parties
where children eagerly await
the decisive blow
that breaks open the piata,
releasing the treats inside.
the traditional way to build
one
starts with a clay pot
suspended from a string.
the piata-maker glues
cardboard shapes to it
and secures them by gluing
on pieces of newspaper.
then she covers
the rest of the pot.
when the glue dries,
she decorates the surface
with colorful paper.
the modern method is to use
a balloon instead of a clay
pot.
after inflating the balloon,
she pastes pieces of newspaper
all over it.
this technique is known
as paper-mache.
the trick is to completely
saturate the newspaper
with a thick paste
and make sure no part of
the balloon is left uncovered.
she continues this process
until she's built up two or
three even layers of newspaper
all over the balloon.
then she suspends it
from a clothespin to dry.
hours later, the paper-mache
is hardened into a shell
around the balloon,
which she now breaks
and removes.
next, she cuts an opening
at the top of the shell.
this is the hole
through which the buyer will
fill the piata with treats.
she'll later reattach the cut
piece to make a trap door.
but first, with the sharp tips
of her scissors,
she pierces a row of holes
along the circumference
and threads twine through
them.
she leaves long ends at the
top
with which to suspend
the piata.
this piata will be
star-shaped.
to make each point,
she rolls thin cardboard
into a cone, taping it closed.
she trims it
to the required size,
then cuts tabs at the base
and bends them back.
she makes seven
of these cardboard points,
then tapes them onto the shell
one by one.
once all seven are positioned,
the decorating with colorful,
glittery foil wrapping paper
can begin.
she tapes a sheet around
each point of the star.
then she applies glue
in between the points
and adheres pieces of wrapping
paper to those areas.
she folds other pieces
into flower shapes
and glues them on, as well.
once the entire piata
is covered,
she tapes matching streamers
to the end of each point.
historians believe
spanish missionaries
used star piatas like this one
to convert the native peoples
in the americas to
christianity.
the star symbolized satan,
its seven points,
the seven deadly sins,
its beautiful colors,
temptation.
wearing a blindfold
represented
blind faith in god.
striking the piata
with a stick meant goodness
and virtue battling evil.
breaking the piata, releasing
a shower of treats or
trinkets,
symbolized heavenly rewards.
narrator: human beings
have always generated garbage.
in the battle
to keep the streets clean,
the mechanized garbage truck
is a combat vehicle.
it crushes tons of trash
en route to deliver it
to landfills,
incinerators,
and recycling facilities.
without it, we'd all be
knee-deep in garbage.
garbage trucks have different
approaches to handling
garbage.
some load from the front,
other from the rear or side.
and some are entirely
mechanized
like this side-loader truck.
the operator inside the cab
barely needs to lift a finger
as the hydraulic lift-arm
does all the heavy work.
the garbage truck
has come a long way
since it hit the street
in 1952.
production
on a modern side-loader truck
begins with a welding robot.
the robot fuses
numerous steel supports
to the truck body floor.
these supports
will allow the truck
to hold up to the force of
tons
of trash being compacted
inside.
meanwhile, down the line,
other
parts like the roof and sides
take shape
in separate assemblies.
once they're complete,
they hoist the large steel
parts
into place
and assemble them
within a metal framework.
the framework serves as a
guide
to piece together
all the parts of the truck
box.
once assembled, the workers
clamp the parts together
to secure the assembly
as they weld the seams.
the garbage truck body is then
ready for the mechanized
parts,
beginning with a hopper.
it's equipped with
a powerful, hydraulic
compactor
to squeeze as much trash
as possible into the truck.
they fit the hopper snugly
to the front of the truck body
and weld it to it.
then they lift the tailgate
into position
at the rear of the truck box.
they hinge it to the truck
by sliding heavy-duty steel
pins
through brackets.
once hinged, the tailgate can
swing up and out of the way
to allow garbage
to be discharged.
the driving force for this
is a pair of hydraulic
cylinders
attached by brackets,
welded to the tailgate
at one end
and the truck body at the
other.
with that job done,
these cylinders
can now extend
to lift the tailgate
and retract to close it.
across the factory floor,
another team assembles
a pair of steel lift-arms.
these lift-arms are designed
for another kind of truck,
the front-end loader.
it's mainly used to collect
hefty commercial
garbage containers.
in action, these arms pivot
around the truck cab
and extend to the front to
fork
up the trash container
and deposit the contents
in the hopper.
hydraulic cylinders
also power these lift-arms.
when the task is complete,
the forks at the end of the
arms
fold back out of the way.
nearby, workers test
this rear-loader garbage
truck.
its tailgate is split
into two hoppers --
one for recyclables
and the other for trash.
hydraulic systems lift them
one at a time or
simultaneously.
collecting garbage
and disposing of it
can be tough
on a truck's paint job,
so they apply
an extra-durable finish.
they spray sealer
on the sanded outer surface,
followed by two coats
of epoxy paint.
after that,
they bake on the layers.
meanwhile, the truck chassis
has
arrived from another factory.
it's a standard size,
so they chop a piece off to
size
it for the garbage-truck body.
they install bracket plates
at the back
and slide thick pins
through the holes
to join the truck body
to the chassis.
using a crane, they lift the
automated side-loader truck
body
onto the modified chassis.
once it's installed,
they test the compactor.
dual hydraulic cylinders
push the ejector blade
to the back of the truck.
they test the tailgate --
which has by now been equipped
with signal lights, mud flaps,
and other parts --
and verify that everything
functions properly.
once a truck passes muster,
it's ready to handle
whatever garbage
society throws its way.
and with these automated
garbage trucks,
there's no need for anyone
to strain their back
or get their hands dirty,
because these robot arms
can handle it.
narrator:
high-performance cars
typically have ceramic
composite
brake disks
rather than
regular cast-iron ones.
that kind of power on wheels
requires being lightweight,
and cast iron is very heavy.
it would also wear out
too quickly
due to the intense heat
friction generates
when you brake a car
with such a powerful engine.
ceramic is heat-resistant
up to 1,830 degrees
fahrenheit.
therefore, these ceramic
composite brake disks
last about 60 times longer
than standard cast-iron disks.
ceramic composite means
the ceramic material silicon
is combined
with carbon fiber for
strength.
the disk factory
prepares the carbon fiber
by mixing two ingredients --
a heat-molded resin and
chopped
pieces of raw carbon fiber,
the strength of which
lies in the interweaving
of its miniscule
carbon filaments.
automated machines pour the
carbon fiber into aluminum
molds
in the shape of the disk ring.
the first filling station
fills
the mold cavity only halfway.
workers then fit a slotted
belt
around the mold
and insert aluminum cores
into the slots.
these cores will form
a ventilation channel
in the disk ring to keep
the disk from overheating.
now the mold moves on
to the next filling station.
it fills the remainder
of the cavity with carbon
fiber.
a roller levels the top.
then workers close up the
mold,
and a small press
pushes down the cover
to lightly compact the
contents.
the mold enters a large press
which applies 20 tons
of pressure
while heating to almost
400 degrees fahrenheit.
this compacts the carbon fiber
and transforms the resin
powder
into plastic.
once the mold has cooled down
enough to be handled,
workers submerge it in cold
water for five to eight
minutes.
this cools the disk ring
completely,
enabling them
to pull out the cores.
a computer-guided laser
then examines the mold
to make sure every last core
has been removed.
when they get the all-clear,
they open the top and bottom
sections of the mold
and extract the disk ring.
computer-guided machines
then smooth out the rough
areas
and drill
tiny ventilation holes.
they put the disk ring
into an oven
which, over the course
of two days,
gradually heats it to just
over
1,800 degrees fahrenheit.
this causes a chemical change
which transforms the plastic
into carbon.
next, they take a crucible --
a high-heat resistant
container --
and position five mounts
inside.
they place the disk ring
on the mounts.
then in the middle, a funnel,
into which they pour a ceramic
material, a fine silicon
powder.
then they load the crucible
into an oven for 24 hours.
it gradually heats the disk
ring
to more than 3,000 degrees
fahrenheit, melting the
silicon.
then it applies
low-level suction,
drawing the now-liquid silicon
into the disk ring.
this creates an exceptionally
hard new material
called silicon carbide.
after a computer-guided drill
bores mounting holes,
the disk ring
goes into a chamber
where it receives
a coat of protective paint.
the paint shields the carbon
in this disk ring from oxygen,
which is critical because at
high heat, oxygen burns
carbon.
this anti-oxidation treatment
significantly extends the life
of the brake disk.
the paint is cured in an oven,
leaving behind a white
residue.
a robot sands it off,
then polishes
the entire disk-ring surface.
here's what
the finished disk ring
looks like before it's cleaned
and polished...
...and after.
every single brake disk ring
undergoes
a meticulous inspection.
this sophisticated machine
takes thousands
of high-definition photographs
of the surface,
which a computer then analyzes
in micron-level detail.
to complete the brake disk,
they affix the bell,
a circular component
in the middle
which connects the brake disk
to the vehicle.
the bell is made of either
aluminum or stainless steel
and bolted into the mounting
holes in the disk ring.
--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...