>> narrator: manufactured
gemstones are typically designed
to imitate genuine mined
gemstones.
not these -- they're made from
heather, a hardy flowering plant
which grows wild across
scotland.
for centuries, scots used
heather to thatch roofs, stuff
mattresses, and even brew ale.
this scottish company turns
heather into gemstone material
for jewelry and other gift
items.
heathergems, as they're called,
have veinlike patterns created
randomly by the plants' stems.
therefore, no two gems can be
identical.
when the handpicked heather
arrives at the factory, its
green foliage still clings to
the upper part of the stems.
after cutting the plants into
lengths of about 10 inches,
workers load them into a
sandblasting machine.
the drum rotates for about half
an hour while tiny iron pellets
blast the heather inside.
the pellets chip away the bark
and remove the foliage.
the heather comes out of the
machine as bare, dried-out,
delicate wood.
workers form 1 1/2-pound bundles
and place them in a vacuum-die
chamber for two whole days.
first, the vacuum draws out the
air in the stems to clear the
way for the die to penetrate.
then, again under pressure, the
stems slowly absorb the dye.
this vacuum method is far more
effective than dipping or
soaking the stems in vats of dye
because the color penetrates
deeply into the heather wood
rather than merely sitting on
the surface.
they open the bundles and make
new ones of the same weight,
this time combining colors.
it's important to combine
thicker stems with thinner ones
to create contrasting lines in
the gem pattern.
next, they soak each bundle in
epoxy resin for two or three
minutes, ensuring the stems are
well saturated.
then they place the bundles on
racks to allow the excess resin
to drain off.
they load four bundles between
the top and bottom halves of a
mold.
a press then slowly closes the
mold, applying 88 tons of
pressure for about a minute.
they clamp the mold closed and
remove it from the press.
then they put the mold into an
oven for an hour to cure the
resin.
they open the mold and remove
what is now a rock-hard,
resin-bonded block of heather
wood.
they put the block on a band saw
and trim off the rough edges.
they cut slices between 4/10 and
5/10 of an inch thick, depending
on what shape gem they'll be
making.
after gluing each slice onto a
plastic backing, a robotic
cutting machine guided by a
computer cuts the gem shapes.
then workers simply pop the gems
off the plastic backing.
this domed oval shape is called
a cabochon.
the finishing team smooths and
polishes each gem on a belt
sander, then applies four or
five coats of clear lacquer.
lacquering draws out the colors
while sealing and protecting the
wood.
finally, they glue each gem onto
the jewelry or gift item.
sometimes they dye the heather
just a single color.
this still produces a striking
gem, because the dye penetrates
the wood with different
intensities, creating
contrasting shades.
the signature feature is the
unique veining produced by the
heather encased within, each and
every gemstone truly capturing
the natural beauty of the
scottish highlands.
>> narrator: invented in the
middle of the 20th century,
instant film made photographic
images materialize almost
magically.
the picture appeared in minutes.
no more waiting for days for
film to be processed.
today it's a digital world, but
instant film is still getting
plenty of exposure.
with instant film, you can watch
an image develop before your
very eyes -- no film lab or
digital printer necessary.
just say, "cheese" and wait to
see what develops.
many decades after its
invention, instant photo
development still seems like a
neat trick.
making the magic happen is a
many-layered process, one that
involves multiple materials and
chemicals.
production begins with the film
negative.
it takes place in the dark to
prevent pre-exposure.
the technician dons night-vision
goggles, allowing him to monitor
plastic film as it unwinds into
a coating machine.
inside, various dyes and
chemicals will transform the
film into a negative.
they switch the lights back on
briefly for our camera.
the film travels up and down
towards the coating machine.
it's a system that prevents any
slackening in the feed.
the coating is also done in the
dark, so this worker
demonstrates the process for our
camera on a small research
machine.
liquid photo chemicals and dyes
flow onto the surface of the
plastic film.
he spreads the liquids across
the film for an even
application.
this is all done mechanically
inside the real coating machine.
once coated, the film will head
into the dryer.
the various coatings will dry in
separate layers without
intermingling.
here's a test tube lineup of the
liquid components of the
negative.
the colorful ones are dyes, and
the white ones are other
chemicals.
they apply black backing to the
negative to block light, again
preventing pre-exposure.
the trip through the dryer is
87 yards long.
hot air dries the chemicals on
the surface of the film.
once again, it all happens in
the dark to protect the
light-sensitive film.
coiled up and packed into light,
tight drums, the color-negative
material is now on its way to a
second factory to be assembled
into the instant film pack.
upon arrival, they thread the
negative onto a machine, along
with other materials for the
film pack.
they include a plastic base
material called the mask and the
positive paper that receives the
photographic image from the
negative.
the various materials are
steered toward assembly stations
by a system of rollers.
here's a lineup of the various
materials to be assembled.
that's the mask on the far left
and the negative in the middle.
the negative heads towards a
series of hot presses.
one press laminates a plastic
spacer called the rail to the
negative.
another lamination head applies
the mask to the positive sheet
that will receive the image.
on a different machine,
equipment folds a kind of foil
pouch and injects it with film
developer.
here's an inside look at the
pouch.
the blue liquid is the
developer.
encased in the foil-lined
envelope, it will stay fresh
until needed.
back on the main assembly
machine, another hot press
laminates the developer pouch to
the other film materials.
this completes the film
sandwich, and it heads into
another station to be sliced
into photo-sized pieces.
the photo frames ride a wheel
with a counter that divides them
into stacks of eight.
meanwhile, robot arms deposit a
rectangular spring on a battery.
then they position the eight
pictures on the spring-battery
assembly, followed by a
light-blocking cover.
the stack then moves forward to
be squeezed into a plastic
cassette.
a suction type of device now
picks up a cardboard box and
transfers it to the end of the
film-pack line.
another device captures the film
pack as it comes off the line
and places it in the cardboard
box.
once folded closed, the box of
instant film rides the carousel
to a scale.
a quick weigh-in confirms
there's enough film in the box,
so it's ready to ship.
the assembly of this instant
film pack has taken roughly
three minutes.
now those instant memories are
just a few clicks away.
>> narrator: a common assumption
is that all white sugar is
derived from sugar cane, but 30%
of the world's white-sugar
supply comes from the sugar
beet.
while sugarcane grows only in
tropical climates, the hardier
sugar beet can be cultivated in
cooler regions and in poorer
soil.
it takes about 7 beets to
produce a little more than
2 pounds of sugar.
the by-products of processing,
molasses and beet pulp, are used
for animal feed.
the processing of sugar beets
yields various grades of sugar.
the lower ones are reprocessed
to become white sugar.
farmers plant beet seeds in the
spring and harvest the mature
crop in the fall.
mechanical harvesters attack six
rows at a time.
they rip the plant out of the
ground, chop off the leaves and
crown, leaving just the bulbous
root.
a beet root typically weighs
about 2 pounds.
17% to 18% of that is sucrose,
which is sugar.
a loader transfers the harvested
beets into trucks.
the loader's sieve removes about
a third of the soil along the
way.
when the trucks arrive at the
sugar factory, they unload the
beets, soil and stones included,
onto a conveyer belt which
transports them to a washing
station.
first they head into a revolving
drum, where, under a shower of
water, the beets rub against
each other, dislodging the soil.
the water flow floats the beets,
which then exit the drum.
the stones stay behind,
collected in separator buckets
along the edge.
a screw conveyer moves the beets
to a transfer system, which
brings them inside the factory
to be processed into sugar.
inside, slicing machines cut the
incoming beets into cassettes,
strips about the shape of french
fries but smaller.
the cassettes travel on a
conveyer belt into a large tank
of hot water, where they soak
for a few minutes.
this gets their cell membranes
to begin opening, clearing the
way for the sucrose to exit
during the next operation, in
which the cassettes are pumped
to the bottom of a 22-yard-high
extraction tower.
a rotating shaft within the
tower transports them slowly
upward against the downward flow
of hot water.
this draws out the sucrose,
producing a sugary water called
raw juice.
the next step is to purify this
in a giant kiln, they burn
raw juice.
limestone with coke to produce
in a giant kiln, they burn
the chemical compound calcium
limestone with coke to produce
hydroxide, also called lime
the chemical compound calcium
milk.
hydroxide, also called lime
they add it in several stages to
milk.
the raw juice.
they add it in several stages to
meanwhile, they press the
the raw juice.
sucrose-stripped cassettes into
meanwhile, they press the
pulp to sell as animal feed.
sucrose-stripped cassettes into
they add carbon dioxide to the
pulp to sell as animal feed.
lime milk-and-juice mixture.
they add carbon dioxide to the
this absorbs 1/3 of the juice's
lime milk-and-juice mixture.
impurities, enabling a
this absorbs 1/3 of the juice's
filtration system to remove
impurities, enabling a
them.
filtration system to remove
the raw juice exits as a golden
them.
sugar solution called thin
the raw juice exits as a golden
juice.
sugar solution called thin
the thin juice then enters a
juice.
6-step evaporation process,
the thin juice then enters a
which reduces it to a thick,
6-step evaporation process,
syrup-like juice.
which reduces it to a thick,
from there, they pump it into a
syrup-like juice.
4-phase crystallization system.
from there, they pump it into a
in phase 1, they heat and add
4-phase crystallization system.
sea crystals, tiny,
in phase 1, they heat and add
identical-sized sugar crystals
sea crystals, tiny,
made separately using a complex
identical-sized sugar crystals
cooling and evaporating process.
made separately using a complex
as the water in the juice
cooling and evaporating process.
evaporates, about half of the
as the water in the juice
sucrose crystallizes, growing
evaporates, about half of the
the seed crystals.
sucrose crystallizes, growing
then a centrifuge machine
the seed crystals.
separates the crystals, called
then a centrifuge machine
refined sugar, from the
separates the crystals, called
remaining syrup.
refined sugar, from the
the syrup goes through this
remaining syrup.
crystallization-centrifuge
the syrup goes through this
process three more times,
crystallization-centrifuge
producing a lesser grade of
process three more times,
sugar each time.
producing a lesser grade of
the factory dissolves and
sugar each time.
recrystallizes the lowest two
the factory dissolves and
grades.
recrystallizes the lowest two
the highest grades of sugar go
grades.
into dryers, on the way, passing
the highest grades of sugar go
through a screening machine
into dryers, on the way, passing
which separates any crystals
through a screening machine
which are too large.
which separates any crystals
the factory dissolves these
which are too large.
crystals, then puts the sugary
the factory dissolves these
liquid through the
crystals, then puts the sugary
crystallization process again.
liquid through the
so, in the end, there are two
crystallization process again.
grades of beet sugar which go
so, in the end, there are two
into silos, where they're stored
grades of beet sugar which go
until it's time to package them
into silos, where they're stored
for sale as refined sugar and
until it's time to package them
white sugar.
>> narrator: the electric car
ruled the road early in the 20th
century, and then the technology
was surpassed by gas.
today the concept is cruising
towards a comeback, its
resurgence fueled by concerns
about pollution from gas-powered
vehicles and by worries about
overdependence on foreign oil.
this sassy-looking sports car is
leading the charge for change.
just plug it into any electrical
outlet, and after a few hours,
it has enough juice for a drive
through the countryside or for
quite a few jaunts around town.
with no tailpipe, there are no
direct emissions, and if the
power generated by the
electrical plant is clean,
everyone breathes a little
easier.
but with the price tag in the
6-figure range, this
eco-friendly roadster is a
luxury product.
production begins with the first
half of the gear box.
a worker bolts a brass fitting
to the center and then attaches
plastic tubing to it.
the tubing will deliver
lubricant to the transmission's
bearings.
he inserts those bearings into
slots in the gearbox and presses
them into place using a
hydraulic tool.
he drips thread-locking compound
into screw holes and installs a
device for locking the
transmission.
it's called the parking pawl.
he applies more adhesive to
screws and threads them through
the pawl to the gearbox.
using a calibrated torque
wrench, he tightens them to a
precise setting.
the transmission is single speed
with four gears, which they
install in the other half of the
gearbox.
these are helical gears.
their teeth are cut at an angle
for gradual engagement and
smooth operation.
they're now ready for the rotor
and the stator.
both are electromagnets, and
together they'll be the electric
motor's driving force.
they insert the rotor into the
stator, where their two
electromagnetic fields will
interact to create torque,
transforming electrical energy
into mechanical energy.
they hoist the rotor-and-stator
assembly onto the gearbox and
bolt them together.
they attach cables for wiring
the motor to the
power-electronics module later.
it's a crucial part that
processes and regulates the flow
of battery power to the motor.
this completes the
electric-motor drivetrain.
they lower the drivetrain into
the back of the preassembled car
body.
they position the motor mounts
over slots in the steel
subframe.
and once in place, they bolt the
drivetrain to the chassis.
now, under the car, they pull
back the rear suspension
temporarily to attach the drive
axle to the gearbox.
the axle is equipped with a
rubber-encased joint that
allows a rear wheel to react to
bumps independently, without
reverberation to the other.
the battery is next.
seen here in a display model of
the powertrain, the metal pack
contains more than 6,800
lithium-ion cells and delivers
215 kilowatts of power, enough
juice to enable this electric
car to accelerate to 60 miles an
hour in under 4 seconds.
machinery now lowers the car
onto the battery, positioning it
in the front of the gearbox and
just behind the car seats.
they jack up the battery for a
precision fit.
they connect wiring for
low-voltage systems, like the
lights and fans.
and now the brains of the
electric car -- the
power-electronics module.
they install it on top of the
motor and battery and wire it to
both.
with all the wires connected,
the module is equipped to
convert dc power from the
battery to the ac power.
it will then supply that current
to the motor as the driver steps
on the accelerator.
with the vacuum system, they
drain air from the battery and
pump in liquid coolant.
coolant continuously flows
through the battery to maintain
an even temperature throughout.
the body panels are made of
durable, lightweight carbon
fiber.
and with the computer software
updated and the car now
completely assembled, it's time
for a test run.
as the sports car accelerates,
there's no throaty roar.
unlike a gas-powered engine, the
electric motor takes of quietly
and quickly.
if you have any comments about
the show, or you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications