>> a turbocharger harnesses a
vehicle's exhaust gases to
compress fresh air, forcing the
pressurized air into the
engine's combustion chamber for
a turbocharged performance.
with it, a small engine can be
as powerful as a larger one,
using energy that would
otherwise disappear out the
tailpipe.
the exhaust gas turbocharger is
an invention that dates back
over a century, but in recent
years the concept has literally
been picking up speed.
design tweaks and the use of
lighter materials mean a bigger
boost to engine output so a
small engine can be as powerful
as a larger one without guzzling
extra fuel.
production begins at the
foundry, an overhead sprayer
blows sand into the shaped
cavity of this box.
the spraying action activates a
binder applied to the sand.
this causes a chemical reaction
that solidifies the particles.
the worker extracts the hardened
sand shape from the box.
the shape is called a core.
it will be used to mold the
inside of the turbocharger's
housing.
he files down any little bumps
and rough edges.
he then pipes adhesive around
the border of a second sand mold
and glues the first part to it
to build up the core.
he applies a putty-like compound
to the seem to plug any gaps.
meanwhile, another worker uses a
different technique to make
smaller cores.
he rocks the box, and this
causes sand to flow into a
shaped cavity.
the sand has been mixed with
heat-sensitive chemicals.
he aims a flame at an opening in
the box as burners warm it from
the sides.
this triggers a reaction that
hardens the sand inside so it
takes the shape of the cavity.
the result is another smaller
turbocharger core.
these snail-shaped sand cones
are now ready for casting.
he places the cores in a mold
which is also made of hardened
sand.
machinery lifts the bottom half
of the mold to the top half,
essentially closing the mold.
he pores molten aluminum into
it, and it flows into spaces
between the cores and outer
mold.
the aluminum solidifies in a
minute, and the molds tumble
onto to a conveyor, revealing
the cast turbocharger parts.
they are connected by hardened
flow lines.
after separating the parts, they
ship them to the turbocharger
factory.
here, computerized tools carve
and contour the aluminum part
to specifications so precise,
they are measured in thousandths
of an inch.
this is the turbocharger housing
before the work was done...
and after.
using a computerized probe, a
technician looks for
irregularities.
even miniscule ones will need to
be fixed.
it's now time to assemble all
the parts.
the worker inserts a bearing
into one end of the iron center
housing.
he lubricates a second bearing
and slots it into the other end.
these bearings will ultimately
support a shaft with the turbine
on one end and a compressor on
the other.
he adds a metal collar and a
third bearing to the assembly.
he caps the bearing parts with a
metal plate.
it will keep lubricant from
spilling out when the
turbocharger spins.
he flips the center housing
around and installs a metal heat
shield on the bottom.
he inserts the shaft and turbine
wheel assembly.
he installs the compressor wheel
on the other end of the shaft.
he heats the wheel briefly,
causing it to expand, which
allows it to be pushed further
down the shaft.
once cold, it shrinks to the
shaft for a tight fit.
next, a machine called a
vibration sort rig spins the
compressor at a high speed as a
computer analyzes it for
vibrations.
even the slightest tremor
indicates an imbalance.
the computer also detects the
source of the problem so it can
be fixed.
he grinds the compressor nose
ever so slightly to balance the
part.
he now nestles the compressor
into the curled aluminum
housing.
it's a shape designed to funnel
air into the engine.
he secures the compressor to the
housing with a metal ring.
he fits the turbine end into its
housing.
it, too, has the distinctive
curl to pipe the exhaust gases
in the right direction.
a blast of air now simulates the
effect of those exhaust gases,
spinning the turbine to power
the compressor.
it takes about 15 minutes to
build one of these turbots.
once installed in an engine,
it's full speed ahead.
>> "enchilada" means dipped in
chili in spanish.
and true to its name, these
stuffed corn tortillas are
typically smothered in sweet and
mildly spicy chili sauce.
first cooked up by native
mexicans centuries ago,
enchiladas are an ancient food,
but they are definitely not
passe.
in modern times, the enchilada
has become a metaphor for having
it all.
"the whole enchilada" means
there's no holding back.
there are numerous enchilada
recipes today.
this black bean and veggie
version starts with a filling
sauce.
it's a chili-flavored tomato
puree.
they add organic corn, a firm
variety that's mildly sweet.
that means the flavor won't
clash with the chili spice.
spiraling blades fold the corn
into the filling sauce.
the mixing action is gentle to
keep the kernels intact.
the next ingredient is tofu
diced into cubes.
like the corn, it's a firm type
for a substantial texture.
the firm tofu is also quite
porous so it readily absorbs the
flavors of the enchilada filling
sauce.
they green up the sauce with
chunks of organic zucchini,
uniformly diced with the skins
on.
black beans are next, already
cooked with the juices drained.
this completes the enchilada
filling sauce.
they cool it to preserve its
thick consistency and overall
freshness.
and now they are ready to wrap.
they pump measured amounts of
the black bean and vegetable
mixture onto each tortilla.
and here the chilling of the
filling pays off.
a warmer, runnier sauce would
spill out and make a mess, but
this cool, thick sauce stays
where they put it, in the middle
of the tortilla.
workers now roll the tortillas
around the black bean and veggie
mix.
there is a trick to this.
if the tortilla is rolled too
tightly, there could be leakage,
too loose, and the enchiladas
could come undone.
a perfectly rolled enchilada
fits neatly into the trays.
they place the enchiladas
seem-side down in the container.
elsewhere in the factory, they
saute various chili powders in
flour and oil.
they liquefy this flavorful mix
with vegetable broth.
mixing blades blend the
simmering ingredients, and the
flavors intensify.
it thickens to a gravy-like
consistency.
and as one would do with gravy,
they strain out any lumps or
impurities.
what exits the sieve is pure
enchilada chili sauce.
next, it flows into a dispenser.
the nozzle head is the exact
same length as the enchiladas,
ensuring complete coverage as
the sauce is pumped on to them.
the enchiladas are now swimming
in chili sauce, imbuing the dish
with mild spice.
the chili sauce also serves to
keep the tortillas moist during
cooking.
they sprinkle on freeze-dried
chives.
this herb adds an onion nuance
to the dish.
every few minutes, they pull a
tray off the production line and
weigh it to confirm that the
portion size is right.
they churn out 53 enchilada
entrees a minute at this
factory.
next, it's into the freezer to
preserve the enchiladas at
arctic-like temperatures.
it's a new day and a new shift
of workers.
they place the enchiladas on a
conveyor en route to the
packaging line.
it takes just one minute to wrap
and box 75 frozen enchilada
entrees.
technology and humans team up
to get the job done fast.
enchiladas have come a long way
over the centuries -- from a
simple meal first whipped up by
the mayans of mexico to a
mass-produced frozen meal.
today, they are consumed in
countries around the world.
and with these frozen versions,
mealtime is no trouble at all.
just heat and eat.
>> the mechanism inside a
wristwatch that measures time
and moves the hands accordingly
is called the movement.
high-end watches typically use
traditional, very intricate
mechanical movements.
such premium watches are made up
of a multitude of components,
requiring hundreds of
manufacturing and assembly
operations.
luxury wristwatches are made of
top-quality materials, often
precious metals.
they are crafted with
painstaking precision, partly by
traditional watchmakers, partly
by high-tech machines.
the main section of the watch
case starts out as a block of
metal -- stainless steel for
this model.
a press stamps the preliminary
shape which a computer-guided
milling machine then finalizes.
another computer guided machine
drills a hole on the side for
the stem and crown, the manual
watch-winding mechanism.
this tool refines the edges.
next, using an abrasive tool,
they manually etch the surface
to give it a brushed metal
finish.
then they apply some polishing
compound and polish to a felt
buffing wheel and polish the
entire surface.
certain models undergo a second
polishing performed by a robot.
the two other parts of the watch
case, the back and the ring
around the watch face, called
the bezel, are made the same way
as this main section.
to produce the movement, they
cut a square brass plate and
stamp it into a preliminary
shape.
this computer-guided mill then
refines it to the correct
thickness.
the next computer-guided machine
makes several slots and holes.
this part, called the main
plate, is the base upon which
all the movement's components
will be assembled.
the milling process leaves
behind traces of metal dust and
oil on the surface, so the main
plate undergoes a thorough
washing with water and solvent.
once dry, a computerized
inspection device examines the
plate from three dimensions,
verifying that every last detail
is precisely as it should be.
then the last machine cuts the
final circular shape.
the main plate is now
technically perfect.
only finishing steps remain.
first, to remove tool marks,
they sand-blast the surface to
give it an even matte finish.
here's what the plate looks like
before sand-blasting and after.
another computer-guided tool
etches tiny circles onto the
main plate surface to produce a
pearl-like effect.
this next component, called the
bridge, covers most of the parts
assembled onto the main plate
and itself holes a number of
parts.
after a laser engraves the
company name, they fill the
lettering with varnish.
they put the bridge into an
automated machine that etches a
brush finish and wipes off the
varnish.
some varnish residue remains
inside the letters, making them
more visible.
next, a robot sets a jewel into
each hole in the main plate.
jewels are tiny, cup-shaped
synthetic rubies.
each will hold one of the
movement's moving parts in a
drop of lubricating oil.
after installing two barrels
containing a spring each, the
watchmaker positions four
wheels.
these form the gear train that
moves the hands of the watch.
next, he mounts the auxiliary
main plate on top.
this sandwiches the barrels and
gear train, holding them in
place.
then the escapement, the
regulating mechanism.
winding the watch fully coils
the springs inside the barrels.
the escapement paces the springs
as they slowly unwind and turn
the gear train.
now a robot takes over,
squirting a drop of oil in each
jewel.
meanwhile, a laser engraves the
watch brand name and logo into
the oscillating weight.
this component is a heavy metal
disk first stamped in a press
then refined by high-precision
computer-guided tools.
>> the oscillating weight is an
automatic winding mechanism.
this weight located on the back
side of the movement
automatically winds the watch as
it's on your wrist.
therefore, the more often you
wear the watch, the less often
you have to wind it manually by
turning the crown.
the watchmaker connects the
oscillating weight to the
springs which move the gear
train so that the weight will
shift backwards and forward with
any wrist movement,
automatically coiling the
springs.
on the front side of the
movement, he screws in the date
indicator and the dial.
the dial is comprised of two
brass plates, the top one coated
in oxidized copper with cutouts
to show the bottom one, which is
painted with this company's
secret formula of
glow-in-the-dark pigments.
next, a machine mounts the brass
hour and minute hands.
this operation is automated
because applying even slightly
too much pressure could damage
the tiny, delicate hands.
now for the watch case.
after twisting an arched ring
called the bezel onto the front
of the main case, he slides a
plastic gasket into it...
then positions the main case
onto to a press...
cleans the crystal...
then presses it forcefully into
the bezel.
the gasket seals the minute gap
between the crystal and the
bezel so that water can't seep
inside the case.
next, the stem and crown.
then on the back of the case,
the casing circle, a ring that
comes between the movement and
the case.
here, too, a gasket seals the
gap to make the case
water-resistant.
he installs the ring in crystal
that form the back of the case.
he applies grease so that it
twists on smoothly.
he closes it tightly with a
tool.
then the fully assembled case
goes off to be tested for
water-resistance.
if it passes, it comes back to
the watchmaker to receive the
movement.
he removes the crown and the
case back, cleans the movement,
then places it in the case.
next, he squirts grease in the
crown hole and reinstalls the
crown.
this time, because the movement
is in place, the crown stem
connects to the two springs so
that turning the crown now winds
them.
the watchmaker affixes the
movement in the case with
several tiny clamps and screws.
then he closes up the back for
the last time.
after checking that the movement
works properly, he has just one
last component to assemble to
the watch head.
this particular watch company
has developed a unique
protective device that goes over
the crown.
a computer-guided mill shapes it
out of the same type of metal as
the case so that, aesthetically,
it blends seamlessly.
the watchmaker screws the device
to the case so that it bridges
the crown.
the device has a lever, the
tension of which the watchmaker
carefully adjusts with the help
of this gauge.
the lever closes the device
tightly over the crown,
immobilizing the crown so that
it can't be turned accidentally.
finally, they mount the watch
head on an automated machine
which closes the back tightly.
this is critical for
water-resistance.
every single watch head this
factory manufactures must pass
several quality-control tests to
ensure time-keeping accuracy and
water-resistance.
for water-resistance, they first
test using air pressure.
then actual water tests.
first a low-pressure test in
four inches of water.
then a high-pressure test in 410
yards of water which far exceeds
the 328-yard depth to which the
watch is guaranteed to be
water-resistant.
finally it's time to assemble
and attach the watch strap,
either a link bracelet in
matching metal or strap made of
fine leather, a fitting finale
to this luxury wristwatch, the
elegant product of precision
technology and time-honored
tradition.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you would like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications