>> narrator: robots perform many
underwater tasks, which are
impossible or too risky for
divers to carry out, like
collecting samples from the
ocean floor for scientific
research, exploring shipwrecks,
inspecting underwater pipelines,
searching for planted
explosives, or recovering
bodies.
this particular underwater
robot is designed to find
unconscious drowning victims.
recent incidents have shown that
a person recovered within 90
minutes can survive without
brain damage when rescuers
follow a specific resuscitation
protocol.
the robot uses a protruding,
interlocking jaw to grab the
victim by a limb and haul him or
her to the surface.
its onboard camera gives
operators at the surface an
underwater view.
when the water's too murky to
see anything, video-enhancing
technology and imaging sonar
detect the outline of objects.
several thrusters propel the
robot through the water.
for each one, technicians
grease, then position a pair of
o-rings onto end caps that they
install on each end of the
thruster housing.
the o-rings seal the end caps,
keeping water out of the motor
located inside the housing.
the motor shaft protrudes
through propeller the end cap.
a mechanical bale secures both
thruster end caps to the
housing.
they fill the thruster with
oil.
this prevents the thruster from
imploding under pressure as the
robot descends deeper and
deeper.
after filling, they draw a
vacuum to remove any air bubbles
and draw the oil into every nook
and cranny.
then then install a reservoir,
which they also fill with oil.
when the underwater pressure
builds, this backup oil supply
fills any remaining miniscule
air gap the vacuum might have
missed.
they close the reservoir with
a sealing screw to prevent any
oil from leaking out.
now they turn their attention to
the thruster's main component,
a two-blade propeller made of
durable nylon.
it goes on the back end of the
thrusters.
they install the camera chassis
onto the robot.
this chassis also carries the
majority of the robot's
electronics, such as the
computer, communications
equipment, and lighting.
here they're hooking up the belt
for the tiny motor, which tilts
the camera to look up and down.
they cover the camera chassis
with a transparent, acrylic dome
called the viewing port.
a cap with an o-ring seal keeps
water out.
they install the robot's power
supply at the opposite end of
the robot, then encase it in a
metal tube, sealed on both sides
with an end cap and an o-ring.
for the thrusters to work at
maximum efficiency, the robot
must be neutrally buoyant,
meaning neither too light nor
too heavy.
so once the robot is fitted with
all its thrusters and
electronics, technicians install
the main float.
certain models have additional
floats.
they cap each propeller with a
vented cover called a kort
nozzle.
this isolates the water flow,
maximizing the propeller's
efficiency.
these bumper frames act like
bumpers on a car.
they absorb the force of impact,
protecting the robot from
damage when it encounters
underwater objects.
the bumper frames also serve as
a structure to attach lights and
other components, as well as
specialized tools, such as that
quick-release jaw, which grabs
the victim by a limb.
they install the jaw at an angle
so that it doesn't block the
camera's view.
now the sonar unit.
it also mounts to the bumper
frames.
the sonar projects a 130-degree
left-to-right 3-d image onto a
monitor at the surface, showing
the outline of objects around
the robot.
finally, at the top, they
install a strobe light -- a
flashing beacon that tells
rescuers on the surface exactly
where the robot is.
every underwater robot goes out
for a test drive.
they submerge it in a tank,
which is essentially an aquarium
inhabited by fish of the
stick-on variety.
these inanimate creatures adhere
to the glass, provide colorful
images on which testers can
focus and unfocus the camera.
from there on in, the first
mission in open water awaits.
>> narrator: there are many ways
to make lasagna, but no matter
how it stacks up, people seem to
never get enough of this classic
italian dish.
popular in italy for centuries,
its appeals transcends
boundaries and cultures.
who anywhere can resist all
those layers of flavor?
ruffled, flat noodles define
lasagna.
they give it structure.
in between the layers, the
possibilities are endless.
ingredients vary, depending on
the recipe.
for a veggie lasagna, things
start off with sautéed onions,
seasoned with pepper and salt.
they add pureed tomatoes to the
pungent mix.
blades stir the ingredients as
they simmer in this steam-heated
mixer, and in no time, they have
a full-body tomato sauce.
they pump the tomato sauce into
lasagna tubs.
this saucy base is the first
layer of flavor, but it also
serves a practical purpose,
preventing the noodles from
sticking to the bottom of the
tray during baking.
workers arrange the broad and
crinkled lasagna noodles over
the sauce.
these noodles have been made
from a blend of whole grain and
semolina flours for a texture
that's firm, yet tender.
now for the filling ingredients.
this factory lasagna will be
made of roasted, organic
vegetables.
they include chunks of broccoli
and uniformly mixed peppers,
onions, carrots, zucchini, and
mushrooms.
they load the sliced and diced
veggies into the next
steam-heated mixer.
the blades swing into action to
stir the ingredients as they
brown in oil.
this causes the natural sugars
to break down and the vegetables
to become sweeter.
creamy mozzarella cheese will
offset the sugary taste of the
veggies.
they add the caramelized
veggies, the shredded
mozzarella, and more pasta
noodles, building the layers of
flavor.
and there's a lot more to come.
over in another steam-heated
mixer, a combination of milk,
oil, and rice flour is on a low
boil.
paddles distribute the
ingredients, and the sauce
begins to thicken.
shredded monterey jack and
parmesan cheeses will enhance
the creaminess and add another
dimension of flavor.
next, a serious dash of nutmeg
and another one of salt spices
it up.
and after more stirring action,
the white sauce is velvety
smooth and substantially
thicker.
meanwhile, a worker shovels
crust into a grinder.
the crusts are broken pieces
from a pizza production line,
and they have been dried to a
specific consistency, so they
should grind up nicely.
a spiraling blade turns the
crusts into uniform crumbs -- a
classic lasagna topping --
adding a bit of crunch to the
recipe.
with these final ingredients,
they're ready to pile it on
thick.
as the layering process
continues, this meal really
comes together.
the cream sauce and bread
crumbs are the finishing
touches.
with numerous sous chefs
involved, things happen a whole
lot faster here than on the home
front.
they assemble 48 single-serving
lasagna dishes per minute at
this factory...
then place them on trays and
transfer them to a specialized
freezer.
this is a blast freezer, which
is also known as a shock
freezer.
it brings down the temperature
of foods very rapidly,
preserving the flavor.
on the next shift, they remove
the lasagnas from the freezer.
it's time to wrap up this meal.
the lasagnas ride a conveyer
through a curtain of cellophane.
an automated system heat-seals
the wrap around the trays.
things move swiftly to prevent
thawing.
they package 75 lasagnas per
minute on this line, and then
it's back in the freezer to
await shipping.
once something only mama made,
now workers and machines team up
to mass-produce this traditional
comfort food.
so at mealtime, one only has to
pop the frozen lasagna in the
oven, and then mangia.
>> narrator: from the home
workshop to the factory floor,
the band saw is one of the most
popular power tools around.
it's called a band saw because
the blade is a metal band with
teeth that moves continuously in
a loop around two or three
rotating wheels.
it can make straight, curved,
and angled cuts.
this is an industrial band saw,
designed to cut wood, aluminum,
and composite materials, such as
plexiglass.
it can cut pieces up to 12
inches thick and can divide a
board up to 40 inches wide into
two equal sections.
the tabletop tilts to a maximum
45 degrees for angled cuts.
it's made of sturdy cast iron.
the band-saw manufacturer
purchases it from a nearby
foundry, then uses a rotary
grinder to make the surface, as
we can see on the right, smooth
and shiny.
one of the saw's key components
is this lower bearing case.
it links the motor to the lower
of two cast-iron wheels, which
turn the saw blade.
workers will later mount that
lower wheel on one end of the
bearing case shaft.
now, on the opposite end of the
shaft, they mount the drive
pulley.
the motor will rotate the drive
pulley, turning the shaft and
consequently the lower wheel on
the opposite end, which moves
the saw blade looped around the
lower and upper wheels.
those cast-iron wheels,
meanwhile, need a rubber edge to
ensure the blade moves smoothly
and without slipping.
workers position a guide over
the first wheel, then slip a
rubber band onto the guide.
next, they coat both the edge of
the wheel and the rubber band on
the guide with contact cement
adhesive.
then they carefully pull the
rubber band off the guide, flip
it over, and press the glued
side against the glued surface
of the wheel.
the first wheel now has a
rubberized edge.
they repeat the same procedures
for the second wheel.
in the meantime, another
department has welded the band
saw's steel steal cabinet.
after the cabinet gets a paint
job, workers begin installing
the various components, among
them the support assembly for
the upper wheel.
behind the wall on which they
mount the upper wheel, down at
the bottom and protruding
forward through the hole in the
wall, they install the support
for the lower wheel.
this support is the shaft of the
lower bearing case, the side
opposite the drive pulley.
after mounting the lower wheel,
they move behind the wall,
install an electric motor right
below the lower bearing case,
and link the two with a pair of
belts.
so now when the motor runs, the
pulley rotates, and the lower
wheel turns.
next, they bolt in the
tabletop.
it tilts on trunnions -- pairs
of mating, cast-iron supports --
one attached to the table's
underside, the other to the
cabinet's table frame.
now for the most critical part
of the assembly process.
workers use this jig as a
precision guide to align the
wheels.
the wheels must be perfectly
balanced to keep the saw blades
stable while it's cutting.
once the alignment's complete,
workers remove the jig and loop
the steel saw blade around the
two wheels.
they adjust the blade to the
correct tautness by simply
setting the tension gauge to the
width of the blade.
and finally, the last step.
above the tabletop, they mount
bearings which guide the blade.
without these, the blade would
wobble or drift offline due to
the force of cutting through the
wood or other hard material.
now just a final check to ensure
everything runs smoothly and
make absolutely sure this band
saw is up to speed when it comes
to cutting construction
materials.
>> narrator: whether skiing down
a snowy slope or hiking up a
rocky one, pointed metal poles
can provide much needed support.
they add balance and rhythm to
both experiences.
aluminum poles were first
developed for skiing.
in recent years, the concept has
been modified for trekking
poles.
ski poles and trekking poles
look alike, but there are
important differences.
ski poles are one set length,
while trekking poles can be
extended as needed.
ski poles begin with hollow
shafts made of aircraft-grade
aluminum.
they bake them for up to 12
hours to stiffen the metal.
next, the poles travel between
rollers, which apply pressure to
straighten them.
the stiffening of the metal
beforehand is key here.
it ensures that the aluminum
doesn't snap during this
critical straightening.
they insert one end of the
ski-pole shaft into a device
that squeezes it down to
precisely tapered dimensions.
it's a shape that will better
resist breakage and will also
make the pole easier to swing.
an automated cutting tool
spirals into the shaft to even
the jagged edge.
another cutter spins around the
outside of the wider end of the
pole to trim it.
next, a machine punches a little
hole in that wider end.
the hole will serve as a guide
during the stenciling of the
trade name and artwork onto the
exterior.
with the ski poles tapered and
trimmed, they head into an
inspection station.
a supervisor scrutinizes each
one.
once he gives them the thumbs
up, they're ready for sanding.
the ski poles spin between two
sanding belts to remove dusty
residue and rough up the surface
so that the paint will adhere.
the poles now twirl on an
overhead rail as a spray gun
applies the paint.
an automated tool then squeegees
paint through stencils to
transfer designs and lettering
onto the poles.
each pass of the squeegee-like
tool applies a different color,
and this layering effect builds
up the designs.
the poles now head towards an
acid bath.
an electrical current ripples
through the acid solution.
this causes the poles to oxidize
for a scratch-resistant finish
called anodizing.
meanwhile, on the trekking
poles' production line,
machinery inserts long-wired,
bristled brushes into the
various shaft.
this roughs up the inner
surface.
it's a step that will enable an
expander device to grip it to
extend the poles.
next, a spray gun coats some
unfinished poles with clear
lacquer.
the owner of the factory now
surveys a lineup of ski poles.
he's on the lookout for smudges
or other flaws.
they meet his approval, and so
it's on to the next step.
a carriage moves each ski pole
forward towards a carbide tip
and presses the tip into the
tapered end.
with this tough tip in place,
the ski pole is now equipped to
pierce any hard snow pack.
next, a worker slides rubber
grips onto the handle end of the
poles.
like a big automated fist, a
hydraulic mechanism shoves the
grip more tightly onto the pole.
there are many different kinds
of grips, each with a different
look and feel depending on the
type of pole being made.
some ski-pole grips even have
clips for attaching gloves.
trekking-pole shafts now roll
down the production line.
an automated arm slides plastic
sleeves with carbide points onto
the lower shaft section.
a spinning tool drives part of
an expander mechanism into the
trekking pole's middle shaft.
this expander will allow the
pole to be lengthened or
shortened to the user's
preference.
machinery then inserts the other
part of the expander mechanism
into the lower shaft.
finally, a worker assembles the
parts, sliding one section of
the expander mechanism on the
other.
finally, she sharpens the tips.
and these poles are now ready
for action.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...