>> narrator: the first ice skates were invented in northern  europe ab
ago when people began lacing animal bones to the soles of
water. in 1592, a scotsman invented an  iron skate b
long, the sport of speed skating took off. these elite-level racing sk
are produced by a small company cofounded by a canadian speed
medalist in short track. every single pair is  cus
after measuring a skater's feet, a technician applies layers of
way one makes a cast for a broken limb, only here, each
parts. each cast serves as the  fi
boot. the plaster bandages take 5 to
at which point the technician carefully removes the mold one part at a time, then  rea
it with elastic bands. he surrounds the mold, called a  negative, wi
he then pours liquid plaster into the negative to produce a
the sand provides counterpressure so that the
outward and distort their shape. the plaster fully cures in an hour or two, at which point
negative mold can come off. then the technician mixes up
to make it easily visible against the dried, white
he applies it in select areas, touching up imperfections and tweaking the shape of the m
he files the toes and the rest of the contours smooth, producing the final shape of
boot. he labels the finished mold with the skater's name and puts it
the storeroom until it's time to begin constructing the skate
construction begins with boot lining. they staple
leather to the mold, pulling taut because any wrinkles in
skater's foot. next, they glue on the various structural pieces, such as
ankle padding. it's made of memory foam so it gradually forms to the
ankle and holds the shape. the next step is the most technically critical because
determines the angle of the skate blade. they apply epoxy-resin putty
the front and back of the sole and adhere two aluminum blade
then prop up the boot as the putty dries over the next four
once the putty's hard, they sand off the excess to lighten the
remainder. then they begin constructing the  outside of
first, they layer pieces of carbon fiber, a strong fabric
high-performance sports products. they tie the bottom piece a
the blade holders with strong thread and bind the layers with spray adhesi
next, they slip a plastic bag over the boot...   tie
and vacuum out the air. this tightly compresses the l
now they inject resin, a type of liquid plastic, and distribute
the resin impregnates the carbon fiber.  after a co
resin dries and hardens, leaving the carbon-fiber boot stiff and    durable.
next, they glue on the outside of the boot, made of vinyl. once the glue dries, they r
the plaster mold and stitch the vinyl in place.   they
cover, sew one side of it to the boot, and attach the other side with a hook
that way it hinges open and closed for lacing and unlacing
the final step is to attach the inline wheels, or steel blades,  to the bl
>> narrator: synthetic rubber was invented in 1909, but the
couple of decades. a shortage of natural rubber during world war ii spurred
development. a kind of elastic plastic, it
temperature extremes than natural rubber. synthetic rubber reinvented
wheel. we're talking about the rubber
tires for all kinds of vehicles are now made from it.  thi
used to make everything from garden hoses to golf balls. m
is now a computerized process, one that takes place under the
operator. he monitors numerous computer screens and live camera
the plan itself is 437 yards long.    there are
enormous storage tanks for the raw materials, as well as se
the raw materials include a petroleum-based liquid called
hexane. they pipe these ingredients through columns to boil off
residual water, essentially purifying them.  this i
demonstration of what happens next.    they comb
butadiene and hexane and add a catalyst. the catalyst triggers a
that changes the chemistry. the mix becomes polybutadiene, a kind of synthetic rubber
to make tires. adding another catalyst stops
moment. the white, milky liquid that
rubber. they now pump in chemicals to tailor it for a specific use,
this case tires. the additives will increase
a mechanized whisk stirs the additives into the liquid ru
they pipe the synthetic concoction into insulated st
inside, pumps mix it constantly so the additives don't settle on   the bottom.
he's a close-up look at the liquid synthetic rubber in a
it looks like a big vanilla milkshake, and it's about to be coagulated in
here's where it all happens. this coagulation unit is like a   big kettle.
they pipe in the liquid rubber, a solvent mixture, and water.
the rubber coagulates into crumbs the size of beans. the water remains because it
a higher boiling point. the mix of water and rubber c
known as the crumb tank until it's time for more processing.
rotary sieve. as it spins, it drains off the
they add more water to cool the rubber crumbs. the rubber and water mix gu
onto a conveyor which is a vibrating sieve. as the crumbs bounce along,
water drains off through the perforations in the conveyor.
lot like wet snow. next, it's into the lab, where
light through a sample to analyze the microstructure. i
continues. a screw-like mechanism presses the wet rubber crumbs against
metal plate to squeeze out more moisture.    another
vibrating conveyor drains off droplets.   then it'
spiral conveyor. as the synthetic rubber travels upwards on
is piped in from the side to dry it. now mostly de
but still sticky, the synthetic rubber crumbs head down a chute and into a baler
this machine uses pressure to compress the crumbs into big
the bales of synthetic rubber head down a conveyor towards a
this inspector examines them for imperfections.  once h
they head to the packaging station. as they travel through a
of plastic film, machinery heat-seals it around them. these bales of synthetic ru
have taken about six hours to manufacture.    and t
creation isn't much different from the real thing. like
melted and shaped into many different things. soon, this batch will be tu
into tires, and that's when the synthetic rubber will really hit    the road.
>> narrator: cocoa beans are the primary raw material for making   chocolate
they come from the fruit of the cocoa tree, native to central
the ancient mayans would grind them to make a special beverage   for marr
other rituals. today, cocoa is cultivated in
countries in the tropic. these cocoa beans from   c
without the use of chemical fertilizers, pesticides, or
farming cocoa organically requires meticulous care and
with grafting techniques to help establish disease-tolerant tree   varieties.
the farmer cuts a budwood, a young branch about to bud, from a healthy, p
grafts it onto a sucker growing from the base of a tree which is   either dise
unproductive. she cuts a slot at the top of the sucker, then wraps a
strip around the budwood to hold in moisture until the graft takes.
next, she cuts a pointed end on the budwood and inserts it into the slot she made in the
then she binds the union and covers it with a plastic bag.
against two potential extremes, dehydration and excessive rain,   which cau
if the graft takes, the union seals itself in a month or even sooner.
strategic pruning strengthens the tree and keeps it growing
to maintain and harvest. before long, flowers begin to
tiny beetles pollinate the flowers, after which tiny
begin to emerge. the pods grow and grow...
when the color transformation is complete, they're ripe for
there are many varieties of cocoa trees, with pods of
it generally takes about five months from first blooms to pod    maturity.
come harvest time, they collect only the pods which are   u
if a pod isn't fully ripened, the cocoa beans inside will be
they carefully cut the pod stem off the branch without damaging    the tre
the pod rind is a little over an inch thick.  it's rou
they hack it open with a machete to remove the fruit inside.
edible pulp encasing 30 to 50 large, white seeds.   the
the beans and pulp go to the fermentation area, where workers lay them in boxes, or heaps,
cover them for four to six days. as heat under the cover builds
the natural sugars interact with oxygen, the pulp slowly breaks
away. the color and chemical composition of the beans
and they become less acidic and develop a chocolaty taste.
beans. workers spread them out on big
sun for about a week.
here's what a cocoa bean is like wet...  versus dri
the dried beans now go through a selection process. worke
pod remnants and any beans with mold or other imperfections. beans which fail inspection
sold locally at a lower price or go to the compost heap.  be
bagged for export, and sold to chocolate makers.  depen
beans, which varies according to the cocoa-tree variety, it takes about 300 to 600 cocoa beans
produce one kilogram of chocolate.
>> narrator: chocolate owes its existence to the cocoa bean.
mexico and central and south america cultivated this
the spanish conquest brought this chocolate drink to europe, but it wasn't until 1847 that
british company invented solid chocolate. this factory makes chocolate
various forms and sells it to companies which manufacture
sale. it also supplies chocolate components, such as cocoa p
and cocoa butter. most of the cocoa beans arriving   here com
which grows 70% of the world's crop.   a conveyor
through a cleaning system, a series of sieves that screen out twigs, stones, and other
next stop is a micronizer, a revolving drum that heats the
shells. then they enter a shell-removing   machi
inside, successive rakes drag the beans across screens,
shell. then a vacuum sucks away the
removing the shell exposes the inside of the cocoa bean, which   is called
the factory will roast the nibs to develop their flavor.
which is cocoa butter. to make chocolate, they'll
butter, and sugar, along with milk powder if they're making
first, the factory processes the nibs by grinding them. t
the cocoa butter, producing pure liquid chocolate called
the factory extracts some of the cocoa butter to sell it sep
ingredient and to use for in-house chocolate production along with other ingredients
various proportions. the dark-chocolate recipe, for
chocolate liquor, sugar, and cocoa butter, but no milk po
the recipe for unsweetened chocolate contains no sugar. the mixer blends the  ing
to the consistency of a very thick cake batter.   the
point, but the coarse texture needs to be smoothed out, so the  chocolate m
machine, passing between a set of five rollers that reduce the particle siz
within just minutes, the chocolate leaves the refiner as   a fine, dry
but now it needs to be reliquefied, so the next stop is    a machine
the friction and heat once again activate the cocoa butter, returning the powder to a l
state. at this point, they add more
the viscosity to the exact thickness they need -- just a
making chocolate chips or much more if they're making a thin
for chocolate chips, the conch feeds a machine called a drop
as the name implies, it deposits drops of chocolate onto a co
the nozzle trays are interchangeable, so the machine can be set up to produce
sizes of chips, disks, or other shapes. the chocolate chips, still
and soft, enter a cooling tunnel... traveling for about five
through several temperature zones, which vary between 30 and 50 degrees f
by the time the chips exit the tunnel, they're hard. a conveyor belt then takes
through a metal detector, a standard food-safety precaution.    the f
10-pound, bulk-format chocolate bars.  a depositor
plastic molds. the conveyor transfers them to an elevator system, which m
through a cold room for about two hours.  this con
optimal air circulation, helping the cooling process.
chocolate shrinks slightly as it
cools, so the bars pop out of
the molds easily.
to make the chocolate look as
good as it tastes, the factory
cools, then reheats the liquid
chocolate before depositing it.
this process, called tempering,
promotes the growth of the most
stable cocoa-butter crystals,
making the surface of the
chocolate smooth and shiny.
--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...