narrator:
the origin of facial tissue
may be japanese.
a 17th-century historical
account describes japanese
blowing their noses
in small, soft papers,
then throwing them
on the ground.
modern-day tissues were first
marketed in the early 1920s
as a disposable cloth
for wiping off cold cream.
while some sneezers still prefer
traditional cloth handkerchiefs,
the disposable paper tissue
is the implement of choice
with the sniffling
and lens-cleaning masses.
this brand is made
entirely of recycled paper --
specifically,
used computer-printer paper
because its short, flexible
fibers produce soft tissue.
the ½-ton bales go into a giant
machine called the pulper.
it breaks up
the paper into fibers
and mixes them with water.
the result is called pulp.
next, it injects the pulp
with air.
this causes the ink
to detach from the fibers
and cling to the air bubbles,
which rise to the top
and drain off.
the machine then feeds
the now-ink-free pulp
through several rollers.
like an old-fashioned
ringer washing machine,
the rollers squeeze out
the dirty water.
a screw conveyor
then breaks up the pulp
and moves it
to the next station,
which rinses it
with clean water.
now the pulp is ready
to become tissue.
that transformation begins
in the paper machine.
it injects the pulp evenly
across the screen conveyor belt.
then the pulp passes
through rollers
that press out the water.
the extracted water drains
down through the screen.
the pulp then passes
through a hot-air dryer
and exits the machine as a thin,
10-foot-wide sheet of paper.
each jumbo roll
coming off the machine
contains
about 37 miles of paper.
the converting machine
is the giant contraption
that now transforms
this paper into tissues.
the first station unwinds
two rolls of paper,
applying modest tension
to remove waves and wrinkles.
the next station mates
the two papers,
producing a two-ply sheet.
the following station holds
the sheets steady with suction
as a knife slices across it
every 8½ inches.
you can see the cuts
in slow motion.
at the next station,
these two-ply sheets meet up
with two-ply sheets coming
from the opposite direction.
here's what that looks like
in slow motion....
and at full speed.
the sheets enter a mechanism
that folds them in half
in an interlocking fashion.
in slow motion, you can see
how they interlock --
each sheet folded in half,
one side inserted
into the fold of the next sheet.
this happens at a speed
of 16 folds per second.
this produces a huge stack
of folded tissue 5 feet wide.
the next station separates
the big stack into small ones
in preparation
for the final cutting.
each smaller stack contains
the precise number of tissues
the tissue box will contain,
from 80 to 250 sheets, depending
on the format they're packaging.
the smaller stacks now travel
to the next station,
where an automated circular saw
cuts every 8 inches,
producing the final tissue size.
the interlocking folds ensure
that when you pull out
one tissue,
it draws the next
out of the box, ready to use.
to produce three-ply tissues,
the converting machine
processes six rolls
into two sheets
of three plies each,
then folds them in the same
interlocking fashion.
the finished tissues travel
by conveyor belt
to the automated packaging line.
a robot with multiple
suction-cupped arms
grabs flattened boxes
one at a time, opens them,
and lines them up
on another conveyor belt
running alongside
the tissue belt.
an automated arm
compresses the tissues
and slides them into the box.
the next station glues
the flaps closed.
the top of the box
has a removable tab
with clear plastic film
underneath.
a tight slot in the film
makes grabbing a single tissue
a nonissue.
narrator:
hitching a travel trailer
to your vehicle
is the ideal solution
if you yearn to travel freely
with all
the conveniences of home
or love camping
but want far more comfort
than a tent has to offer.
today's trailers come equipped
with beds, mini kitchen,
dinette, toilet, and shower.
this 16-foot-long travel trailer
is made of aluminum
and composite materials.
unlike traditional
fiberglass trailers,
there's no steel or wood
in the structure,
so it's resistant
to both rock and corrosion.
it's ultra lightweight and has
a pop-up roof with windows.
the trailer's a-shaped chassis
is made entirely of aluminum.
the only steel components
are the tongue
that attaches the trailer
to the vehicle's hitch
and the axle.
workers insulate both
with duct tape.
they bolt the axle, with brakes
installed, to the chassis,
then line the chassis
with styrofoam insulation.
this prevents the copper propane
line from touching the aluminum.
contact between the two metals
can trigger corrosion.
next, they mount
the trailer's plastic freshwater
and waste-water tanks,
then glue the aluminum floor
to the chassis.
other workers construct
the trailer's two side walls
as a single piece.
on a large vacuum press,
they spread glue
onto an aluminum sheet.
then they lay down
the wall's core,
a honeycomb-shaped sheet
of polypropylene.
they coat it with glue,
then top it
with another sheet of aluminum.
the honeycomb core makes
the wall rigid
while adding minimal weight.
they cover this sandwich
with a protective fabric sheet,
then with an airtight cover.
after sealing the perimeter,
they vacuum out the air
for about four hours.
this pulls everything tight,
compressing the glued layers
so that they fully adhere
to each other.
when the wall comes
out of the press,
they lay down templates
and, with a router,
cut it into two side walls.
they also make openings
for windows...
...and holes for trailer lights.
after inserting a rubber seal
in each hole,
they install the lights.
next, a porthole-style
tinted upper window.
they glue it
into the round opening
just like a car windshield.
the side walls are now ready.
workers affix them to the floor
with an l-shaped
aluminum bracket.
once the walls are up,
workers saw out a door opening,
then install the door,
sliding windows, toilet cabinet,
king-size bed, dining table,
and kitchen unit,
which has
a sink and propane stove.
they install
a rubber-sealed trapdoor
into an opening in one wall.
this gives outside access
to a storage area
about the size
of a large suitcase.
upholstered cushions hide
under-the-seat
storage compartments
in the dining area.
they construct the roof
the same way as the walls,
only in a teardrop-shaped
vacuum press.
this aerodynamic shape creates
75% less drag
than a traditional box-shaped
trailer roof.
when the trailer is parked,
you can raise the roof to reveal
fixed windows on both sides.
workers glue
this tinted, tempered glass
to each aluminum window frame,
glue the frames to the roof,
then install taillights,
roof vents, and solar panels
to recharge the battery powering
the lights,
vent, and water pump.
they install the roof,
then mount a hinged back wall.
with assembly finally complete,
workers apply decals and test
all appliances and systems.
cables connect the roof
to the back wall,
so when the roof lifts,
it pulls up
the otherwise-collapsed wall.
the trailer's interior layout
is versatile.
the king-size bed converts
into two twin beds,
and the dining table
can be moved
to create
two distinct dining areas,
a two-seat
and a five-seat dinette --
all the comforts and amenities
of home on wheels.
narrator: there's nothing
like a pair of slippers
to soothe your tired tootsies
or warm your frigid feet.
designed strictly
for indoor use,
slippers typically have
a soft sole and looser fit
and are made of supple,
often cushy materials
so that feet feel
comfortable and cozy.
this style of slipper
is known as charentaise,
named after the region of
charente in southwestern france
where they originated
in the 17th century.
the slippers are made
primarily of felt,
which is made from layers
of compressed wool fibers.
this french slipper factory uses
a particularly thick and durable
type of felt
composed
of five wool-fiber layers.
to cut the soles,
workers position
a cookie-cutter-type die
for the specific shoe size
in production.
then a 5-ton press forces it
through the thick felt.
after cutting
one sole of the pair,
they turn the die
in the opposite direction
to cut the second sole.
once the batch of soles is cut,
they mark the size in ink
with a rubber stamp.
for the rest of the slipper,
called the upper,
they use fabric
that's felt on the outside,
velvet on the inside.
the cutting process
is the same as for the sole,
with the die corresponding
to the size in production.
once the uppers are cut,
workers lay a stencil of the
embroidery pattern on each one
and lightly mark
the design in pencil.
seamstresses embroider
each slipper individually
by a machine.
the yarn is made of hemp.
for this model, the design
is applied in a chain stitch.
felt flowers give the design
three-dimensional features.
with the design complete,
it's time to stitch
the back of the upper closed.
next, they cushion the opening
at the top with velvet binding,
bending the wide velvet ribbon
over the edge of the felt
so that the binding runs along
both the inside and outside
of the slipper.
they cover the back seam
with a backstrap,
a felt strip
with a loop at the top
through which you can
put your finger
to easily pull the slipper
onto your foot.
next, they turn
the back of the upper inside out
in order to attach the sole.
they position the sole 3/10
of an inch from the bottom edge,
then, with hemp thread,
straight-stitch along the entire
perimeter of the upper.
they cut the slipper's insole
from a fabric
that's felt on one side
and velvet on the other.
they position the felt side
against the felt sole,
then sew them together
along the perimeter
with a particular
cross-shaped stitch
traditionally used
for the charentaise.
the inside felt's underside
gives the slipper
additional rigidity,
while the soft velvet surface
cushions
the bottom of your foot.
the slipper
is now fully constructed.
however, it's inside out.
so the next step is to
turn the slipper right side out
using this piece of equipment
called a goat,
perhaps because its shape
resembles goat horns.
all that manipulation
can slightly deform
and crease the upper,
so they put the slipper
in a steam box
for three minutes
to soften the fibers,
then on a foot-shaped
aluminum press
heated
to 158 degrees fahrenheit.
the press irons out
any remaining wrinkles
and resets the shape.
this factory's
charentaise-style slippers
range from conservative
to funky.
all are designed
to be comfortable, cozy,
and as the term "slippers"
implies, easy to slip on or off.
narrator: the development
of the motorcycle helmet
happened by accident.
in 1935, the british war hero
known as lawrence of arabia
died from a head injury
in a motorcycle crash.
he wasn't wearing a helmet.
that tragedy moved
one of his doctors
to research the safety potential
of motorcycle helmets.
the motorcycle helmet
is the most important part
of the motorcyclist's
safety gear.
today, wearing one
is a rule of the road
in many places around the world.
modern helmets
are entirely synthetic.
they design them on a computer.
the software guides
milling tools
to produce a prototype
from polyurethane foam.
the prototype gives them
a good look
at the helmet's shape and style.
once they're satisfied with it,
they build a metal mold
for mass production.
the molding material is
a pile of polycarbonate pellets.
it's the same thing used to make
astronaut bubble helmets.
an injection molding machine
melts the pellets
and injects them
into the two-part helmet mold.
the polycarbonate cools
and solidifies
into the shape of the mold.
the result is
the outer shell of the helmet,
complete with holes
for vents and other parts.
next, a robot grips
the helmet's shell
and moves it
against a sanding belt
to smooth the seam
left by the mold.
the robot also gives the shell
an overall polish.
it then goes for a spin
as sprayers coat it
with black paint.
a factory employee pulls
a sheet of decals through water
to lift them from the backing.
she applies the decals
to a white, unpainted helmet.
it's a flashier look
than basic black.
it takes practice to be able
to apply the decals correctly
because the helmet surface
is complex and curvy.
she smoothes out air bubbles
in preparation
for the application
of a protective clear coat.
the next assembler installs
a pivot mechanism
on each side of the helmet.
they'll enable
the face shield and visor
to be raised and lowered.
the hardware fits perfectly
into the molded niches.
there's just enough room
for the mechanism
to operate smoothly.
she attaches
the velour-lined chin strap
with its quick-release mechanism
to the outer shell.
then these foam polystyrene
pellets are transformed
into the helmet's
cushioning inner shell.
the pellets flow into another
injection molding system.
a nozzle injects the melted
polystyrene into the mold,
and it takes the shape of
shock-absorbing helmet liners.
the foam solidifies,
and the machine ejects
the completed liners.
the density
of the polystyrene foam varies
throughout the helmet
for strategic shock resistance,
enabling it to meet
international
safety requirements.
padding in the crown
and around the chin area
makes it
more comfortable to wear.
they now join the helmet's
inner shell to the outer one.
after a liberal application
of glue,
she pushes the liner
into the shell.
it's a snug fit,
and it takes a bit of
maneuvering to get it in there.
she attaches a robust chin guard
to the helmet.
this molded polycarbonate part
is designed
to protect the lower half
of the rider's face.
the assembler screws it
to the helmet on both sides.
with this part in place,
the rider should be able to take
it on the chin if necessary.
a transparent
polycarbonate face shield
completes
this motorcycle helmet.
and now a test.
they drop a helmet
from a height of 10 feet
to confirm it can take a fall
without falling apart.
it survives, and the entire
production batch is approved.
designed for impact
and made to specification,
this helmet could
just save your skull.
if you have any comments
about the show
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop up a line at...
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications