-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
the best way to protect
your bicycle against theft
is a heavy-duty lock.
a u-lock is
the most secure option.
unlike a cable or chain lock,
you can't quickly sever a u-lock
with a pair of bolt cutters.
it takes
large conspicuous tools --
not something a thief can likely
get away with unobserved.
u-locks come in various sizes
so that you can lock your bike
to different structures
from thin bike racks
to thicker tree trunks.
the shackle and lock are made
of hardened high-alloy steel,
which is resistant to cutting,
sawing, and twisting.
to shape the shackle,
workers load steel bars
into a computer-guided
bending machine.
the machine applies
more than 25 tons of force
to bend the bar
in the shape of a "u".
the machine also notches
each end of the shackle.
these notches are what receive
the locking bolts.
to make the steel hard enough
to be tamper-proof,
they send the shackle
to an outside facility
for heat treatment.
this demonstration re-creates
a small part
of that complex process,
which is to heat the shackle
to almost
1,500 degrees fahrenheit
to rearrange
the molecular structure,
cool it in oil
to set the hardness
of that rearrangement,
then reheat
at moderate temperature
to restore the flexibility
the steel lost
due to the previous steps.
when the shackle returns
to the factory,
a laser machine
precision measures
and, if necessary,
corrects the dimensions
as per specifications.
then the shackle is dipped
in durable anti-corrosion paint.
once the paint dries,
and automated machine slips
a pvc tube over the shackle.
next, they screw
a plastic bracket
to one end of the shackle.
this connects
to a corresponding bracket
you screw to your bike frame
to mount the lock on the bike
when you're cycling.
the rectangular block
that houses the locking system
is called the lock body.
it, too,
is made of hardened steel.
an automated press punches holes
on the ends for the shackle
and in the middle
for the lock cylinder.
the locking system has a housing
in the center for the cylinder.
workers mount two metal plates
over it.
when you insert
the security-coded key
in the cylinder and turn,
the cylinder rotates
within the housing
and the plates move apart,
triggering other components
to lock the inserted shackle.
the cylinder is made of brass,
a relatively soft metal,
so there's an impenetrable
steel plate on top
to prevent a thief
from drilling into it.
workers give the cylinder
grooves a squirt of grease --
the housing, as well --
then insert pins
into the grooves.
these act as blockers,
preventing the wrong key
from opening the lock.
with the correct key,
they give way,
enabling the cylinder to rotate
within the housing.
this spring applies tension
to the cylinder's steel
and drilling plate,
keeping it in position
so that the key inserts
easily into the cylinder.
on each side, workers insert
a lever and bolt.
when you turn the key
to the locked position,
the lever pushes the bolt
into the shackle's notch,
immobilizing the shackle.
this component spring-loads
the bolt
to prevent the inserted shackle
from popping out
prior to being locked.
a pneumatic machine inserts
the locking system
into the steel lock body.
a two-tone plastic cover gives
the u-lock a snazzy appearance
and makes the surface easier
for the cyclist to grip.
here's how the lock works.
when you turn the key,
the cylinder rotates.
this moves the two plates
over it outward,
triggering the levers
on each side
to hold the bolt
in the shackle notch,
locking the shackle in place.
every lock undergoes
an opening and closing check.
random samples are subjected
to more extensive
quality-control testing.
it takes 13 tons of cutting
force to break the steel --
far more than even this
larger-than-typical bolt cutter
can apply.
this torsioning machine
measures how much twisting
the u-lock can withstand.
a bike-robber
would have to apply
more than 350 pounds
of force with a crowbar.
the bike owner, on the other
hand, needs only the coded key.
narrator:
the native north american tepee
was designed to be a home
where the buffalo roamed.
centuries ago,
tribes were constantly
on the move hunting the buffalo,
which was their main source
of food.
easy to pack up and reassemble,
the tepee served
as a portable shelter
for this nomadic lifestyle.
today, people are rediscovering
the appeal
of a cone-shaped tent
with a cook fire inside,
and that's put the tepee
on the comeback trail.
no need to hand-stitch tepees
anymore.
today, they produce them
at a factory
using
industrial sewing machines.
they start with the front panel.
it's three layers
of canvas and vinyl.
they sew details like pockets
for poles to open smoke flaps
and rectangular patterns
to prevent stretching
and tearing
from holes for lacing
the front of the tepee together
when pitched.
the sewer now chops through
the three layers of fabric
with a chisel
to make those holes.
another sewer stitches strips of
buffalo hide to the door opening
to make it more rugged.
using a pattern as a guide,
the next worker cuts
another panel on a slight curve.
he then pieces together
panel after panel
to construct
the rest of the tepee cone.
he reinforces the hem
with heavy nylon webbing.
he tucks loops between
the webbing and the fabric
and secures them
with more stitching.
the loops will be used to stake
the tepee to the ground.
the team stretches out
the completed tepee cover.
an artist maps out some lines
for painting on the fabric.
there's 73 yards of it.
it becomes a huge canvas
for traditional artistry.
the designs are
southwest american in style
and highly symbolic.
circles can represent
phases of the moon or the sun.
a sample of the artwork
has been drawn up beforehand
for the client, and the artist
refers to it as she works.
she brushes exterior latex paint
thinned with water
around the perimeter
of the designs.
then she soaks up paint
onto a pad
and presses it to the fabric
within the painted lines.
this avoids brushstrokes
and produces a flat finish
that almost looks like dye.
with the artwork complete,
the tepee cover now makes
a colorful statement.
outside, an employee shaves
the bark off young trees
to prepare the poles.
there are 17 per tepee.
each one is 27 feet tall --
the height
of a two-story building.
a two-person team now arranges
three of the poles
in a specific sequence
to build the tripod
that is the basic framework
of the tepee.
the assembler lashes the poles
near the top
with thick rope
and a tight knot.
he leaves a length of rope to
dangle as they raise the tripod.
the rope will come in handy
later on.
the arrangement situates
the door pole
east towards the rising sun
and away from westward winds
that could interfere
with the cook fire.
the team props up
the remaining poles
between the main tripod poles.
the first two groups of poles
form the front of the tepee,
and a third group forms
the back.
the assembler grabs the rope
that still dangles
from the central tripod,
and, from the ground,
winds it around all the poles
where they meet at the top.
the last pole is called
the lifting pole.
it's used to lift the painted
tepee cover to the wood frame.
they unbundle the cover
and wrap it around the poles
like a blanket
around a person's shoulders.
once the fit is nice and snug,
he laces the front panels
together
using willow branches
for lacing pins.
there are 18 pins in total
fastened above and below
the doorway.
he pegs the canvas to the ground
and then installs two last poles
for opening and closing
the smoke flaps from the ground.
traditional in design
with modern-day materials
and construction,
the tepee is still an idea
worth pitching.
narrator: "croissant" is
the french word for "crescent."
this flaky, curved roll is
generally associated with france
even though many food historians
believe
its origins are austrian.
regardless
of where it came from,
the croissant is
a popular breakfast pastry
in many parts of the world.
plain, with jam,
or dipped in a cup of coffee,
there's nothing like the light,
flaky texture
and buttery flavor
of a croissant.
this commercial bakery makes
its croissants
with soft-spread margarine
in lieu of butter.
the other ingredients are yeast,
very cold water --
because warm water
would trigger the yeast
to react prematurely --
sugar, a touch of salt,
and white all-purpose flour.
all the ingredients
go inside an industrial mixer
for 10 minutes --
first at slow speed to blend
everything and form the dough,
then faster to knead it.
next, the sticky, elastic dough
enters the multi-roller machine.
as an automated dispenser
lightly dusts the dough
with flour
to prevent it from sticking
to the equipment,
a series of 16 rollers
progressively flattens the dough
into a thinner
and thinner sheet.
the next process, lamination,
is what creates
the croissant's flaky layers.
the first station on this line
extrudes 44-pound blocks
of margarine
into a 2/10-of-an-inch-thin
sheet.
the next station lays
the margarine sheet
on top of the thin dough sheet
then folds the ends of the dough
upward,
enveloping the margarine.
then rollers compress
the overlapped dough ends
to seal the margarine inside
and flatten the whole thing down
to about 4/10-of-an-inch thick.
the next station repeatedly
folds the dough over itself,
then, with rollers again,
presses the layers
into a thin sheet.
this laminating cycle repeats
over and over again
until each dough block
coming off the line
comprises 243 layers.
plastic wrap keeps the dough
moist
as it now undergoes
eight hours of refrigeration.
the cold re-hardens
the by-now softened margarine
and lessens
the dough's elasticity.
the dough is now ready
for the automated machine
that forms the croissants.
the first rollers progressively
flatten the connected blocks
into a thin sheet.
then another roller runs over
the dough horizontally
to expand the sheet
to the required width.
next, cutters divide the sheet
into seven thin bands,
each one four inches wide.
then a roller surfaced
in triangular blades
cuts each band of dough
into triangles.
a robot separates the triangles
and turns them all
in the same direction
with the flat side forward.
a stopper running the width
of the conveyor belt
aligns the triangles
in straight rows
for the next station,
inside which
a device rolls each triangle
into the shape of the croissant.
the bakery's two forming
machines
output 50,000
raw-dough croissants per hour.
next stop -- the proofer,
a steam chamber inside which
the heat and high humidity
activate the yeast.
the dough rises,
and by the time the croissants
exit an hour later,
they've doubled in size.
they now bake for 14 minutes
in a tunnel oven
at a temperature
of 350 degrees fahrenheit.
the moisture in the dough
evaporates,
the resulting steam, along with
the melting margarine,
producing air bubbles
which separate the layers,
creating
that signature flakiness.
the croissants
are now fully baked,
golden brown, and fragile.
soft rubber suction cups
delicately transfer them
to a conveyor belt.
the belt leads
to a spiral tower.
by the time the croissants
descend to the bottom,
they've completely cooled.
as they travel to packaging,
a quality inspector pulls
any misshapen croissant.
a multi-tasking robot slaps
an adhesive label
on plastic bags,
counts out and drops in
two dozen croissants,
then securely seals the bags
to lock in the freshness
until the croissants reach
your breakfast table.
narrator:
thousands of years ago,
someone invented the wheel.
in 1970, this fundamental
invention was applied to luggage
thanks
to an american luggage executive
who came up with the concept
while carrying heavy bags
on a trip.
by the 1980s, virtually
all luggage had wheels.
today, we take rolling luggage
with us everywhere we travel.
they take the heavy lifting
out of a trip
so it feels more like
a vacation.
these hard-shell rolling bags
start
with polypropylene pellets.
it's a synthetic material.
they add a small amount
of colored polypropylene pellets
to the uncolored ones.
they'll act as a dye
for the batch.
they allow the mix
to dry for an hour,
getting rid of humidity that
would freeze in icy temperatures
and cause the luggage
to fracture.
they mix and melt
the polypropylene pellets
into a thick blue liquid.
then it's over to the injection
molding system.
the molds close
and a nozzle injects
the liquid polypropylene.
the molds are equipped
with a cooling system
so that the polypropylene
hardens almost instantly
into a lightweight
yet durable material.
a pile of pellets becomes
half of a luggage shell
in mere seconds.
a robot transfers the molded
shell to the next station.
an employee glues
the company logo into a slot.
to ensure it really sticks,
it's over to the logo machine.
it uses hydraulic energy
to press the logo
firmly into position.
he now screws a service handle
into its molded slot.
this handle is for those times
when the traveler has to lift
the bag by hand, up stairs,
or onto a baggage belt.
these triangular molded parts
are the side feet.
they'll keep the luggage
upright.
he fastens them
onto the base of the shell.
it's time to close this bag.
he adds the other half.
he threads a steel rod
into hinge holes
to hold the two shells together.
next, they mold wheels
from nylon.
a robot transfers the wheels
to another part of the mold.
the mold closes and a nozzle
pipes in hot liquid rubber
to apply it
to the rolling surface
of the wheels.
the rubber adheres to the nylon
and solidifies.
they attach two wheels
to a polypropylene hub
for stable swiveling action.
a factory worker now inserts
an extendable handle.
then, working from the inside,
she screws the handle
to the luggage shell.
she reinforces the connection
with a metal bracket,
ensuring
that the extendable handle
will hold fast
even when the load is heavy.
she plugs the wheels
into their slots
in the base of the luggage.
she secures them with screws.
this bag is now mobile with
360-degree swiveling action.
the next employee installs this
water-resistant rubber piping.
it will seal the bag
and keep the rain out.
she presses it onto the edge
of one of the shells.
she attaches brackets
for hanging dividers
to the other shell.
she snaps three side-locks
and one central combination lock
onto the bag.
she screws down
the hanging divider brackets.
the fabric liner, with its
zippered pockets, goes in next.
the elastic dividers extend from
it to attach to the brackets.
it's time for the tumble test.
a technician places the luggage
in a rolling steel drum,
and it bounces around.
they conduct this test
on a random bag
every now and then
to confirm that the luggage
will bear up to rough handling.
and with that, these bags
are ready for a vacation.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...