--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
...and water skis.
whether it's a hangnail
that needs fixing
or it's simply time for a
trim,
a nail nipper is a good thing
to have at your fingertips.
a nipper is a precision tool,
one that offers
a bit more control
than lever-style clippers.
the result is usually
a more manicured look.
heavy duty
and made of stainless steel,
the nipper nail cutter looks
as
if it belongs in a tool chest
and it actually works like
cutter pliers.
squeezing the handles
brings the curved blades
at the end together
for a well-rounded trim job.
the handles offer
a bit moore maneuverability
than the lever mechanism
on a standard nail clipper.
production begins with
these forged-steel blanks.
they'll make two pairs
of nail nippers from each one.
they load the blanks
onto a carriage
that transports them
into a furnace.
subjected to intense heat,
the steel blanks become
white-hot and malleable
in minutes.
the foundry worker
transfers a blank to a die.
he moves it across the die
and flips it over
as a hammer slams it into
the shape of two
nail-nipper shanks,
each with a cutting head.
it takes several strikes
to create the right impression
on both sides of the blank.
the process transforms the
narrow blank into a wider
piece
with two nail-nipper
formations.
this is the blank before
forging
and now.
once the two shanks have been
separated and trimmed,
a drill cuts a hole
under the blade end.
this is the area where
the nipper shanks
are to be joined.
a milling tool
shaves down the area
for a neat and level joint.
this is the nail-nipper shank
before the joint work and
after.
they transfer the nipper
shanks
to a finishing machine.
they bounce around in a stream
of abrasive ceramic pebbles
for a few hours.
this rubs off the rough bits.
a magnetized conveyor
pulls out the steel shanks,
leaving the ceramics behind
and carries the shanks
forward.
an employee sands
the entire surface of each
shank
until it looks
completely smooth.
he brushes oil
onto a shank joint
to prevent rust and abrasion.
it's time to rivet the two
nail-nipper shanks together.
the rivets funnel into tooling
above and below
the nail-nipper shanks.
the machinery drives the
rivets
into the holes in the shanks.
once joined,
they cannot be pulled apart
without completely destroying
the nail nippers.
at this point,
the rivets protrude slightly
and could snag on clothing
or other things.
an employee sands each rivet
until it's on the same plane
as the rest of the nipper
joint.
the vigorous sanding
makes the rivet seem
to almost disappear.
he polishes
the inside of the nipper
blades
to completely smooth
the surfaces.
an even surface
can be more thoroughly cleaned
and disinfected
between manicures.
the blades
are still blunt at this point.
the next member of the team
files them on an angle
to give them a cutting edge.
filing too little could hamper
the clearance
between the blades.
filing too much
would ruin the nippers
entirely.
he tests them on paper.
if the cutting edge slips,
the blades may need more work.
if they slice right through,
they're just right.
next, he clamps the nail
nippers
onto a circular bench.
it revolves
to meet up with a laser
that etches the company logo
and other information
onto the shanks.
after that, they drill holes
and attach a spring
to make the nippers
easier to open and close.
for the professional
who will be opening and
closing
these nail nippers
a few hundred times a day,
this is a nifty feature.
they manufacture
these nail nippers
in batches of 300 or 400 over
a period of about two weeks,
so they're should always
be plenty on hand.
narrator:
this putter is made of jade,
a precious stone traditionally
used in jewelry and sculpture.
long coveted for its beauty,
jade is in demand
on the putting green.
as tough as steel with a feel
that's distinctly different,
a putter made of jade
is definitely up to par.
the jade putter is among
a number of new clubs
on the green...
along with crystal quartz
and fossilized vegetation,
known as petrified wood.
to make a jade putter,
they head for the hills --
specifically, a nephrite
jade outcrop in wyoming.
here, the putter maker finds
a 20-foot wide vein of
nephrite.
this stone has taken 2 billion
years to form and develop
a very hard and fibrous
crystalline structure.
the carver selects slabs
that are thick enough to shape
into four or five putter
heads.
this one has weathered
to a rusty color,
but it should clean up nicely.
the color of wyoming jade
ranges from white to green
to black.
he strikes the slab with
a sledgehammer a few times
to break it down
to a more manageable size.
he slices through one of
the cut pieces with a rock saw
while flushing it with coolant
to save the diamond blade.
he makes 9 or 10 cuts
to rough out the triangular
mallet shape of the putter
head.
he slices off the ends
to complete the basic shape.
next, he anchors the jade
in a wooden jig
and cuts on an angle to
profile
the sides of the putter head.
he slices off a back section
to give the putter clearance
from the ground when swung.
this putter
has really taken shape.
he removes material
from the corners
to center the mass
behind the golf ball
for more striking energy.
he sands the edges
to round and soften them.
he's careful not to remove
too much in one place
because that would affect
the symmetry.
he then polishes
the entire piece of jade
against diamond-abrasive
belts.
it's an intensive process
that takes about two hours.
he aims a drill and cores into
the putter head on a 20 angle
to make a hole
for inserting the putter
shaft.
a perpetual flow of water
keeps the diamond core bit
cool
and also flushes out
the little bits of filings.
he gently taps the drilled
core
to jar it
so it falls out of
the putter head.
a laser emblazons
the product name onto the
jade,
swiftly etching it
into the surface.
the putters can be customized
with a customer's name and
logo.
he swabs gold-colored paint
into the laser etching
to make the letters
really stand out.
the swabbing leaves
a lot of residual paint
around the letters,
so he rubs it off.
he sprays the putter with
a wax-based gloss
to seal the stone.
he then buffs it
against a felt belt
to give the jade a satiny
sheen.
he mixes epoxy ingredients
to attach the shaft
to the jade putter's head.
he deposits epoxy
in the hole in the shaft.
he inserts the steel shaft
into the 20-angle hole.
the angle of the hole
positions the putter shaft
to match the golfer's
upright stance.
once the pistol-style grip
has been slipped on,
he applies a metallic-look
decal
just below it.
the decal displays
company contact information
in the event of a problem
that doesn't have to do with
the golfer's technique.
after cleaning and inspection,
this jade putter
is ready for action.
putters carved from jade and
other materials
are crafty editions to
the golf-club arsenal
and could lead to some
artful moves on the green.
narrator:
ice cider is an alcoholic
drink
made from fermented,
frozen apples or apple juice.
it's also known as
apple ice wine
and is produced
the same way as ice wine
but with apples
instead of grapes.
it's typically served with
food
such as foie gras,
cheese, fruit,
and dark chocolate.
there's a world of difference
between ice cider
and regular cider.
regular cider
is made from fresh apples,
whereas ice cider
is made from frozen apples
or frozen apple juice.
and while cider can be
a non-alcoholic beverage,
ice cider is always alcoholic.
there are two methods
to making ice cider.
one is to leave the apples
on the tree
to freeze over the winter,
then pick them and press them.
the other method,
which we're about to see,
is to harvest the apples
in the fall when they're ripe,
press them,
then freeze the juice.
the apples are always
handpicked at perfect maturity
and always right off the tree.
an ice-cider producer
never uses fallen apples
because they often get damaged
when they hit the ground
and then pick up bacteria
from lying there.
this producer uses
different varieties of apples
to make several types
of ice cider.
the one we're about to see is
made from empire, spartan,
cortland, mcintosh,
and golden russet.
straight from the orchard,
the apples go onto
a conveyor belt
which feeds them into
a multistage press.
the first part of the press
crushes the apples
into what's known as pumice.
a screw conveyor moves the
pumice onto a mesh conveyor
belt
that transports it through
five stainless-steel rollers.
each roller applies
275 pounds of pressure,
progressively extracting
the apple juice.
the juice drains down through
the mesh conveyor belt
to a vat below.
from the vat, the juice is
pumped into a large container
made of food-safe plastic.
the container holds 264
gallons.
however, they leave
13 to 26 gallons of air space
to leave room for expansion
when the juice freezes.
at the end of december,
they haul the containers
outdoors.
the juice stays outside
from 40 to 50 days,
during which time
the water in it freezes,
leaving
unfrozen, concentrated juice
at the bottom of the
container.
workers measure
the sugar content daily,
and once it reaches
a certain level,
they pump the juice indoors
into temperature-controlled,
stainless-steel tanks.
then they add yeast
to kick-start fermentation --
the conversion of those
natural sugars to alcohol.
every day,
they measure the sugar level
to monitor
the fermentation process.
when they hit their target,
which typically takes
between 40 and 50 days,
the juice has transformed
into ice cider
with an alcohol content
of 10.5% to 11%.
ice cider is bottled
just like wine.
the corking machine
automatically pops in a cork
as soon as its sensor detects
the presence of a bottle.
the next machine
slips a plastic seal
over the mouth of the bottle,
then heats the plastic
to shrink the seal
tightly around the cork.
finally,
an automated labeling machine
simultaneously applies
self-sticking labels
to the front and back.
it isn't only the apple
variety
that determines the flavor.
it's also the production
method.
the process we've just seen,
called cryoconcentration,
produces ice cider with
a strong, fruity flavor.
the other method,
called cryoextraction --
letting apples freeze on
the tree, then pressing them
--
produces ice cider which
tastes like baked apples.
narrator: water skiing
was invented in 1922
by an american teenager
named ralph samuelson.
with his brother
pulling him by motorboat,
he experimented first with
skis made of barrel staves,
then with snow skis,
then with skis he had made
out of pine boards 94" long.
this type of water skiing
is known as slalom,
winding through a course
on a single water ski,
one foot behind the other,
in boots mounted to the ski.
the core of these
top-of-the-line
competition slalom skis
is high-density pvc foam --
exceptionally strong,
yet lightweight.
a computer-guided machine
cuts the ski shape,
then pockets
to receive various components.
workers
flip the core upside down,
and the machine
shapes the bottom.
workers then turn the core
right-side up again
and fill the pockets with
glue.
they insert an alignment tab
in the tail pocket
to help correctly position
the core in the mold.
they install fiberglassed,
reinforced nylon blocks
in the others.
these will anchor
threaded inserts
for mounting
the boots and the ski's fin.
now they begin
building up the water ski
with multiple layers
of carbon fiber,
an ultra-strong fabric.
they apply the first layer
to the bottom,
wrapping it around to the top.
this will
prevent the ski from twisting.
after stapling down
the carbon fiber
and trimming off the excess,
they saturate it with resin
and apply carbon fiber
to the top of the ski.
depending on the model and
its performance
specifications,
they wrap the core
in up to seven layers
of resin-saturated carbon
fiber,
controlling the flex
in select areas along the way
with additional patches.
then they top the ski
with a layer of woven,
synthetic fabric
to prime the surface for
the decorative graphics.
on the bottom of the ski,
they apply a sheet of
super-lightweight polymer.
it creates a white background
to highlight
the printed polyester sheet
of decorative graphics.
they coat it with
a special resin
that cures into
a hard, hydrodynamic surface
that increase the ski's speed.
the graphic design that
decorates the top of the ski
is printed on nylon.
they mount it to the top part
of
a ski-shaped mold,
then lay the wrapped core
into the bottom part.
a heated press closes the
mold,
compressing the contents under
high pressure for nine
minutes.
this bonds the layers,
forms contours in the ski,
and adheres the graphics.
the pressure squeezes out
excess resin along the
perimeter
so once they remove
the ski from the mold,
they cut off the excess
with a band saw.
then with
a custom-made router bit,
they precision-trim
to exact specifications.
next, a three-phase filing
of the ski's edge --
first with a large file,
then a small file,
then with either a razor blade
or medium-grit sandpaper.
then with
the help of a template,
they drill 18 holes
into those
fiberglass-reinforced
nylon blocks in the core.
they screw a threaded insert
into each hole,
and it locks into the block.
there are more inserts
that are actually required
for mounting the fin
and attaching the ski boots.
this gives the skier
different positioning options.
now the last edge-sanding
with fine-grit paper.
after wiping down the entire
ski
with an alcohol-based cleaner,
they install the final
and most important component
--
the fin.
it's made of aluminum
that's chemically treated
to be corrosion-resistant
and ultra-durable.
the fin's position
critically affects the ski's
traction and stability,
so they use a micrometer
to measure to the millimeter,
securing the fin precisely
where
the design engineer specified
in the
performance-maximization
sweet spot.
nonetheless,
competitive water-skiers
typically readjust the fin
to their own preferences
in hopes of leaving
competitors
in their wake.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...