-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
when christopher columbus
discovered the americas,
he also discovered
the tobacco pipe.
the pipe was an important part
of native culture
to be shared during times
of negotiation and celebration.
columbus and other explorers
brought the concept home,
and the rest is history.
since the 19th century,
pipes have been made from briar,
a hard, fire-resistant wood
from the root of a mediterranean
heather shrub.
after the briar
has cured for several months,
the pipe-maker saws it
into a rough pipe shape.
using a lathe and chisel,
he rounds the larger block
to approximate the shape
of the pipe bowl.
he bores through the center
to carve out
the tobacco chamber.
then he slims down the stem,
marking the center
for drilling later.
the pipe-maker finalizes
the shape by hand.
he now sands both the inside
of the tobacco chamber...
...and the outside
of the pipe bowl.
next, the pipe's mouthpiece
takes shape.
the pipe-maker pierces a piece
of hardened rubber
called vulcanite
to establish the center
and then drills
a channel through it.
using a grindstone,
he sculpts one end,
taking it from round to oval,
a shape that fits
more comfortably
between the lips.
he checks his work
with a sizing template...
then shaves the exterior
of the mouthpiece,
reducing it considerably.
he shapes the other end
to form the tenon,
which fits into the pipe stem.
he polishes the tenon
with a special compound.
the smoother surface
makes this part easier
to join to the pipe stem.
using a series of sanding disks
with progressively finer grit,
he gives the exterior of
the mouthpiece a sleek finish.
then he steadies it in a clamp
and widens the hole
in the center of the mouthpiece
to broaden it
into a funnel-shaped cavity.
attention now turns to the seam
between the rubber
and wood parts.
he sands it to make them
perfectly flush.
hand-filing removes blemishes
and adjusts the thickness
for a more comfortable bite.
the thickness can be customized
for individual preferences.
he drills a tiny hole into
the top of the mouthpiece...
...then dips
a thin plastic rod in glue
and inserts it in the hole.
he sands it down,
leaving a white spot,
a marker that indicates
the mouthpiece is right-side-up.
for bent or curved pipes,
the mouthpieces are heated in an
oven at 320 degrees fahrenheit.
this makes the vulcanite
flexible enough
to be shaped by hand.
the pipe-maker bends the
mouthpiece to the desired shape,
and a quick cool-down in water
re-hardens the vulcanite,
fixing its curve.
next, he buffs the wooden part
of the pipe.
this removes fine scratches
and brings out the wood grain.
it also gives the wood
a glossy finish.
but for a different finish,
a craftsman sand-blasts
the briar wood,
giving it a ripple texture.
he stains it darker
with an alcohol-based dye,
working the stain
into every crevice.
and now for a neat trick.
he sets it on fire,
and the alcohol burns off
to set the stain.
the pipe doesn't go up
in flames,
proving it's truly
fire-resistant.
he burns up to 10 layers
of stain into the pipe,
depending on the effect
he's trying to achieve.
finally,
he stamps the company name
and other information
into the pipe.
after a final
quality inspection,
this handcrafted briar pipe
is on its way to making
a statement at the country club.
narrator: rock-climbing is no
pastime for the faint-hearted.
scaling natural rock formations
or manmade rock walls
requires a certain fearlessness,
along with good
physical conditioning,
balance, agility,
and you must be well-trained
in climbing techniques
and use specialized equipment.
climbers usually work in pairs,
using a system of ropes
and other devices
to catch them if they fall.
a key piece of gear is the
spring-loaded camming device.
the climber pulls the trigger
to contract the cams
and position it in a crack
then releases the trigger
to expand the cams,
which securely grip the rock
on either side,
then attaches a rope through
a device called a carabiner.
climbers typically carry
several types and sizes of cams,
carabiners, and other devices.
the equipment must be
as lightweight as possible,
yet, at the same time,
strong enough
to save a falling climber.
which is why this manufacturer
uses aircraft-grade aluminum.
to make carabiners,
automated saws cut aluminum bars
into pieces the required length.
then a bending machine
forces each piece around a form
in the basic shape
of the carabiner.
carabiners come
in various sizes and shapes.
workers simply mount the
appropriate form on the machine.
next, they place the roughly
formed carabiner onto a hot die.
another die slams down on it
with up to 800 tons of force,
forging the final shape.
then the most critical part
of the manufacturing process --
a multi-phase heat treatment
to harden and strengthen
the aluminum.
next, they use a clipping press
to slice off excess metal
along the perimeter.
this leaves rough edges,
which they now smooth out
using an abrasion process.
the carabiners
go into a vibrating tub,
where they rub against porcelain
chips for the next 20 hours.
next, workers drill holes
for the rivets
on which the spring-loaded
opening mechanism will hinge.
that mechanism, called the gate,
has channels
which align with these holes.
assemblers slide a spring and
spring-pusher into the gate,
then insert the rivets through
the aligned holes and channels.
a riveting machine
locks each rivet in place
by rounding
and widening the head.
then they adjust
the carabiner's frame
until the alignment is perfect.
after a thorough inspection,
a laser etching machine
inscribes product information
and a unique serial number.
random samples undergo strength
and other quality-control tests.
elsewhere in the factory,
camming device production
is under way.
computer-guided equipment
machines the same aluminum alloy
to a preliminary shape,
saws off slices,
then machines each slice
to the final shape of a cam.
an assembler attaches a wire
to each cam...
then takes four cams
and joins their wires
to the trigger wires
with a metal crimp.
the cams, by this point,
are different colors.
that's because they've undergone
chemical treatment
to make them
corrosion-resistant.
this process can, in fact,
produce various colors.
so, at the same time,
the company can color-code
the different models.
as assembly continues,
they thread the cams
onto an axle-like component
called the spindle,
positioning a spring
in between each cam.
the springs provide
the resistance required
to expand and retract
the device.
a cone-shaped washer
on each end of the spindle
holds everything together.
this time, the riveting machine
locks in the components
by flattening and widening
the end of the spindle
to fill the hole in the washer.
with that,
the camming device is finished.
this is how camming devices,
carabiners,
and other climbing gear
all work together
to catch climbers
who lose their foothold.
not only do they keep
the climber safe,
they also protect nature,
because they attach
to the rock face
without damaging it in any way.
narrator:
leather bike saddles
feature a leather top
suspended on a metal frame.
with time and use,
the leather molds itself
to perfectly suit
the rider's anatomy
and their cycling style.
and just like a pair
of leather shoes,
the saddle becomes
very comfortable.
leather bike saddles
look almost the same
as they did 100 years ago.
they are still made by hand
and by some machinery that is
sometimes over 60 years old.
saddles are made exclusively
of metal and leather,
traditional materials
that retain
the style and quality
of the early days.
the first step is making
the steel wire springs
for saddles
that have a suspension.
the machine coils and cuts
the wire to the proper length.
liquid lubricant keeps
everything running smoothly.
depending on the saddle's model,
some springs are then chromed.
this machine folds and curls
steel or titanium wire
to form brackets.
it's adjustable,
so it can make brackets
of different sizes and shapes,
depending on the model
being produced.
a technician assembles
the springs and brackets
to form the saddle's frame.
he attaches the clamp
so that the saddle
can be attached
to the bicycle's seat post.
saddles come in different sizes
and shapes,
with or without
suspension springs
to accommodate
various riding styles --
racing, mountain biking,
or city commuting.
now for the saddle's
leather top.
using a hydraulic
clicking press,
the worker cuts the leather
with a sharp blade.
the blade cuts ventilation holes
at the same time.
tanneries provide leather in any
color required by the factory.
after the tops are cut,
they soak in tepid water
for 20 minutes to an hour,
until the leather
is completely saturated.
the wet leather top
then goes to a press,
which applies 2,000 pounds
of pressure per square inch.
using a leather cushion,
the technician pads
the leather piece
to help reinforce the shape,
especially
in the narrow front end.
because the top is wet,
it retains the shape
and does not bounce back.
they carefully sand the leather
to get a smooth edge.
the tops now go into the oven
for three hours
at a maximum temperature
of 130 degrees fahrenheit.
now they're ready
for the finishing process.
a worker rivets a name plate
to the rear of the saddle...
...then stamps a trademark
on each side.
each saddle model
has its own trademark.
they attach the nose
to the front of the saddle
using solid copper rivets.
they hammer each one down
carefully
to follow the contours of the
leather without scratching it.
this machine now rivets the
frame to the back of the saddle.
they insert a tension pin
between the frame and the nose.
this pin will allow the rider
to adjust his saddle
if the leather starts sagging
after a few years.
it takes about three days
to make a leather bike saddle.
and with careful care,
it can be used
for years to come.
narrator:
luxury sports cars
are coveted by people
around the world,
and with good reason.
the extraordinary skills
and materials
that go into making them
were developed
from a long racing heritage.
each one of these automobiles
is born
from expert craftsmanship
and a passion for racing.
underneath the beautiful
exterior of these cars
lie a chassis and power train
capable of delivering
remarkable performance.
the aluminum frame is engineered
to be lightweight, yet rigid,
and provide crumple zones
that can evenly distribute force
in the event of an impact.
it takes highly skilled
technicians
to perform these complex welds.
on the factory floor,
robots transport the body panels
that will later be fitted
onto the chassis.
once the frame is completed,
technicians use
a pneumatic hoist
to position and attach
exterior panels and doors.
door panel cutouts
reduce the car's weight
while retaining a high degree
of structural integrity.
the elongated cutouts
on this model
will house
its stylized headlights.
next, they coat the car
in a compound
which fluoresces
under a special lighting system.
this helps technicians detect
any minute imperfections.
these imperfections
are then filed down by hand.
here, a robot fully immerses
and rotates the chassis
in a galvanizing solution
that prevents corrosion.
once the body has been primed,
it passes through a device
that dusts off the entire body
with ostrich-feather brushes.
next stop, the paint room,
where robots spray the car body
with a smooth,
even coat of paint.
once the paint dries and cures,
the robots apply several coats
of varnish.
the final step in body prep
is a meticulous waxing by hand
to remove
any remaining blemishes.
moving on to the chassis,
a technician uses a hoist
to position and fasten
the engine and gearbox in place.
here, robots transport
the completed power train
to the assembly area...
where an automatic crane
gently lowers the car body
onto the chassis,
which includes
the fully assembled suspension,
gearbox, and engine.
this step is known
as the marriage.
next, a worker
installs the wheels
with some help
from a hydraulic lifting system.
at the next station,
technicians test
all the dashboard components.
this vehicle features
a combination
of analog and digital displays.
a master computer
runs the electronics
and information systems.
again with the help
of the crane,
technicians install
the finished dashboard.
the next step
is the steering wheel.
assisted
by a special assembly jig,
a technician positions
and tightens it
onto the steering column.
workers lower the trunk cover
and convertible hardtop
into position,
which is particular
to this model of car.
a worker double-checks
the installation
of the hydraulic mechanism.
this beautiful road machine
is the culmination
of years of racing history,
modern engineering,
and dedicated craftsmanship.
now watch this.
this is one of the few cars
that features a fully automated
convertible hardtop.
this beauty is now ready
for the sun, wind,
and the open road.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...