-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: at many work sites,
grapples do all the heavy lifting.
dangling from crane booms,
these huge mechanized claws move mountains of material
one load at a time.
some are equipped with powerful electromagnets
for gathering small bits of metal
along with the large ones.
not much can escape the grasp of the mighty grapple.
a magnet at the center pulls metal from the scrap heap,
while four fingers dig into the pile.
it then transfers the load of steel for recycling.
it actually takes some of that recycled steel
to make a grapple in the form of steel plate.
a computer-guided flame burns through the steel
to cut out the various part shapes.
it will take approximately 50 pieces
in a range of shapes and
thicknesses to make one grapple.
a press brake repeatedly rams one of the parts
while an operator adjusts it forward between thrusts.
the process curls the part to give it a claw-like profile.
it's the basic shape of a grapple finger.
using a template,
he checks the curvature to confirm it's on target.
he'll curl four fingers per grapple.
meanwhile, a welder pieces together the grapple's core,
working within a special fixture
that allows him to assemble it precisely.
after he tack-welds them together,
it's over to the robot.
it does the permanent welds
as the core slowly rotates in a special device.
they hoist the welded grapple core over to the magnet
and feed its main wire up through the core.
they lower the core,
and it fits onto metal dowels protruding from the magnet.
this allows them to align the two precisely.
they thread high-strength bolts
into the dowels
to secure the assembly.
next, they place a turntable bearing
on the grapple's top flange.
this bearing is an important part
of the claw-rotator mechanism.
they fasten the bearing's outer ring to the flange
with numerous bolts,
torqueing each one tightly
to withstand the spinning action
of the bearing's inner ring.
as demonstrated here,
the bearing turns in both directions
to give the grapple's claw movements a lot of flexibility.
a worker now lowers the upper rotator assembly
onto the turntable bearing.
this assembly holds the rotator's motor
and the manifold that feeds hydraulic fluid
to the cylinders that power the claw.
they now slide the hydraulic cylinders into their slots
and lock them in place with pivot pins.
they install a total of four cylinders.
each one will power one grapple finger,
and together, they'll open and close the grapple claw.
they connect the hydraulic feed
lines to the cylinders
and reinforce the connection with a four-bolt flange
that can handle the pressure of the hydraulic fluid.
they guide each steel finger into slots in the grapple core
and align them correctly.
they slide a pivot pin into the attachment holes
to link the two.
this pin will also act as a kind of hinge
as the finger opens and closes.
they fasten the pivot pin to the grapple
with a nut that's split in one spot.
this split enables it to be squeezed tightly
around the large pin with a small bolt.
they attach the hydraulic cylinders to the claw fingers
with more large steel pins.
and they're now ready to power the grapple claw
and test the gripping action.
the four tines, or fingers, open and close in unison.
the tips mate correctly. there's no overlap.
they roll paint onto the company emblem,
and this grapple claw is now ready for the jobsite.
it weighs 4.5 tons,
and just dropping it on a car
will crumple it like a piece of tissue paper.
it takes about 150 hours to manufacture a grapple claw
that can get a grip on the really big jobs
in a matter of seconds.
narrator: whether it's boysenberry in your muffin,
hazelnut in your coffee,
blue cheese in your salad dressing,
or spearmint in your chewing gum,
the source is usually a prepared flavoring.
food and drink makers typically
approach a flavorings company
to custom-design and produce whatever flavor they need.
not only do flavoring companies
produce ingredients
for commercial use,
they also manufacture stand-alone flavoring products
for retail sale,
such as those syrups you squirt into coffee,
fountain drinks, and other beverages.
in the company's research and development laboratory,
flavor chemists create each recipe,
drawing from an elaborate arsenal of ingredients.
if they're designing an orange flavoring, for example,
they might combine orange essence and orange peel
with extracts from other citrus fruits,
tweaking the proportions
until they achieve exactly the taste they're after.
this chemist is designing flavoring for a soft drink.
he pours a specific amount of his trial recipe into water,
then carbonates the mix
by adding pressurized carbon dioxide.
then he bottles the drink
and sends it to the client for approval.
once the client gives the okay,
plant technicians mix a production formula,
following very precise weights and measures
set out in the recipe.
once they combine the formula's key ingredients,
they add them to the liquid fillers --
such as fruit juice and water --
and solvents such as ethanol.
the solvents trigger molecular changes
that transform the oil-soluble key ingredients
into a water-soluble state.
without this conversion,
the finished flavoring would simply float on top
of any liquid to which it's added.
at several points throughout the process,
the company's quality-control lab
performs an array of tests
to assess color, flavor, viscosity,
and other characteristics.
the last ingredients to go into the production formula,
when the recipe calls for them,
are colorings.
sometimes a client wants a powdered flavoring
rather than a liquid one.
so chemists develop a liquid recipe
that a machine called a spray dryer
can process into a powder.
in the production plant,
workers pour the required quantity of production formula
into a large processing kettle.
they add whatever additional ingredients
the recipe may call for,
and if required, heat the mix.
if they're making a powdered flavoring,
then from the kettle,
they pour the liquid into a mixer
containing water, gums, and starches.
these keep all the ingredients evenly blended.
then they open a hatch
and drop the mix directly into the spray dryer.
the machine uses high pressure
to transform the liquid into a fine mist,
then heat to dry the mist particles
into powder particles.
they put the powder
into a machine called a ribbon blender
and add whatever dry ingredients
the flavoring recipe calls for.
then mixing blades slowly blend
all the powders together.
the plant sends a sample from the blender
to the quality-control lab.
among other tests,
lab technicians put the sample under a microscope
to analyze the particle size,
which indicates how thoroughly the ingredients are blended.
exiting the ribbon blender,
the finished flavoring passes through a vibrating screen,
a magnet, and a metal detector.
the packaging equipment weighs a specific quantity
and dispenses it into cartons lined with polyethylene.
a suction hose vacuums what dusts up in the process,
because airborne powder is an explosion hazard.
the plant sends a sample from every batch it produces
back to the lab.
trained testers smell and taste the sample
and compare it to the model lab batch.
the testers flag any production sample
that's even the slightest bit off the mark,
in which case they alert the flavor chemists,
who then diagnose and fix the problem.
this procedure,
along with the various quality-control measures
throughout the production process,
ensures taste consistency, which is absolutely critical,
whether the prepared flavoring is an ingredient
in a commercially produced food or beverage
or a retail flavoring
that you squirt into or sprinkle onto a drink or snack.
narrator: for centuries,
dog-driven sleds were a lifeline
across the frozen north,
delivering medicine and other supplies
to far-flung communities.
today, aircraft and snowmobiles
have mostly taken over that work,
and dog-sledding has become a sport.
and a well-made sled is behind every winning team.
a dog-sled race is an endurance test for the dogs,
the driver, and the sled itself.
a good sled is both flexible
and sturdy enough to go the distance.
at this factory, they make sleds from white ash.
a worker angles the ends of vertical bars
so they can be fitted
to the sled's top rail and handlebar.
these bars are called stanchions.
he shapes the other end of them
so they'll fit into grooves in the sled's runner.
all the parts of this sled are designed
to fit together like pieces of a jigsaw puzzle.
a worker now screws aluminum rails
onto the bottom of the two runners.
he slides plastic strips into those aluminum rails,
which gives the runners a smooth base
for gliding over ice or snow.
he secures the plastic strips at each end with screws.
the crew is now ready to assemble
all the pieces of the dog sled.
they attach metal screw eyes to the runners.
they'll thread rope through them
when they're ready to tie the parts of the sled together.
all the parts of the framework
fit into notches made specifically for them.
the location of those notches has been precisely mapped out.
if one is even a fraction of an inch off,
the sled would collapse like a house of cards.
they measure the space between the runners
to confirm they're perfectly aligned,
and now tie the joints together
with nylon rope.
these ties are called lashings,
and there are 22 of them on this dog sled.
historically, lashings were made
of moose hide,
but nylon is tougher.
they cut the rope with a hot blade,
which seals the fibers so that they won't unravel.
they tie the midpoint joints together...
...and the focus then moves to the dog-sled handlebar.
a worker glues strips of ash together.
the strips are thin so they can be easily bent,
allowing him to curl
the glued layer around a u-form.
he clamps the wood to the form,
and the glue cures for three hours.
it hardens into the u-shape,
creating the dog-sled handlebar.
he secures the handlebar to the dog sled
with the nylon lashings.
the team then assembles the bed
of the sled.
they clamp the slats into place,
and then screw them to the framework.
they install the sled's front bumper,
called the brushbrow.
next, a worker cuts off
the metal bead of a bicycle tire
and discards it.
he uses the remaining tire tread
to create foot pads
by wrapping it around pieces of thick plastic
and screwing it into place.
he installs a treaded pad on each runner
to keep the driver's feet from slipping off.
then they install an aluminum bar brake.
these pivot bolts will allow this bar brake
to be raised when not needed,
and lowered to engage the metal talons.
he loops a bungee cord on each side of a cross bar
and burns off an end.
he hooks the other end of the cord to the brake.
this simple bungee-cord mechanism
will enable the dog-sled musher
to activate the brake.
he heat-shrinks rubber tubing around the base of the cord
to protect it.
they now weave the back of the sled,
using nylon cord to create a basket for carrying things.
it's big enough to hold a tired animal.
the worker then loops and ties the bridle
to front stanchions beneath the sled.
he forms a "v" as he threads it
from the back of the sled to the front.
he paints urethane onto the wood,
and even over the lashings.
this will protect them against wear.
it's taken about three days
to make this traditional basket dog sled,
and now it's ready to mush.
narrator: athletic footwear dates back to ancient times,
but the concept gained traction
with the development of treaded rubber soles
in the early part of the 20th century.
these rubber-soled shoes
were lightweight, comfortable, and hit the ground quietly,
earning them the name "sneakers."
design improvements
have broadened the appeal of athletic shoes.
people wear them everywhere.
the athletic shoe
has definitely gone main street.
using a hydraulic press,
this employee forces a die through synthetic fabric
to cut out patterns for the upper part of the shoe.
at the next station,
he punches out leather toe tips.
the toe tip is one of numerous cut-outs
that add shape and structure to the synthetic upper.
after arranging the tip parts on a nonstick tray,
this worker places strips of thermal resin onto them.
she drapes a nonstick sheet over the tray,
then slides it into a hot metal press.
the resin melts into the leather
to stiffen and strengthen it.
another worker stamps the model
number onto the heel cutout.
then it's over to the sewing department,
where a worker stitches a reflector
onto the athletic shoe upper.
other accent pieces call for more intricate stitching,
so she arranges the parts on a computerized platform.
the platform moves back and forth,
allowing the needle to do a perfect job
of stitching the accent pieces to the upper.
this stitching would be difficult to execute manually.
once some of the more substantial pieces
have been applied to the shoe,
it's time to sew on a reflective logo,
and the needle is once again guided by computer software.
this athletic-shoe upper is now ready
for its resin-fortified leather toe tip.
she stitches it in place,
and then pieces together the collar
and sews it to the back of the shoe.
she installs thick foam padding
on the inside of the collar,
and then turns it right-side-out
to tuck the padding
neatly inside and hide the seam.
putting on the collar
has obscured the top lace holes,
so she clears them with a compressed-air punch.
down the line,
more computerized needles embroider brand information
onto the tongue panels.
the next worker sews a liner and padding to the panel,
again working inside-out to hide the seam.
another worker then stitches a fabric base
onto the athletic shoe.
she applies a rigid plastic to the heel.
that adds structure and support
to the back part of the shoe.
further down the production line,
a worker tugs the shoe onto a foot form called a last.
they heat it to make it malleable enough
for this machine to pull it to the shape of the last.
at the same time,
nozzles apply cement to glue the overlap to the fabric base.
then a machine heats both the upper and the rubber sole.
the heat activates glue applied to the sole earlier
and also prepares the upper for bonding to that sole.
they initially use manual force
to press the two together,
and then the shoe is subjected to mechanized pressure.
inside this machine,
a rubber bladder expands to force the two together
for a complete seal.
the shoe then gets a foam insole
with an arch support.
the worker laces it partially
and then pairs it up with the other shoe.
an inspector examines the pair for defects.
it has taken about 21 minutes
to make this pair of athletic shoes.
and they should be able to take
a real workout.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...