[ beeping ]
--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: being eaten alive by mosquitos is no picnic...
well, except to the mosquitos.
not only are the bugs annoying,
but just one bite from an infected mosquito
can transmit potentially debilitating
or fatal diseases
such as the west nile virus, malaria, and dengue fever.
one way to ward off mosquitos is to light a coil
that releases mosquito-repelling vapors.
these coils, manufactured in thailand,
contain three natural ingredients
traditionally used in this country
to keep those biting bugs at bay --
eucalyptus, citronella, and turmeric.
the first step is to mix them
with certain nonactive natural ingredients
which form the coil --
coconut shell powder, sawdust,
tapioca starch, and joss powder,
an adhesive made from the bark and leaves
of the litsea glutinosa tree.
after blending
all these powdered ingredients
for 10 to 15 minutes,
workers bag the mix in an empty ingredient sack,
then empty the contents in a kneading tank.
they add fragrance and dye.
the coil comes in four varieties.
this batch of coils will be pink and cherry blossom scented.
then, they add the coil's only chemical active ingredient,
metofluthrin.
its vapors are toxic
to mosquitos' nervous systems,
yet harmless to humans in low doses.
metofluthrin makes up less than 1% of the mosquito coil.
after about 10 to 15 minutes of kneading, the mix
exits the tank as a formable paste.
a conveyer belt transports it to an extruder,
which squeezes the paste through a slot-shaped die,
producing sheets approximately 4 millimeters thick.
a stamping machine then punches out seven coils per sheet.
the leftover paste travels back to the extruder
to be reformed into fresh sheets ready for stamping
while the stamping machine
ejects the paste coils onto a mesh tray.
workers conduct a visual inspection
and remove any coils which are misshapen.
then they stack the trays onto trolleys.
they roll the trolleys into the drying chamber,
which they heat to a temperature of 131 degrees fahrenheit.
after 5 1/2 hours, the coils
come out of the drying chamber hard and sturdy.
after conducting another visual inspection, workers
transfer the dried coil
to the automated packing line.
the machine's first station stacks
the coils in piles of five.
workers place a metal coil stand
on each stack.
then, the machine's next station
packages each stack in clear plastic film.
the package holds the five coils tightly together
so they don't rattle against each other
and get damaged.
it also prevents the scent from dissipating before use.
at the next station,
a high-speed robotic arm grabs
and opens the retail boxes,
aligning them opposite the arriving packages of coils.
the machine inserts a package of coils into each box...
then closes the box.
before packaging the mosquito coils,
the company lab tests
randomly selected samples from the batch.
the chemist lights a piece of coils and places
it in the center of a sealed test chamber.
five minutes after the coil has completely burned,
she releases mosquitos into the chamber
and clocks how much time elapses until they're debilitated.
the lab also conducts a burn performance test.
this verifies that the coils take between 7 and 8 hours
to burn completely.
these mosquito coils also come in lavender, rosemary,
and herbal blend scents.
provided they're kept sealed in their plastic package
and stored away from moisture,
the active ingredients remain effective for at least 10 years.
narrator: the solar-assist
tricycle takes urban commuting
in a whole new direction.
it's part tricycle and part motorized vehicle.
the motor runs on a lithium-ion battery
that gets its juice from the solar panel on the roof.
and it can also be plugged into an electrical outlet
for a charge.
the solar-assist tricycle is a vehicle for change.
propelled by both pedal power and solar energy,
it's an alternative way to get around town.
making a solar-assist tricycle starts
with the side panels for the cab.
they've been thermoformed from rugged plastic.
an employee cuts open doorways in the panels using a router.
a fender was molded into the cutout
to minimize waste.
he cuts a hole in the panel to assemble that fender.
another employee then peels off the plastic film
that has protected the panel during the cutting process.
she attaches led signal lights
and headlights to the tricycle body.
she connects the lights to the wiring harness.
the molded fender completes the tricycle side panel.
she hangs it on a rack
to await the next stage of production
and writes the order number on it
in order to keep track of it.
they build the frame
from tempered aircraft-grade aluminum.
an employee mounts crank arms and chain rings to the front
and then attaches pedals.
the crankset transmits human pedal power
to the drivetrain.
next up is the antlers,
an assembly of metal tubes
that includes the suspension mechanisms
and steering linkage.
they install steering arms at the ends of the antlers,
then mount an aluminum dashboard support
to the antlers.
he inserts the steer tube for the handlebars into the slot
in the dashboard support.
he connects the steering linkage to the antlers
using swiveling joints for precise handling.
he inserts the handlebar into the steer tube.
the team then secures two rugged bicycle wheels
to the axle using cap bolts.
they position the 1-horsepower motor and transmission
between the tricycle's parallel spines
and attach them with brackets and bolts.
they loop a roller chain from the crank
to the transmission
and another one from the transmission
to the rear drive wheel.
they also link the motor to the rear wheel
with a roller chain.
they equip all three wheels with disc brakes.
they install aluminum casing over part of the rear wheel
and driveline.
this protects these components
and also provides structural support.
a computerized tool now carves into corrugated polypropylene
to create a box for the vehicle battery.
an assembler then rivets the battery box
to the front of the solar-assist tricycle.
the team attaches metal struts
to serve as supports for the vehicle body.
they're now ready to assemble
the body parts to the chassis.
they align each panel to the frame
and bolt it in nine locations.
the fenders frame the wheels to keep road spray down.
they fasten side mirrors to the vehicle,
drilling the bolts through the body
to the dashboard support.
the employee then applies decals that identify the product.
he protects the motor and transmission
with a rugged plastic bonnet.
and he screws the adjustable seat
to the tricycle's aluminum spine.
the team curves the flexible solar panel to the top.
they attach the windshield to the front
using high-strength double-sided tape.
the windshield is made of polycarbonate
that's optically clear and shatterproof.
after the installation, he peels off the protective liner.
the next worker inserts the battery in its compartment.
he clips it shut,
and the solar-assist tricycle is ready for the road.
with its egg-shaped cab, it's certainly unusual-looking.
and that's fitting because this hybrid vehicle
is something entirely different.
narrator:
most people use palm oil daily
and don't realize it because it just blends in.
it's a component of half of packaged food products.
and it's also used in cosmetics, detergents,
and even biofuels.
it has a smooth texture, a natural taste.
and it's a natural preservative.
brought to southeast asia from africa a century ago,
oil palms have thrived here.
today, this region generates 85%
of the world's palm oil supply.
at the heart of this palm oil boom
are breeding programs that ensure high yields.
technicians start by dissecting the fruit bunches.
they analyze the quality of the fruit fibers,
kernels, and nuts.
they also assess their oil content.
this identifies the most productive palms,
as well as the trees
best suited to particular growing environments.
next, the research team climbs the selected mother palms
and pollinates
the female flowers with pollen
from high-quality male palms.
they cover the flowers with thick fabric
that allow light in
but shields them from accidental pollination
by insects and from other flowers.
this ensures that hybrid seed will be the product
of the selected parents only.
it takes 6 months for the new hybrid seeds
to be produced.
then it's into a heat chamber for 3 months
to break the seeds' dormancy.
they soak the awakened seeds in water.
along with the heat treatment, this rehydrating
accelerates germination --
a process that takes many years in nature.
they place the seeds in drawers
and regularly mist them with water.
after a few days, the seeds begin to sprout.
skilled staff sort through the sprouted seeds.
they reject any that haven't germinated completely
or that have crooked shoots.
the seed on the left is the ideal specimen.
they plant the selected seeds
in small bags of soil outside.
they shade them during
this initial period of growth,
protecting them from harsh sunlight.
after 3 months, the seedlings develop roots and leaves.
they transfer them to larger bags of soil,
and 6 to 9 months later,
they're 3 feet tall and ready for planting in farmers' fields.
after 3 years of growth, the young palms bear fruit.
the time is now ripe to tap into the oil-generating potential
of these huge fruit bunches.
the farmer loads the oil palm fruit
onto a tractor cart.
and it's on its way to the palm oil factory.
here, fruit from many farms
accumulates in the receiving area.
when the factory is ready to process the next batch,
they open a gate.
the fruit spills onto a conveyer.
and it delivers it to giant pressure cookers.
cooking the fruit sterilizes it.
it stops enzyme activity
that would degrade the quality
of the oil that's to be extracted.
it also loosens the fruit from the stalks,
and some break away.
a spiraling blade moves them onto a grid screen
that sorts the fruit from the stalks.
the loose fruit drops into a bin below.
and the stalks with remaining fruit go for further separating.
next, presses crush the fruit
to squeeze out the crude palm oil.
the oil flows into a vat.
impurities will now be spun out in a centrifuge
and also filtered out.
meanwhile, the fibers and palm nuts toss in a drum.
this knocks off fibers that are stuck to the nuts.
a fan sucks up the lighter fibers,
which will be used as factory fuel.
they crack the nuts,
and then a vibrating system
separates the shells from the actual kernels.
the shells will also be used as factory fuel.
and the kernels will be crushed into palm kernel oil.
in the lab, they now test samples
to determine the oil extraction rate
and confirm that the yield is good.
they also analyze the oil's purity
and the amount of free fatty acids.
they confirm that the batch is of good quality.
this crude palm oil has gone
through many stages of purification.
and although tests confirm it,
the difference is also plain to see.
narrator: today, everything from boats to outdoor furniture
to shower stalls are molded
out of fiberglass-reinforced plastic resin.
this wouldn't be possible
without a tool called a chopper gun.
it shreds the fiberglass into thin, loose fibers
and impregnates them with resin
while shooting them into the mold.
a fiberglass chopper gun has a chopper that shreds
and shoots the fibers, a nozzle that sprays those fibers
with resin, and a catalyst to harden it, an air cylinder
that drives the entire system,
and separate pumps for the resin and catalyst.
the make the resin pump,
they first cut a stainless steel tube
to a length of about 10 inches.
all the pump's key components are made of stainless steel,
which is very durable and doesn't rust.
this tube will become the cylinder for the resin pump.
they turn it on a computer-guided lathe.
the first machining tool reduces the tube
to the required diameter.
the second machining tool cuts a groove
in the cylinder for an assembly pin.
they manually file the edges of the cylinder smooth,
then polish the entire surface with sandpaper
to remove marks left by the machining.
once all the components are ready,
they begin assembling the resin pump.
it has a ball valve at the top and another at the bottom,
which open with suction and close with pressure
to enable or block the flow of resin.
workers fit a rubber o-ring seal around the seat
for the bottom ball,
then insert the seat into the bottom of the pump.
this retaining clip holds the seat in position.
they fit another o-ring seal on top,
then place the ball,
about 10 inches in diameter,
in the seat.
this spring retainer limits how high the ball can rise
when it's lifting to open the valve.
next, they attach the pump cylinder.
they take a preassembled upper ball valve,
attach a thermoplastic piston seal, then a retainer
that holds the seal in position
as the pump's piston,
which they now screw on,
moves up and down with the pumping action.
they insert the piston into the cylinder.
the tight fit creates a vacuum when the piston moves upward,
drawing resin into the pump and pressure
mo when the piston ves downward,
next, they add the top of the pump,
then assemble the top seal,
which contains a guide held in place by a retaining clip
that aligns the vertical movement
of the piston.
they screw the top seal to the pump top.
they secure the top
by inserting a pin into the cylinder groove.
the chopper's main components are the cutting head,
the anvil sleeve, and a hard rubber roller,
which the chopper's air-driven motor spins,
rotating the cutting head at 4,000 revolutions per minute.
this bearing pulls the woven fiberglass yarn, called roving,
into the cutting head, which has slots
for up to eight supersharp stainless steel blades.
the more blades you use, the shorter the chopped fibers.
this safety cover prevents fingers
from accidentally getting chopped in the process.
they mount the chopper to this spray gun.
the lines from the resin
and catalyst pumps connect to the back of the gun.
at the front of the gun, dual nozzles
simultaneously spray these chemicals onto the fibers
right after they exit the chopper.
workers mount the resin pump
on a stand along with a filter
that prevents the nozzle from clogging.
they install the air cylinder, then mount the catalyst pump
and hook up lines from both pumps
to the spray gun.
to operate the machine,
you hook up an air compressor to the machine's air input,
connect the pumps to the resin and catalyst reservoirs,
and set how much catalyst to deliver.
then you insert a strand of fiberglass roving
into the chopper and let her rip.
no resin and catalyst in this demonstration,
but normally, they hit the fibers
about 4 inches in front of the chopper gun,
which shoots a stream
of fiberglass-reinforced resin into your mold.