[ beeping ]
--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: a rubber tree's life-span
for natural rubber production is limited to about 25 years.
but making toys out of their wood
gives unproductive trees a second life.
this idea comes from southeastern asia,
home to most of the rubber and latex production worldwide.
this company, based in thailand,
manufactures toys such as this series
of animal-shaped racers made of locally farmed rubberwood.
they buy old trees
that have exceeded their productive life.
a worker feeds lumber through a wood-rounding machine.
the machine drives the log through a mill
and turns it into a rod.
the worker places the rod on a tray
alongside other pieces ready for cutting.
a cutting machine automatically
matches the length of the rods
while a round saw cuts out blanks,
which accumulate in a crate.
a router removes the sharp edges on the blanks.
stacked in a feeder tube,
the blanks drop down one by one on the router table.
an automated feeding mechanism
pushes each blank against the router head.
the router blade bites
into the blank and trims off the edge,
leaving the pieces ready for sanding.
at another station, a lathe
turns spherical shapes out of the wood.
several blades move in sequence to form the piece.
when a new length of wood comes through,
the front blade moves in.
once it backs away,
another set of blades shapes the piece laterally
before a cutter blade separates it from the rod.
a worker now pours a nontoxic, water-based paint
over the sanded blanks.
he transfers the batch into a tumbling machine.
the tumbling process will even out the color
and drain the extra paint to accelerate drying.
the worker closes and secures the lid of the tumbler
before he starts the machine.
the facility can simultaneously process 40 batches
of painted parts in 30 minutes.
the painted parts now go to a pad printer.
an automated arm feeds the parts to the printer,
which stamps each piece with a nontoxic paint.
a worker uses a table saw
to groove another set of painted parts.
the custom-made jig ensures that the cut is straight and even
and that the blade makes only a narrow
and shallow groove in the wood.
the worker places the grooved part
on a jig and bores a hole into the piece with a drill.
the machined piece goes to another pad printer.
the pad picks up paint from a tray
and transfers it to the wood.
this process, called tampography, allows the printer
to reproduce a design on an irregular surface,
such as this wood piece.
the printed parts dry at room temperature.
as a last pad printer paints two dots on the wood,
the face of the animal racer slowly takes shape.
this red-colored powder is processed rubberwood sawdust
entirely recycled
from the machining operations.
a worker fills molds with the reprocessed sawdust
and prepares them for casting.
the machine compresses the sawdust in a die
and turns it into a solid
and compact material called planwood.
a worker starts assembling the planwood pieces
to form the body of the racers.
she applies a thin coat
of nontoxic, formaldehyde-free glue
and presses two corresponding planwood pieces together.
she removes the excess glue with her finger
before she hammers a dowel
into the assembled planwood body.
to finish the head of the racer,
she inserts a felt piece into the groove
machined on top and presses the head
into the racer's body using a pneumatic press.
the worker then drives the axles
through holes in the planwood assembly.
she takes painted and pad-printed wheels
and applies a drop of fast-hardening glue
inside each wheel hub.
she then hammers the wheels into the axles
and takes the assembled toy
to a customized machine designed
to press the wheels firmly into the axles.
this finished chicken racer is one of a wide variety
of rubberwood toys
manufactured with
environment-friendly processes
and materials.
narrator: whether your preferred shade is light, medium, or dark,
owning a reliable electric toaster that evenly heats
and browns both sides of your bread just the way
you like it is one of life's small pleasures.
and if that toaster adds some style to your kitchen,
all the better.
making retro-style toasters is this british company's
bread and butter.
while some of its models are new designs
in a vintage style,
this one is authentically retro,
in continuous production since the 1960s.
the manufacturing equipment, however, is modern.
a computer-guided laser cutter cuts out many components
from sheet steel coated with
zinc for corrosion resistance.
they stamp the company logo
and then use the same press
to begin forming a rectangular box.
they bend three sides on this press...
then bend the fourth
on a machine called a box folder.
they rivet the body closed, then spray on a thick layer
of paint powder known as powder coat.
then, they run the body through a tunnel oven
for 10 minutes to bake the finish.
the computer-guided laser cutter also
cuts out several toaster tops
from a sheet of stainless steel.
this model is a four-slice toaster,
so the machine cuts four slots per top.
to make the manual bread ejector that pops up the hot toast,
they weld steel strips to a round steel bar.
moving the toaster's ejector knob lifts this bar,
raising the top of the toast out of the slot.
they bend the strips,
creating a cradle to stabilize the bread
so that it doesn't wobble and get caught
while moving up and down within the slot.
this machine makes the toaster's guard wires
out of copper-coated steel.
the guard wires are barriers that prevent the bread
from touching the toaster's heating elements.
the machine first welds cut horizontal wires
to four continuous vertical ones.
then, a blade chops the vertical wires
every 12 inches, producing two side-by-side guard wires.
workers cut them apart on a guillotine, then,
with a hand press,
fold over the top of each one.
this prevents the bread
from catching on the top of the guard wires.
now they take the toasting compartment
and insert the eight guard wires,
one for each side of the four bread slots.
then, they install the bread ejector.
next, the heating elements.
being a high-end toaster,
the elements are sheets of pure mica,
a mineral that's heat-resistant up to 1,800 degrees fahrenheit.
they connect them with
electrically conductive copper links.
they mount the switch
that selects the number of bread slices to toast.
then, they install a red neon light that illuminates
when you start the toaster and turns off
when the toast time has elapsed.
the timer switch has a bell
that sounds when the toast time is up,
at which point the switch cuts the current to the elements.
they attach the dials for the slice selector
and timer switches
and connect their wires to the main power cord.
then, they place the toaster compartment
into the body and screw on
the toaster's stainless steel top,
the protective film now removed.
they flip the toaster upside down
and wire up the elements.
they install the ejector knob,
positioning its spring against the bread ejector.
when the bell rings, indicating your toast is ready,
you move the knob to raise and retrieve your slices.
a technician tests the toaster thoroughly, ensuring
that all of the elements heat to the correct temperature,
that only the selected slots heat up,
that the timer is accurate,
and that the bell rings when the selected time elapses.
[ bell dings ]
they install the removable crumb tray,
then close up the bottom of the toaster
with a ventilated base plate.
nylon feet elevate the toaster for ventilation
and to prevent the screws attaching the base
from scratching your kitchen counter.
the style may be retro,
but this 1960s-design toaster was ahead of its time
with its energy-saving slice-selector feature
that stops the toaster's empty slots
from heating up unnecessarily.
narrator: laboratory furnaces
are small but powerful appliances.
they can reach temperatures
of 3,000 degrees fahrenheit or more.
these incredible furnaces are often used to test
the quality of things like fuel oil, greases, coal,
and to confirm the strength of structural materials.
exposed to the red-hot intensity of a laboratory furnace,
this piece of steel
should endure and even be strengthened by the exposure.
it's the ultimate test of the steel's integrity.
making a laboratory furnace
starts with this laser cutter.
it carves out steel panels for the lower cabinet.
a press brake folds the panels with precision
to make three-sided pieces of cabinetry.
a worker stacks them up.
the next worker applies a powder coat
to the metal parts using a compressed-air sprayer.
when baked on, the powder forms a tough thermoplastic skin.
at the next station, a worker
tucks the end of an iron alloy wire
into a lathe.
as the lathe spins,
it winds the wire around a mandrel,
producing a tight coil.
this coiled wire will serve
as one of the furnace's two heating elements.
after stretching the coil to widen the gaps
and bending it to create parallel rows,
the technician attaches electrical clips.
he flips a switch.
and electricity surges through the coil.
this relieves stresses in the metal caused
by the winding and bending.
he now inserts two coils into the ridges of the mold.
he transfers it to a vat filled with a ceramic fiber mixture.
a powerful vacuum pump pulls the mixture into the mold,
filling all the crevices.
the vacuum then draws out the moisture.
the coils are now embedded in a ceramic cake.
this cake bakes in an oven overnight
and solidifies,
encasing and insulating the heating coils.
a worker cuts the solid ceramic-fiber block in two,
creating two separate heating modules.
he trims them so they fit neatly in the furnace chamber.
a computerized router cuts out other insulation pieces
to fit the rest of the furnace chamber.
this ceramic brick is a threshold insulator.
this piece is a surround for the furnace door.
a team now puts all the ceramic fiber pieces together
in a metal framework.
the heating element blocks form the sides
of the furnace chamber.
they thread the wires from the coils
through the back panel.
they insert the side and back panels
in the framework.
they assemble the other ceramic fiber parts
to form an insulated chamber.
they screw the framework tight,
and this nestles the ceramic-fiber walls
more closely together.
they tuck the threshold insulator into place,
completing the laboratory furnace's heated chamber.
a technician now places the furnace's
electric heating control panel in the lower cabinet.
he fastens it to the metal cabinet with screws.
he wires the temperature-control board to a touch screen
and connects the power supply for the touch screen.
he installs a stainless steel shelf on top, towards the front.
he screws the front panel
that houses the touch screen to the cabinet.
he adds the top panel
that the furnace chamber will sit on.
he assembles the metal surround for the furnace chamber
to the control cabinet,
then slides the furnace chamber into place.
moving to the open back, he wires the heating elements
for power and inserts a temperature sensor
into a hole in the center of the chamber.
he assembles a connector block,
which will relay the sensor signal
to the controller.
he encloses the back with another metal panel.
the next technician hinges the door to the metal surround.
the door is a metal structure
that's filled with many layers of ceramic-fiber insulation.
he lowers and raises the door
to confirm that it operates smoothly.
this metal cover is the finishing touch.
he snaps it onto the door and secures it with screws.
the laboratory furnace's thick, insulated chamber
is ready to contain the extreme heat
and maintain it.
and these torrid conditions
are ideal for quality-control testing.
narrator: aerogels are the lightest solid materials
on earth.
they have nanosized pores that make it difficult
for cold or hot air to penetrate.
used to insulate the electronics of the mars rovers
and to capture comet dust,
aerogels are among the most fascinating materials.
aerogels in shaped forms look almost like holograms.
yet they feel like hard foam.
it's why they are often called frozen smoke or solid smoke.
making them starts with four ingredients --
a chemical called tmos, methanol,
concentrated ammonia, and water.
the technician adds measured amounts of tmos and methanol
to a beaker that has a magnetic stir bead
at the bottom.
he transfers the beaker
to a device that generates a rotating magnetic field.
this causes the bead in the bottle
to evenly mix the ingredients.
he pours the mixture into a larger beaker
and adds specific amounts of water,
additional methanol, and ammonia hydroxide.
as the ingredients are blended, a chemical reaction occurs.
the tmos and water react to form silica.
the chemical reaction
will also cause the mixture to become a gel.
but before that happens,
he quickly prepares the molds.
he pours pure methanol over a plastic grid
and arranges rectangular molds over the grid.
he injects precise amounts of the silica gel mix
into the molds
and leaves them to gel.
during this process, the methanol under the grid
evaporates, preventing excessive drying of the gels.
the mixture coagulates in just minutes,
but it takes about a day
for the gels to fully strengthen.
he then soaks the silica gels in methanol baths repeatedly
over a period of several days.
the methanol seeps in the gel's pores
to flush out impurities.
the gel pores are so minuscule
they can't be seen with the naked eye.
the technician decants the used methanol into a container.
he'll send it to a recycler to remove impurities,
and this will allow it to be used again
in the aerogel production process.
after several days of soaking in methanol,
the silica gels are purified.
they're ready for a process
known as supercritical drying.
it's a process that will convert these silica gels into aerogels.
a technician places the gels in a pressure vessel.
he locks the heavy steel lid with 12 large bolts and nuts
so it will hold tight against a pressure
that's 100 times greater than
that of the normal atmosphere.
he connects the hose that delivers liquid
and carbon dioxide to the vessel.
the liquid carbon dioxide replaces the methanol
in the gel's pores.
they then heat and pressurize the gels
until the carbon dioxide
in them becomes supercritical.
it's semiliquid, semigas.
the supercritical carbon dioxide
diffuses out without collapsing the gels' solid skeletons.
this transforms the silica gels
into transparent solids that are mostly air.
to demonstrate the insulating properties
of the nanosized pores,
they aim a blowtorch under an aerogel
with a peanut butter cup on the top.
it doesn't melt.
a technician then places the aerogel on a scale
to confirm its incredible low density.
this aerogel weighs less than a nickel.
next, using a scoopula,
which is a tool with a v-shaped dent,
she breaks an aerogel into little pieces.
she inserts the bits
into a glass tube with a bulb at the base.
she transfers the tube to a machine
that measures how much nitrogen gas
the aerogel bits take up at different pressures
to determine the size of the pores
and the surface area.
aerogels can have other magical properties.
to demonstrate,
she rubs specially treated aerogel particles on her hands.
she then plunges her hands into water.
the aerogel particles act like waterproof gloves
and repel the water.
this water resistance makes aerogels useful
for a variety of applications.
they can be added to paint
or other things to make them waterproof
and add insulating properties.
scientists continue to explore the potential of aerogels.
a gossamer synthetic material that weighs almost nothing,
there's a lot more to them than it may seem.