♪♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: a commercial drone is
a small, unmanned aircraft
with an onboard camera
it can capture a bird's-eye view
of the ground,
collecting up-to-the-minute
data useful for many types
of applications.
they're used to plan
infrastructure projects,
overseeing natural resources,
or manage farmland.
spanning about five feet
and a half in diameter,
this commercial drone
is known as an octocopter
it has eight rotors,
which enable it to maneuver
in the air like a helicopter.
the drone's components
are made of carbon fiber,
a highly stiff,
strong, and durable material
carbon fiber is also
lightweight,
a critical factor in aviation.
computer-guided milling
machine cuts the parts.
a technician manually
sands their edges smooth.
this component is half of one
of the drone's legs.
the mill also cuts out the top
and bottom frames
for the drone's body.
technicians then assemble
the two halves of each leg.
some of the drone's components
are produced by a 3-d printer,
the printer builds each part
layer by layer
out of a thin stream of plastic.
this is one of the drone's
eight arm receptacles.
a technician bores the hole
where the arm will be fitted.
the hole must be precise
to ensure a secure fit.
after verifying its diameter
with digital calipers,
the technician
installs the back part
of the receptacle and the lever
that clamps the inserted arm
firmly in place.
he attaches an electronic speed
controller to one end.
then, he screws the receptacle
to the bottom frame
of the drone's body.
the wires coming out
the other end of the controller
connect to an electrical power
harness and to the autopilot.
the autopilot is the onboard
computer that runs the drone.
he installs
the seven remaining receptacles,
then the power harness.
it has eight connectors,
one for each electronic
speed controller.
next, he attaches the top frame,
then the payload mount that
holds the camera and hard drive.
he links the payload mount
to this servomotor,
which is guided
by the autopilot.
the drone's body
is protected by a cover.
workers mount a sheet of plastic
on a vacuum former machine.
they start up
the machine's heating element
and position the plastic
just beneath it.
this gradually heats the plastic
to a malleable state.
once the plastic is soft,
they position a wooden mold
on the machine,
activate the suction,
then drop the sheet
onto the mold.
the vacuum draws the plastic
tightly against it.
they let the vacuum-formed
plastic to cool and harden,
then carefully
trim off the excess
they cut out a rough opening
for the payload mount
through that opening,
they secure the cover
to the computer-guided
milling machine,
which finalizes the shape
to precise specifications.
once the cover is finished,
they install it
on the top frame.
they attach the four legs
to the bottom frame.
then, they install the camera
on to the payload mount.
the mount pivots to angle
the camera at the ground.
they insert and clamp the arms
into the receptacles.
each arm is a carbon fiber tube
with a plastic rotor
that's driven
by a small motor underneath.
upon inserting an arm, its motor
makes contact with
its electronic speed controller.
they also install the autopilot,
the autopilot executes
the programmed flight path
and operates the camera,
the servomotor
that moves the payload,
and the electronic
speed controllers.
the drone operator
can communicate wirelessly
with the autopilot
using a remote control.
but it's more common
to program the gps coordinates
of the drone's route
prior to takeoff.
narrator: aquariums have been
around for hundreds of years.
even now, having a body
of water in a glass box
seems like magic.
the most common aquarium
fish is the goldfish,
domesticated in china
more than 1,000 years ago.
goldfish are a type
of carp native to asia.
they tend to be
silver or gray in color.
but ancient chinese breeders
took advantage of orange
and yellow mutations
to breed a gold-colored fish.
like all fish, aquarium goldfish
start life as eggs.
to start the breeding process,
a worker separates the males
from the females.
telling the girls
from the boys can be difficult.
but if she finds eggs,
there's no question.
it must be female.
the eggs fall to the bottom.
this facility harvests around
1,000 eggs a day.
adding oxygen
helps the eggs mature.
a week later, the eggs hatch.
the hatchlings are called fry.
by the second week,
they're little fish.
not all of them are
the typical orange color
even after centuries
of breeding,
many of them are still
silver and gray.
as the fry increase in size,
workers must transfer them
from buckets
to larger holding tanks.
this facility sells fish
at different stages of growth.
here, a worker selects
a particular size to sell.
once the selection process
is complete,
she transfers the selected fish
to a bag for transportation.
she adds air so the fish
will have enough oxygen
during transport.
a worker tosses dry food
into a series of ponds.
each pond is
roughly 100 square feet
and holds about 500 fish.
the food provides the nutrients
needed for growth.
a worker checks the fish tanks
for signs of illness,
such as parasites or fungus.
he carefully portions out
and adds a liquid
known as methylene blue.
it's an anti-fungal treatment.
these 1-year-old fish
are a different type
of carp known as koi.
koi were first bred in japan
for their color
and pattern variations.
a worker isolates
a quantity of koi
with a specially designed
shallow net.
this allows her to select
the right-sized fish
to bag for sale.
the bagged fish await
transport to the market.
it's time to prepare the bags
of goldfish for shipping.
a worker empties a batch of them
into a netting
suspended in water.
a team of workers sort
through the goldfish.
they select the fish
that meet the size criteria
and use spoons
to transfer them to a bucket.
to prepare fish for shipment,
workers dip them
in a green solution.
they then rinse them
in clear water
before bagging them again.
the green solution contains
a specially
calibrated medication
that helps reduce stress
during transport.
next, a worker
adds air to the bag,
ensuring the fish
have plenty of oxygen
while en route.
the fish have been
double bagged for protection.
a second worker squeezes out
some of the oxygen
so the bag won't take up
too much room,
then seals the top
of both layers.
a packer carefully loads four
bags into a styrofoam box.
the box provides a rigid casing
to protect the fish
while insulating them
against temperature fluctuations
during transport.
this facility also sells
whole aquariums
already populated with fish.
a worker inspects
a row of aquariums,
assessing the size
and quality of the fish
while checking for
any signs of disease.
the facility sells
50,000 fish a week,
or to two million every year.
narrator: when a plane lands,
the tires burn rubber
that melts into the pavement.
this can make the runway
slick when wet.
special cleaning machines ensure
that the runway is always clean
and clear for
takeoff and landing.
they blast off
the rubber streaks,
then suction
the rubber bits into tanks.
a runway-cleaning machine
is a serious power washer.
it pressurizes hot water
to at least 20 times the force
of the average power washer.
the spray heads
are designed specifically
for blasting away
aircraft tire rubber
that's melted into
airstrip pavement.
they ensure airports
are a safe place to land.
making one starts
with the hydraulic motors
that spin the sprayers.
a technician inserts a shaft
that will hold the spray bar
into a motor unit.
he installs sealing cylinders
to prevent hydraulic oils
from leaking.
he tops the assembly
with a metal plate.
the plate serves as a base
for thrust bearings,
which he installs next.
ceiling caps complete
the thrust bearing assembly.
a computerized test system now
measures the motor's torque
and the flow
of hydraulic fluids.
the system also
simulates the force
of the highly pressurized water
to confirm that
the thrust bearings
will keep the motor stable.
a powerful water-jet tool
carves through steel
to produce the components
for the arm
that holds the runway
cleaner's spray heads.
a worker then fits
the steel plates together.
he welds the seams
to create permanent bonds.
and this completes
the stray arm's structure.
after the arm has been
sandblasted and painted,
they hoist it to the front
of the runway-cleaning truck.
they attach it with large,
zinc-coated steel bolts.
a worker then mounts
hydraulic motors
to a long, wheeled bracket.
he removed the sealing caps
before this installation
to make it easier.
once the motors have been
secured to the bracket,
he replaces the caps.
he attaches the wheeled bracket
to the spray arm
and installs metal shrouds
for the sprayers.
they have fringes
of nylon bristles
to contain the spray.
he fastens rotating sealers
to the hole in the center
of each shroud
to keep out dirt and water.
he screws the spray bars
to the shafts that
extend from the motors.
the nozzles are made
of sapphire, a tough mineral
that can withstand the force
of the pressurized spray.
the next worker runs
vacuum hoses to the shrouds
and connects them using
cam and groove couplings.
the sprayer assemblies
are now complete.
the team lowers a large gearbox
between the frame rails
of the truck.
they bolt it to the rails.
this gearbox will transfer power
from the truck engine
to a high-pressure pump
and the vacuum.
the pump and vacuum systems
have been assembled
into one big module.
a technician
tests the belt and pulley
that will connect
to the gearbox.
it's in good, working order,
so they cover the system
with steel casing
for safety reasons.
this module is ready
to be assembled
to the runway cleaner truck.
it weighs 2 1/2 tons, so a crane
does the heavy lifting.
workers then build a tank
that's as tall as they are.
this tank will contain
the rubber bits
vacuumed off the runway,
along with the water used
in the cleaning process.
once it's been painted,
they assemble it to the chassis
next to the clean water tanks.
moving inside the truck cab,
a worker installs
controls for the runway
cleaner's operation.
one console has a joystick
for manipulating the position
of the spray heads.
other switches
are for the operation
of the water pump and vacuum.
runway cleaners can also be used
to erase painted lines
when landing strips
need to be reconfigured.
just adjust the nozzle size
and forward speed,
and, like the rubber streaks,
the lines disappear.
narrator: people have been
playing games
with shuttlecocks for millennia.
in the mid-19th century,
the british created
the game badminton,
in which players
hit a shuttlecock
back and forth over a net.
made of feathers and cork,
the shuttlecock
predates badminton
by thousands of years.
many people are familiar
with the plastic shuttlecocks
used for badminton games
in backyards everywhere.
but serious players
use the original
feathered shuttlecock.
this facility uses duck feathers
to build their shuttlecocks.
workers start by aligning them
with the feather side up
and storing them in cups
in preparation for
the next phase of production.
having the feathers aligned
makes it easier
for a worker to feed
them, one by one,
into a specialized
sorting machine.
this device has
26 different sensors
that measure each feather.
the feathers must be
a specific size
and have a precise angle.
the machine sorts feathers
of the same size and angle
into different bins.
sometimes, the sensors
are unable to measure
certain feathers,
those feathers fall
into a separate bin.
a worker uses a special chart
to measure them by hand.
the tips of these shuttlecocks
are made of cork
and synthetic foam
covered with white leather.
it's time to start
assembling the shuttlecocks.
each shuttlecock
has 16 feathers,
which must all be
precisely the same length.
the punching machine
begins the assembly process.
it starts by punching 16 holes
in the perimeter
of the shuttlecock tip.
the worker feeding the feathers
into the device
must keep pace
with the machine.
a worker uses flat-nose pliers
to adjust the angle
of each feather.
she then places the shuttlecocks
inside a miniature wind tunnel
to see if they're
properly balanced.
on some shuttlecocks,
each feather might have
a slightly different angle
to maximize balance.
once the angle of the feathers
has been adjusted,
they're transferred to a machine
that applies a bead of glue
around the interior perimeter
of the shuttlecock tip.
this secures
the feathers in place.
to further stabilize
the feathers,
workers place them in
a specialized sewing machine
that binds them
securely together
with two rows of thread.
the threads stitch
each feather to the next.
this process
strengthens the shuttlecocks,
helping them maintain
their shape
even when they're getting
slammed back and forth
over a net.
when the machine has finished
stitching a shuttlecock,
a worker ties off the thread
to keep it from unraveling
and cuts off the excess.
finally, she evens out
the thread rows.
with the threads in place,
the shuttlecocks must
undergo a final tuning.
a worker once again
adjusts the feathers
to ensure proper balance.
a machine applies glue
to the threads
on the shuttlecock,
locking them in place
to give them
the necessary rigidity.
the thread is made to
quickly absorb glue.
a worker applies a green strip,
which indicates
a slow-speed shuttlecock.
medium-speed shuttlecocks
get a blue strip.
fast ones are red.
it's time for
quality-control testing.
a machine equipped
with a racket-like arm
fires the shuttlecocks
to a waiting worker.
shuttlecocks can
travel at speeds
as high as 300 feet a second.
that's twice as fast as
a pitcher can throw a baseball.
once the shuttlecocks have
passed the quality-control test,
a worker inserts 12 at a time
into long cardboard tubes
similar to those used
to hold tennis balls.
with its 16 feathers,
it's no wonder
the shuttlecock is also
known as a birdie.
these high-quality products
are ready to fly.