-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: coconut shells used to be considered
agricultural waste,
but today they're processed into biofuel for the barbecue.
in countries like thailand,
companies convert the shells into briquettes
that burn cleanly for an extended period.
throwing away these shells
would be a real waste of energy.
instead of ending up as landfill,
coconut shells are being used to fire the grill.
processed into briquettes that burn virtually smoke-free,
the shells are now considered a resource instead of garbage.
converting coconut shells to charcoal starts
with the partial-combustion process.
inside these brick igloo-style kilns,
they create a burning environment
that allows the shells to be carbonized
but doesn't reduce them to ash.
the kilns are partially underground.
the surrounding soil helps to seal the fire.
this keeps the air levels down for a slow, smoldering burn.
a worker bricks up the kiln door.
and he seals these bricks with mud instead of cement.
this will allow the door to be dismantled later
without ruining the bricks,
preserving them for reuse in the next burn.
from the top, he ignites the fire using soft
wax as starter material.
because of the limited air in the kilns,
the fire burns out after 20 to 24 hours.
a worker takes the door apart and rakes the charred remains
of the coconut shells into a basket.
they have been converted into a rich charcoal.
he heaps the blackened shells into a pile.
and under the intense sun, moisture from water,
used to extinguish any hot spots, evaporates.
the charcoal dries out and breaks easily.
it's now ready to be processed into briquettes.
workers load the charcoal pieces into grinders.
this is dirty work.
so they protect their faces with scarves
and their hands with gloves.
inside the grinding machines,
rollers pulverize the charcoal,
reducing it to a fine powder.
the powder flows into bins below.
a worker then transfers the charcoal powder to a mixer.
he adds a generous amount of starch made
from the root of the cassava tree.
together with water, the starch will bond
the charcoal particles together like glue.
the mixer whisks it all together like pastry.
the consistency is right when the particles form clumps
when pressed together.
the moistened blend exits
the mixer and spills into a bin.
this coconut shell charcoal
is now ready to be pressed into briquettes.
the next worker loads the charcoal into a press.
it forces the tacky black powder through a die
to press it into a perpetual hexagon
with a hole in the center.
as the machine extrudes the charcoal,
a worker chops it into briquettes
that are just over 3 inches in length.
these coconut charcoal briquettes
have now taken shape.
but they're not yet ready for the grill.
they're soft and mushy
to the touch and crumble easily.
to firm them up,
they place them in structures
with open fires in the center.
they close the doors
and leave the briquettes to bake
over a period of about 24 hours.
the heat fuses
the charcoal particles together.
and the briquettes harden.
out of the curing chamber,
this briquette is solid to the touch and clean too.
it leaves no sooty residue.
from coconut shells to barbecue briquettes,
it's been quite a transformation.
this coconut shell charcoal is now ready to sizzle.
♪♪
narrator: in many disciplines, you have to take measurements.
sometimes, those measurements are so minute
they're difficult or impossible
for the human eye to determine.
so a ruler or tape measure can't help.
what you need instead is a precision-measuring tool
called a dial indicator.
on this dial indicator,
each graduation is 0.001 inches.
a full revolution of the hand measures
100 thousandths of an inch.
to make a key component, called the bridge plate,
this automated punch press stamps out brass circles,
which are about 2 inches in diameter.
workers place each bridge plate
into a manual punch press,
which makes location holes
that will correctly position the bridge plate
on the next press.
this press makes holes for mounting screws,
locating pins, as well as for three precision jewels,
which reduce friction on moving metal components.
this lathe begins the process
of shaping a stainless steel rod
into the dial indicator's main measuring component,
called the rack.
under a shower of cutting oil,
the machine drills and threads a hole on each end
for attaching a contact made of plated steel.
next, this milling machine cuts teeth spaced
25 thousandths of an inch apart.
one of the dial indicator's gears runs
along these rack teeth to turn the hand
that displays the measurement.
this computer-guided machine forms an aluminum bar
into another key component,
called the bridge.
the bridge has holes for screws
and locating pins
that align with those in the bridge plate
so that the two can fasten,
sandwiching the gears in between.
the bridge also has holes for three jewels,
which workers insert with a punch press.
jewels are doughnut-shaped synthetic rubies
set in a brass ring.
they line the holes for the gears
and other moving components.
the jewel's surface is very smooth.
so it eases friction on the component.
workers check every jewel under a microscope
to make sure it didn't crack when pressed into the hole.
the dial indicator's outside case is made of aluminum,
shaped by this computer-guided turning and milling machine.
workers spray the case with powdered paint
using an electric charge
to draw the particles onto the surface
in a thorough, even coat.
then, they bake the case in an oven for 20 minutes
to make the paint finish ultra durable.
they put the case on a machine
that presses in top and bottom steel stems,
which will hold the rack in place.
they mount a hair spring on the bridge plate.
this spring allows the gear
to return to its original position
after moving the rack upward to take a measurement.
they insert what's called a pinion
for the large dial hand in the center jeweled hole
and a second gear into the jeweled hole
for the small dial hand.
then, they attach the bridge.
next, they insert the rack
into the case through the stem
and screw a contact into each end.
then, they install a brass spring-loaded rack guide.
it prevents the rack from rotating
so that its teeth always face the rack gear.
they mate the case with the rest.
then they push in the stem
while holding the hand pinion to wind the gear.
they install the printed aluminum dial
on the bridge plate side
and mount the hand for the small dial on a pinion
protruding from the top of the gear.
they mount the large dial hand onto its pinion.
they place the movable dial
into a grooved ring, called a bezel,
and snap the bezel onto the case.
when you turn the bezel, the dial moves with it.
the back of the case is shaped with a lug
for mounting the tool to a fixture.
the movable dial lets you zero the indicator.
you lock in the dial position with this twist bolt.
the factory tests every dial indicator
with this micrometer head.
it pushes in the rack to a specific measurement.
every time the large hand rotates a full revolution,
indicating 100 thousandths of an inch,
the small dial hand clocks one graduation.
this test guarantees no tool leaves the factory
without delivering made-to-measure accuracy.
♪♪
narrator: cutting or sanding metals and other materials
can produce combustible airborne dust or fumes,
which can ignite or be inhaled.
that's why it's safer to do this work
on a wet downdraft table.
this machine captures and filters hazardous particles
from the work space.
a powerful blower pulls the flammable dust down
through the openings of the grid tabletop.
then a continuous spray of water
extinguishes the dust
and washes it down into a reservoir at the bottom,
where a filter removes it.
because stainless steel doesn't corrode,
this computer-guided laser cuts the components
that come into contact with water
out of stainless steel sheets.
workers pass each part through a wide-belt sander
to smooth out rough edges left by the cutting.
when the part exits the sander,
they thoroughly brush off the metal dust.
then, they bend the part into the required shape
using a computer-guided machine,
called a press brake.
a welder then fuses the parts,
constructing the machine in sections.
this is the table section that contains the tabletop
and the wash-down system
that processes the combustible dust.
workers clean all the welds with a machine
that uses a combination of chemicals and electricity.
they brush on a protective coating
to make the welds corrosion-resistant.
then, they wash the unit with soap and water.
in the reservoir at the bottom,
they install the water-inlet filter.
when the blower sucks the dust under the tabletop,
spray nozzles douse it with water.
the dusty water flows down into the reservoir,
where this filter traps the dust
before a pump sends the water back up to the spray nozzles.
to ensure that no water leaks out,
a worker caulks this entire section of the machine
with marine-grade sealant.
on the left side, they mount the housing
for the mist-eliminator filter.
it captures water droplets from the airstream
before the blower exhausts it.
to that, they attach the blower housing.
it has a side opening for the blower
and a top opening for a silencer
that muffles the noise of the blower exhaust.
now, they install the blower.
it consists of an electric motor
turning a blower wheel.
the resulting centrifugal force
sucks air through the machine
and out the exhaust.
they insert the filter into its housing.
the filter is polyester, so it's mold resistant,
which is critical given that it gets wet.
now, they install the water tree,
a stainless steel wall with baffles
that make the dusty water cascade into the reservoir.
these probes ensure there's always the optimum amount
of water circulating through the machine.
they send an alert to the control panel
if the water level in the reservoir
rises too high or drops too low.
after installing a plumbing connection
for the wash-down system,
they install walls to contain
the dust over the work surface
and the silencer over the blower exhaust.
then, they complete the assembly
of the wash-down system
by connecting pipes with spray
nozzles to the plumbing connection.
finally, workers install the tabletop,
made up of two steel grates.
the blower sucks the dust through the grates' openings.
you can cushion the tabletop with a rubber grid mat.
when you press the start button on the control panel,
the blower begins drawing air.
and the nozzles begin spraying water.
this demonstration with the smoke machine
shows the powerful downdraft
that gives industrial workers a breath of fresh air.
♪♪
narrator: to play most woodwind instruments,
the musician blows air through a reed made of cane.
the reed vibrates to create sound,
just like the vocal cords in our throat.
a bassoon reed is comprised of two thin blades of cane
rather than one, so it's called a double reed.
[ bassoon playing "in the hall of the mountain king" ]
a bassoon reed has twin blades at the top
that vibrate to produce sound and a tube at the bottom
that fits onto the bassoon's lead pipe.
the reed maker begins with a stalk of cane
that's almost an inch in diameter.
with a single strike of a cylindrical,
x-shaped blade,
he splits it into four equal strips,
then uses a guillotine to cut each strip to a length
of 4 3/4 inches.
after soaking a strip in water
for about 8 hours to soften the fibers,
he laterally slices off about half the cane.
then, he places it in a precision gouger
and thins it to approximately 0.05 inches,
give or take a fraction of an inch.
he verifies the thickness
with a precision-measuring tool,
called a dial indicator.
he clamps the cane in a reed-shaped template
and trims away the excess.
this gives the cane a distinct contour.
he removes the outer layer of rigid bark
and thins out the middle,
which will become the dual blades of the reed.
next, he cuts a pattern that will enable the reed
to vibrate at the frequencies required to produce
the bassoon's full range of 44 notes.
then, he scores both ends of the cane
to make them flexible enough
to be bent into a half circle.
he folds the cane in half and ties it
with a piece of brass wire.
the fold will form the double blades
at the top of the reed.
the opposite ends,
once bent into mating half circles,
will form the tube at the bottom.
keeping the cane wet, he heats a cylindrical-forming mandrel
over the flame of an oil-burning lamp.
then, he wraps the tube end tightly with twine.
the heat softens the cane's fibers,
molding them under pressure from the tightly wound twine
to the shape of the mandrel.
this forms the two adjoining half circles
into a perfectly round tube.
after a few seconds,
he removes the forming mandrel
and unwraps the twine.
he inserts a holding mandrel of the same diameter
and wraps it with a rubber band.
he puts the reed aside to dry for about a week.
this sets the shape permanently.
when he unwraps and unfolds the reed,
he sands the edges of the two adjoining half circles
so that they meet perfectly.
then, he refolds the reed,
securing it with three wires
spaced at specific intervals.
the distance between the wires,
in concert with the curved shape of the cane,
finalizes the contour of the reed,
which determines how it vibrates.
one the wires are correctly positioned,
he wraps the tube end of the reed
with strong synthetic string.
this will contain the tube dimensions
when the reed is resoaked.
he coats the string with glue
to further strengthen the tube.
once the glue dries,
he reams the inside of the tube
to fit perfectly into the bassoon's lead pipe.
he places a ruler against the first wire
and makes a mark of just
over an inch out toward the folded tip.
then, he clips off the folded tip.
the reed now has double blades
that vibrate when a musician blows air through them.
[ bassoon playing ]
because cane is a plant, not a synthetic material,
there are slight natural variations from reed to reed.
so bassoonists make the last minor adjustments themselves
with profilers and other tools
until their reed vibrates beautifully.