>> narrator: today on
"how it's made"...
scalpels...
oil paints...
british police helmets...
and ice axes.
the scalpel is the surgeon's
trademark tool.
its short blade is razor-sharp
and designed to slice swiftly
and cleanly.
this little knife may seem like
a simple instrument, but its
incredible precision, along with
a surgeon's steady hands, is key
to a safe and accurate medical
procedure.
scalpel handles are made from
rods of stainless steel.
the blades are made of either
carbon steel or stainless steel.
they're sterile and designed for
one-time use only.
the blade steel is extremely
thin, less than .02 of an inch.
it arrives at the scalpel
factory in coiled strips.
the first machine feeds the
strips into a press.
a die inside punches out
unfinished blades, called
blanks.
blades will vary in size and
contour, but they all have the
same center slot for attaching
the handle.
when you flex a blank, it bends
entirely out of shape.
that's because the steel still
needs to be tempered.
the blanks pass through a
furnace for about 30 seconds.
the heat alters the molecular
structure of the metal,
hardening it.
now the blank has the
flexibility a scalpel blade
requires.
next, the blanks move through a
punching tool that pops them
from the strip...
and stacks them on a peg.
a worker threads a metal ring
through the slots to keep them
together, then sends the whole
set of blanks for surface
polishing.
this process will restore the
metal's original sheen, which
was dulled by the heat
treatment.
next, workers visually inspect
every blank, discarding any
defective ones.
they transfer the blanks from
the ring to a metal rod using a
gauge to measure out the right
number.
from here, the rods are mounted
onto grinding machines.
each one picks up a blank with a
magnet, then places it in a
holder.
the holder runs the blank
against a wheel coated with
diamond particles.
this powerful abrasive shapes
and sharpens a cutting angle,
transforming the blank into a
blade.
as the blades come off the
grinder, they cling together
because the magnet that fed them
into the machine magnetized
them.
to cancel this effect, a
demagnetizing machine passes an
electromagnet behind the stacks
of blades.
after a thorough washing in an
ultrasonic cleaning tank, the
blades move on to final
inspection.
wearing protective rubber gear,
workers carefully scrutinize the
cutting edges, discarding any
blade that's less than perfect.
each and every blade passes
through two different
inspectors.
in the packaging department, a
machine covers each blade with a
brown paper strip that contains
an anti-corrosion chemical.
this provides extra protection
against rust.
a second machine slips each
blade into a foil packet, then
cuts the packets apart.
each packet bears the blade
model number and tracking code.
as the blades come off the
packing machine, an inspector
does one last quality check.
then he counts the blades and
boxes them.
of course, it's critical that
surgical blades be sterile, so
the boxes go into a cobalt
radiation chamber for about six
hours.
this obliterates any lingering
contaminants.
when the boxes exit the chamber,
they're hospital-ready.
in the operating room, it's
simply a matter of sliding the
blade onto the protruding part
of the handle, called the
bayonet.
surgeons make the most of their
dexterity by choosing a handle
that best fits their hands and
best suits the procedure their
hands will be performing.
coming up, mixing up a wide
palette of colors at an
oil-paint factory.
>> narrator: oil paint dates
back to ancient times when
artists mixed minerals and other
elements with wax or oil.
in the 1400s, they discovered
that linseed oil was ideal as a
pigment binder because it
allowed blending and glazing in
layers.
centuries later, the colors in
those paintings are still
vibrant.
today, many oil paint pigments
still come from natural sources,
though most are synthetically
made.
factories buy both types of
pigments in powdered form to
make their paints.
cuttlefish ink yields brown
pigment, lead produces a
specific yellow, and mercury ore
makes red.
in the past, pigments have also
come from stones, tree bark,
plant gum, ground up glass, and
even arsenic.
this company's research
laboratory spends about two
years developing a color recipe.
a chemist mixes specific amounts
of linseed oil and pigment into
a machine called an automatic
mueller.
it rubs the ingredients
together, dispersing the pigment
particles throughout the oil.
for each sample, the formulation
is altered slightly in search of
the perfect result.
the research team compares the
resulting colors and selects the
best one.
to produce a color on a large
scale, workers start by pumping
a specified amount of linseed
oil into a mixer.
then they add the precise amount
of pigment.
most colors are made with just
one pigment.
the precise mixing time and
speed depends on the kind of
pigment formulation being
created.
next, the mixture is spooned
into a mill.
three dispersion rollers rub the
ingredients, separating pigment
particles and coating them in
oil.
the recipe specifies how much
pressure the rollers apply,
how fast they turn, and how long
they work the mixture.
milling can take hours or even
days, depending on the texture
of the pigment.
the quality-control lab takes
samples from each batch coming
off the mill and subjects them
to a series of tests.
technicians scrutinize paint
from both sides of the mill to
ensure the mixture is being
processed evenly.
first, a spread test.
a heavy brass weight goes onto a
blob of paint for a prescribed
period of time.
then, inspectors evaluate the
volume of color and measure the
distance it spread.
if it doesn't spread far enough,
it needs more milling.
next, a dispersion test.
the markings on this gauge
indicate the size of the paint's
particles in microns, millionths
of a meter.
if the particles are too big,
the paint hasn't been milled
enough.
finally, inspectors time how
long it takes the paint to dry
to the touch.
each color has a specified
drying time, ranging from two
days to two weeks.
the factory produces a chart
that displays its 120 paint
colors.
workers brush each color onto a
primer-coated paper.
when the paint dries, they cut
each bar into rectangular
swatches called chips.
the chart is assembled using
this mounting machine.
the bottom has a section for
chips of each color.
and the top contains a cardboard
chart coated in glue.
as the machine closes, each chip
aligns perfectly with its
designated spot on the chart.
back in the production line, the
factory packages one color at a
time in toothpaste-style tubes
that will be finished off with
twist caps.
once the labels go on, the tubes
make their way to the filling
machine.
there, the tubes have their tops
screwed on.
a nozzle squirts in the paint.
then clamps flatten the edges
shut.
a roller folds over the edge to
strengthen the seal against
squeeze pressure.
now these oil paints are finally
ready to meet the canvas.
when we return, a new twist on
the traditional british police
helmet.
>> narrator: british bobbies are
used to standing tall because of
their distinctive hats.
these traditional police helmets
are almost a foot high.
that added height can't hurt
when you're staring down a bad
guy.
bobbies' helmets have looked the
same way for a century and a
half.
today, hatmakers use a metal
mold to create that signature
shape in fortified plastic.
the mold descends into an oven.
a worker places a sheet of
plastic overhead.
he lowers the lid and slides the
heated cover over it.
it takes a couple of minutes for
the heat to soften the plastic.
the mold rises.
a vacuum below pulls the plastic
into shape.
it hardens almost instantly.
a firm tap with a rubber mallet
releases the shell from the
mold.
a band saw slices away the
excess plastic along the brim.
and now the helmet is ready to
be covered.
for that, the factory uses
water-repellant wool.
the helmet pattern is cut out in
two pieces.
these halves are stitched
together, making a raised seam,
which gives the helmet a
smoother line.
the insides of the fabric covers
are covered with glue.
then they're steamed.
a coating of glue is brushed all
over the helmet's shell.
the fabric cover has now reached
the perfect dampness, making it
easier to pull over the glued
surface of the plastic helmet
shell.
the fabric gets stretched a bit
so it'll fit tightly without
buckling.
then, a wooden tool is used to
smooth away any remaining air
bubbles.
the excess fabric is trimmed
away.
then, rubber piping is sewn
around the brim to reinforce it
and give it a neater edge.
the prong ends of the helmet's
decorative metalwork are dipped
in a chalky powder, which mark
its positioning on the crown.
holes are drilled through the
markings.
then the ornament is installed
and its prongs are folded
against the inside of the
helmet.
next, workers stitch together
strips of tape, plastic, and
foam to make the helmet's
harness and chinstrap.
they fit the harness assembly
inside the helmet, then secure
it with an industrial stapler.
metal banding is wrapped around
the helmet and pinned down.
not only does this banding hide
the staples, it gives the helmet
a snazzier look.
an ornate helmet plate featuring
the police department's insignia
goes on the front.
next, a sponge liner is tucked
inside the helmet to protect the
officer in the event of a blow
to the head.
ventilation holes are punched in
the sides.
now it's time to size the helmet
with a special gauge.
any excess fluff is tweezed away
and the wool is brushed to bring
up the pile.
finally, workers attach the
label that assures the product
meets all specifications.
this police helmet is now ready
to report for duty.
it takes about half an hour to
make one of these helmets, but
it should keep a bobby on the
beat safe and stylish for much,
much longer.
up next, ice-axe production
begins with a little heat.
>> narrator: when it comes to
mountain climbing, the ice axe
is a fundamental tool.
ice axes were invented in the
mid 19th century to help
mountaineers get a grip on
slippery slopes, pull themselves
to the summit, and stop a fall.
they're designed for peak
performance.
talk about a steep learning
curve.
climbing with an ice axe takes a
bit of practice and a lot of
courage.
production of an ice axe starts
with an aluminum rod.
a powerful press bends it into a
curve, giving it the basic
contour of an ice axe.
it's flattened and shaped in two
fiery dies.
each die has a top and a bottom
half, which are lubricated
between forgings.
the hot forging transforms the
metal rod.
it starts to look a lot more
like the shaft of an ice axe.
the long ridges add strength to
the metal while other
indentations mark where the
attachments are to go.
the forging creates a lip around
the perimeter of the shaft.
they call this excess metal
flash.
this press takes care of it in a
snap.
now, the ice-axe shaft has a
cleaner edge and it's quite a
bit lighter than the original
rod, an advantage when you're
toting it up a mountain.
that aluminum rod has gone
through quite a few stages, and
now it has a whole new profile.
this tub of vibrating ceramic
cones will smooth the shaft's
rough edges.
here, a computerized drill makes
holes into recesses that were
stamped into the shaft earlier.
these holes will be used to
attach other parts.
the machine changes the drill
bit to a circular blade.
then, guided by the computer, it
cuts a slot for the ice-axe
pick.
next, the saw moves to the other
end and thins out the area where
the handle will be attached.
using another drill bit, the saw
carves out a hole for the
adjustable finger rest.
here's a shaft that's already
been milled and drilled compared
with one yet to undergo the
process.
the shaft gets a protective
coating.
then, it's time to bring all the
pieces of the ice axe together.
a worker applies epoxy to the
inside of the rubber handle and
slides it onto the shaft.
the handle has an open end.
he beads a little more epoxy
onto it and inserts a steel
spike.
the spike is then riveted to the
ice-axe shaft.
this spike will come in very
handy on the mountain side.
plunging it into a snowy slope
can help a climber maintain his
or her balance on a slippery
uphill trek.
next, the adz slides into the
slot at the head of the shaft.
climbers use this tool to chop
steps in hard snow and ice.
the worker secures the adz with
nuts and bolts, and then he
installs the pick.
this hooked and jagged
attachment will help get the
climber up a mountain of hard
ice.
the bolts are tightened with a
torque wrench.
after all, a solid job here
could be a lifesaver.
and finally, the adjustable
finger rest is screwed to the
shaft just above the handle.
and now you have a tool that can
help you scale new heights.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...