>> narrator: today on
"how it's made"...
bacon...
snowblowers...
and a special 2-part report on
the making of the rolls-royce.
when it comes to breakfast,
bacon is one of our favorite
side orders.
its popularity actually goes
back centuries to the days when
people cured and smoked meats in
their own homes.
but, today, a quick trip to the
store, and anyone can bring home
the bacon.
bacon is now processed and even
precooked in factories.
it all starts with a load of
pork bellies.
they're tossed into a big
tumbler.
the action softens them, so it
will be easier to remove the
skins.
each pork belly goes skin-side
down on a conveyor belt.
this conveyor takes the pork
bellies to a long, automated
blade that slices the skin away
from the meat.
the skins drop onto another
conveyor belt to be processed
into pork rinds.
meanwhile, the meat pieces head
toward a flipping device that
turns them backside up, so
workers down the line can trim
off any remaining pieces of
skin.
next, they mix up a brine
solution which will cure the
pork.
salt is funneled into a tank of
water.
it's mixed thoroughly until the
salt dissolves.
then, liquid smoke and other
flavorings are added.
the pork bellies now pass under
an injector head.
its needles repeatedly inject a
curing solution into each pork
belly.
a metal hanger, called a comb,
is pressed into each of the pork
bellies so they can be hung on a
rack.
then, it's into the drench
cabinet for a shower of liquid
smoke.
as liquid smoke bombards the
meat, it adds flavor and color
to the surface.
the pork bellies are transferred
to a big oven.
they'll cook for five hours at a
low temperature.
that allows the flavoring to
permeate the meat.
now it's into a blast freezer
for a quick chilldown, then into
another cooler for a couple of
days.
the cooling firms the meat,
which makes it easier to slice.
the pork bellies head to a
sizing station, where their
sides get a quick trim.
they also pass under a metal
detector to confirm that no
piece of the metal hanger has
gotten lodged in the meat.
after that, the pork bellies are
stacked and wrapped, then stored
in the freezer until they're
ready to be sliced into bacon.
this is called the slice line.
here, workers load the meat
slabs into chutes.
the chutes sway back and forth
over a blade, which slices the
meat into bacon-sized pieces.
the bacon falls neatly onto a
conveyor belt.
another conveyor belt rolls over
the bacon slices to secure them
for cooking in a browning
microwave.
as the fat cooks off the bacon,
it drain into a trough.
these drippings will be used to
make gravy and pet foods.
the cooked bacon now exits the
microwave oven and comes under
the watchful eye of an
inspector.
she discards slices that are
broken or not up to par.
these wheels then roll the brown
bacon slices onto parchment
paper.
a tiny electronic eye keeps
track of the number of slices.
finally, the bacon is stacked
for packaging.
now, that's a job well done.
time to put the coffee on and
scramble up some eggs.
when we return, making the
machine that makes snow
shoveling obsolete.
>> narrator: snowblowers first
came on the market in the 1950s,
and before long, this
alternative to shoveling really
took off.
today's machines come in a range
of sizes, from smaller models
with 26cc engines to 50cc
machines 3 feet wide for plowing
through even the deepest snow.
at the heart of a snowblower are
rotating blades called augers.
the left and right augers spiral
in opposite directions in order
to move snow toward the middle.
there, a fan called an impeller
swallows the snow and blows it
out a chute.
each auger starts out as a
blank -- a partially formed
steel disk a little less than
1/8 inch thick.
this press finalizes the shape
with about 200 tons of pressure.
the bigger the snowblower, the
bigger its augers.
the press forms the left and
right augers at the same time.
then, a blast of air ejects them
onto separate conveyor belts.
next step, workers take a steel
tube, called a hub, and mount it
upright on an assembly jig.
then, they take an auger and
center it on the hub.
the hub and auger then travel
down a conveyor belt to a
robotic welder.
the robot fuses the two pieces
into a single unit.
elsewhere in the factory,
workers construct the steel
housing that will encase the
augers.
this housing consists of four
parts -- a cup to hold the
impeller, a backpiece with a
hole for the cup, and two side
plates.
this bar aligns the pieces in a
holder.
first, everything turns
upside down so the robot can
access the back and weld the cup
to the backpiece.
then, it flips right-side up
again, and the robot welds on
the side plates.
total construction time --
55 seconds.
the housings now undergo an
electrostatic paint process.
powder paint laced with a
positive electrical charge is
drawn like a magnet to the
housings, which have been
negatively charged.
workers inspect the coat of
paint and do any necessary
touch-ups.
then, the housings spend 15
minutes in an oven which bakes
on the paint.
in another part of the factory,
workers have bolted a
gas-powered engine to a painted
steel frame.
inside this frame, they assemble
the transmission -- the gear
system that transfers power from
the engine to the snowblower's
wheels and augers.
after bolting on the impeller,
that black component in the
back, they attach a large, steel
axle to the transmission-driven
sprocket.
then, they slide the now-painted
auger and hub units onto this
axle.
now the housing arrives.
workers bolt the auger assembly
into it.
the impeller slides into the cup
that's centered at the back of
the housing.
then, they screw the housing to
the transmission frame.
the last component is the
snowblower's handle, where the
control panel is mounted.
there's a lever for selecting
different speeds and clutch
levers that can be locked down
to direct the wheels and augers.
there's also a headlight so that
you'll be visible to oncoming
cars while clearing snow at
night or on a snowy day.
and, of course, there's a lever
that lets you choose the
direction you want to blow the
snow.
coming up, behind the scenes at
one of the most luxurious
production lines in the world.
>> narrator: if you have one of
these cars, you may also have a
chauffeur and a pretty big bank
account.
this rolls-royce costs more than
an average house in some cities.
but a house is just a place to
live, and you can really live it
up if you have a car like this.
since the company's inception in
1906, rolls-royce has been going
the extra mile when it comes to
perks and performance.
for many people, the car they
drive is a measure of their
personal success, and you don't
get much more successful than
this.
each rolls-royce starts with a
hand-welded aluminum body shelf
that's rigid yet lightweight.
then, workers handcraft the
components for a lavish
interior.
this gadget stitches together
sheets of wooden veneer.
the veneers have been cut from
the same piece of wood.
workers match the grain so each
side is a mirror image of the
other.
the technique is called
book-matching, and the look is
seamless luxury.
there are 40 or more solid,
wooden parts in the interior of
this rolls.
these are for the dashboard.
each of these parts is
hand-finished.
workers meticulously polish the
wood with a special paste that
enhances the grain.
a lacquer job puts a shine on
the woodwork.
inspectors scrutinize the
leather for any natural defects
and mark them in white.
they'll work around those
blemishes so no imperfections
will be visible on the car's
upholstery.
it will take as many as 18 hides
to make all the seats, panels,
and consoles.
leather pieces are carefully
stretched onto various
components.
the fit is set with a dryer.
ensuring the sewn leather parts
conform to all the curves and
crevices on the door panels can
be tricky.
but these workers, some of them
former saddlemakers, are experts
at the job.
they mount the upholstered
leather parts to the car's
interior and secure them tightly
with screws.
they fit handles and control
panels into the tailored slots.
next, they attach switches,
wiring, and other controls to
the instrument panel.
this framework has been crafted
from a single piece of magnesium
so there aren't any squeaky
joints.
the impressive radiator grille
has a purpose besides bringing
in cool air.
it houses the rolls' signature
hood ornament and its automated
platform.
workers test the platform to
confirm that it rises and
retracts smoothly.
then, they mount it under an
opening at the top of the
grille.
they check the spacing around
the opening's cover to make sure
there's enough room for things
to run smoothly.
the rolls-royce mascot is called
the spirit of ecstasy.
with the mascot now locked in
proud position, workers are
ready to assemble the car's
mechanics.
so stay tuned.
>> narrator: this rolls-royce is
looking good.
the body shell has the long
lines of luxury.
it's been equipped with flawless
leather upholstery and elegant
wooden paneling.
plush and posh, this car is now
ready for some serious engine
power.
it's bumper-to-bumper opulence
at this factory as these cars
are lined up to receive their
engine components.
workers install soundproofing
material on the floor of the car
to muffle engine noise.
then, they run the wiring loom
along the length of the vehicle.
this is the car's nervous
system.
it transmits huge amounts of
information that help run the
engine, transmission, even the
car's entertainment system.
next, the engine and
transmission system are hoisted
onto a metal platform.
this v-12 engine has 400-plus
horsepower.
workers complete the assembly
and make some final adjustments.
then, it's time for the engine
and car body to become one.
they call this the marriage.
the platform rolls the engine
down an aisle to be joined with
the awaiting car body.
then, it lifts the engine into
the cavity of the car.
it's secured with bolts.
then, the platform moves away to
get the next engine for the next
car.
workers double-check the
installation and mark parts with
yellow to confirm that they've
been fitted.
the engine is now installed, but
there are still a number of
steps before the car is
complete.
the instrument control panel is
mounted to the dashboard and
gets an upholstered leather
cushion.
veneer paneling is fitted around
the dashboard controls.
and the headlining, made of
cashmere and wool, goes into
place.
workers check the hydraulic cup
holders in the rear of the car.
then, they install two
batteries -- one for the engine,
the other for the cabin
controls.
a rocker cover is fastened to
the engine to stifle any noise.
they hook up a large air-intake
system because optimum engine
function requires a lot of
airflow.
there will be no fingerprints on
this windshield.
after it's wiped clean, workers
use a pulley system with suction
cups to lower it onto the car.
it's taped into place to allow
the adhesive to set, then it's
measured to ensure a perfect
fit.
next, the wheel-arch liners are
installed.
these hefty guards will protect
the car body from mud, gravel,
and debris.
finally, the wheels are mounted,
and this rolls-royce is ready to
roll.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
it takes several weeks to
assemble a rolls-royce, compared
to the day or two it takes to
manufacture an ordinary vehicle.
that's part of the reason why
one of these will set you back a
princely sum.
but if you win the lottery, this
could be one way to splurge.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...