--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, llc
>> narrator: today on "how it's made," boomerangs...
pinball machines... and strobe lights.
>> boomerang is a throwback to primitive times. back t
to hunt and that's likely how they discovered that certain
boomerangs have come a long way since then and are now finely
>> narrator: boomerangs come in many shapes, but fundamentally,    they
aircraft. construction begins with a solid piece of wo
this tree's growth rings have been highlighted to demonstrate how comp
become. because the wood from this section is denser than the i
rings, it's easier to work with. a woodworker takes 16 strips of that dense wood and places
in a steam box for 20 minutes. the steam makes the strips much more flexibl
in fact, they're so elastic, they can be bent by hand.
watch how he arcs all 16 layers at once with little effort.
has taken shape. to improve the contour, the s
mold. they'll stay in this mold for a day or two, l
and harden into the bent form. now it's time to laminate the
glue is spread onto each bent strip.   then the
together again back into the mold.  this time,
coated with wax to prevent the glue from sticking to it.
overnight. the next day, the laminated
it's solid but far too chunky to take flight.   a wood
pieces 8 to 12 millimeters thick.
one piece of laminated wood yields about six thinner pieces,   each of
boomerang in its own right. but it needs more form, and
so a more refined design is traced onto the wood and cut
but there's an easier way to make a boomerang -- with sturdy    aircraft
with plywood, there's no need to laminate and then physically
a woodworker simply cuts out the pattern...  then scu
wings with a drum sander.
he's made the tops of the wings curve upwards but in opposite
it's this contouring that will make the boomerang fly in a c
on some models, embedded lead weights are added for improved
that laminated boomerang gets the same contouring but files
sander. laminated wood responds better to this technique, but it's
more labor intensive and requires specialized skill.
size and the boomerang's aerodynamics will be thrown off kilter.
but our woodworker has the job down to a fine art.
to fine-tune the boomerang, he first softens it over a steaming kettle while twisting the w
into an upward flip. this blower dries the wood to
then the woodworker sets it on a flat surface to check the curve.  a sealant
boomerang, and finally, it gets several coats of lacquer for a
and now these boomerangs are ready to fly.    up ne
grilling.
>> narrator: the barbecue's origins are clouded in a bit of a smoky haze, but it's
that native caribbeans were the first to cook this way.   o
didn't have charcoal grills. they roasted meat over a smoky
today, people still love a good cookout, but now we have better   equipment
basic charcoal grills begin with big steel disks.   roll
soapy lubricant. then they're fed into a press that shapes each one into a
bowl. molding steel can be tricky.
it could tear instead of bend, so workers need to make sure
application of the soapy solution before it goes into the press.
this is a back view of the press. with each p
ram delivers 500 tons of pressure.  a similar
the barbecues' lids.
an operator inspects each part for splits and cracks. the
trims the rim. the scrap is tossed into a bin
next, the barbecue bowl spins around while an automated roller    flanges
after that, holes are punched into the bowl for ventilation.
welding guns. the guns fuse metal couplings to  the bowls to
attachments for the barbecue's legs. here handles
assembly machine. below, a turntable swings the
then the handles are welded to each side.
at another station, the barbecue lids get a handle of their own. no chef can
of a burger without this essential part. this one will allow the chef
lower the lid, to control the cooking temperature, and then lift it again when it's time
flip the burgers. the barbecue parts now travel on  an overhead
station. they're hosed down with soapy
once they're dry, it's off to the finishing department. he
a glass powder. then it's into a red-hot furnace  set to 1,
the furnace bakes the glass dust into an enamel finish that protects the barbecue from
and stains so they'll last for years.
next, they go under intense lights that expose any defects in what should be a  mir
finish. an inspector examines each part inside and o
a punch machine now makes dampers from aluminum.   i
shapes and embosses the company's logo onto them.  t
the chef to control the flow of air to the grill. nylon grips go onto the
and the damper is installed over the lid's ventilation holes.
complete the final assembly, and in just a few minutes, the
coming up, a high wire at a pinball factory.
>> narrator: before video games, the pinball machine reigned
you pull a plunger to get the ball rolling, and as your flippers send the silver sp
flying, the machine comes to life with flashing lights and
no wonder it's not yet game over for pinball. the game
unprogrammed and unpredictable. it all starts with reams of wiring for the game's   e
system. there's almost half a mile of
the color-coded wire is wound around pins and attached to connectors on the circuit b
technicians follow a detailed set of instructions, and an engineering diagram keeps t
from getting in a tangle. once the wires are all laid out, they're removed in loosely
bunches and dipped into a hot metal soup to solder them
but not all wires are soldered. some get attachments called
these connectors are crimped onto the ends of the wires with  a hydraulic
eventually, the lugs will be used to connect wires to at
but first, the cable is hooked up to a testing board where technicians check every
meanwhile, the play field is placed on a bed of nails and
as the nail bed rises and presses against the header, the nails prick the back of the
board, but the foam strips stop them from going all the way
these nail holes will serve as markers for installing pinball targets and tactical features
the play field. technicians drill a few holes, then cover the play fieldwi
metal template and drill some more.   these hole
mount the pinball gadgetry onto the play field. next, anchors are hammered
place. they'll secure the metal  r
balls from rolling off the play field.    a lamppo
place... followed by some plastic bumpers    and 115
now it's time to permanently attach all that wiring. some are soldered directly
the board. others are attached to switches.  a speake
cabinet for some major sound effects. then it's
essential tool -- the spring-powered plunger. workers attach a toy   vi
and add a ramp in the shape of a sword, along with a few other
finally, it's time for the inaugural run. the pinball is rolled into e
target and mechanism to test the game's electronic switches.
game. as technicians press all the
diagnoses any malfunctions. they rigorously test all of the    game's fe
if everything works, the play field is inserted into its
a shatterproof window slides into place to protect the play
gamers. a metal bar locks the window
finally, the header is attached, and this pinball machine is
coming up, little lights with lots of flash.
>> narrator: strobe lights often conjure up images of '70s di
but you'll also find strobe lamps -- the proper term, by the  way -- on a
police lights, and on towers and tall buildings to warn  lo
strobe lights even play a role in photography and on factory
a strobe lamp emits repeated flashes of high-intensity light.   at this f
begins with glass blowers. using a ribbon burner, they heat  glass tubes
3,000 degrees. this softens the glass for
but if it's too soft, the tubes will collapse, so the  gla
through a rubber hose to build counterpressure.
the size and shape of the glass tubes varies by model, but its
house a strobe lamp's essential components -- electrodes, lead
the electrodes conduct the current, which charges the gas
illuminate. this factory makes several
large quantities for the mass market, others in small quantities, custom-designed
specific clients. with mass-produced models,
after the glassblowing. custom orders are handmade from    start to
workers even make the electrodes manually. they weigh
metal powder and pour it into the cavity of a press similar to  what pharmac
use to make pills. this powder is a blend of several different materials,
the company won't divulge the ingredients.   the pr
pressure, compressing the powder into a pellet.   the f
pellet to ensure it meets quality standards.   the
hardening process called centering. they bake for nine minutes in
hydrogen-fueled oven. hydrogen is one of the hottest
3,000-degree heat fuses the powder particles into a solid
next, workers weld a lead wire to each electrode. then they insert two  ele
one for the positive current, one for the negative, into each   glass tube
then they melt the end of the tube closed. then they attach a wire
trigger lead. it prompts a transformer to send a high-voltage electric pulse
the electrodes, illuminating the gas.
this automated machine assembles the factory's mass-produced m
before starting it up, workers load the components -- a pair of electrodes fo
tube on top. now the machine takes over.
tube, injects xenon gas, melts the tube closed, then cuts off
the tube's interior must be completely free of contaminants   for th
so, just before the vacuum fill-and-seal operation, a hot coil encircles each tube to
away any impurities. on custom-made models, all of
with the strobe lamp complete, it's installation time.  th
lights you see on tow trucks and road-construction vehicles. i
lined with metallic film. a transformer regulates the
its three wires connect to the positive, negative, and trigger leads protruding from the l
a glass lens covers seals and protects the lamp within the reflector, and then this
is good to go.
strobe lamps are also used in
stroboscopes -- industrial
devices that help factories
perform quality-control
inspections on high-speed
production lines.
calibrate the light pulses to
the right interval and they
appear to stop the action so
that cameras or workers can
examine the goods.
it's the size, shape, and
configuration of a strobe lamp's
components, along with voltage
and other electrical specs, that
determines how long, how often,
and how quickly the light
flashes.
if you have comments about this
show, or if you would like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...