>> narrator: today on "how it's
made"...wooden bowls...
chain saws...
stackable potato chips...
and jet compressor blades.
there was a time when bowl
making was a cherished trade
passed down through generations
of woodworkers.
but today, with so much mass
mass-produced tableware,
handcrafted wooden bowls have
become a specialty item, and
this century's-old traditional
craft is practically a lost art.
each of these exquisite bowls is
made from a solid piece of
hardwood -- beech, maple,
walnut, or cherry.
logs arrive at the bowl mill
fresh from the forest, so
they're still very damp, and
that's an advantage.
because the moisture lubricates
the cutting tools.
the first step is to divide the
log into blocks with a chain-saw
operator measuring and
inspecting as he goes.
defects such as knots or
scarring dictate the length of
each block.
any cracks or other flaws are
marked with a red crayon.
next, a rip-saw operator uses
different size bowl patterns to
determine the best way to cut
the block.
the goal is to get the biggest
bowl-size pieces possible
without including any defective
wood.
each bowl-sized piece is called
a bowl blank.
this block is large enough to
yield three blanks, each of
which will produce a 17-inch
bowl and a series of
progressively smaller bowls that
nest inside it.
the blank is mounted on to a
woodworking lathe.
from this point on, production
is entirely dependent on the
lathe operator's skill.
as the block spins, he carves
out the bowls using a series of
specialized knives designed and
forged at this very mill.
first he uses this curved knife
to shear off the outer portion
of wood.
it takes great expertise to know
exactly how to angle the tool
and when to pull it out and
release the wood shavings and
prevent a jam.
after two or three minutes, the
exterior bark shell has been
sheared off.
the bare wood that's left
represents the outside of the
largest bowl that he'll mill
from this blank.
with a finer blade, he sculpts
the wood to just the right
thickness and smooths the
surface.
now he switches to a smaller
curved knife and cuts into the
wood.
this forms the inside of the
largest bowl and the outside of
the next smaller one.
the lathe worker repeats the
smoothing and cutting process
was progressively smaller
knives, making bowl after bowl
at a rate of about one a minute.
this one bowl blank produces
four nested bowls, the smallest
measuring about nine inches in
diameter.
the bowls are steamed for about
four hours to draw out the sap
and hydrate the pores of the
wood uniformly.
once a bowl is dry, about a
month later, workers even out
the top rim on a sanding table.
then, using a belt sander, they
smooth the outside and inside
surfaces.
a motorized saw shaves off the
bottom of the bowl, giving it a
flat base on which to sit and
a place to inscribe the company
name.
businesses can order custom-made
bowls featuring their company
logo.
artists burn the design into the
wood or paint it on.
the bowls now go for a bath in
food-safe mineral oil.
this nourishes the wood,
preventing dryness and cracks.
oiling also brings out the
natural beauty of the wood
grain, and because all raw wood
is unique, no two bowls are ever
alike.
up next...high-tech production
at a chain-saw factory.
>> narrator: it's loud.
it's powerful.
and it rules the forest.
the chain saw has revolutionized
the logging industry by
replacing simple muscle power
with mechanical might.
the chain saw can fell a tree
and quickly turn logs into
lumber.
production begins with the
plastic housing.
three aluminum inserts must be
molded into the housing to
provide solid anchors for other
parts.
a robot picks up the inserts one
at a time and delivers them to
an injection molding machine.
then it places the inserts into
a mold at the front of the
machine.
the machine injects melted
plastic into the mold to make
the chain saw's engine cover.
during the molding process, the
metal inserts become integrated
into the housing.
it takes just seconds to
transform these plastic pellets
into a chain-saw engine cover.
the robot carries each engine
cover to an automated cutter
that removes any unwanted bits
of plastic.
the scraps drop into a bin
below.
the hot covers cool for about
10 minutes.
then the robot moves them to the
next station.
there's one more piece of
plastic housing -- the fuel
tank.
the sonic welder melts and fuses
it to the engine cover using
high-frequency vibration.
now it's time to move on to the
engine and install a spring
system for the starter cord.
the two-stroke engine slides
into the plastic casing.
and a spark plug is popped into
place.
after the crankshaft is
lubricated, the chain saw's
automatic oiling system is
installed.
the carburetor is attached,
along with a pull-cord starter
system.
this saw gets an air filter.
then the chain bar's stud bolts
are dipped in adhesive and
screwed into the inserts molded
into the plastic housing.
the rear handle goes on...along
with a safety-release trigger.
the front handle is screwed into
place.
and the oil line gets a filter
attachment that lubricates the
bar and chain.
that will strain out any
impurities.
next, workers install bearings
and the crankshaft clutch
system.
the clutch is the link between
the engine and chain.
when it's engaged, the chain
will move around the cutting
bar.
the engine is now ready for a
test run at typical speed --
8,000 rpm.
technicians adjust the
carburetor so that it mixes the
right amount of gas and air and
check the exhaust to make sure
it doesn't exceed pollution
standards.
workers attach the company's
logo and other operational
information.
then the brake system goes into
place.
finally, the metal bar and chain
blade are packed in a protective
sleeve.
once the saw's chain blade is
installed, the owner has a power
tool with teeth for almost any
job.
when we return...get the skinny
on stackable chips.
>> narrator: it's a snack that's
made to stack.
unlike other chips that come in
irregular shapes and sizes,
these chips have a uniform
concave shape that allows them
to tightly interlock and fit
neatly in a tubular container.
the process for making these
tubes starts with big rolls of
plain brown paper and
foil-backed paper that help
keep the chips fresh.
the streams of paper travel
across rollers that apply a coat
of glue.
the paper layers then twist
around the mandrel that's
turned by a big belt.
the belt also presses the glued
layers together.
next, the label paper gets a
coat of glue.
this helps it stick to the paper
on the mandrel.
a camera photographs the white
edging on the label paper, then
relays its location to a set of
circular knifes.
they make a precise cut just
below the white edging.
cued by the camera, the carriage
then moves the knives into
position for the next cut.
you the tubes then head into a
turning station...
a box with a pathway inside that
flips the tubes right side up.
hot metal heads curl the tops to
accommodate lids.
a roller pulls foil-backed paper
into a cutter that punches out
the lid shapes.
little vacuums take the lids to
the tubes and heat-seal them on.
plastic lids go over the paper
ones.
the lidded tubes are now turned
upside down, ready to be stacked
with chips.
the chip recipe is 1/3 water to
2/3 potato flakes with a little
cornstarch mixed in.
a conveyor delivers the mix to
an auger, which disperses it.
then it sets out on the
production line.
using four tons of pressure, the
mix is rolled into one long
potato sheet.
a rotary cutter then punches out
oval shapes.
a device pulls away the scrap
dough, leaving flat, uncooked
chips.
this scrap dough goes back into
the chip-making process, while
the potato chips head for the
fryer.
as they travel through the
fryer, rolling molds give the
chips their uniformly concave
shape, making them more easily
stackable.
the chips spend 11 seconds in
hot oil, crisping.
then they travel under blowers
to get rid of excess oil.
the chips get a coat of
seasoning, then do a backflip
off one conveyor and onto
another, falling into neat
piles.
a worker inspects the rows of
chips.
then it's on to another conveyor
that shakes them up to loosen
the stack.
they travel over scales to be
portioned out for packaging.
automated spoons shove the chips
into the open ends of the tubes.
guides tap the tops of the tubes
to nudge the chips into
position.
grippers then lower the stacks
of tubes to a station, where
spinning heads force metal
bottoms onto them.
now they're ready for shipping.
it takes about 20 minutes to
make a tube of stackable chips,
but it takes less time to polish
them off.
up next, jet compressor blades
that really make the cut.
>> narrator: compressor blades
are key components in a jet's
engine.
thousands whirl inside the
engine, rotating 400 times per
second and whipping air into
small hurricanes.
large compressor blades made of
titanium compress the air in
front of an engine's turbo
chamber.
in the back of the chamber,
smaller blades made of nickel
alloy compress it even more.
the air heats up to more than
1,000 degrees, then combines
with jet fuel, creating a
powerful mix that explodes out
the back of the engine.
the blades start off as metal
pellets called slugs.
a ceramic layer prevents their
surfaces from oxidizing when
exposed to intense heat.
the slugs are heated for 15
minutes in an 1,800-degree oven.
meanwhile, a robot sprays
lubricant on two dies inside a
press.
the robot retrieves the slugs
and loads them in the first die.
the press applies over 1,000
tons of pressure to pre-form the
metal.
the robot then transfers the
slugs to the second die, where
they take the initial shape of
the blade.
the blades are dipped in water
to cool.
another robot cleans the metal
burrs off the edges.
the blade is now an airfoil.
robots will shape the rounded
base of the blade, called the
dovetail, later.
the airfoil has gone from this
to this.
after a new ceramic layer is
applied, the blade is heated
again.
each heating and cooling cycle
tempers the metal, making it
more resilient.
almost 1,800 tons of pressure
gives the airfoil its final
shape.
a trimmer shaves off the excess
metal.
the searing heat has turned the
protective ceramic layer into
glass.
that will come off later.
it's taken an hour to shape the
blade's airfoil.
the dovetail, that nub on the
right, is next.
but first, this measuring
machine inspects the airfoil.
if any measurement is off by
just half the thickness of a
human hair, the blade doesn't
make the cut.
this casting machine will encase
the airfoil in a matrix, a
coating that protects the
airfoil during work on the
dovetail.
the matrix is molded from liquid
tin and bismuth.
it solidifies into a metal cast
around the airfoil.
the future dovetail sticks out
at the end.
the cast is then loaded into
what is called the broach
machine.
its series of teeth carve the
dovetail into its final shape.
now the cast can come off.
a worker loads it onto the
removal machine, and a hydraulic
cylinder hits the cast at its
weakest point, breaking it in
half.
the finished airfoil emerges
unscathed.
a dot-matrix machine punches
identification numbers onto the
blade.
next, the blades are submerged
in a fluid that penetrates any
flaws in the metal.
this inspection is critical,
because even the tiniest nick
can spell disaster when a jet's
engines are working at full
speed.
inspectors examine the blades
under a black light.
this one's perfect, but spots
of fluorescence on this one
indicate microscopic cracks and
weaknesses.
this one gets rejected.
the dovetail gets two strips of
rubber silicone that ensure an
airtight seal when the dovetail
slides into the slot on the
compressor drum.
a final check, and the blades
are now ready for takeoff.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at
sciencechannel.com/howitsmade.