-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, llc
>> narrator: today on "how
it's made," ccd
semiconductors...
airline meals...
paper cups...
and trumpets.
a ccd semiconductor is the image
sensor in a digital camera or
camcorder.
when you snap the shutter or
press record, you expose the
ccd to patterns of light.
it captures them electronically
by converting them into millions
of electrical charges.
the camera's processor then
reads these charges and
translates them into pictures or
movies.
ccds, or charge couple devices,
are made of silicon, the main
element in sand.
what's special about silicon?
when light hits it, you get
electrons.
production begins with a round
silicon wafer six inches in
diameter and about as thick as a
shirt cardboard.
it goes into a steam oven for
three to four hours.
the intense heat, along
with oxygen and hydrogen
gases in the steam, create a
glass-like layer on the wafer.
this insulates the silicon
against the miniature
electrical circuitry that will
be built on top of it.
but first, the wafer is covered
in conductive material.
this layer measures less than a
micron.
a human hair is 100 times
thicker.
next, a robot applies a
one-micron-thick layer of
photo-sensitive resin, which
will undergo a chemical reaction
when exposed to light.
a technician places a mask over
the wafer.
the pattern on this mask is the
scheme attic for part of the
circuitry.
when you take a picture, you
expose the silicon wafer to
light and that generates
electrons.
the circuitry carries those
electrons to the camera's
processor, which reads the
charges and translates them
into an image.
this machine exposes the masked
wafer to ultraviolet light.
the resin underneath
the circuitry pattern
remains intact,
protecting the conductive layer
beneath it.
the resin on the areas not
masked by the circuitry pattern
needs to be removed.
chemicals are sprayed on.
this dissolves the resin
exposing the conductive layer
underneath.
technicians repeat this entire
process with anywhere from 13 to
30 masks until they've built up
the full circuitry pattern on
the wafer.
next, technicians submerge the
wafer in acid, which eats away
the uncovered conductive layer.
so, now, the only conductive
material left on the wafer is
the actual circuitry.
next step, a thorough rinsing in
tap water to remove the residue.
then a rinse with purified water
to remove any impurities left
by the tap water.
throughout production,
contamination is a concern.
a single speck of dust can ruin
an entire wafer.
to protect and insulate the
circuitry, the wafer is coated
in liquid glass, then baked for
two hours, until the glass
hardens.
the wafer surface is divided
into 25 million tiny square
cells called pixels.
when you take a photo, each
pixel records the light
intensity of a minute portion of
the scene, generating an
electrical charge.
a filter on the ccd translates
each pixel charge into color.
the company makes this filter
with three pigment powders --
red, green and blue.
these three colors combined in
varying ratios can reproduce any
color.
the camera's processor reads and
then reconstructs the photograph
scene pixel by pixel.
each finished ccd undergoes a
battery of automated tests to
ensure that all the circuits are
functional.
the machine marks faulty
circuits with ink.
just one bad circuit means the
entire ccd needs to be
discarded.
technicians then check every ccd
under a microscope looking for
scratches that might have
occurred during the production
process.
the number of pixels on a ccd
varies depending on what type of
camera it's for.
this one is a 25 megapixel ccd,
meaning it has 25 million
pixels.
this company even produces a
single ccd that has 111
megapixels.
so the next time you say,
"cheese," remember that you're
producing a digital photo thanks
to all that painstaking work
that went into the sophisticated
ccd semiconductor inside your
camera.
>> when we return, creating the
ultimate to-go meals for
today's highflyers.
>> narrator: in the earliest
days of air travel, passengers
really lived the high life.
they were served
multi-course meals that
were actually prepared during
flight.
but as air travel boomed, this
kind of service became
impractical, and airlines turned
to premade meals.
not all food fares well at high
altitudes.
that's why you don't see any
souffles at 30,000 feet.
they couldn't possibly rise to
the occasion.
it's just one of the
restrictions airline chefs need
to consider when preparing a
menu.
airline meals start with tons of
ingredients, literally.
just one facility can turn out
45,000 meals in a single day.
of course, the cooks wash their
hands very thoroughly because
they don't want any germs stowed
away in the meal.
they cook on grills that are
five feet long.
at one end, they stir-fry
vegetables, while at the other,
they sauté potatoes.
then, they spice it up.
airline food isn't as bland as
it's reputed to be.
researchers believe that low
humidity and the pressurized
environment cause our taste buds
to work less efficiently in an
airplane, something to take into
account when you're traveling
by air.
recipes vary according to the
route.
flights to more exotic locales
will offer spicier dishes, while
a domestic north american flight
usually calls for more moderate
seasoning.
cooks fire up different grills
for the meat.
they prepare food for the crew
as well as the passengers.
on many airlines, the pilot and
co-pilot must eat different
meals to minimize the risk of
food-related illness
compromising the flight.
the cooked food will now be
blast chilled in special
fridges.
cooks scrub up again as they
prepare to assemble the meals.
they start with the food that
needs to be reheated on the
plane.
it goes into foil containers.
smaller containers inside help
control the portion sizes.
cooks must be careful not to
overstuff them because that
could cause messy spills later.
a little sauce and a generous
dab of herb butter, and you have
the makings of a first-class
meal.
finally, the food is covered
with a vented lid.
with each menu change, chefs
must meet with airline
representatives.
they serve up sample dishes and
discuss the ingredients with
them.
there's often a lot of
negotiation before the final
menu is agreed upon.
every detail about an airline
meal is carefully planned right
down to the plates and bowls and
how they're placed on the
serving tray.
it takes a bit of arranging to
make everything fit.
once planners finalize the
arrangements, they follow that
formula in the kitchen.
as with any meal, presentation
counts for a lot.
of course, meals in economy
class are more simple, and the
planning less detailed.
the food-laden trays go onto
trolleys and are rolled into a
big, refrigerated room, where
they're arranged according to
the flight number.
they won't be here for long
because every meal is made to be
served that day.
and all the groundwork
beforehand is sure to pay off
once passengers and crew are in
the air.
up next, a popular product that
lets us all enjoy one for the
road.
>> narrator: the paper cup was
invented around the turn of the
20th century to stop the spread
of disease.
today, it's an integral part of
our culture.
paper cups provide a convenient
and hygienic way to serve food
and beverages, and the lining of
water-tight plastic or wax
prevents any nasty leaks.
and where would we be without
our disposable coffee cups?
production starts with paper
that has a thin plastic coating.
it unrolls into a printer that's
as long as a bowling lane.
as the paper weaves through the
machine, printing cylinders
layer an image onto the paper
one color at a time.
when the image is complete, a
rotary die cuts the paper
into what's called a flat.
the dimensions of the flat vary
depending on the size of the cup
being made.
each flat will eventually become
a paper cup.
they land on a conveyor in a
shingle-like lineup.
a computerized system counts the
flats and divvies them up into
stacks of 200.
the flats drop into an elevator
stacker.
it creates piles that workers
can easily collect.
they load them into another
conveyor in a different part of
the factory.
it moves the flats in a
vibrating shuffle up into the
cup machine.
meanwhile, a roll of paper winds
into the other side of that
machine, where a die punches out
bottoms for the paper cups.
this leaves a long strip of
scrap paper which gets sucked
away for recycling.
meanwhile, the flats are relayed
to a carousel.
now the paper cup takes shape.
mechanical jaws wrap each flat,
and a heat gun seals the seam.
and now, you have a paper cup
with no bottom.
that crucial step comes next.
bottoms are shoved onto the cups
and heat-sealed in place by
melting the plastic backing on
the unprinted side of the paper.
the cups then fall down a chute
to the next operation, which
will give the cups a rim and
allow you to take a sip without
spilling.
a hot tool curls the top edge of
the paper.
then, the vacuum sucks each cup
into ductwork overhead.
each piece of ductwork comes
from a different production
line.
there are big cups and small
cups, all traveling to the
packing department, where they
land in stacking tubes.
a counter keeps a running tally
and portions out the stacks.
the stacks then slide into a
curtain of plastic.
hot jaws seal the plastic wrap
around the stack.
and now, the cups are ready to
be packed and shipped.
meanwhile, over in the testing
department, this is no coffee
break.
inspectors have pulled some cups
off the production line to
check for leaks.
a mirror below reflects the
bottom line, but leaks are one
in a million, so they made one
leak deliberately for
demonstration.
in the case of a real leak,
production is halted and
inspectors follow the paper
trail until they determine the
problem.
it takes about a minute to
transform pieces of paper into a
cup.
now, it's time to hit the road
without any leakage.
when we return, a factory
with something to trumpet about.
>> narrator: the ancestor of the
modern trumpet was a straight
horn that could emit just a few
notes.
by the 15th century, instrument
makers learned how to bend a
horn, allowing for more notes to
be produced.
the invention of the valve in
the mid-1800s finally allowed
the trumpet to play in any key.
a trumpet is made up of five
feet of tubing.
three valves allow air to flow
through additional tubing to
alter the trumpet's pitch.
trumpets are made from sheets of
metal, most often brass.
this factory combines different
thicknesses of brass in a single
instrument to attain a
particular sound.
workers first lay a template on
a brass sheet and trace it out.
then they cut along the score
line with electric shears.
this piece will become the
trumpet's bell.
a manually operated press forms
a perfect fold down the middle.
then, they notch the edges.
then, they close up the bell by
hammering the notched pieces
onto the opposite edge.
they use a rawhide mallet
because anything harder would
damage the brass.
a brass alloy is melted along
the joint.
it solidifies in a metal seam
that permanently bonds the
edges.
next, the bell goes over a
cone-shaped mandril where the
brass is hammered until it, too,
is cone-shaped.
then the bell goes onto another
mandril mounted on a lathe.
here, the brass cone is refined
into a more refined shape.
then, the metal is filed smooth.
now for the bell's rim, called
the bead.
a brass rod with a notch at the
end catches the edge of the bell
and rolls it back into a rim.
metalworkers use what's called a
concave roller to round the
rim's jagged edge.
then they slide a brass alloy
wire into the rim pocket.
this makes the bell stronger and
adds weight to the edge of the
flare to project the sound
better.
they roll the rim over even more
to enclose the wire.
now they heat the rim and apply
acid flux to clean the surface
for soldering.
silver solder ensures the wire
won't rattle when the bell
vibrates.
after wiping off the excess
flux, the bell goes back on the
lathe to scrape off the excess
solder.
using an abrasive sponge,
workers smooth away any
scratches left by the scraper.
then, they remove any solder
bits trapped in the rim.
now, the entire bell is filled
with a soapy solution.
then, it's frozen at minus 56
degrees.
when the solution is frozen, the
bell goes into a bending block.
the frozen solution provides
counter pressure, preventing the
brass from buckling inward, and
because there's soap mixed in,
the pliable ice doesn't shatter
under the pressure.
after the angle of the bend is
checked with a gauge, the bell
is defrosted.
in the mounting department,
workers assemble smaller
components made of brass and
nickel.
valve casings, the sliding tubes
to which they connect, the
slide for tuning the trumpet,
the pipe that holds the
mouthpiece, then they solder on
the bell.
they lubricate three pistons and
install one in each valve
casing.
these slides have to be loose
enough to move but tight enough
to prevent air leaks.
one slide has a finger ring for
holding the trumpet.
after polishing and lacquering
the brass, workers test the
trumpet for sound quality.
this is one company that likes
to blow its own horn.
[ playing mid-tempo music ]
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...