>> today on "how it's made,"
solid tires...
cheesecake...
canoe paddles...
and globes.
solid rubber tires are designed
to conquer the toughest turf,
the kind of rough terrain
found at construction sites,
landfills, and mining
operations.
these places are full of hazards
that would flatten ordinary
air-filled tires, but solid
tires don't go flat.
even with a dozen nails sticking
out of them, these big boys
just keep on turning.
strong and dependable, these
tires are ideal for heavy work.
and because there's no inner
tube, you never have to worry
about getting a flat.
it all starts with a wide strip
of partially processed rubber.
as the strip is forced through a
series of holes, it's turned
into a long, tubular shape.
next, hot cylinders roll it thin
and soft like a pie crust.
in another part of the factory,
the tires' metal frameworks are
being prepped.
a worker moves them along an
overhead rail into a special
chamber.
steel pellets are added to the
mix.
inside the chamber, a machine
tosses the pellets around and
the friction polishes the metal
tire frames.
next, workers spray on a coat of
primer and apply an adhesive.
then one by one, the frames are
mounted on a mechanical arm
that's positioned in front of
the rubber rolling system.
the arm moves the tire frame
forward to meet the turning
cylinders.
the metal surface, still tacky
from the glue, easily takes up
the freshly rolled rubber.
depending on the kind of tire
being made, the machine can
layer the rubber around the
frame up to 100 times.
then, workers weigh the tire and
slice off bits of rubber until
it meets specifications.
this solid tire is now in good
shape, so it moves on to the
next stage.
over at another station, they're
building a different type of
solid tire.
this one has no metal framework,
so it can fit on a rim made for
an air-filled tire.
rubber strips are wound around
the metal hub that serves as a
mold.
then a heavy press squeezes out
any air pockets.
these rubber strips contain
recycled material which is
stiffer than regular rubber.
this will help the tire hold its
shape in the absence of a metal
framework.
now it's time for some tread.
workers begin the process by
spraying a release agent onto a
mold so it will be easier to
remove the tire later.
then they lightly glue the i.d.
label and serial-number plate
to position them for transfer to
the tire.
the tire is centered in the mold
with a metal ring.
then the top section of the mold
is lowered into place.
now it's time to get cooking.
the mold is hoisted to another
station and sandwiched between
two steaming hot plates.
the searing temperature melts
the rubber into the crevices of
the mold.
minutes later, the mold is
opened and out comes a treaded
tire.
the heat has also vulcanized the
rubber, a molecular change that
makes it much more durable.
changing one of these tires
isn't a job for just anyone.
typically a specialist travels
to the work site and switches
tires using a heavy-duty
hydraulic system.
and that's how you put a solid
tire on a wheel rim made for an
air-filled one.
big tires with metal frameworks
go into this autoclave to be
shaped and undergo
vulcanization.
a forklift, equipped with solid
tires, of course, extracts the
finished tires from the
autoclave.
and now they're ready to roll.
when we return, another round
creation.
>> people associate cheesecake
with new york, but actually, it
comes from greece.
the ancient greeks served this
rich delicacy to the athletes of
the first olympic games in
776 b.c.
the roman conquest spread the
dessert across europe, and many
centuries later, european
immigrants brought to
north america.
the ancient romans even brought
cheesecake to their temples as
an offering to the gods.
the basis of a cheesecake is its
rich, creamy filling made from
ricotta, neufchatel, or
cream cheese.
but first, bakers need to make
the crust, similar to a butter
cookie.
for a batch of about five dozen
cakes, this bakery combines 50
pounds of butter with 10 pounds
of sugar.
next, 16 egg whites.
then, 25 pounds of flour.
after mixing just long enough to
incorporate the flour smoothly,
a conveyor belt shuttles the
dough to a vat.
gravity pushes the blob of dough
through a slot at the bottom,
expelling a sheet less than a
quarter inch thick.
a dusting of flour prevents the
dough from sticking, not just to
the conveyor belt but also to
the rolling and cutting tools.
this prickly roller preparates
the dough sheet.
the holes allow any trapped air
to escape during baking, which
prevents the dough from
shrinking and ensures a flat,
bubble-free crust.
the next roller has plastic
circles that work like cookie
cutters, slicing the dough into
cake-size discs.
the leftover pieces go into new
batches of dough.
each dough circle goes in a pan,
then bakes at 375 for 16
minutes.
meanwhile, the batter starts
taking shape.
for a batch of about 20 cakes,
the bakery combines 25 pounds of
cream cheese with two pounds of
cultured sour cream.
that's sour cream processed a
little longer than usual to give
it extra flavor.
after slowly mixing in 15 pounds
of sugar and about 2 1/2 cups of
flour, workers blend in 3/4 cup
of vanilla extract.
now they get cracking with 1 1/2
dozen eggs.
that's the recipe for plain
cheesecake.
flavored versions come with
extra goodies.
this batter is caramel pecan.
it's paired with a chocolate
cookie crust.
as the baked crusts arrive,
sprayers grease the inside of
each pan with butter so that the
cake will slide out easily after
baking.
then a machine, called the
depositor, shoots in just the
right amount of batter.
the pans now enter a
tunnel-shaped oven that's almost
25 yards long.
the temperature inside is a
toasty 350 degrees.
by the time the cakes exit the
other end, they're fully baked.
these 10-inch cakes take just
under an hour.
from the oven, the cheesecakes
go onto a cooling conveyor, and
by the time the hot cakes do the
nearly hour-long circuit, they
are at room temperature and
ready to come out of their pans.
from there, most cheesecakes go
straight into the storage
freezer, but there are a few
exceptions which detour to the
decoration department.
this belgian chocolate
cheesecake isn't complete
without a squirt of chocolate
ganache, a decadent mixture of
chocolate and cream.
workers spread it all over,
then make swirls with a
decorating comb.
and now the final touch, a
sprinkling of cocoa.
some cakes go into an automated
cutting machine that divides
each cake into 14 equal slices
and inserts parchment paper in
between them.
back at the decorating
department, they are putting
shards of chocolate on a mud
pie, a combination chocolate
souffle, chocolate cheesecake
with pecans and coffee mousse
topping.
you might want to put off that
diet just for one more day.
coming up, an age-old implement
gets a new spin.
>> they keep us from going
adrift, and no one wants to
be up the creek without one.
paddles have been around so long
no one know who is invented them
or when.
but there's no question they've
evolved.
made with sophisticated
craftsmanship, today's wooden
paddles really go the nautical
mile.
modern paddles are often made
from a blend of hard and soft
woods for a product that's
strong yet lightweight.
first, wooden boards are fed
into a multi-bladed rip saw
that slices them into uniform
strips.
each strip has a flat, smooth
joint on the side.
glue is rolled onto those flat
joints and then the strips are
pressed together.
these glued sections will be
used to make paddle blades.
over at another station, workers
are creating the paddle shafts
two at a time.
they glue shorter pieces of wood
for the handles, and clamp them
together to allow the glue to
set.
the blade chunks are arranged in
a much bigger clamp.
then the glue-coated ends of
some shafts are wedged between
the blade pieces.
in a process called lamination,
the blades are bonded to the
shafts.
the laminated paddle shapes are
called blanks.
next, the blade design is traced
onto one of the blanks...
and the design is cut out with a
band saw.
laminated wood doesn't warp
easily.
this allows the factory to
produce wider blades, which
give the canoer more power
through the water.
but paddles cut from a single
piece of wood have a more
traditional look and feel, and
some canoers prefer them.
these narrower paddles are made
with cherry wood.
modern tools make quick work of
a design that hasn't changed
very much over the centuries.
in no time, a basic paddle has
been carved from a single piece
of wood.
next, the edges are rounded off
with a large router.
it shapes and contours the
paddle to its final dimensions
and gives it a smooth finish.
in just minutes, that
chunky-looking piece of wood is
transformed into a sleek
traditional paddle.
meanwhile, back in the laminated
paddle department, notches are
sawed into each paddle blade.
workers mix up a liquid plastic
concoction...
then pour it into the slots to
harden.
the plastic gives the paddle
tips some extra protection
against rocks and other
obstacles in the water.
now it's time to improve the
profile of the laminated
paddles.
with the same type of router
used to shape the solid paddles,
workers fine-tune the design.
both types of paddles then get a
heavy sanding.
the final touch is to taper each
paddle head so that it's much
thinner at the tip.
trademark information is branded
onto each paddle using a hot
iron.
then it's time for the paddles
to take a dip in a tank of
varnish that contains a
sunblock.
the varnish both protects the
wood and enhances its natural
beauty.
the paddles are suspended on an
overhead conveyor to dry.
and soon, they'll be on their
way to a waterway near you.
up next, a factory that makes
the world go round.
>> because the world is round,
flat maps don't give us the full
picture.
a globe is the most accurate
representation of the earth.
it depicts countries in true
spatial relation to one another,
and better defines latitude and
longitude lines.
at the globe factory, production
revolves around world events.
as war and political upheaval
redraw boundaries, these
spherical maps have to be
constantly revised.
globe construction begins with a
big roll of cardboard.
a machine pulls it under a
roller that coats it with glue.
a knife then slices the
cardboard into smaller pieces,
which will serve as liners for
the maps.
one more coat of glue, and then
the liners are attached to the
back of maps.
heated rollers press them
together, completing the seal.
each map represents a
hemisphere.
a powerful press now cuts the
maps into a pinwheel shape.
each map must be carefully
positioned in the cutting press.
after all, one false move, and a
whole country could end up on
the factory floor.
it takes two punch cuts to do
the job.
then, the excess paper is pulled
away, leaving behind a map
divided into 12 spoke-like
sections.
here's a top view of that
cutting press.
it acts like a giant fist to
punch out pinwheels.
and now it's time to shape the
world.
workers place a map cutout and a
liner into a mold.
it rises into a heated cavity
that presses the paper into a
bowl-like shape.
one hemisphere down, one more to
go.
the southern hemisphere is
created using the same type of
mold.
molds also emboss each map to
represent the peaks and valleys
on the earth's surface.
here's an inside look.
the raised and indented sections
of the molds allow people to see
and feel variations in the
world's topography, both
aboveground and underwater.
with the hemispheres complete,
it's time to go global.
the northern hemisphere goes for
a spin while a razor blade trims
the edges.
then the lower hemisphere takes
its turn while a nozzle beads
hot glue along the inside.
this stiff cardboard ring
adheres to the globe and gives
it some re-enforcement along the
equator.
glue is applied to the northern
hemisphere...
and it is fitted over the ridged
edge of the southern one.
the two halves are precisely
aligned, then tape is attached
over the seam.
this both disguises the seam and
marks the equator.
next, each globe is mounted on a
pedestal that's attached to a
metal arc called a meridian.
suctioned to the top of the
globe, the meridian will allow
the earth to revolve.
from fragments of paper and
glue, a whole new world's been
created in just a couple of
hours.
globes tell us where we are and
help us figure out where we're
going.
they come in many different
languages.
and because they help us get our
bearings, you could say they
make the world a better place.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, llc
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...