>> narrator: today on "how it's
made"...
steel wool...
ranges...
carved candles...
and slot machines.
with so many rough edges, steel
wool is very abrasive.
that's what makes it so useful
for heavy-duty cleaning and
other chores.
mechanics were the first to use
steel shavings for cleaning and
polishing parts.
by the early part of the 20th
century, equipment was invented
to mass produce the stuff.
then steel wool became a
household name.
there are thousands of metal
threads in each steel-wool pad.
manufacturers start with a
coiled steel rod that unwinds
through metal guides into a
16-foot-long die machine.
as the rods travel through six
progressively smaller dies, it
gets narrower and more uniformly
shaped.
spools wind up the rod after it
passes through each die to
prevent any snarls in
production.
the progression through the dies
reworks the steel's basic
structure, doubling its tensile
strength.
when it reaches the end of the
die machine, the steel rod has
been narrowed by a little more
than half.
the slimmer, stronger wire will
be easier to process.
to check its tensile strength, a
technician places a wire sample
in a testing device.
clamps pull from both
directions.
it takes over half a ton of
force to snap it, an indication
that it's tough enough to be
machined.
so, it's over to the steel-wool
cutting machine, which spans 50
feet.
here, the wire travels over a
series of drums, while 29 blades
shave it.
each blade produces shavings
thinner than a human hair.
streams of the shavings exit the
machine and join the river of
steel threads flowing through
the factory.
each of these steel threads has
been cut in a pyramid
configuration, making it
razor-sharp.
the shaved steel winds onto
large rolls.
workers align several of these
rolls onto racks, then secure
them in place.
the ends of each roll are
bunched together...
and threaded through a series of
bobbins.
finally, the ends are fed into a
needle-punch machine.
here, hundreds of fish-hook
shaped needles weave the steel
threads together.
this very basic crochet job
produces a long mat of wool
that's of suitable density for
woodworking.
to make household cleaning pads,
workers bulk up the steel wool
even more.
they insert layers of needle mat
into the streams of steel
fibers.
this gives the pads extra
strength for big scouring jobs.
this multilayered stream then
heads over to the needle-punch
machine to be woven together.
once the steel wool goes onto a
final roll, it's ready to be
turned into pads for cleaning,
sanding, or polishing.
next, see what's cooking with
today's high-end ranges.
>> narrator: the range is where
the action is in the kitchen.
it's where we whip together
meals -- baked, broiled, roasted
or sautéed.
high-end ranges like this one
are hot, and not just in the
obvious way.
they're an upmarket trend that
make home cooks feel like the
chef of their very own
restaurant.
the construction of one of these
double-oven ranges starts with a
big sheet of galvanized steel.
a machine flips it and feeds it
to a press.
the press folds the sheet twice
to make the oven walls, closing
it around the framework.
the oven bottom is placed into
position, and automated welders
fuse everything together.
the back section goes on next.
those holes are for the oven's
fan.
the oven shell gets a porcelain
finish on the inside, and then
the heating element goes in.
fans are fitted into those
precut holes.
more heating elements run along
their perimeters.
the oven is then wrapped with
synthetic insulation to keep it
from scorching nearby cabinetry.
side panels cover the insulation
and help support the oven's
structure.
this piece of steel will
reinforce the range bottom.
several feet are attached.
the front ones have wheels so
the range can be moved without
tearing up the floor.
workers cushion it with packing
foam, flip it, and hoist the
oven onto it, next to a smaller
second oven that's part of this
double-oven range.
next, a technician hooks up the
microprocessor board that
controls everything from the
oven's fans to their timers.
and all of that wiring needs to
be double-checked.
on this range, the burners are
fueled by gas.
this electrical board will sense
gas-flow problems.
workers assemble the igniter
boxes that will spark the
burner's flames...
then mount them on the cooktop.
after installing the gas valves
on the framework...
they slide connectors onto some
gas lines and attach them to the
valves.
on this upscale cooktop, there
are two gas lines for every
knob -- one for a low flame, and
the other for a high flame.
with the installation of the
burners and the porcelain drip
pan...
the cooktop is now ready to be
lowered onto the oven.
this is where the knobs fit.
it's called a bullnose, and it's
a bit of a showpiece.
so, workers grind and polish it
to give it a gleaming finish
with no sharp edges.
for handling purposes, the
bullnose is protected with
plastic.
this machine punches and bends
the edges of panels so
they can be attached to the
sides of the range.
at another station, the oven
doors get a good buffing so
they'll match the shiny
bullnose.
with the side panels and doors
attached, all that's left are a
few more finishing touches, and
the final product is ready to be
fired up.
coming up, an art form where
every second counts.
>> narrator: carving candles is
an old german craft still
practiced by artisans.
it involves layering
different-colored wax...
then carving designs to expose
those luminous colors.
it's hard to beat the radiant
beauty of a carved candle.
carved candles are known for
their swirls and curls, a look
so elaborate that lighting one
is an occasion in itself.
the process starts with vats of
hot wax in various colors.
the candlemaker stirs them to
circulate the specially
formulated dyes.
she dips a star-shaped wax core
into clear wax and then yellow.
the clear wax dilutes whatever
color wax follows it.
the layers are hardened in cool
water.
she repeats this process between
30 and 35 times, building up
different-colored layers on the
candle core.
as the dipping continues, the
candle becomes warmer and
softer, which will allow it to
be carved.
the quick water dips only cool
the outer layers.
partway into the dipping, the
candlemaker deepens the candle's
grooves.
and she resumes dipping, she has
to keep a close watch on the
candle's temperature.
if it absorbs too much heat, it
will be too soft to carve.
but if it's too cool, the wax
can splinter.
achieving the right consistency
is crucial.
it's almost time to get carving.
but first, the candlemaker
squeezes the drippings
together....
and slices them off.
they're too attractive to waste,
so she quickly shapes them into
a mushroom candle.
she pokes a hole in the center
for the wick, and, within
moments, the candle is complete.
with the big candle at the
perfect temperature, the clock
is ticking.
it has to be carved in just 15
minutes, or it will be too hard
to work with.
the candlemaker slivers the
bottom and curls the pieces
back.
she dunks the row of curls into
water to harden them a bit so
they don't sag.
on the second row, she curls
each row in the opposite
direction to the one before.
she carves a total of four rows,
with the last curls fixed
upright.
using the square-edged gouging
tool, she cuts a windmill design
into the upper section of the
candle.
then she shapes the wax cutout
into a base for the windmill.
tulips and other designs
decorate the top of the candle.
she must work with a quick but
steady hand.
it takes at least a year of
training to learn to carve with
such confidence.
this one is a neat trick.
she jiggles the straight-bladed
knife to cut the fluted edge of
a hummingbird wing.
one last character, and this
carving job is complete.
now she presses a
cookie-cutter-like device around
the wick.
this forms a well that will
allow the wax to burn down the
center instead of dripping down
the sides, which would ruin the
carving.
she spins the candle in a hot
pan to melt the bottom so that
it's level.
and while it's still hot, she
attaches the company sticker.
finally, an acrylic glaze seals
the candle's decorations and
protects the finish.
once lit, the light from the
clear core shines through the
design for a real glowing
beauty.
when we return, a gambler's
dream come true -- peeking
inside a slot machine.
>> narrator: a san francisco car
mechanic invented the first slot
machine in 1895.
its heavy cast-iron cabinet
housed three spinning reels.
each one had 20 playing-card
symbols and an image of
philadelphia's famous liberty
bell.
if you were lucky enough to
line up three bells in a row,
you won the big jackpot --
50 cents.
today's slot machines have come
a long way.
they've got computers for brains
and endless themes and
configurations all packaged in a
light-weight sheet-metal
cabinet.
workers first assemble what's
called the bulkhead, the upper
part of the cabinet that
contains all the game-playing
components, such as the audio
amplifier...
the circuit boards...
the speakers...
and what's known as the meter,
the electromagnetical counter
that keeps track of the coins
and credit going in and out of
the machine.
at the base of the cabinet, the
machine gets a serial number, as
required by law.
workers install the machine's
bill acceptor, then the ticket
printer.
when there's a win, it spits out
a voucher that the players can
redeem for cash, or insert in
any machine's bill-collector
slot.
next comes the arm mechanism
players pull to spin the reels,
then the upper door that frames
the reels and the lower door
that frames the button panel.
slot machines have several
illuminated buttons for
different types of bets.
workers plug a tiny l.e.d.
behind each button, then wire
up the panel.
a plastic insert labels each
button.
once the panel is assembled,
it's installed in the lower
door.
workers now turn their attention
to the metal panel that
accommodates the spinning reels.
on the back, they install two
circuit boards -- one to operate
the machine's digital
scoreboard, the other to
illuminate the reels.
then they cover the panel with
special glass.
it's been treated with a
chemical that conducts
electricity.
should a cheater try to rig the
reels using an electronic
gadget, this glass will ground
the charge.
a decorative window goes over
the anti-tampering glass.
then workers place the whole
unit into the upper door.
in the lower door, they install
a touch-screen video monitor to
display the payout information.
casino technicians also use
it to configure the machine.
then workers install panels with
slots for receiving tickets and
for inserting either money or
debit cards.
and now for the slot machine's
most famous feature -- the
reels.
after a machine tests the
spinning motion and lights, a
worker attaches a plastic strip
with printed symbols -- 18 to 22
symbols per reel.
the reels easily snap into a
waiting electrical connection.
next comes what's called the
top box.
workers mount it onto the
bulkhead, then install
fluorescent bulbs.
these will light up the
eye-catching artwork on the
glass front of the box.
nearing completion, the slot
machine is finally ready to
receive its brain -- an internal
computer with its operating
system on a programmable
microchip.
the software that runs the game
is installed on a memory card.
it randomly determines the
course of play within defined
parameters.
essentially, it's preprogrammed
to pay out a certain amount at
random intervals over a given
period of time.
but less money, of course, than
the machine takes in overall.
before embarking on its spinning
spree, each slot machine
undergoes extensive
quality-control testing.
casinos demand that these
one-armed bandits are durable
and reliable because slots
generate more than two-thirds of
casino revenues.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at
sciencechannel.com/howitsmade.