narrator: mankind has always cooked food,
using everything from campfires and barbecues
to gas and electric stove tops.
now he can use an induction cooktop.
it doesn't need a fire, a flame,
or a red-hot burner.
it uses innovative cooking technology
our ancestors never dreamt possible
and would swear was pure magic.
an induction cooktop doesn't use
traditional cooking elements
above or below the cooking surface.
it uses copper induction coils
that generate high-frequency electromagnetic fields.
these fields
excite the molecules in the pan,
creating heat only in the cookware itself.
that's why the yolk remains cold
and only what touches the pan cooks.
the magic starts with a punching press
that stamps computer-generated shapes
into sheets of cold-rolled steel.
these cutouts fix the position
of the induction coils that sit
under the glass surface.
a press break bends the four sides of the steel
so it will hold a glass-ceramic top in place.
in the meantime, a machine spray-paints the burner box,
the visible part of the cooktop.
a technician affixes the labels
and the power cord onto a housing box
that will conceal the induction
electronics and coils.
she secures the power cord for strain relief.
she then attaches the power-cord ground
and a system ground wire to the housing box.
she places a cover on the box and screws it into place.
another technician puts together
the induction electronics.
these assemblies
of circuit boards, cooling fans,
and semiconductors drive the cooktop.
she covers the electronics with insulation
and a metal carrier plate
that will support the induction coils.
then she feeds the user-interface wires
through the top of the coil-carrier plate.
the technician screws the carrier plate
and the electronic assemblies together,
then grounds the electronics.
protective tape around the openings
will prevent the user-interface wires
from rubbing against the coil-carrier plate.
and some insulation will protect
the electronic assemblies.
she closes that side of the electronic housing box
and attaches all the power cables.
a sheet of insulation goes on the flip side of the box,
where she mounts the
electromagnetic-coil assemblies.
the iron slugs on the back of each coil pod
help distribute the electromagnetic energy
to the cookware evenly.
she connects the coil assembly to the system board.
then she places the remaining four coil assemblies
onto the carrier plate
and connects their leads to the system board.
meanwhile, another technician assembles the components
of a glass touch-user-interface panel.
she connects the interface to the steel holder
that was bent into shape at the start
and is now attached to the black burner box.
she covers the cooking surface and control panel
with an attractive stainless-steel frame,
then connects the system board to the control panel.
she closes up the other side of the burner box.
then she bolts everything down to complete the cooktop.
a technician tests the unit.
using a metal object to activate
the electromagnetic field,
he verifies that the controls respond properly.
he makes sure all five induction coils are working
and the power output from each coil is correct.
the control panel confirms it's a success.
clean, safe, and energy-efficient,
induction cooktops make cooking food quick and easy.
narrator: at a highway weigh station,
inspectors weigh each transport
truck on a road-level scale
to calculate taxes on the goods it's hauling
and to make sure the load doesn't exceed safety limits.
you also find truck scales at grain silos, quarries,
and other sites that move bulk products.
the key to this enormous scale
is the tiny component called a strain gauge,
which sends signals to the scale's computer
when compressed.
they make the strain gauge from a laminate
by bonding paper-thin sheets of nickel-iron foil,
epoxy, and teflon in a press.
then they coat the laminate in a light-sensitive chemical
and apply a plastic film
with an image of strain gauges in negative format.
then they expose the setup to ultraviolet light.
the light-sensitive chemical reacts,
imprinting the images into the laminate's metal surface.
now they have rows of strain gauges.
an inspector examines every gauge
and marks any flaws to be discarded.
now a technician measures how much voltage
flows through each gauge.
if it's too low, she raises it
by rubbing off a microscopic amount of surface metal.
when the strain gauges are finished, they cut them apart
and send them to the load cell department.
there, workers delicately tape four strain gauges
into each stainless-steel load cell.
then they solder electrical wiring to each one.
the wires all run to a circuit board
at one end of the load cell.
and from the load cell,
wiring runs to the scale's computer readout.
the smallest amount of moisture or dirt
would cause a strain gauge to malfunction,
so they weld a cup over each one
to hermetically seal it within the load cell.
every finished load cell
undergoes a quality-control check
to verify that it works properly.
the testing machine applies weight in increments
until it hits the maximum weight
the cell can bear --
34,000 kilograms, or 75,000 pounds.
the truck-scale structure
in which they'll install the load cells
is called the weighbridge.
they begin assembling it upside down,
with a surface made of steel plates.
to build the base of the weighbridge,
they lay out a grid of thick steel tubes and crossbeams.
workers lower a guide to help them align the parts perfectly.
beneath each load cell is a pin.
in order to weigh accurately,
a load cell has to be level,
so it's critical to make sure this pin is level
before welding on the bulkhead that holds it.
once fully welded,
the weighbridge is assembled and ready for painting.
the paint equipment laces the powdered paint
with a positive electrical charge
and the weighbridge with a negative one.
this evenly draws the paint particles
onto the steel like a magnet.
in another department, they assemble the steel stand
on which the load cell will sit.
a welder tacks the pieces together,
then a robot does the full welding.
now that all parts are ready,
final assembly of the truck scale can begin.
the weighbridge, right-side up now,
contains eight load cells at different locations.
the first step is to install each load-cell stand
into its respective position.
they insert a link on each side of the stand.
they position the load cell at the top of the links...
...and the bulkhead pin at the bottom.
then they close up the location
with an access plate.
the last step is to calibrate the scale.
they lay a 10,000-pound weight on different parts of the scale
to check if the digital readout
is accurate.
it takes a lot of time
to get a truck scale just right,
but it's definitely worth the "wait." [weight]
narrator: tetra pak containers
keep drinks and food products
safe to consume for up to a year
without refrigeration or the use
of additional preservatives.
made mostly from paper, they're recyclable
into things like egg cartons, paper towels, and toilet paper.
a tetra pak container
is packaging built with nature and freshness in mind.
tetra pak containers
hold all sorts of food products,
from smoothies to fine wines.
the package gives products a long shelf life
because of its special layers --
the plastic layer, the paperboard, and the foil.
a plastic coating makes the package leakproof.
tetra pak containers
are made entirely from recyclable materials.
the first step to making them is printing.
a worker selects the appropriate printing plates
for a given customer
and applies them to the cylinder
of the printing press.
the press transfers one color at
a time to the paperboard layer
using solvent-free ink.
a tetra pak container can have up to six colors.
at full speed, it takes only minutes to print.
a strobe light visually stops the motion,
helping the pressman check the quality of the printing.
a worker feeds the printed paperboard
into a lamination machine
that will join it with the plastic and foil layers.
at the same time,
a worker loads a roll of micro-thin aluminum foil
into the laminator.
a gas flame heat-treats the paperboard
to ensure adhesion to the plastic layer.
the laminator extrudes liquefied plastic
between the roll of aluminum and the heated paperboard.
rollers squeeze all the layers together.
the printed paperboard, with all
its protective layers applied,
then comes off the back end of the laminator
in a large master roll.
the operator threads it into a cutting machine
called a slitter.
it cuts and winds the printed material onto individual rolls.
the slitter's knives cut the material into four lanes,
each of which becomes a smaller roll.
the operator trims the excess material from each roll.
then a conveyor system sends the rolls for shipping
to a packer to be filled with their product.
at the packer's plant,
an operator loads the roll of flat packages
into a filling machine built and installed by tetra pak.
tension rollers guide the material
into the filling machine where it is sterilized.
the machine then forms and seals the material
into one continuous tube.
and a little further down,
the machine fills the tube with product.
it then cuts the tube into individually sealed packages...
and drops them into a chute for folding.
it ejects the finished packages
onto a conveyor belt.
finally, it sends the packages on their way to the customer.
lightweight, compact, and recyclable,
tetra pak containers are eco-friendly,
and that's certainly something to celebrate
over a glass of fine wine.
narrator: there are two main types of harmonicas.
a diatonic harmonica has 10 mouth holes.
it plays a 7-note major scale in a single key of music.
a chromatic harmonica has up to 16 holes,
plus a special slide mechanism to produce extra notes
so it can play in any key.
[ harmonica plays melody ]
as air goes through a harmonica,
so does saliva,
which is why they make the inner structure
from a type of wood that doesn't expand or smell
with repeated exposure to moisture.
making a standard chromatic harmonica
begins with a block of pearwood
measuring about 5 1/2 by 1 1/4 inches.
they run it against a cutter
that carves a row of air chambers front and back.
this produces the component known as the comb.
a press stamps slots in a millimeter-thick brass plate
that will hold the reeds.
the plate will eventually go on top of the comb,
its slots aligning with the comb's air chambers.
another machine cuts reeds
from brass-based metal specially
formulated by this company
to produce quality sound and be corrosion-resistant.
working one size at a time,
they cut a batch of a few hundred reeds.
they test a reed from each batch
with a tuning machine,
plucking it to see if it produces the correct pitch.
the size and profile of a reed
determines the note it produces.
the longer it is, the lower the note, and vice versa.
now they rivet the reeds to the reed plate --
one reed for each note.
consecutive reeds go on opposite sides of the plate.
with this configuration,
blowing into the harmonica vibrates one reed,
while drawing air out vibrates the other.
they flatten each rivet on one side of the plate.
this fastens the reed securely at the bottom,
leaving the rest free to vibrate.
if necessary, they file the reed down
so the slot doesn't obstruct its movement.
[ humming ]
now a tuning specialist gets to work.
she plays each reed on the plate
and compares the tone
to a perfectly tuned set of reeds for reference.
if the pitch is off, she adjusts
it with a bit of filing.
[ high-pitched humming ]
once the reed plate is in tune,
it goes on top of the comb,
the reeds and slots aligning with the comb's air chambers.
workers attach the parts
with steel nails that have a brass plating
to prevent corrosion.
now for the two-piece cover
that encloses these internal components.
for standard models, the factory
uses stainless steel,
starting with a sheet
that's less than a half a millimeter thick.
fancier harmonicas have silver- or gold-plated covers.
the sheet goes through a press that has a series of dies.
they progressively stamp out the cover pieces,
first embossing the artwork,
then cutting the size, then forming the shape.
workers sandwich the comb between the two cover pieces,
then attach everything with either brass-plated nails
or brass- or nickel-plated screws.
chromatic harmonicas have
a mouthpiece over the blowholes.
it's usually made of chrome-plated brass
that they curve slightly in a press.
the mouthpiece shields the lips
from a slide mechanism inside.
that mechanism has three parts --
a slide with a button positioned
in between two plates.
they screw the mouthpiece
onto the front of the harmonica.
when you press the mouthpiece button,
it redirects the air, raising the notes half a tone.
no harmonica leaves the factory
without a sound test.
rather than blow into every instrument,
the testing department uses a machine
that blows air in and out.
[ harmonicas playing ]
last stop is the cleaning department.
there, workers inspect for scratches,
then polish and package
so that each and every harmonica
will look as good as it sounds.
[ harmonica plays melody ]
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...