-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
>> narrator: a baseball glove is
an extraordinary thing.
each and every one starts out
brand spanking new and ends up
fitting its owner like a second
skin.
before long, the player and his
glove are inseparable.
the glove helps him live his
dreams and fills his imagination
with lifelong memories.
baseball gloves have evolved
from hard, leather mitts to the
sophisticated design players
depend on today.
it all starts with a hydraulic
press that punches out the
felt padding that will cushion
the fingers and thumb.
the holes will be used to lace
the glove.
another press cuts out the palm
section of the glove from a side
of leather.
the palm section also has lacing
holes cut into it.
the hydraulic press then cuts
out the web, or pocket, of the
glove, preparing it for lacing,
as well.
meanwhile, a machine heat
embosses the palm section with
the company logo.
embossing also helps identify
different leathers and glove
styles.
another worker hand-weaves the
front and back pieces of the
pocket.
this special basket-weave web
gives the glove additional
flexibility and control.
pockets first appeared in gloves
in the 1930s.
she stitches the pocket
together.
then, she applies glue to secure
the tail ends, closes the flap,
and stitches the web shut.
another worker then sews the
palm lining and the finger
lining together.
by stitching the palm and finger
linings together, she completes
the interior piece of the glove
that touches a player's hand.
she then sews the felt finger
pads to the lining.
these pads give the glove extra
comfort and control.
to build the outer shell of the
glove, she sews welting leather
between the fingers.
this makes the seam stronger.
then, she sews the fingers and
the palm piece together to
complete the back part of the
outer shell.
some leather softener helps
prevent tearing as she stitches
the back and the front parts of
the outer shell together.
she also uses welting leather to
add strength and rigidity to the
outer shell.
a worker mounts the finished
outer shell on to a finger form,
heated to about 248 degrees
fahrenheit.
it takes heat and leather
softener to allow the worker to
manipulate the shell without
damaging the leather.
the worker then transfers the
softened outer shell on to a
stationary turning stick in
order to turn the outer shell
inside out.
he works the outer shell one
finger at a time so he doesn't
spoil the leather or the
stitching.
he makes sure all is perfect.
another worker slips the
interior lining on to a mounting
support, then covers the lining
with the outer shell.
he works the leather to make
sure the lining and the shell
fit together properly.
then he applies a special paste
that makes the palm more
flexible.
he inserts a felt pad into the
thumb...
then another cushioning pad into
the pinky finger, using a metal
rod to fully insert both pads.
he then starts lacing the glove
with a long strip of leather.
lacing the glove is a
labor-intensive skill that can
take up to an hour.
no machine can do this.
he makes sure the lacing gets
the right tension and the
attractive side of the leather
faces upwards.
using special knots and loops,
he laces the entire glove by
hand.
a worker inserts wooden dowels
and mounts the glove on more
hot fingers to open up the
fingers and thumb.
this helps the player's hand fit
into the glove more easily.
now this truly looks and fits
like a glove.
today's baseball gloves come in
all different colors and styles.
they are so finely hand-crafted,
they could be called works of
art.
>> narrator: medical electrodes
can help your doctor find out
what's going on with your health
in a heartbeat.
these little sensors detect
electrical currents in the
heart, brain, and other parts of
the body, and they're wired to
monitoring equipment that
records it.
they're inexpensive, disposable,
and essential to healthcare.
when the nurse says this won't
hurt a bit, you can trust her,
if the test she's about to give
you involves medical electrodes.
these electrodes stick to the
skin and probe beneath the
surface without actually
piercing it.
they send information to
monitoring equipment so
specialists can assess it.
these electrodes start with a
roll of foam.
the foam is coated with
medical-grade adhesive and has a
paper backing to keep the layers
from sticking together.
machinery pulls the foam over a
punch cutter which make small
holes in it.
but first, razors slit the
paper, and equipment pulls it
away from the thumb to expose
the adhesive.
the process leaves strips of
paper along the edge.
the thumb moves forward, sticky
side up, as plastic elements and
metal snaps cascade into a
feeder system.
they're cueing up to be
installed in the holes punched
in the foam earlier.
vacuum heads picked up the
elements and insert them into
those holes.
the elements are coated with
silver chloride, which makes
them electrically conductive so
they'll help pick up electrical
activity in the body.
next, pneumatic equipment
press-fits the metal snaps onto
the elements.
these snaps are also
electrically conductive.
down the line, a blade slices
through gel that's sandwiched
between two thin plastic liners.
machinery pulls those liners
away from the gel.
this gel is water-based and
contains salt, which will seep
into the skin to help establish
electrical contact.
another blade cuts the gel into
small rectangles, and they land
on a thicker plastic liner.
the gel liner and foam with its
elements and snaps come
together, and the gels land
directly on the elements.
rollers press everything
together in a tight sandwich.
equipment pushes that sandwich
forward into a cutting station.
that's protective padding you
see around the cutters.
it protects the blades from the
adhesive on the foam as they
punch out electrode shapes.
blades now lightly perforate
the plastic liner around the
electrodes, while below,
equipment pulls away the scrap.
the perforations will allow the
electrodes to be torn into
individual units later, and
it also makes it easier to fold
up for packaging.
remember that paper left along
the edge of the foam early on?
it serves as pull tabs on some
of the electrodes.
the tab makes it easier to apply
the electrode to the patient
and then remove it.
they package the electrodes in a
special material made of
plastic, aluminum, and paper.
hot metal plates melt and seal
the material to form an
airtight pouch.
finally, a long blade cuts the
pouches into individual units.
it has taken less than a minute
to make this package of medical
electrodes.
they'll use many of them in just
one test.
with the gel side of the
electrode pressed against
the skin, they wire it to the
monitoring equipment.
and within minutes, these
electrodes can signal problems,
and that could save a life.
after the test, the electrodes
will be discarded --
disposable and yet indispensable
in the world of medicine.
>> narrator: the cowboy hat was
made popular in 1865 by the
stetson hat company and its
founder, john b. stetson.
part of its attractiveness in
the american old west was the
wide brim that protected the
cowboy from the elements,
a high crown that kept a pocket
of warm air on his head, and the
ability to carry water if he
needed to.
all models of stetson hats are
made from blends of pretreated
fur, including beaver, rabbit,
and wild hare.
first, a worker gathers the
mixture of different fur and
deposits it into a picker
machine that begins blending the
fur together.
the picker roller, which dates
from the 1890s, sends the fur
into a mixer.
inside the mixer, compressed air
blows the fur around.
this settles and removes any
dust and dirt that may be
trapped in the fur.
after about an hour, the blended
fur settles into a collection
box.
a worker puts it through a
rotating loader machine that
sends the fur into a
multichambered blower.
a look inside the blower reveals
a series of picker rollers.
these rollers, along with
blowing air, allow the lighter
fur to flow through the chambers
while the heavier hair and the
impurities fall to the bottom.
at the back of the blower, the
worker gathers and weighs the
amount of fur needed to make
just one hat.
that amount varies depending on
the size and style.
the proper amount of fur then
moves by conveyor belt into a
forming machine.
here, a vacuum sucks the fur
onto a cone form.
the fur builds up like a fragile
blanket of dust that must be
held down by wet cotton mesh.
for extra protection, a worker
wraps burlap onto the cone and
puts a metal cover over it.
he weighs it down and gives the
fur cone a good soaking in a vat
of hot, soapy water to make the
fur fibers curl up and lock
together.
shortly after, the worker peels
the newly formed felted fur
blanket off the cone.
at this stage, the interlocked
fur fibers are still very
fragile, so a worker protects
the cones from damage by
wrapping them in cloth.
then, she puts them through a
hardening process which consists
of a series of massaging
rollers and hot-water baths.
the rollers in the hot-water
baths increasingly shrink and
tighten the fur fibers together.
the final and most aggressive
massage makes the fibers felt
together even tighter, and the
cone is now strong enough to
manipulate by hand.
but the cones must be even
stronger than this, so she puts
them through a final hardening
stage that shrinks and tightens
the fur fibers to the maximum.
at last, the fragile cone that
came out of the forming machine
becomes the desired hat size.
tearing the felt by hand is now
impossible.
after the cones are dyed,
they're placed on a crown
machine.
here he works the top of the
cone and makes the felt more
flexible.
another machine softens the
brim.
together, the machines form the
cone into more of a hat shape.
after soaking the cone again, a
worker puts it on a wet blocker
machine.
its brass fingers secure and
stretch out the felt while it
forces a crown shape into the
hat body.
then he puts the hat body into a
hat sucker or vacuum that sucks
out most of the water.
he then sets the hat bodies
aside to dry for 24 hours.
up next, we'll see how these hat
bodies are transformed into
classic stetson hats.
>> narrator: making a stetson
hat takes almost as much work
now as it did since the early
1900s.
every hat made is still handled
from start to finish by hand.
even some of the machines used
are the same as in the past.
the stetson hat is an icon of
the american cowboy lifestyle.
a worker steams a hat body to
make it supple.
he puts it into a blocker
machine with brass fingers that
secure it in place.
he steams it again, then inserts
a wooden block and presses it
into the crown.
this gives the hat a specific
head size.
he puts another hat into the
blocker, this time making
another hat size.
this is called blocking a hat.
blocking transforms the brim
diameter and the crown from an
almost shapeless cut of felt
into a more solid body and
precise hat size.
a worker puts the blocked hat on
a brim stiffener which applies
shellack.
this shellack gives the
brim extra firmness, making it
easier to shape and style.
he completes the brim-stiffening
operation and readies the
correct number of hats to fill
an order.
a worker hangs up the hats for a
natural air dry.
two days later, a worker inserts
blocks into the hat, which are
color-coded for size.
the blocks fit the hat on a
pouncing machine that gently
spins and sands the felt.
this unsanded felt gets buffed
until the hat ends up with
the smoothest finish possible.
then a worker puts the hat onto
a hydraulic crown press.
inside it, he places a piece of
ink transfer paper and a heated
aluminum mold.
he lowers the press and applies
the exact amount of pressure
needed to mold a specific shape
into the crown.
on this particular hat, the
press imprints the logo inside.
now the crown has a distinct
shape.
a worker then puts the hat on a
brim cutter and holds it down
flat with a cutting guide.
she cuts the brim to the
required dimension and removes
the excess felt and the guide.
a worker then puts the hat into
a brim flanger -- an aluminum
mold that heats and shapes the
brim.
he then puts the hat onto an
identical wooden shape and
covers it to keep its form while
cooling.
once cooled, this hat will keep
its symmetrical curves that
will make it so distinctively
western.
a worker then marks the center
of the hat.
she lines up a leather sweatband
with the chalk mark and sews it
in along the bottom edge of the
crown.
she then folds the sweat band in
and makes sure the hat is
perfect.
she ties the classic ribbon band
into a knot and secures it
around the outside of the hat.
she trims the ribbon to the
appropriate size, which
completes the work on the
exterior of the hat.
then another worker puts it into
a holder and peels up the
sweatband.
she places a lining inside the
hat, applying drops of glue all
the way around to keep it in
place.
she then puts the hat inside a
box for shipping anywhere in the
world.
authentic stetson hats.
looking good, partner!
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...