-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: the distinctive sound
of the accordion
appears in almost every kind of music.
the piano-style keyboard on the right-hand side
produces the melody,
while the buttons on the left
produce the chord accompaniment.
in between are bellows that force air through reeds,
producing that unmistakable accordion sound.
[ up-tempo music plays ]
the accordion is a beautiful and complex instrument.
it contains up to 10 sets of steel reeds
with different pitches.
each reed set goes into a wooden block.
under every section is an opening called a tone hole.
the bellows drives air through it,
vibrating the reed above to produce a musical note.
these leather-and-plastic pads cover the slots
on the accordion's aluminum reed plates.
each plate holds two reeds.
both reeds produce the same note --
one when you push the bellows, the other when you pull.
they now apply a special wax to
secure the reeds to the block.
if they used glue, they wouldn't
be able to remove the plate
should a reed ever need repair.
each reed played corresponds to a specific note or chord.
to assemble the keyboard,
they begin with a lever made of
fiberglass-reinforced plastic.
it has a wooden core to give the keys sufficient weight.
a long metal lever goes into the top.
when the musician presses a key,
its mechanism unblocks the corresponding tone hole,
allowing air to flow inside
and vibrate one of the plate's two reeds.
next, they drive in the steel axle on which the keys pivot.
then they apply suction to a keyboard-size tray.
in it, they line up the plastic key tops.
in top-of-the-line models,
the white key tops are made of celluloid.
with the suction holding the keys down,
it's just a matter of flipping the tray
and clamping it onto the keyboard frame.
the tops adhere to the levers,
which have since received a coat of glue.
after about an hour, the glue is dry.
they cut the suction, and the keyboard is finger-ready.
meanwhile, the reed blocks
are in the hands of a tuning specialist,
who pumps air with a foot pedal
to vibrate the reeds one at a time.
he compares each note to a reference tone
from a tuning apparatus
and files the reeds gradually until their pitches match.
now for the button keyboard.
starting with the valves,
they install a wooden pallet over each tone hole.
to that, they glue a steel lever.
then to that, they connect a brass rake.
when the rake moves, it pulls the lever,
which opens the valve, unblocking the tone hole.
air enters and vibrates the reed, producing the note.
each keyboard button opens three valves.
that's why pushing one button produces a three-note chord.
with the complex connections
between buttons and reeds complete,
the reed blocks go into a celluloid-on-plywood housing.
it'll attach to the bellows
made of strong pleated cardboard
reinforced with leather and metal corner protectors.
[ chords playing ]
but before permanently attaching
the bellows,
all the reeds have to undergo
a final and very extensive tuning adjustment.
[ notes playing ]
an accordion can have up to 600 reeds,
so this meticulous reed-by-reed
tuning can take up to 16 hours.
[ notes playing ]
they now pin the bellows' wood frame ends
to the treble and bass housings.
then they cap each housing with a cloth-covered grille
to keep out dust.
after polishing the accordion to a high-gloss finish,
it's time for a musical road test in white gloves.
there's no sense in leaving fingerprints
on that exquisitely polished surface.
with the test checklist complete,
the inspector signs off on it.
you can't say this job's all work and no play.
[ up-tempo music plays ]
narrator: the pineapple is native to south america,
but colonization spread it to other tropical areas.
the latin name for pineapple is "ananas,"
which comes from nana, what the natives called the plant.
the english word "pineapple"
came from the european explorers
who thought that this strange but delicious fruit
looked like a giant pinecone.
pineapples need temperatures
between 73 and 86 degrees fahrenheit and full sun.
it takes seven months for the pineapple plant
to produce a bunch of little reddish-purple flowers.
at this first bloom, as it's called,
farmers spray the plant with ethylene,
a natural gas that stimulates full flowering.
as that happens, the stem of the flower bunch
gradually thickens and becomes bulbous.
this is the pineapple.
five months after first bloom, a year since the last harvest,
a fresh crop of pineapples is ripe for the picking.
but not before the farm has tested samples
to make sure the sweetness level
is just right.
this is prickly business, so
the workers have to wear gloves,
long sleeves, safety glasses, and rubber boots.
the pineapples travel
from the field to the factory upside down.
that way the crown of leaves bears the weight of the fruit
during the bumpy ride.
upon arrival at the factory,
the pineapples go through a 10-step cleaning
in chlorinated water.
this washes away insects and frog eggs.
frogs like to lay their eggs in pineapple crowns.
a final rinse with clean water removes any chlorine residue.
now workers classify the pineapples
and cut off misshapen crowns.
a first-class pineapple has a straight crown
and no more than three damaged eyes,
those diamond shapes on the peel.
if a pineapple passes the first-class test,
it's fit for export.
second-class sells on the domestic market.
third becomes dried fruit, and fourth, juice.
at the drying plant for third-class pineapples,
workers first chop off the crown,
and then about two inches from the bottom end.
with a coring machine,
they remove the pineapple's hard center called the heart.
knife-wielding employees work their magic,
each peeling five to seven pineapples per minute.
the coarse skin dulls the blades quickly,
so they have to keep sharpening
their knives
about every half-hour.
the peeled pineapples then move on to a slicing machine,
which produces slices a little more than a half-inch thick.
the average pineapple yields about seven slices.
workers place the slices on large trays...
load the trays on large racks...
then roll the racks into a gas oven.
the slices bake for 24 hours
between 147 and 151 degrees fahrenheit.
this dries them almost completely.
when they come out of the oven,
their moisture level is 6%,
just enough to ensure the slices are chewy.
from the oven to packaging.
these preservative-free dried pineapple slices
stay fresh in the package for 18 months.
now back to the pineapple factory,
where the first-class fruits pass under a shower of hot wax.
fans cool and harden the wax
into a coating that creates an air barrier.
this slows the ripening process,
ensuring the pineapples don't overripen
by the time they arrive at their export destination.
last stop is the packaging and labeling department.
workers box pineapples with and without crowns separately.
those with crowns are for export.
the crownless ones go to a canning factory
to be sliced, diced, or crushed.
from the field to your table,
pineapples are the fruit of many people's labors.
narrator: artificial body parts
used to be the stuff of science fiction.
nowadays artificial joints, at least, are routine.
an artificial joint is a prosthesis that surgeons insert
to replace diseased or worn-out
bone and cartilage.
in nearly all cases, an artificial joint
relieves pain and improves the range of motion.
from your knees and hips to your
wrists, elbow, and shoulders,
if your joints go, you can replace them.
an artificial joint has both metal and plastic components.
the metal acts as bone, the plastic is cartilage.
this factory makes the metal parts three ways.
it either casts them, forges them, or machines them.
casting is the most complex method.
the first step is to pressure-inject melted wax
into an aluminum mold.
this makes a pattern,
a wax replica of the metal part.
now they build the mold for casting the part in metal.
workers fuse a group of patterns
with hot wax
to a holder also made of wax.
the patterns will shape the cavity in the molds.
they submerge the patterns in a thick liquid ceramic
which soon hardens into a fragile shell around the wax.
then they sprinkle the shell
with a mixture of two minerals --
silica sand and zircon -- to build up a strengthening crust.
the shells now go into a furnace
for about two hours.
the intense heat hardens them and incinerates the wax inside,
leaving a cavity in the pattern shape.
the shells are now molds
strong enough to withstand molten metal.
that metal is cobalt chrome.
in this crucible, the chrome liquefies in about 10 minutes.
they remove the molds from the furnace
and lock them to the top of another one above the crucible.
then they flip it over.
the molten metal flows from the crucible into the molds.
it solidifies within two minutes.
then they transfer the hot molds
to a cooling bin.
cold air flows around them for about two hours
until they're finally cool enough to handle.
then workers mount each tree on an automated machine
that works like a jackhammer.
each mold disintegrates, freeing
the cast-metal part inside.
they use a saw to separate the parts from the tree,
then a grinding belt to remove any unnecessary metal
that hardened in the channels.
next, they laser-engrave a unique serial number
on each part for tracking purposes.
every part undergoes a thorough inspection.
they dust the part with fluorescent powder,
then rinse it off.
powder residue settles in any flaw
and glows under ultraviolet light.
after inspection, they buff every part
until the metal's so shiny, you can see a reflection.
another method for making metal parts is forging.
they use a titanium alloy,
which is more flexible than cobalt chrome,
making it better suited for hip joints, in particular.
they clean the metal, then heat
it in a 2,200-degree furnace.
this 660-ton press forms one piece at a time
into a preliminary shape.
then they move it to the next die and stamp twice
to refine and then finalize the shape.
the last stamping on the third die
trims off excess metal and adds detail.
the forged part now goes into a sandblasting chamber
which cleans the metal and gives
the surface a matte finish.
here's what the part looks like
before sandblasting and after.
now a computer-guided milling machine
smooths away the rough edge
that trimming the excess metal left behind.
this removes all but the last bit,
so they get rid of that with a sanding belt.
but sanding leaves metal residue behind.
so the parts now go for a bath
in a water-based citric solution.
the metal surface has to be perfectly clean
in order to stamp on the serial number in ink.
quite a difference before cleaning and after.
each and every metal part, whether forged or cast,
goes to the quality control department.
there, using digital calipers,
an inspector checks all the dimensions,
then examines the part under a magnifying glass.
so far we've seen two of the ways
they make the metal parts of an artificial joint --
casting and forging.
the third method is coming right up.
narrator: the metal portion of an artificial joint
plays the role of bone,
while the plastic portion mimics cartilage.
however, the plastic isn't your run-of-the-mill plastic.
it's medical-grade polyethylene,
meaning it's formulated to be lightweight,
but also extremely durable
so that it withstands years of wear and tear within the body.
the type of metal they use
to make the bone portion of an artificial joint
depends on how flexible that joint has to be.
a knee joint requires less elasticity,
so they mold it out of cobalt chrome.
a hip joint, on the other hand,
needs to be more bendable.
so for that, they use titanium.
they either forge the shape in a press
or mount the titanium block on a computer-guided mill.
under a steady shower of lubricant,
the mill's 20-odd machining tools
carve the block from all angles.
after a primary rough machining,
the mill's precision tools finalize the shape.
from start to finish,
machining just one part takes about half an hour.
now a robot takes over.
it runs the part against a series of sanding belts,
their grits progressing from rough to fine.
this removes marks the machining
tools left on the metal
and polishes the surface to a mirror finish.
the robot can't reach the edges,
so a worker sands them manually
and verifies the dimensions.
then the parts go for a thorough cleaning.
the factory puts random samples
through wear testing.
the machines simulate joint movement,
complete with fake joint fluid.
the factory sprays some parts with titanium powder
to help bone tissue to cling to them.
this machine, called an optical comparator,
projects an image of the part's coated outline
against a technically perfect template.
the technician makes sure
the part and the template match.
to become an artificial joint,
the metal bone now needs its plastic cartilage.
that requires polyethylene powder.
a technician weighs out a specific amount,
puts it in the outer sleeve of a mold,
then inserts the mold's inner piece.
the technician loads the mold into a press
that applies both pressure and heat --
374 degrees fahrenheit.
the powder gets squeezed between the mold's two parts
and turns into solid plastic.
using various instruments, they measure the molded part
to ensure all its dimensions are exact.
now a computer-guided machining
tool carves the grooves
into which the metal part will slide.
these details are far too intricate for a mold to shape.
then some final measurements to make sure the finished part
adheres to the engineering specifications.
random samples undergo fatigue testing
equivalent to 10 years of wear.
some plastic parts are just too
complex to be molded outright,
so, instead, the factory molds a block of plastic,
then machines it.
the block spins on a lathe
as various computer-guided tools
shape it.
samples of these also undergo wear testing.
after a specific number of movements
over a specific time period,
technicians remove the parts and weigh them.
by comparing to the starting weight,
they can calculate how much plastic has worn off.
the packaging room is what they call a clean room,
meaning the air runs through a filter system
to keep out dust and dirt.
workers pack the artificial joints against foam
to protect the metal surface,
because even the tiniest scratch
can cause premature wear.
after heat-sealing the packages,
the factory ships them off to a sterilization plant.
there, powerful gamma rays penetrate
right through the packaging
and kill off any bacteria that might be lurking inside.
make no bones about it, these joints may be artificial,
but the movement they restore is as real as it gets.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...