♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator: electrophoretic
technology mimics the effect
of ink on paper.
the screens reflect light,
unlike conventional back-lit
displays that emit light.
also known as e-paper,
this technology has changed
the way we see our screens.
mobile devices, e-readers,
smart watches,
and credit cards all contain
electrophoretic displays.
with its print-like readability
and bluetooth capability,
it's easy to see
the attraction.
to make
an electrophoretic screen,
polyethylene film is placed
on a sheet of glass,
which holds the film
as its processed.
♪
production takes place
in a filtered room,
to keep the area
contaminant-free.
inside the room,
robots move the glass carrier
through processes
that transform the film
into the backplane.
the backplane is the main
structure of the screen.
it carries
the organic transistors
that drive the
electrophoretic display.
machinery builds up
micro-thin layers of metal,
organize solutions,
semiconductors, and isolators.
this spin coder evenly spreads
the material across the film.
♪
nozzles apply
an organic solution
that acts as a booster
for the semiconductors.
the spin coder closes
and rotates the glass carrier
to spread the deposited material
by centrifugal force.
♪
the automated system
adds layers of semiconductors,
electrical isolators,
and metal.
a rinse of de-ionized water
cleans the coated film,
and a blast of air
blows off the water.
rollers apply gentle pressure
to ensure the film
sticks to the glass
even when positioned vertically.
♪
once the photoresist chemical
has been applied,
the film goes into
an exposure chamber.
a patterned mass is placed
in front of the film
to block out lighting
in some areas.
♪
the exposure defines the
structure of the metal layers
so that, when combined
with the other materials,
they'll serve as transistors.
♪
the backplane film is removed
from the glass carrier.
now the film is ready for the
electronic-ink-sheet placement.
a technician places
the backplane in a laminator.
he uses a camera to magnify
and position the backplane.
a vacuum in the laminator chuck
holds the backplane in place.
he places the electronic
ink sheet on the chuck
beside the backplane
and peels off the liner,
exposing the adhesive.
♪
then the ink sheet and the
backplane are fused together.
♪
a roller presses the assembly
for full adhesion.
♪
once the lamination process
is complete,
a technician removes
the screen from the chuck.
this is the backplane before
and after the electronic
ink lamination.
an automated system bonds the
electronics to a circuit board
that's attached
to the display screen.
the system mechanically seals
the circuit board.
polymer resin is applied
for stability.
u.v. light cures the resin.
this is
the electrophoretic display
before and after
the electronics have been added.
♪
this particular display screen
will be an e-reader.
they load a graphic with
black strips onto the screen.
the strips serve
as reference points,
as a printer applies
a combination red, green,
and blue filter.
the filter adds the option
of colored text or pictures.
the primary colors can be
combined to create other shades,
expanding the visual
possibilities
of the electronic ink.
♪
a machine bends
a sample screen repeatedly
to confirm that the sample
is flexible enough to be formed
into a bracelet or credit card.
♪
additional tests are conducted
to confirm that
the electrophoretic display
has the desired
clarity and color.
display patterns can be sent
from a phone to a bracelet
that has
an electrophoretic screen.
with electrophoretic technology,
there are many different ways
to enjoy screen time.
♪
narrator: a dry-erase board
is a non-permanent surface
most commonly used
in professional
or classroom environments.
you simply write on the board
with the dry-erase marker
and use a specialized cloth
to wipe away the markings.
these effective tools
are an easy way
to get your message across.
dry-erase boards are also
known as whiteboards.
the boards wipe perfectly clean
due to its non-porous surface
and the dry-erase ink.
dry-erase ink contains
release agents
which prevent the pigments
from permanently
adhering to the surface.
green and black dry-erase boards
can also be used as chalkboards,
while gray and low-gloss white
double as projection boards.
the surface material is a
porcelain-coated steel sheet --
flexible enough to be rolled up,
but also pressure sensitive.
♪
to start, the roll is mounted
on a cutting machine.
♪
a technician programs
the machine to cut the roll
to a specific length
based on the board's dimensions.
workers verify the length and
check that the piece is square.
the surface material
will be applied
to one of seven types
of substrate,
ranging from cardboard
to medium-density fiberboard
known as mdf.
the next step is to cut
the large sheet of substrate --
in this case, mdf --
into board-size pieces.
another technician
enters the length and width
into the cutting machine.
♪
once complete, the machine
ejects the substrate,
which is now cut
to the exact size of the board.
♪
next, the substrate is put
through a hot-glue machine.
the machine applies polyurethane
adhesive
to what will be the back
of the dry-erase board.
as the substrate exits,
a sheet of foil
is applied to the glued surface.
the foil prevents moisture
from entering,
which would warp the substrate.
the board moves through
two steel rollers
which flatten the foil
and press out any trapped air.
next, the surface material
is applied
to the other side
of the substrate.
a craftswoman uses an air hose
to clear away any dust
from the side of the board.
once cleaned, the board
goes through the glue machine.
the porcelain steel sheet
is placed on the glued surface.
technicians work carefully
to ensure they don't touch
the pressure-sensitive surface
with their fingers.
then the board moves
through the steel rollers
to press the porcelain steel
flat and remove any trapped air.
♪
once 50 boards are stacked,
technicians put them in a press
for half an hour,
until the glue cures.
♪
in another part of the factory,
a machine cuts material
to create the board's frame.
it punches "v"-shaped notches
in a length of aluminum trim.
the trim bends at each notch
to form a wraparound frame.
♪
some boards come with a marker
tray that runs along the bottom.
to make these trays,
a technician cuts
board-length pieces
from a piece
of "l"-shaped metal trim.
♪
since the tray ends are sharp,
a technician attaches
plastic covers for protection.
♪
he secures the plastic
end covers with screws
on both ends of the part.
♪
meanwhile, technicians
peel off the protective film
covering the writing surface.
♪
then they flip over the board
to assemble the parts
from the back.
♪
this model doesn't have the
traditional wraparound frame.
instead, it has
a frame comprised
of four straight
"c"-shaped pieces
that fit over the board's edges.
to add stability,
technicians attach screws
through the trim
into the substrate.
♪
once assembly is complete,
the dry-erase board
is placed into a box,
ready to be shipped to a
business or classroom near you.
♪
narrator:
air rifles are not toys.
they're serious weapons.
used primarily for hunting,
air rifles should only
be handled by trained,
licensed professionals.
chemically, air rifles use one
of three types of power
depending on their design,
all of which utilize
compressed air
instead of an explosive charge.
handling air rifles
should always be treated
in a serious manner.
it is very important
to follow proper storage
and operating safety guidelines
to ensure it does not
go off accidentally.
air rifles are made
out of pre-machined parts
for the trigger assembly.
to build one half
of the trigger housing,
a craftswoman uses a jig
to align the end pieces
to the side plate.
then she screws
the parts together.
♪
she attaches the release latch
to the inside
of the trigger housing
and installs a base
for the trigger shoe.
she hooks one end of a spring
to the side plate,
and the other end
to the release latch.
a second spring links the first
spring to the trigger-shoe base.
♪
next, a lever is installed
which releases the firing pin.
once the trigger shoe
and the trigger are attached,
the assembly is complete.
this part absorbs
the recoil effect from firing.
a technician inserts
the recoil spring in a cylinder
and adjusts the tension.
♪
he slides the recoil assembly
into the bolt housing.
the bolt housing seals
the end of the gun barrel.
he installs the recoil system
and the housing,
a lever for cocking the rifle,
and inserts a lever pin.
♪
this end screw
will enable the user
to adjust the cocking position.
he attaches the firing pin
and the spring system...
♪
...and builds
the air-pressure regulator
by joining metal rings
with rubber seals
to create the housing.
he stacks washer springs
on a shaft.
♪
he inserts the assembly
into the regulator housing
and attaches an air-pressure
adjustment mechanism to the end.
♪
using a special
measuring device,
he connects the regulator
to an air cylinder.
the cylinder feeds compressed
air to the pressure regulator.
the measuring tool indicates
the regulator's performance.
if needed, he'll adjust
the pressure setting.
a technician inserts
the pressure regulator
in the firing chamber housing
and places a rubber seal
in another opening,
followed by a spring.
the spring will open and close
the one-directional valve
that supplies compressed air
to the firing chamber.
once the valve is installed,
he joins the firing chamber
to the recoil assembly.
the two units are held together
with substantial screws.
assembly of the air rifle's
mechanics are now complete.
a metal cover is screwed on top
of the trigger system.
♪
meanwhile, automated drills
bore into steel cylinders
to convert them
into rifle barrels.
a technician aligns one of the
barrels to the firing chamber.
using a spacer tool,
he tweaks the barrel's placement
against the firing chamber
and tightens the bolt
to the barrel.
♪
the trigger system
is run through a test
using a special machine
that measures the force it takes
to open the valve.
♪
an inspector fires the air rifle
to measure the pellet's velocity
and the accuracy of the shot.
he adjusts the tension
on the firing-pin spring.
he loads the rifle again
and fires it once more
to confirm the accuracy
of his adjustments.
♪
another technician
attaches the stock,
also called the shoulder stock,
to the rifle.
♪
he screws
the compressed-air cylinder
to the pressure regulator,
securing it in place.
narrator: quartz is one of the
most abundant minerals on earth.
it's no wonder artisans are
crafting this plentiful crystal,
mixed with polymer resin,
into kitchen
and bathroom countertops.
these engineered countertops
have low porosity,
are resilient,
and can be enhanced
by pigments, sparkles,
or other minerals.
♪
quartz countertops offer
more creative designs
than other stone surfaces.
some are fused with flecks
of mother of pearl,
metal for a more
dramatic look...
♪
...or speckled with materials
like glass,
porcelain, and granite
for visual effect.
♪
quartz rock
arrives at the factory
broken up into small,
sharp-edged crystals.
they're stored in outdoor bins
until production.
the crystals
tumble into a hopper
that follows them
into the factory.
the glittery quartz crystals
cascade onto a conveyor,
heading to a rinsing station.
♪
the crystals enter a revolving
drum, known as the tumbler,
and are tossed in the fire
burning inside the drum.
the intense heat removes
residual moisture
and sanitizes the crystals.
then the crystals are
transferred to sifter machines.
the sifter machines
shake the crystals
through screens
fitted with smaller mesh.
♪
the particles flow
into separate bins.
♪
the ingredients for
the quartz countertop formula
are loaded into feeder bins.
the formula calls for a black
countertop with shiny flecks
and green undertones.
the ingredients include
two different sizes
of quartz crystals --
green glass and mirror chips.
a computer releases
specific amounts
of the ingredients
into a hopper.
as the hopper opens,
a conveyor takes the ingredients
to a blender.
black pigment is mixed
into the blender,
along with
powdery filler quartz.
the mix is over 90% quartz.
a polymer resin will act
as a binder and add strength.
♪
down the line, a large mold
moves into position...
♪
...and an overhead mixer
disperses the quartz blend
into the mold.
♪
the mixer repeats
the process twice
to build up the materials
to the desired thickness.
♪
then the mold vibrates,
shaking the mixture
into a more level state.
♪
this will be the back
of the quartz countertop.
for additional strength
and flexibility,
nylon mesh is added
to the countertop mixture.
a device pulls the mesh
over the mix.
once it's aligned
with the mold contents,
the machine drops
the mesh into place.
an automated dispenser
spreads granulated limestone,
filling any voids
in the countertop mixture.
next, the ingredients are placed
in a kiln for two hours.
a blade scrapes off the loose
limestone from the slab backing.
polishing heads studded
with industrial diamonds
will now give the top
of the slab a serious shine.
simultaneously, an operator
adjusts the tension
of the polishers.
the polishers spin as water
flows across the countertop
to produce the desired
level of gloss.
this particular quartz slab
is about 1/4 inch thick.
its thin, flexible profile means
the quartz can be shaped
to different structures
if needed.
♪
a technician preparers
the transfer of pattern
onto a white quartz slab.
he drapes a long sheet of paper,
pattern side down,
onto the slab and tapes it
to the work surface.
♪
he activates a heat press,
which turns the ink on the paper
into a gas that penetrates
the resin in the slab.
the pattern becomes intrinsic
to the engineered stone.
with this process, any design
can be part of a slab,
including some that give
the illusion of marble.
♪
but unlike marble,
engineered quartz won't stain.
with quartz countertops,
the possibilities
are almost endless.