-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
fencing masks...
♪
...books...
...ocean drone transformers...
♪
...and 3-d puzzles.
fencing is one of the
oldest forms of armed combat.
in the late 18th century,
fencing evolved into a sport.
as fencing gained popularity,
a steel mesh mask was invented
to protect the eyes and face
from injury.
before fencers say "en garde,"
they don a face guard.
today, fencing is recognized
as an olympic sport,
so special mesh masks are
required to compete.
regulation fencing masks
are made
from rectangular pieces
of tight steel mesh.
a machinist uses
a guillotine blade
to cut the corners of
the mesh piece on an angle.
then he transfers
the mesh to a press
with a large mold that's
shaped like a face.
the hydraulically powered
mold press bears down
on the steel mesh and forces
it into a rounded shape.
using a special tool,
the machinist bends steel wire
to a form.
he brings the ends of the wire
together to close the loop.
an automated welder
fuses the ends.
the machinist transfers the hoop
to the next fixture
and places the rounded
steel mesh on top of the hoop.
a frame descends,
affixing the mesh to the hoop.
then multiple welding guns
spot-weld the mesh
to the hoop.
a large welding gun closes
the gaps between the spot-welds.
once fused,
the hoop will prevent the mesh
from fraying
and add structural rigidity.
using a nibbler tool,
the machinist trims the mesh,
revealing a clean edge.
next, the technician works
on the mask's side piece
by bending steel wire
into a rectangle.
he places the rectangular
frame in a fixture
and sets a piece of mesh
over the frame.
he spot-welds
the mesh to the frame.
this step provides
a more consistent weld
around the entire mask.
copper welding wheels fuse
and seal the mesh to the frame.
♪
then the machinist uses
a grinding wheel
to remove any sharp bits
or protrusions.
this is the result.
a bending device rounds the part
so that it will fit to
the sides and top of the head.
he welds the rounded part to
the back of the fencing mask.
a large welding gun
spot-welds the assembly together
in preparation for a final weld.
♪
once complete, the machinist
makes a full seam weld,
closing all gaps.
this will prevent a sword
from piercing through the mask,
potentially wounding the wearer.
next, the technician
pounds out any remaining dents
with a hammer,
restoring the mask
to the desired contours.
he places the fencing mask
on a rounded post
and uses a plastic mallet
to hammer the mask
against the post.
this step will improve
the overall shape of the mask.
they big is made out of
high molecular polyethylene,
which is strong
and extremely light weight.
the bib includes
a thick rubber band
that attaches to the mesh mask.
once the mesh
is coated with plastic,
another technician installs
rubber trim
along the perimeter
of the mask.
the plastic coating
on the mesh
insulates the mask, preventing
electrical interference
from the scoring
system's wiring.
the technician pipes epoxy glue
around the mask
just above the rubber trim.
he pulls the bib's
rubber band over the mask
and down to the bead of glue
at the bottom.
he tucks the pieces of material
under the band
for a neater look.
as the glue cures,
the bib's rubber band
adheres to the fencing mask.
another machinist
drills rivet holes
through the bib and mesh
along the sides of the mask.
♪
then he inserts
and flattens the rivets
to pull the bib flush
to the mesh.
each fencing discipline
requires its own
uniquely designed mask.
regardless of the design,
each mask will allow the athlete
to safely enjoy the sport.
♪
narrator: book-making
has evolved over time,
from scrolls
to writing on sheets of paper
bound together,
to the invention
of the printing press.
people continue to develop
new ways of recording history.
today,
thanks to digital technology,
the possibilities
of recording the spoken word
are endless.
a fine book-making specialist
makes just a few
limited edition books per year,
using traditional printing
and binding techniques.
production begins with a case
of tiny brass molds.
one mold,
called a matrix,
contains letters, numbers,
and punctuation marks.
a typecasting specialist inserts
the matrix case into a machine
called a monotype
composition caster.
and melts lead alloy ingots in
the machine's gas heated pot.
guided by a computer,
the machine casts
one character at a time
for every word of the book.
the computer program assigns
a location code to every matrix.
to cast a character,
the program communicates
a specific code
through plastic tubes,
while puffs of air
align that character's matrix
with the injection nozzle.
the nozzle dispenses molten lead
into the matrix
while the machine ejects
the cast character
onto a tray
called the galley.
as the lines of text exit
the machine,
the typecast specialist inserts
a strip of lead
to create spacing, called
leading, between each line.
he transfers the galley
to the press room,
where a proofing press
spreads ink on the type.
he places a sheet of
newsprint over the galley
and releases
an impression roller.
the roller prints the characters
on to the paper,
generating a proof.
meanwhile, a typesetter
assembles the larger
display copy manually
by placing individual letters
into a composition stick.
this method was used for all
copy prior to the invention
of the automatic typecasting
machines in the 1890s.
books printed
in large sizes of type
must be made entirely
by manual typeset.
once complete,
multiple galleys that make up
several pages of the book
are placed in a steel frame
called a chase
and loaded into
the printing press.
this cylinder press feeds
one sheet of paper at a time
to grippers that pull the paper
around a cylindrical roller.
as the roller rotates,
the paper drops
onto the inked type,
printing the characters
into the sheet.
one press sheet typically
contains eight pages per side.
another machine
folds the sheets,
then bookbinders
manually collate groups
of 16 consecutive pages to form
sections of the book
called signatures.
next, a bookbinder sews
the signatures together
one at a time
until the book is
fully assembled.
this method of bookbinding,
called smyth sewn binding,
after its 19th century inventor,
is of the highest quality
because pages can't
fall out or be removed.
♪
like the binding,
the book cover is
meticulously handcrafted.
a book binder hot glues
a piece of cloth
to the back of the cover.
the cover is made
of flexible paper
and thick cardboard.
then she flattens the cloth
on all sides.
using a razor blade,
the book binder makes a slit
for the cloth,
where she'll place
a recessed label later.
this enables the cloth
to spread out
and form to the spine's
rounded shape.
the cloth is pressed
firmly against
the structural components with
a plastic tool called a bone.
another book binder
attaches the cover
to the bound pages,
called the book block.
first, she applies glue
to both components.
then she positions
the book block on the cover...
...and presses them together.
she places the book
in a nipping press.
that puts pressure
around the spine,
fusing the book block and cover
together.
then the front and back
of the cover
are glued to the first and last
pages of the book.
the book then sits in
another press overnight,
bringing this book-making story
to a close.
♪
narrator: there's a new class
of autonomous vehicles
that can travel the ocean.
some dive and some sail,
but very few can do both.
an ocean drone transformer
shifts from sailboat
to submarine
by rearranging its shape
and altering
its mode of operation.
this is an autonomous
underwater and surface vehicle.
it's an information-gathering
machine
capable of propelling itself
over and under waves,
using nothing but wind
and solar power.
to create the vehicle's hull,
technicians unroll sheets
of fiberglass over a mold,
which has been machined
from a block of styrofoam.
they fiberglass fabric
is cut to fit
the interior of the hull.
thanks to its
extraordinary durability,
the fiberglass will allow
the watercraft
to spend months at a time
at sea.
and it won't interfere
with the vessel's
electronic signals.
technicians carefully tape
the material to the mold.
this yellow material will allow
liquid resin to flow easily.
then technicians unroll
a strip of gray ribbon
which will help
direct the flow of resin.
next, an incision is made
in the middle of the ribbon
for the nozzle,
which will be
the entry point for the resin.
a layer of plastic
is taped onto the hull,
which will help to vacuum seal
the assembly together.
a shut-off valve is added
to control the flow of resin.
the resin is poured
into a container.
and as the resin infuses
the flow media,
it displaces the vacuum
until it has completely
saturated
the fiberglass material.
the resin is cured for 12 hours.
the mold splits open
at the bottom
so technicians can easily
release the hull assembly.
a technician paints
the vehicle's keel,
which is made of
marine-grade aluminum.
the torpedo-shaped keel bulb
is made of lead.
electric cables run through
a hole drilled length-wise
down the center of the keel.
the interior structure
of the vehicle starts
as a flat material made from
a combination of fiberglass
and epoxy which they
form into large sheets
using intense heat and pressure.
then water jet technology
precision cuts the sheets
into the required shapes
and sizes.
technicians assemble
the shapes into a structure
that supports the hull
while housing
the vehicle's equipment.
in-house technicians build
the multiple circuit boards
that make up the central
processing unit, or cpu.
each board controls a separate
element of the vehicle,
such as the sensors, the wing,
or the communications system.
electronics and water are not
a compatible combination,
so the manufacturer designed
a water-tight acrylic tube
to hold all 10 of the circuit
boards that make up the cpu.
specialized cable connectors
are installed
so water doesn't leak
through the cover plate.
once the enclosure is sealed,
technicians vacuum out
flammable oxygen
and pump in non-flammable
gases to protect the cpu.
a technician
prepares the battery,
which is an off-the-shelf
lithium ion unit.
a battery housing is 3-d printed
out of a.b.s.
and infused with epoxy
to ensure
that it's completely
water tight.
next, a technician installs
the battery
in its designated spot.
solar panels on
the vehicle's surface
will recharge the batteries.
a hose will allow
the cpu to transfer water
from one ballast tank to another
to control the boat's
up and down motion or pitch.
the vehicle's tails
serve as housings
for the backup
communications antenna system.
in stealth mode, the vehicle
can sit below the water surface
with only its tails
above the waves.
designed to fold down
and tuck into the body
of the vehicle,
the rigid wing multi-tasks
as the primary antenna
and the sail,
which propels the vehicle
when it's above water.
due to its user-friendly
technology,
an operator can program
a mission
at any time
from any location
via satellite or wi-fi.
♪
narrator: the first jigsaw
puzzle was invented
in europe in 1760.
nearly two centuries later,
a canadian inventor reshaped
the popular pastime.
his puzzle pieces, made of thick
foam rather than cardboard,
could stand upright,
turning the puzzle
into a three-dimension model.
constructing a 3-d puzzle
yields impressive results.
to do so, two 800-piece
puzzle sets are used to create
this spectacular
castle replica.
an industrial designer creates
the puzzle's
three-dimensional structure.
an illustrator uses techniques,
such as visual textures
and shading, to transform
flat graphics
into a three-dimensional
rendering.
the industrial designer prepares
the printing and cutting layout,
fitting up to three
puzzles per sheet.
the puzzle pieces are made
from rigid foam.
the foam
is specifically engineered
to be chemically compatible
with the paper graphics
and proprietary adhesive.
a technician feeds one
sheet at a time
into a custom designed
lamination machine.
the first station
spreads hot glue
over the top of the foam sheet.
an automated arm with
vacuum suction cups
lifts a single sheet
of printed paper
and places it on
the glue-coated foam sheet.
as soon as the paper
adheres to the foam,
the she is released
from the suction cups.
then the foam moves
under a roller
that presses down the paper.
as the laminated foam
exits the machine,
a technician rolls a tube
over the foam, pressing out
any remaining air bubbles
to ensure the paper
adheres fully.
♪
in the development phase,
the industrial designer
assembled a blueprint
for how the puzzle pieces
would be shaped
and laid out.
that design
went to a toolmaker
who produced a corresponding
cutting die
out of steel knives.
the die is mounted
inside the cutting machine.
♪
a technician feeds the machine
one laminated foam sheet
at a time,
paper side down.
grippers grab
the edge of the paper,
pulling the sheet
into the machine.
the cutting die slices
the puzzle pieces
into the foam.
even though the cutting pressure
compresses the foam,
it immediately bounces back,
keeping the sheet intact.
thanks to a high-quality
rubber sheet
inserted between the blades,
the pieces don't get stuck
in the die.
the stiff rubber
provides counter-pressure
to help remove
the foam sheet.
if the sheet has two or three
puzzles printed on it,
the cutting die
separates them.
then a technician places
the puzzle
on a semi-automatic
conveyor belt
that moves it
to the dismantling machine.
the machine infuses
the die-cut puzzle sheet
with steam.
the steam prevents
static electricity,
which causes pieces
to cling together
or to the inside of the machine.
the machine
separates the pieces.
and dispenses them
into a puzzle box.
a technician adds the standard
instructions sheet,
and seals the box.
the instructions are
in black and white,
but can be viewed
in color online.
the first step is to sort
the pieces by color and design
and set aside the ones
marked with a red dot
which is part of
the manufacturing process,
not the puzzle itself.
the next step is to assemble
the puzzle, section by section.
all the sections are flat,
so the final step is to
attach the flat sections
to make the puzzle
three-dimensional.
for an additional challenge,
you can forgo
the step-by-step instructions
and refer only to
the photos on the box.
if you happen to
lose a puzzle piece,
you can go to
the company's website
to trace the number
of your missing piece,
then order a new piece online.
the company will mail it to you
so that you can
complete your puzzle.
unlike a traditional
flat puzzle,
you can move your 3-d puzzle
without it falling apart.
it takes four to six months
to develop and design
this incredible 3-d puzzle.
now it's time to spend
even longer
piecing this puzzle together.