-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪
narrator: table tennis is more commonly known as ping-pong.
folding table-tennis tables
are popular in homes and kept outdoors
because they can be closed up and rolled out of the way.
these tables can also fold down
on just one side,
allowing for solo play.
this high-end outdoor table-tennis table
has an aluminum bottom
that prevents the tabletop, called the plate,
from warping or splitting
due to expansion and contraction.
a press stamps cups into a sheet of aluminum.
this pattern creates nearly equal areas
both in contact and out of contact
with the rest of the plate layers, providing flexibility
to withstand temperature-related movement.
each table needs two embossed aluminum sheets --
one for each half of the plate.
a technician assembles frames for the plate halves
out of square extruded aluminum tubes,
cut to the lengths and widths of the plate half perimeter.
an automated milling machine makes miter cuts,
which allow the tubes to be made into rectangles.
then, the technician moves the frames
onto a rotating fixture...
♪
...and welds the corners together.
the frames are inserted into a brushing machine.
inside, wire brush rollers allow the aluminum surface
to become rough.
this helps the components to adhere to one another.
♪
another technician places the embossed aluminum sheet
into a rectangular assembly jig.
and adds the brushed aluminum frame.
a conveyor transfers the jig to the next station.
then, the jig connects with
an 8-millimeter-thick sheet of particleboard,
made of wood chips and glue.
the board is coated with a heat-activated adhesive film
on both sides.
at the next station, an aluminum sheet is placed
on top of the particleboard.
this step completes the plate component assembly.
next, the conveyor loads the jig into a press.
once 12 jigs have been loaded onto the press,
it heats to 239 degrees fahrenheit.
and compresses them for about 10 minutes.
this process activates the adhesive
and bonds the components of
each plate into a single unit --
one framed plate half.
each plate half goes through an automated milling machine.
♪
the machine trims any excess material from all four sides
to ensure the table won't have any sharp edges.
♪
the plate half goes through a paint machine,
then into an oven.
the process repeats, applying a second coat of paint
and a u.v.-resistant clear coat.
a machine applies paint through a screen stencil,
printing the lines that mark the boundaries
of the playing surface.
after the paint is dried in an oven,
a team places the finished plate half in a cardboard box
and attaches folding legs to the base.
the factory mills the legs in-house
out of high-tensile steel,
then finishes them in baked-on paint.
the net, along with several components,
are packed and made in-house,
which the consumer later assembles to the table.
components include the net posts, side panels, wheels,
wheel brakes, and the ball return box.
finally,
the plate half is transferred to
an automated system, which completes the packaging.
many ping-pong tables on the market
require the net to be removed
every time you fold the table.
the design of this table
enables the net to remain in place
whether the table is folded for storage
or has one or both sides open for playing.
less setup time means more time to play.
♪
narrator: plastic model kits were developed before world war ii,
when people became interested in seeing machines
in small-scale replication.
today plastic model kits continue to offer
building opportunities to hobbyists,
who love the challenge
of putting little pieces together.
with a plastic model kit,
a colossal ocean liner can be replicated in small scale.
built with nearly 2,000 pieces,
assembly is all about the details.
each model kit starts with extensive research
and design,
a process that can take up to a year to complete
and cost up to $100,000 dollars.
using the computer design,
a set of steel molds is made
for every piece of the kit.
tools carve into steel chunks
to make the molds.
precision work done entirely by machinery.
installed in large dies, the molds are linked by channels.
melted plastic will flow through the channels
to fill the molds.
clear polystyrene is used for transparent components.
the melted polystyrene is pumped under high pressure
into the molds.
once the plastic hardens, a pusher ejects the parts.
the connected kit parts are known as a tree.
the opaque polystyrene pellets are used to form
the other kit parts and are molded separately.
the scale of the parts is 1 to 24,
which means the model will be 1/24 the size of the original.
since the manufacturing is automated,
the risk of contamination is reduced.
next, the tree is put through a technical analysis test.
the technician photographs the tree
and compares it to an image already fit to scale.
if some parts haven't taken shape
or if they're only partially formed,
more pressure may be needed to ensure that the polystyrene
flows into all the mold cavities.
a technician compares a randomly
selected tree to the design
and verifies that no parts are poorly formed or missing.
once the confirmation is attained,
the technician slides the model kit parts
into a clear plastic sleeve.
before it's ready for retail,
the kit needs a set of illustrated instructions.
the designer deconstructs the model
and then reconstructs it on his computer
as he draws up the instructions.
with the instruction manual complete,
a team packs all the components
of the model kit in a box.
one of each of the kit trees is placed in each box.
the kit also includes decals
and large, separately molded parts,
like the ocean liner hull.
a technician closes the box.
as it moves down a conveyor,
a laser prints the date of production
and the batch number on the side.
then, the box is wrapped in plastic,
and the ends are sealed with heat guns.
a year of planning has gone into
making the plastic mold kit.
but took less than 10 minutes to mold the kit parts
and package them.
building the model will take 10 to 12 hours.
the factory does a test build on each model
to confirm that it comes together as planned.
this is the iconic constellation aircraft,
a world war ii military transport plane
that was later converted to a commercial airliner.
assembling a plastic model kit
can be a great learning experience for the builder.
decals mimic the i.d. information
on the outside of the original aircraft.
these decals have been pretreated with adhesive.
soaking the decals in water activates them.
the assembler brushes more water
onto the design spots on the model.
and applies the decals to the dampened spots.
as the glue dries, they adhere to each other.
the plastic models can also be painted
before the decals are applied
for refined and clean look that really comes together.
♪
narrator: the light microscope was
invented in 16th-century europe.
it allowed the human eye to see tiny things
that couldn't be seen before.
a sophisticated research tool
with focused light and optical lenses,
can magnify biological tissue,
minerals, and computer chips.
observation is an important aspect of science.
the light microscope increases the power of observation,
making it possible to see things
that can't be seen with the naked eye.
this 19th-century microscope represented a turning point,
with lenses that delivered more light to specimens,
increasing resolution.
a light microscope often has multiple lenses,
all made from special optical glass.
a drill with a core bit tunnels into the glass
to produce several solid cylinders.
the drill cuts them larger and thicker
than the final specifications.
this gives technicians extra material to work with.
a tool moves the cylinder against a spinning blade
slicing it into lens blanks.
the cylinder is first glued to a glass block,
then glued to the tool.
this method holds the cylinder in the correct position.
since bits of glue are left on the lenses,
a thorough washing removes them.
next, a device grips the lens using vacuum pressure
and angles it for grinding.
multiple grinding tools remove any excess glass
and shape the radius of the lens.
in a process known as lapping,
a technician applies a fine abrasive compound
to a bowl with the desired contours.
he rotates and rubs the lens against the bowl
to further shape the lens.
he rinses off the lens and holds it against a light
while he examines it for scratches.
he measures the radius of a master lens
and compares it to that of the lens he's been working on.
if the measurements are off,
he'll remove more material.
once additional material is removed,
he measures the thickness of the lens
and compares it to what it was before the adjustments.
next, these polishing tools will be used
to fine-tune the profile of the microscope lenses.
to protect the lenses during polishing,
a technician sprays on a temporary lacquer.
these tools will remove
just a fraction of a millimeter
of glass,
but it will make an important impact.
polishing liquid provides fine abrasion
and enables the tool to move across the glass.
then, a robot trims the edges of the lens.
a device clamps the lens in place
as trimming continues along the edges.
trimming allows the lens to reach the correct diameter.
next, the lenses are cleaned
in multiple water-based solutions.
in the baths, the vibrations from high-frequency sound
create a gentle scrubbing action.
the intensive cleaning leaves the lenses pristine.
a technician places the freshly cleaned lenses
in round trays.
she handles them very carefully
inserting them individually into each tray slot.
because they're extremely fragile,
the slightest pressure could crack them.
the lenses in the trays will receive
an antireflective coating --
one that will prevent a loss of light due to reflection.
next, the antireflective material
is loaded into a coating machine.
the technician adds a specific amount
of magnesium fluoride into a receptacle in the base.
she inserts a piece of aluminum oxide
in the next receptacle.
and transfers the microscope lenses to the chamber,
placing the rack on top.
inside the chamber, heat and a targeted plasma beam
evaporate the materials.
they precipitate onto the lenses,
forming a coating.
coming up, all is revealed
as the lenses come together in the microscope.
♪
narrator: light microscopes bring the invisible into focus.
similar to telescopes,
a tiny specimen is placed under the lens assembly,
from which the viewer can discover what lies within.
by magnifying the minuscule,
the light microscope has become an indispensable
scientific tool.
the light microscope often has multiple lenses.
throughout the production process,
the lenses are put under the microscope
to confirm that the geometry is correct.
a technician magnifies the lenses one at a time,
measuring their radius and the diameter.
meanwhile, computerized tools
shape the edges of glass prisms.
the prisms are triangular lenses
that bend or refract light,
aligning colors at a focal point
for a clearer image.
once the shaping is complete,
a technician positions a prism on a holder to be calibrated.
she aims a laser at it.
the light passes through the prism,
reflected in a mirror, and bounces back.
a computer magnifies the surface of the prism
a thousand times bigger than its
original size,
measuring the degree to which the prism refracts light
and the flatness on each side.
this is an inside look at a microscope lens assembly,
revealing the combination of lenses.
a prism can be an important part of this combination.
the cast-aluminum housing has been equipped
with the circuitry.
some of the connections have already been made.
it's ready for the focusing mechanisms
that allow the user to zoom in on tissue or other specimens.
a technician inserts the motorized focus drive
into the housing
so that the ends protrude from both sides.
♪
he attaches adjustment knobs to the ends.
the larger part of the knob is for quick motorized focus.
the small one is for slower and more precise focusing.
♪
he slides a protective rubber cap
onto the fine-focus component of the knob.
another technician mounts a system
for revolving lenses to the microscope.
this is called the nosepiece.
he wires the nosepiece to the controls.
using compressed air,
a technician cleans a part
known as the side port revolver.
it's equipped with a mirror, prism lens,
and a magnifying lens.
it will reflect light to the lenses in the eyepiece
or external cameras.
then the side port revolver is tested.
at this point, multiple lenses have been installed
in the tube lens assembly.
the technician screws the assembly to a revolver.
light from the illuminated specimen
shines through the tube lens in parallel rays
the rays are projected onto the eyepiece
or external camera.
he looks through the eyepiece
to check the positioning
of the lens in the revolver slot
making adjustments if needed.
a reflected-light illumination system is installed.
this part directs light through
the lens and onto the specimen,
then back through the lens
to the eyepiece or external cameras.
this system makes it possible to magnify opaque specimens.
then a technician installs the transmitted light arm.
the light arm is used for magnifying transparent
or thin specimens.
it does this by directing light through them.
a technician performs a final inspection.
he places specimens under the microscope,
checking the brightness of the transmitted light
and the resolution of the magnified image.
he tests the focus of all the lenses in the nosepiece
to confirm that each one delivers a sharp, clear view.
he verifies that the revolving mechanisms move smoothly
and are in good working order.
after this final inspection,
this light microscope is ready for research.
by imaging small things, big discoveries are possible.
♪