-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator:
today on "how it's made,"
belts...
♪
...3-d metal printers...
...detectable warning panels...
♪
...and model stirling engines.
belts have been worn with
different types of garments
since the invention of clothes.
made to cinch your waistline,
this accessory is worn with
pants, shirts, robes,
or dresses,
making a fashionable addition
to any outfit.
durable and flexible, leather
is the classic material
used for belt making.
this production facility
manufactures stylish,
high quality belts
at top speed.
a designer creates
a belt pattern on her computer
and sends the design
electronically
to the in-house
laser etching machine.
a craftsman places
a cowhide on a large table.
he examines the hide
for any flaws
and carefully marks each one.
the cowhides are made from
meat industry byproducts,
and most are sourced
from italy.
a device scans
the shape of the hide
and the craftsman digitally
marks the location of the flaws.
a specialized cutting machine
uses the marked information
to create an efficient
series of cuts.
this process results
in a high quality product
with minimal waste.
another technician sorts
the various belt lengths
into containers,
preparing them for
the next step.
the cutting machine
is capable of slicing
up to 2,400 belts per day.
the cutting machine creates
straight, sharp-edged strips.
the technician feeds the belts
into a machine
that bevels the edges at
the rate of 6,000 per day.
at the next station, a series
of small suction devices
quickly lift and place each
belt on a conveyor system.
a stamping machine
accurately cuts the shape
of the belt tip
and the holes for the prong.
the craftsman stacks a group
of belts and packs them
tightly together,
then he dyes the edges with ink
and sands them down.
these steps complement
the edge dyeing machine process,
which can add color
to the belt edges.
then the belts are transferred
to a drying machine.
the edges must be completely dry
before they move
to the next step.
powered by world war ii
jeep engines,
a rotating wooden drum tumbles
the belts,
while simultaneously
burnishing the leather.
this type of machinery
comes from
italy's famous
leather working region.
this imported machine,
from milan,
rapidly punches out
the pattern of perforations,
which make up the belt's
signature design elements.
since the machine's die is less
than 20 inches long,
the complex pattern along the
belt can't be stamped at once.
instead, the machine punches out
a section at a time
resulting in a production rate
of 1,400 belts per day.
a laser etching machine
burns a second pattern
into the leather surface.
this pattern was created
by the designer
prior to production.
at the next station,
a craftswoman fills the holes
of a specially crafted
two-part metal die
with nail heads.
the nail heads are made of
zinc with a brass finish.
using a press,
an operator places the die
in a waiting repository.
she removes the top half,
ensuring that all of the holes
are filled with nail heads.
then she turns the belt around
and places it over the die
before sliding the belt
inside the press.
the press affixes the nail heads
to the leather.
before attaching the buckle,
the belts go through
a process called skiving.
this device shaves off
a section of the leather
so that when it's folded over,
it won't be too thick.
a loop is attached
on to the end of the belt,
followed by a buckle.
the craftswoman uses the loop to
temporarily hold
the buckle and tag in place.
the tag contains the belt's
size, price,
and brand information.
another craftswoman sews the
belt buckle and tag in place,
using 69 weight thread
and a bar tacking stitch.
this facility manufactures
nearly 10,000 belts per day.
this intricate
leather fashion accessory
might be a cinch to wear,
but not to make.
♪
narrator: 3-d printers generate
metal parts for spacecraft,
cars, and medical devices,
to name a few.
3-d printing technology allows
for the production
of complex design structures
which can't be achieved
using traditional
manufacturing methods.
the 3-d metal printer could
truly break the mold.
thanks to advancements in
technology,
it's now possible
to print metal parts.
this 3-d printer melts
and layers metal powder
and a part materializes.
this part will become
a rocket nozzle heat exchanger.
at the core of the 3-d metal
printer is the deposition head,
which feeds and melts the
the metal powder.
so far the designing process
has taken hundreds of hours.
tools guided by
the design software transform
a brass cylinder
into the nozzle cone.
the profile of the nozzle cone
can vary slightly,
depending on the parts
the 3-d metal printer
will be used to produce.
next the powder inlet component
is added.
metal powder will
flow through this part
to a mixing chamber and,
eventually, the nozzle cone.
computerized tools
cut angled channels,
delivering different
metal powders
to the mixing chamber
with an angular velocity,
creating a vortex to
help blend the powders.
the part has been nickel plated
and fasteners are installed.
the technician aligns
the laser delivery channel
to the powder inlet part,
and screws them together.
the laser will melt
the metal powder
as it flows through the inlet.
she installs latches on the rim
of the powder inlet part
and tightly torques the screws
that hold them in place.
using the latches, she locks
the mixing chamber to the inlet.
the latches will help make
further assembly and disassembly
of the 3-d metal printer head
a snap.
♪
next, a laser nozzle is screwed
onto the mixing chamber.
then, the technician places
the main nozzle cone
over the laser nozzle
and connects the threaded rim
to the mixing chamber.
the deposition head
is now complete.
next, another the technician
mounts the laser system
to a vertical axis
in the printer housing.
he runs coolant lines
for the laser
and attaches
the deposition head,
screwing it in place with
a threaded brass collar.
the laser system and deposition
head are now integrated.
first, the powder feeder
is assembled with
a substantial base to
accommodate a feed drive system.
the technician installs
the feeder shaft
in the upper half of the base.
then, he screws a disc
to the shaft.
the disc will spin to
move the metal powder
into the printer head system.
he slides a spring
on to the shaft
which helps maintain its
position.
then, he connects the upper half
of the base to the bottom half.
he installs an inlet
for carrier gas
that will be used to move
the powder through tubing
to the printer head.
he assembles windows to a lid.
they'll provide a view
of the metal powder
swirling in the feeder disc,
so that any problems
can be identified.
he press fits the hopper cone
into a ridged hole in the lid.
♪
he attaches the hopper
to the cone.
he clamps the feeder motor to
the hopper using long screws,
which seals the hopper and turns
it into a pressure vessel.
the resulting pressure
will help force the powder
through tubing to
the deposition head.
he installs the lid and hopper
assembly on the base.
once assembly is complete,
the technician sets
the base on a mount,
sliding protruding pins into
corresponding holes in the lid.
this completes
the powder feeder.
the powder feeder now ready
to supply the raw material
for 3-d printing.
an operator connects
it to the printer
and pours metal powder
into the hopper.
the system delivers the powder
to the printer head.
the dispensing and melting
of the metal powder,
as well as the layering,
are all controlled by
a computer generated program.
this 3-d printer can manufacture
a part in a few hours,
so you can sit back
and watch it materialize.
♪
narrator:
detectable warning panels
are cautionary signals
for the visually impaired.
their specific
pattern of domed bumps
are detectable by touch or with
walking aid equipment.
they also serve as
warning systems
at intersections
or on transit platforms,
alerting all people
to proceed with caution.
for the visually impaired,
these little bumps
on the road aren't a problem.
they're a solution.
embedded in surfaces
at intersections,
detectable warning panels
help people
find their way through touch.
making a fiberglass polymer
version of the panels
starts with a carefully
calculated formula.
technicians add pigment
to resin paste
keeping a close eye
on the scale
to confirm the amounts
are correct.
next, a chemical thickener
is added,
this ingredient will increase
the viscosity
to a syrupy consistency.
then the ingredients
are blended together.
the agitation from the blender
causes the mixture to heat,
starting a chemical reaction
which will eventually
cause solidification.
as the mixture thickens,
it turns a vivid color
that people with compromised
vision can still perceive.
the technician gauges
the temperature
to confirm that the chemical
reaction isn't too advanced.
then,
the mix is set aside,
so technicians can
prepare other ingredients.
rams punch the bag of mineral
fillers to break up any clumps
as they flow into a hopper.
stearic acid is added to
cut the thickening.
a computer dispenses
the mineral filler and resin
into a large mixing tank.
♪
an operator adds an inhibitor
to delay the chemical reaction
as the mixing blade
blends the ingredients
into a paste.
zinc stearate is added to
the mixture,
which will allow the completed
panel to release from the mold.
glass bundles, known as
rovings, then unwind.
a blade chops them into
toothpick sized pieces.
the pigment mixture,
which has been blended
into the resin paste,
flows on to a plastic liner.
shards of glass fall down
on to the yellow resin mixture.
as the machine pulls
the mixture forward,
the liner takes
the glass-encrusted resin
to the next stage.
more resin and a top plastic
liner,
create an encasing with
the glass in the middle.
rollers squeeze
the encasing together,
forcing the resin to flow
around the glass shards.
the material is compacted
to the desired thickness.
then, the glass
and resin material
cures for 24 hours.
this allows
the materials to thicken,
so it can be cut into panels.
a circular cutting wheel moves
on a carriage across the mat
slicing it to length.
the mats are retrieved from the
machine and stacked.
the plastic liners on both
sides are still intact.
next, the material is weighed
to confirm the specified amount.
if more is needed,
a technician will adjust
accordingly.
he then peels off the liners.
the glass and resin material are
transferred to a heated mold.
the mold applies 500 tons
of hot pressure.
the material liquefies and flows
into the crevasses of the mold,
forcing air out.
as the bumpy panels take shape,
a chemical reaction causes
the material to solidify.
a worker trims
the freshly molded panels
to give them a cleaner line.
and sands the edges smooth.
he clamps the panel to
a fixture at both ends.
the clamps keep
the panel in position
and prevent it from bending.
as mounting holes are drilled
into the panel.
♪
the technician
uses an air gun to
blow off drilling residue
and dust.
this detectable warning panel
is now ready for installation.
two craftsmen pipe adhesive
into channels
at the back of the panel.
the panel is installed in
a recessed part of the curb
and screwed into anchors
in the concrete.
for people with limited vision
trying to navigate
their way around,
these tactile panels will make
a difference they can feel.
♪
narrator: a stirling engine
produces power
by circulating hot and cold air,
or other types of gas,
at different temperatures.
heating expands the gas,
while cooling contracts it.
these alternating reactions move
up to four pistons at a time,
driving the machine and the
pulleys attached to the engine.
this german company manufactures
model stirling engines
and accessories,
like this marble tower.
the engine parts move by
a closed loop of air
that circulates
inside the engine,
expanding and contracting as
it repeatedly heats and cools.
a specialist designs the engines
and produces digital renderings
for each component.
the dimensions must be accurate
within 1/1,000
of a millimeter.
a computer guided turret machine
shapes the engine's
cooling cylinder
out of a solid piece of brass.
heat escapes brass quickly,
making it ideal for a component
to rapidly reduce its
hot air temperature.
the cooled air contracts,
producing a vacuum
that draws the engine's
working piston downward.
when reheated, the air expands,
pushing the piston up.
this repetitive motion
drives the crankshaft.
the cooling cylinder has
fins to help diffuse heat,
a hole on top for
the working piston
and another hole on the side
for the displace piston.
after cleaning the cylinder
with compressed air,
a technician performs
a quality control check.
first, he inserts multiple
test pins into the hole
for the working piston
until one is the right fit.
this tells him
the diameter measurement.
using a digital caliper,
the technician measures a series
of aluminum working pistons
until he finds the one
that's the correct size
for the hole's diameter.
he inserts the piston
into the cylinder,
then holds the cylinder
upside down.
if the piston falls out slowly,
it's the right size.
the fit must be precise to
prevent the circulating air
from leaking out
of the cylinder.
in the assembly area,
another technician superglues
a crankshaft ball bearing
into each of the engine's
stainless steel side frames.
she glues the displace axle
to the displace piston.
the part should fit loosely
in the cooling cylinder
to allow the air
to flow around it,
while moving back and forth
between the engine's
heating and cooling zones.
she inserts the displace
piston into the side hole
of the cooling cylinder.
then the heating cylinder is
mounted over the piston.
the heating cylinder draws heat
generated by the flame
into the engine.
she attaches it to the cooling
cylinder with four screws.
a connecting rod is attached
to the working piston
and the piston is inserted
into the cooling cylinder.
next, the technician
mounts one of the side frames
to the cylinder,
attaches a rocker arm
to the side frame,
then puts one end
of the crankshaft
through the side frame's
ball bearing.
she attaches
the second side frame,
by inserting the other end
of the crankshaft
through its ball bearing.
she mounts what has been
assembled so far
on to a wooden base plate,
then she connects one end
of the rocker arm to the
working piston's connecting rod.
the other end of the rocker arm
is joined
to the crankshaft
connecting rod,
which is connected at
a 90-degree angle
to both the rocker arm
and the crankshaft.
on each end of the crankshaft,
a heavy brass flywheel
is mounted.
the flywheels increase
the momentum of the engine.
to power an accessory
with the stirling engine,
one end of a drive belt
is run around a pulley
on the accessory,
and the other end of the belt
around a plastic drive wheel.
the finishing touch is
an engraved brass
identification plate.
here's how this engine works.
first, the burner case is filled
with denatured alcohol
and the wick is attached.
the burner case is placed
under the heating cylinder,
light the wick,
and let the engine preheat
for 10 to 15 seconds,
then turn a flywheel to
kickstart the engine.
the flame heats the air
inside the heating cylinder.
the hot air expands
into the cooling cylinder,
causing the cylinder
to cool and contract.
this moves the working
piston up and down,
turning the engine's crankshaft.