-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator: throughout europe
in the late 1700s,
peaked caps were traditionally
worn by industrial workers.
today, they are worn
by professionals
such as security personnel,
members of the military,
and police officials
that wear uniforms.
in the united kingdom,
some police officers
still wear
the classic custodian helmet,
but now many officers
have chosen to wear
the lightweight, comfortable,
and practical peaked cap.
to make these caps,
a hat maker, or a milliner,
assembles a number of components
using patterns
to cut out the required pieces
of wool, foam, and plastic.
a milliner bends a strip
of polypropylene plastic
into a circle.
she sews the joint
with a high-strength thread,
creating the hat band
that will go around the head.
she positions a smaller piece
of polypropylene,
known as the badge support,
and sews it in place.
the support will prevent
the weight of a police badge
from distorting
the shape of the hat.
these crescent-shaped components
are pieces of wool
glued to thin, flexible foam.
she sews the crescents together,
creating a circular piece,
which will form the bevel.
she uses a specialized,
long-arm sewing machine,
which has been customized
to make hats.
the seams are carefully ironed
flat to prevent any bulging.
if the iron is too hot,
the foam will melt.
too cool,
and the wool won't flatten.
she aligns two strips
of 100% wool fabric
and sews them together
at the ends.
this piece will cover
the plastic stiffener
forming the outer band.
to ensure the sizing is correct,
the milliner places the wool
cover over the stiffener.
♪
the stiffener is installed
at the end
of the production process.
next, the milliner irons
the seams of the band covers.
she finishes the band covers
on a sewing machine
known as a flat bed
and creates a fold
to hold the plastic stiffener
and sews the edges together.
then the band cover is sewed
to the bevel.
while it's difficult to attach
two pieces of cloth
at different angles,
this step creates an even seam
that runs 360 degrees.
it takes at least six months
of training
to learn how to make hats.
the crown is made
from three materials --
a combination of wool and foam,
a polyester lining,
and a protective-grade
p.v.c. layer.
once the three materials
have been sewn together,
the machinist trims
the perimeter of the crown.
she marks the side edges
and aligns them with the seams
on the bevel.
then she sews the crown
to the bevel.
having spent a great deal
of time perfecting the skills,
this milliner
makes it look easy.
finally, the components
begin to resemble a hat.
using a polypropylene template,
the machinist positions
and marks
two spots on the bevel.
she places two small brass rings
on a special device
and aligns the marks
with the device's posts,
which cut out two holes
through the fabric.
then she places two cup-shaped
rings on the posts,
and the machine
punches them down,
forming eyelets for ventilation.
next,
the polypropylene stiffener
is inserted into the hat.
finally, the hat begins
to take on its final shape.
the tag containing the hat's
size is sewed on hat band.
she places a checkered-pattern
band on the brim of the hat,
called dicing
or the sillitoe tartan.
the milliner inserts
a replica badge
through holes
in the badge support
and secures it with a pin.
this is a replica,
since we can't show
real police badges on tv.
next, the milliner sews
the peak onto the band.
it took a highly skilled
milliner
more than half an hour
to sew this hat.
they might look straightforward,
but peaked caps
are surprisingly complex.
♪
narrator:
a home water heater stores
and heats water in a tank.
this is how it works.
when you turn on a faucet,
hot water flows out of the tank
from the top,
while cold water flows
into the tank from the bottom.
conventional water heaters
are fueled by natural gas,
electricity, propane, or oil.
this company custom-builds
several types of water heaters
for use with different types
of heat sources,
such as boilers, heat pumps,
and solar panels.
each work order includes
a picture outlining
the pipe configuration
and the connecting valves,
along with a list of the
water heater's specifications.
to make a copper tank,
a technician cuts a thick sheet
of copper to a specified length.
he aligns the end of the sheet
to the gradation on the table
that corresponds to
the tank's circumference.
then he actives the guillotine
blade with a foot pedal.
a computer-guided machine
punches holes for the valves.
this water heater requires
two valves
at each end of the heating coil
and one that will connect
the water pipe to the tank.
the technician inserts
the copper sheet
into a mechanical roller.
the rollers apply pressure,
forming the sheet
into an open cylinder.
one end of the cylinder
is clamped into a machine
that welds linear seams.
the technician inserts
the other end
of the cylinder
through the machine
and joins it
against the clamped end.
the machine is programmed
to weld a seam
to the length
of the connected ends.
the technician monitors
the welding arm
through a u.v. lens
to protect his eyes.
the machine stops automatically
when it reaches
the programmed seam length.
this process closes the cylinder
with a strong,
pressure-resistant seam,
creating the water-heater
tank's structural component.
another technician places
the tank's top on a press.
the press punches a hole
for a threaded pipe fitting.
the fitting connects the pipe
to the hot water.
using a different press,
the technician makes
another hole
into the cylinder
for a threaded fitting.
this fitting connects to
an electrical element
that heats water
in conjunction with a boiler.
another technician makes
the tank's heating coil
by running a straight copper
tube through three rollers.
the tube is bent under pressure,
forming it into a coiled shape.
the heat from the boiler,
pump, or solar panel
flows through the heating coil,
heating the water stored
in the tank.
since the copper-tube wall
is too thin to weld,
a technician uses a fusing
technique known as brazing.
this metal-joining process
brazes a flow fitting
on one end of the heating coil
and a return fitting
on the other.
next, the heating coil
is placed in the tank.
the fittings protrude through
a hole at the top and bottom.
the technician secures each one
with a nut,
then tightens the nuts
with an impact wrench.
like the dome top, the bottom
component's edges are grooved,
allowing the tank
to fit perfectly
into the cylinder base.
once the top and bottom
components are installed,
the tank goes back
to the brazing station
for final assembly.
a welder brazes
the top and bottom components
to the cylinder,
then he brazes
a feed fitting to a hole
near the bottom of the tank.
this location is where
cold water enters
the tank to be heated.
next, a technician conducts
a quality-control test.
he blocks the three fittings,
fills the cylinder with air,
then submerges the tank in water
to check for air bubbles,
which would indicate a leak.
♪
a stainless-steel water heater
is constructed
just like a copper heater,
except that they don't require
any brazing.
a robot sprays the tanks with
expandable polyurethane foam
for insulation.
the customer selects
the degree of insulation,
one to four inches thick.
the foam takes just five minutes
to cure.
as the tank stores hot water,
the insulation reduces
the amount of heat
the tank loses over time.
♪
narrator:
electrically powered vehicles
may seem like
a 21st-century phenomenon,
but they were actually
first invented in the 1880s.
during that time,
they were very popular,
until combustion-engine vehicles
became the new normal.
today,
these electrically powered
alternative-fuel vehicles
are making a comeback.
this manufacturer produces
a wide range of electric boats.
thanks to powerful batteries,
some of these vehicles
can travel
over 35 miles per hour.
craftspeople apply
a gel-coat skin to a mold,
using a product
derived from vinyl.
then they layer on
a dry fiberglass fabric
and vacuum-bag
the entire assembly.
the vacuum suction
draws in liquid resin,
infusing the material.
a craftsman marks a dry spot
as a test point
to monitor and ensure
complete saturation.
the infusion process
takes about two hours.
once complete, the assembly
will cure for four to six hours,
depending on the general
humidity and temperature levels.
once cured, the assembly
is removed from the mold.
despite the structure's
light weight,
this deck is incredibly
strong, rigid, and durable.
the fiberglass decks and hulls
make up the boat's shells.
a craftswoman applies
a high-strength marine glue
to a recessed area of the deck.
she installs an anti-skid
deck insertion.
this material is a composite
designed to resemble wood.
unlike real wood,
this composite material
will last the lifetime
of the boat
and won't require
any additional maintenance.
the craftswoman uses a roller
to apply pressure evenly
across the entire
decking surface.
this step will eliminate
any unwanted air pockets.
next, a mirror-image
decking section
is applied to the other side.
a specialist installs
the electrical-wiring harness.
to avoid corrosion,
marine-grade wiring is stored
in a sealed environment
under the deck.
since the decking
is lightweight,
it only takes two people to lift
and install it on the hull.
the lip of the deck
fits snugly into place.
the most powerful boat models
require lithium-ion batteries.
these boats are built
with military-grade foam.
the density of the foam
adds structure,
causing the boat
to become unsinkable.
using a hoist, technicians
install the deck
of a large, powerful
electric boat.
the deck lip slides
over the top of the hull.
depending on the boat model,
the manufacturer uses
either lithium-ion
or lead-acid batteries
as a power source.
a specialist installs a series
of marine-grade
dc31 lead-acid batteries.
at 6 volts, 225 amps,
they're similar to batteries
used in cars.
by contrast, the 7.7-kilowatt
lithium-ion batteries
pack a charge of 48 volts.
the batteries are installed
under the seats.
to create a watertight seal
between the deck to the hull,
a craftsman installs
a rubber bumper
around the perimeter
of the boat.
holes have been pre-drilled
to avoid cracking
when installation is complete.
this manufacturer sources
their motors
from an outside
electric-motor company,
which also builds motors
for cars.
the fin, made of aluminum
encased in marine-grade rubber,
is installed on the bottom
of the motor.
the propeller attaches
to the motor with a zinc nut.
two circuit boards located
on board
will send instructions
to the motor.
a waterproof cover is placed
on top of the circuit boards
for added protection.
locknuts with nylon washers will
prevent unnecessary vibrations
while the motor is on.
with the steering cables
installed,
the entire unit pivots
right and left,
allowing the pilot
on deck to steer.
the powerful motor is equivalent
to a 10-horsepower
combustion engine,
and because it sits
in the water,
it stays cool and quiet.
finally, a craftswoman places
the boat's sun canopy
over the framework.
this will allow customers
to add solar panels
for charging the boat.
also, a customer can choose
the colors
for both their canopies
and upholstery.
there's no denying
that electric boats
are the future of fun
on the water.
♪
narrator:
modern fencing is a sport
consisting of three disciplines,
one of which is foil fencing.
while in play,
a lightweight foil sword
is used to score points.
points can be scored
when the tip of a player's sword
makes contact onto
their opponent's torso.
a fencing foil is
a piece of equipment
that should only be used
by trained professionals.
this sword doesn't have
a sharp edge or pointed tip.
it's all about scoring hits.
fencing foils are made
out of thin steel bars.
the steel is a low-carbon,
nickel-rich alloy
that's strong yet flexible.
an automated saw cuts the bars
to a length of 35 inches.
the bar will be stretched and
shortened as it's transformed.
a forge heats and hammers
the hilt end to a round shape,
leaving the rest of the rod
rectangular.
here you can see the difference
in the rod's shape.
another forging machine
softens the end of the rod
and pushes the blade
through a series of hammers.
this tapers the blade
and stretches the steel,
doubling it in size.
an operator clamps
the tapered blade in a jig
to hold it straight
while the steel cools.
then the operator slices
the hilt end to length.
the excess steel will be
recycled into new swords.
next, the blades are heated
in a 932-degree oven.
this step removes stresses
and makes the metal
less brittle.
after a second heating,
the blades soak in oil
to cool and harden.
the exposure to intense heat
causes a rusty scale
to form on the blade,
so technicians clean it off.
a sword maker clamps the blades
in a disc grinder.
the grinder carves a fine groove
from the hilt to the tip.
the groove will house a wire
for the electric scoring system.
the blade is cleaned to remove
any remaining
surface imperfections.
a spinning belt
coated with an abrasive
grinds all four sides
of the blade.
then the sword is polished
using a buffing wheel
and polishing compound.
you can see the difference this
makes in the blade on the right.
the craftsman hammers the blade
against an anvil
to straighten out any kinks.
then he inspects the blade.
if needed, the craftsman will
make adjustments
to the blade with a hammer.
now it's time to work
on the hilt end of the blade.
another craftsman locks the end
of the blade in a threading die,
applies lubricant,
and activates
the automated system.
the system turns the sword
in the die, carving out threads.
then the threaded hilt
is cut to length.
at the next station,
a computerized laser engraves
the company logo into the steel.
after the sensor barrel
is installed
on the end of the sword
and the electrical scoring wire
is placed in the groove,
the technician applies glue
to keep the wire secure.
the sword blade is placed
in a rack
that holds it
in a bow-like bend.
this step will give
the glued wire
the flexibility it needs
to bend with the rest
of the sword while in use.
after the blade has cured,
a pressure sensor spring
is inserted into the barrel
and capped with a sensor button.
the technician uses screws
to hold the components together.
to assemble the hilt,
the scoring wire is threaded
through a hole in the guard
so it can easily slide
into place.
then the sensor wire
is connected to a socket.
the wiring assembly is covered
with a plastic pad
that allows the socket
to protrude.
finally, the pistol-grip handle
is screwed into
the threaded end of the blade.
this fencing foil is now ready
for testing.
the technician plugs the fencing
foil into testing equipment,
then he places a one-pound
weight on the sensor button
and checks to see
if it responds.
and the results are in.
this fencing foil is now ready
to stand up to its competition.