♪
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
custom shoe trees...
...clay targets...
...squeeze chutes...
...and composite
boat propellers.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
shoe trees are a device
placed inside
leather shoes
to preserve their shape.
they also absorb foot
perspiration by wicking away
leather-damaging moisture
from the inside of the shoe.
shoe trees are
a worthwhile investment
because they extend
the life of footwear.
shoe trees can be purchased
at any price.
some are mass produced
and inexpensive,
while others can be
handcrafted and custom ordered
like these from
a small workshop in france.
the customer can select
their preference of tree style
as well as the type
of wood and color.
a craftsman uses a model
in the customer's size
and marks its length
on a piece of wood.
using a band saw,
the craftsman cuts the wood
to the marked length.
he saws one side flat to be able
to lie the piece on its side.
then he traces the general shape
of the model
and saws along
his previously marked lines
to remove excess wood.
once complete, the block is
roughly shaped like the model.
next, the block is mounted
on one side of a pantograph,
a milling machine that copies
the form of one object
to shape another.
he mounts the model on the
other side of the pantograph.
♪
once the machine is turned on,
both model and block
begin rotating.
the machine's tools, a tracer
and a cutter, are linked.
as the tracer runs across
the model, the cutter moves
in identical carving motions
across the block.
by the time the tracer finishes,
the block is an exact copy
except for those extra inches
on the ends
for mounting the block
to the machine.
the craftsman takes the copy
off the pantograph
and uses the sanding belt
to remove any excess wood.
he repeats the process
to make a second copy.
the craftsman measures and marks
where he'll drill a hole
on each piece of wood.
for this style, he drills a hole
right through the wood.
next, he measures the front
of the customer's shoe
and measures the length
of each shoe tree.
he does this to ensure that
he has the correct dimensions.
if the shoe tree is longer,
he marks how much wood
he needs to remove.
then he uses a template
to create the top opening
and traces the design
on to the wood.
with the band saw, the craftsman
cuts along the marked line.
the top opening is now complete.
he drills holes in the bottom of
each shoe tree to hollow it out.
♪
the drill bit is replaced
with a different tool,
to carve out the remaining wood
in the cavity.
♪
with another tool, he smoothes
the the surface of the bottom
and top openings.
♪
with a band saw,
he slices the shoe tree in half
to create a hinged style.
♪
on each piece, he makes
markings for the hinge,
which will connect the two parts
and cuts out a notch.
after drilling holes
for the hinge screws,
he files the notch smooth
and attaches
the polished brass hinge.
♪
to ensure there
are no rough edges,
the craftsman sands
the shoe tree.
depending on the style,
the craftsman may apply
a stained wood finish
or a coating of liquid wax.
finally, the shoes are ready
to be shipped back
to the customer with the custom
shoe trees rooted firmly inside.
♪
narrator: clay targets
are made to be destroyed
the very first time
they're used.
manufactured in multiple colors,
these inverted saucers are used
as practice targets
and can be launched by hand
or through automated machines.
also referred to
as clay pigeons,
these targets are not
actually made of clay.
they're made with pitch,
a ceramic-type material,
or resin.
since the 1920s,
this french company has been
producing clay saucers for
both target practice
and competitions,
including the olympics.
the founder invented
the first automated
target molding machine in 1947.
pitch targets are made
from petroleum pitch,
a substance derived
from crude oil,
and calcium carbonate,
commonly known as talc.
talc is the filler
while petroleum pitch
is the binding agent,
which solidifies into
a hard, brittle material.
the talc arrives
at the factory
heated at 176 degrees
fahrenheit.
a technician transfers the talc
from the truck
to a heated storage silo.
a screw conveyor moves the talc
from the silo
to the blender tank,
mixing it with the pitch.
the petroleum pitch
arrives to the factory
heated to 392 degrees.
the pitch is transferred
to a heated storage silo
and pumped into a blender.
every 10 seconds,
22 pounds of petroleum pitch
and 64 pounds of talc
are released into the blender.
the materials cool as soon
as they leave the heated silos.
a gas boiler reheats the
ingredients in 509-degree oil.
the hot oil circulates in pipes
around the blender,
heating the pitch talc mixture
to about 390 degrees.
this process changes
the consistency to a paste.
the paste flows from the blender
to the automatic
molding machine.
this valve cuts the flow
at regular intervals
to time the injections
into the target-shaped molds.
the machine compresses the paste
while cooling it with water
so that it solidifies.
a transfer distance moves
the targets on to
a conveyer belt one at a time.
as they move to the next
conveyer belt,
the molds are flipped
right-side up.
even though the molds
are still hot,
they've remained soft
and pliable.
as the targets continue
to cool and harden,
a separating device lines
them up for the conveyer belts
that go to the paint chambers.
the paint is made primarily
of carbonate
and biodegradable
powdered pigment.
a technician pours a
pre-measured amount of water...
...and a bag of pigment
into a mixer.
the mixer combines
the ingredients together.
once the water and pigment
have blended together,
a pre-measured amount of
carbonate is added to the mixer,
along with a binding
and thickening agent.
after additional blending,
the paint is ready.
the targets move from the
conveyer belt
onto spinning holders,
which carry the targets
through the paint chamber.
inside, a sprayer coats
the spinning targets with paint.
the targets exit the chamber
wet and cooled.
another separator divides
the targets on to
two conveyer belts,
which carry them through
a hot-air tunnel for 30 seconds
to dry the paint.
the conveyer belt feeds
the targets to a machine,
which piles them in stacks.
clay pigeons can be
manufactured in several sizes.
olympic regulation size
is the largest,
containing a width
of four inches.
a smaller target is used
for training purposes
and contains a width
under four inches.
regardless of their size,
all targets are engineered
to remain stable in flight
while following
the intended trajectory.
and, finally, shatter when shot.
♪
narrator: the average cow weighs
up to 2,000 pounds.
during medical procedures,
due to its size,
a device called
the squeeze chute
is used to hold a cow steady.
the walls of this stall
immobilize the animal,
allowing a veterinarian access
to administer treatment.
a squeeze chute holds an animal
still for medical
and other procedures
so that no one gets hurt.
the key to the design
is a front gate
that closes
around the animal's head
and a cage-like structure
with a squeeze wall
that contains the rest
of the body.
production starts with
a big coil of steel.
as it unwinds, rollers
straighten the steel
and the blade
cuts it into sheets.
the sheets move
to a laser-cutting station.
the laser cuts out the same
part multiple times,
producing many parts
from one sheet.
the part that's produced
is a component of
the side exit gate.
the steel is formed into tubing.
an operator loads the tubing
into a bending machine.
the machine wraps the tubing
around dies,
shaping it into
one of the chute's access hoops.
the machine cuts the ends
of the hoop and ejects it.
an automated system
transfers the hoops to a rack.
a technician arranges the hoops
on the upper half of one
of the chute's side frames.
the jig serves as a template
for the placement of the hoops.
the bottom of the hoops are
welded to hinges on the frame.
these clips are for opening
or locking the hoops.
he welds one to the top
of each access hoop.
the operator can reach
through the hoops
to gain access to the animal.
the hoops can also be opened
if needed.
another technician
assembles a panel
to the bottom
of the second side frame.
he welds clips to the top
so the panel can be opened
for access
to the lower part of the animal.
he hinges the panel
to the base of the frame.
next, an operator uses a machine
to bend steel tubing
against a circular form.
after the first bend,
the operator repositions
the tubing so the machine
can make the second bend
in the specified location.
the tailgate frame
has taken shape.
with the frame and a jig,
a technician installs
vertical bars
and diagonal linkages
and welds a metal shield
to the lower half.
this part keeps the cow's hooves
safely inside.
meanwhile, holes
have been drilled
in both ends of the chute floor.
they'll be used to move
one wall inward
to tightly contain the animal.
then the chute's skeleton
is constructed.
using a hoist,
a technician transfers
the tailgate to the structure.
the technician guides the top
on to the squeeze chute
framework
and welds
the structure together.
next, he attaches the squeeze
wall to the structure.
he opens the tailgate to test
the clearance and assembles
a steel panel to the lower
half of the squeeze wall.
he mounts the other side panel
with the exit gate
to the structure.
he places hinges into
the tailgate frame and welds
the panel
to the frame at the top.
to verify the side gate
is operating smoothly,
the technician pulls the lever.
then he opens the tail gate
to check its clearance.
he moves the squeeze side
to various settings,
making adjustments if needed
to ensure that the squeeze wall
is properly aligned
at each notch.
next, the entire structure
is dipped in a paint vat,
providing the structure
with even coverage.
the head gate has been
especially contoured
to hold the animal's
head in position.
then a worker slides
rubber grippers
on to the operating handles.
this squeeze chute is now ready
to assist veterinarians
and ranchers with a safe way
to lock an animal into position.
♪
narrator:
until nearly 30 years ago,
boat propellers were normally
made of steel or aluminum.
today, developers have since
tested the waters
with composite propellers.
made from nylon resin
and fiberglass,
composite propellers are
light weight and don't corrode.
and, in certain models, broken
blades can even be replaced.
composite propellers
provide boaters
with another way
to move on the water.
these props are the latest way
to convert rotational motion
into thrust.
production starts with
a computer design.
this one is for
a houseboat propeller.
the design will drive
the machinery
that manufactures the molds.
pellets that are
half fiberglass, half resin
are placed in a dryer
to remove moisture.
an operator takes a sample
of the dried pellets.
first, he weighs the pellets.
then he heats them to evaporate
any additional moisture.
the change in weight indicates
how much moisture
has been removed.
these two-part metal molds
form the pellets
into propeller blades.
this process takes just a minute
and a half to complete.
a technician starts a molding
machine that melts the pellets.
a large feed screw forces the
molten material into the mold.
the composite material
solidifies,
and the operator removes the
newly formed propeller blade.
the process leaves a piece
of unwanted material
known as the sprue.
the sprue is composite material
that hardened as it flowed
into the mold.
once cut, it falls into a bin
to be recycled into
the next composite propeller.
the trim propeller is now
a functional part.
next, composite material is
molded around an aluminum core
to create the hub.
a band saw cuts an extruded bar
of aluminum to size.
each piece will serve
as one core.
using a tool with
a sharp-curved blade,
the technician trims the rough
bits left behind by the saw.
these rough bits are known
as burrs,
so this process
is known as deburring.
once the edges are smooth,
the technician attaches clips
to the three wings.
these clips will be used to
center the core in the mold.
the technician slides the core
into the mold.
the clips hold it
in a precise position.
then the machine is activated.
the machine allows molten
fiberglass and resin material
to flow into the mold cavity and
encapsulate the aluminum core.
it also forms channels
for the insertion
of the propeller blades.
a computerized milling machine
moves the hub into position
for trimming.
a drill cuts into the center
to widen the hole.
♪
the next operation
called broaching
will carve teeth into the hole,
which will help connect
the hub to the motor shaft.
a machine pulls a spiraling tool
called a broach
through the center hole
of the hub.
the tool carves through
the composite layer
and into the aluminum core
to cut the teeth.
here's a close-up look
at those teeth.
now it's time for all the parts
to come together.
an assembler slides the blades
into grooves in the hub.
the grooves help hold
the blades in place.
using a hammer, the assembler
makes sure the blades
are connected accordingly.
finally, a part called
a rear cap is attached.
for an inside look,
the propeller has been cut open.
the cut-out reveals how
the composite material
has become one
with the aluminum core.
and now a test.
the technician attaches
a chain to a blade.
using a hydraulic ram,
he applies pressure.
he measures the breaking point.
at 1 1/2 tons of force,
it's significant.
♪
this composite boat propeller
has taken about
20 minutes to produce.
once attached
to the motor shaft,
it should last for years.
now this boat is ready
to provide boaters
with a ton of fun
while out on the water.