♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
today on "how it's made"...
♪
the distinctive sound
of the tin whistle
is characteristic of
the traditional music of
england, ireland, and scotland.
when this flute
was first manufactured
in the mid-19th century,
it sold for just a penny,
making it affordable
and earning its nickname
"the penny whistle."
this u.k. company was the first
factory to make tin whistles.
in 1843, the company produced
whistles using tinplate --
that's tin-coated steel --
from british metal foundries.
a press strikes each sheet
with a dye 20 times,
stamping out 20 flat shapes
called blanks.
each blank contains six
finger holes toward the bottom
and a rectangular opening
called a fipple near the top.
a technician inserts
one blank at a time
into a custom-made mandrel,
then turns the crank.
the mandrel rolls the flat blank
into a tube.
while some tin whistles
are straight,
this company's tin whistles
are tapered.
the signature shape
creates a distinctive sound.
next, a technician slides
four tubes into tapered slots
on a custom-built jig.
the slots align the tube's
edges, creating a seam
that will prevent air blown into
the instrument from leaking out.
the seam is coated
in a chemical called flux.
without it, solder wire
won't adhere to the tinplate.
using a custom-designed
soldering gun,
the technician melts lead-free
solder wire onto the edges,
fusing them together.
♪
the flux and solder
are both nontoxic
since they're being used
on an instrument
that goes into the mouth.
a worker washes the tin whistles
in mild soap and water
to remove any excess flux.
♪
another technician uses
a custom-made file
to scrape off any excess solder
and ensure the seam is smooth.
then he shapes the top end
of the tin whistle
with this custom-made
squaring tool.
the round top of the instrument
is now square.
♪
the tin whistles are sent
to the factory's paint shop.
an operator hooks the whistles
onto a track
that moves through
a paint chamber.
inside, automated nozzles spray
the instruments
with powder paint.
then the tin whistles
head to an oven,
which bakes the paint
for 20 minutes,
at a temperature
of 255 degrees fahrenheit.
as each instrument exits
the oven,
the operator inspects
the paint job.
a pad printer spreads gold ink
into the engraved company logo
and design.
the pad picks up the ink,
and stamps the logo and design
on the instrument.
to create the narrow air channel
that produces sound,
a wooden plug is created
and placed above the mouthpiece,
or fipple.
the plug is made from cedar
or beechwood.
this type of wood
contains closed grains
that prevent swelling.
after pieces of wood
are cut to the required shape,
a tin whistle tuner
applies a water-based,
nontoxic adhesive inside
the top of the instrument.
then he takes a plug,
sands the cut edge,
and glues it into the top.
♪
once he's completed sanding,
the whistle specialist
tunes the tin whistle
by inserting a sizing tool
in the gap
between the tinplate
and the plug.
he gently hammers the tinplate
against the plug and tool.
this step adjusts the air
channel to the required width,
perfectly tuning the instrument.
after tuning
50 or so tin whistles,
he performs a musical
spot-check.
♪
once the adhesive has cured
for 24 hours,
the tin whistle is ready
for packaging.
after the instrument
has been cleaned,
a technician includes
a fingering chart
and a sheet of tunes
in the package
so that beginners can
teach themselves how to play.
♪
the tin whistle comes
in the key of c and d.
the musical landscapes of jigs,
reels, highland flings,
and other traditional melodies
of the british isles.
♪
narrator: animal horns are made
from meat-industry by-products.
they can be shaped
and cut easily,
while remaining
incredibly durable.
in the 20th century, synthetic
plastics largely replaced horn,
but today,
it's making a comeback
as an all-natural
biodegradable material.
in 1749, this manufacturer
made inexpensive utensils
for people on a tight budget.
two and a half centuries later,
horn products
are desirable luxury items.
this facility sources its horns
from nigeria
where ankole cattle are known
for their long,
magnificent horns.
a craftsman cuts the horns
on a band saw.
horn is formed from keratin,
the same material
in hair and nails.
even though it's hard,
woodworking tools
can easily cut and shape
the horn.
the horn is also biodegradable.
the craftsman uses a sanding
disk to shape the edges.
this particular horn will become
a drinking mug.
horn is thermoplastic.
it can be shaped when heated
and will retain its new shape
when cooled.
an artisan heats a thin section
and bends the tip.
he heats the base of the thin
section over an open flame
and then carefully folds it over
to form a perfect handle
for the mug.
♪
the craftsman puts the mug
into a vice
to ensures that the handle
will retain its new shape
once cooled.
in just a few steps,
this cattle horn
has been transformed
into a unique mug-shaped object.
now the mug needs a bottom.
a technician glues a set of mugs
to wooden planks
and then pours in a food-safe
resin to form a watertight seal.
♪
it takes 24 hours
for the resin to cure.
once cured, a craftsman uses
a band saw to separate the mugs.
then he trims the wood
until there's only a small
amount left around the edges.
♪
the sanding disk easily removes
the excess
until the wood
is even with the horn.
♪
a specialized wheel
with sandpaper edges
smoothes hard-to-reach areas
of the mug.
a craftsman sands
and polishes each mug thoroughly
until they shine.
for constructing
other types of products,
this facility uses
a deep fryer
to heat sections of horn
in 392-degree cooking oil.
a hydraulic press flattens
the heated material
by applying pressure,
then it's set aside to cool.
after 10 minutes, the horn
will retain its new shape,
which is called a plate.
flat horn plate is used
to make a variety of products.
here, a cutting form stamps
out spoons.
artisans use a sanding disk
to refine the spoon's shape.
another press hollows out
the end of the spoon.
horn is a naturally
non-stick material
that won't absorb odor
or color from food.
beside their many
other products,
this facility also
manufactures shoehorns.
shoehorns get their name
from the horn material
used to make them.
a sanding disk is used
to shape the horn.
it takes artisans years
to develop
this particular set of skills.
the horn, which has been
straightened
in a specialized press
is now ready
for the final phase.
a craftsman refines
the shape of the horn
by using a specialized tool,
equipped with a narrow belt
of sandpaper
he smoothes the inner curve
of the shoehorn
by pressing on
the sandpaper belt.
this operation requires a high
degree of concentration
and skill.
too much pressure will remove
more of the horn material
than necessary.
polishing wheels give
the shoehorn its final sheen.
once polishing is complete,
the horn's color is revealed.
the colors of a horn
are near the surface,
so the sander must be careful
not to remove too much material.
skilled craftsmanship
has transformed a raw horn
into a shoe horn
in just a few steps.
a laser engraving machine
brands the shoehorn
with the manufacturer's mark.
horns may be
an ancient material,
but they still make relevant
instruments for modern life.
♪
narrator: many professional
race-car drivers got their start
in a formula f car,
an entry-level racing car
developed in britain
in the 1960s.
initially called "formula ford,"
the name was changed
to formula f
when a motor
other than a ford was permitted.
♪
a formula f racecar is driven by
both aspiring professionals
and amateurs.
this car can give drivers
a start in the sport
and hopefully a strong finish.
productions starts
with a steel tube skeleton
known as a space frame.
the frame is designed
to be lightweight yet rigid.
the technician measures
a piece of steel to be trimmed.
using a band saw, he cuts the
steel to its specified length.
this piece will be used
for the roll hoop,
which protects the driver's head
in the event the car rolls.
he measures the tubing
one last time.
when satisfied
with its placement,
he lowers the saw
and cuts off any excess steel.
he clamps the tubing
in a hydraulic bending device.
♪
once activated, the device wraps
the tubing around a dye
forming it
to the desired curvature.
next, he builds
the car's front bulkhead.
he arranges steel tubing in
the desired configuration
and clamps them to the work
bench to hold them steady.
using angle-measuring tools,
the craftsman verifies
that the corners
of the bulkhead structure
measure 90 degrees.
this confirms that the bulkhead
is perfectly square.
next, the bulkhead structure
is welded at the joints.
the space-frame tubing is made
up of varying thicknesses.
this ensures the bulkhead steel
is strong and protected
in the event
there's a frontal collision.
he compares the newly fabricated
bulkhead to the standard.
once the frame is complete,
the builder applies epoxy
to the base in preparation
for floor installation.
since the steel floor
is substantial
in thickness and weight,
it takes two technicians
to lift it onto the epoxied
section of the space frame.
in addition to the epoxy,
a craftsman uses rivets
to fasten the floor
to the frame.
the floor will be
the only barrier
between the driver
and the track.
with the space frame
and floor secured,
the racecar is ready for
mechanical-component assembly.
after installing adapter plates
to the engine,
the engine is hoisted into
the back of the space frame.
then the adapter plates
are bolted to the frame,
securing the engine in place.
the technician uses a hoist
to carry the transmission system
to the motor.
once in position, he connects
the input shaft to the engine.
♪
he straps a fire extinguisher
to the cockpit floor
using metal bands.
then he runs wires from
the instrument panel
to the extinguisher
for easy activation.
he screws the panel to the cowl.
moving to the front,
the technician bolts
the foot pedals to the floor.
♪
next, he works on the
rack-and-pinion steering system.
this assembly will convert
the rotational motion
of the steering wheel
to the lateral motion
of the rack.
tie rods link the tires
to the system.
the technician tests
the movement of the rack
to confirm
that it's operating smoothly.
at another station,
computerized tools drill holes
in a solid piece of aluminum.
this step transforms
the aluminum
into a part called
the bell crank.
the bell crank
will provide a link
between the car's suspension
rods and the shock absorbers.
it takes about 10 minutes
for these computerized tools
to turn a piece of aluminum
into a precision-crafted
bell crank.
♪
the technician installs the
bell crank onto the car frame.
♪
with that, they've turned
a production corner,
and it's full speed ahead to
the next phase, coming up.
♪
narrator:
a formula f car is designed
to make semi-professional
racing accessible to amateurs.
this vehicle's steel space frame
is inexpensive to produce
and easier to repair
in comparison to frames
made of carbon fiber.
with the steel frame complete
and the engine
and transmission installed,
the technician bolts shock
absorbers to the chassis,
one for each wheel's
suspension system.
a technician connects the shock
absorbers to the bell crank,
linking it to the rest
of the suspension system.
he bolts suspension arms
to mounts on the frame.
a push rod links the arms
to the bell crank.
♪
he bolts the wheel hub assembly
to the suspension arms.
♪
he assembles a brake rotor
to the hub.
♪
then he installs
the drive shaft assembly.
this assembly connects
the transmission
to the wheel hub.
that completes the push-rod
suspension system for one wheel.
♪
this sheet of aluminum
will be used
for the back of
the fuel-cell compartment.
he measures and marks the sheet
accordingly.
he clamps the sheet in a press
brake along the measured line
and activates the press brake.
the bend forms a flap
that will be used to attach
the sheet to the car frame.
he measures and marks spots
for mounting holes
so they'll be evenly spaced
when drilled.
♪
the panel is placed in the space
frame behind the cockpit
with the flap resting
on lateral tubing.
the fuel cell is made of
a flexible rubber-like material
that's unlikely to rupture
if in an accident.
he assembles the sides
and front panels to the back,
creating a compartment
that encloses the fuel cell.
next, the technician wires
the racecar's electrical systems
together.
he crimps connectors
to the ends of the wires
and plugs them into
their corresponding
electrical components.
he routes wiring through the car
and plugs in the alternator.
he installs fiberglass
support parts to the radiators,
attaching one to each side
of the car.
♪
he runs hoses from
the radiators to the engine.
♪
with the radiators now
on the supports,
the packing material
is removed.
♪
a cone-shaped air filter located
on the engine's throttle body
will keep dirt
out of the engine.
after installing
front shock absorbers,
he assembles the steering column
and shaft to the car.
♪
he slides the steering wheel
onto the column.
he tucks a special safety seat
into the cockpit.
the seat has been custom-made
for the driver.
the harness has six straps
for upper-body protection.
♪
then he connects an exhaust pipe
to the engine
and hangs it to the car
with metal bands.
♪
after the fiberglass body parts
are molded,
he maps out holes
for components.
♪
he cuts out the holes
with a rotary sanding tool.
♪
the cockpit's side panels
are fitted to the space frame
and screwed into place.
♪
the nose of the car
is made of carbon fiber.
the strength
of the carbon fiber
provides additional
crash protection.
♪
the body panels are attached
with fasteners
that can be quickly
during a race.
♪
with the front suspension
installed,
this racecar
is ready for wheels.
the technician
torques the locknut
that holds the wheel in place
and slides a pin onto the axle.
♪
it takes about
two to three months
to build
this formula f racecar.
♪
now that it's left the shop,
things are sure to accelerate.
♪