narrator:
a rally car is a compact vehicle
that's had a radical makeover.
it's been stripped to the steel
core and completely rebuilt.
international rally regulations
govern the process.
in the end,
that efficient little vehicle
becomes
a lean, mean racing machine.
fresh out of the factory,
this compact car
is about to be ripped apart
and put back together again.
the rebuild
will pump up the power
and transform a quiet road car
into a vehicle that roars
on the rally racing circuit.
bold graphics will also make
this compact car look fierce.
as they dismantle the car,
they get rid of some superfluous
brackets and panels
to shed weight.
they blast off the paint.
then they weld
a tubular steel roll cage to it
to protect the driver
and co-driver
in a rollover or crash.
the roll cage
also stiffens the chassis
for better handling
on hard turns.
they widen the back end slightly
to accommodate an upgrade
to a 4-wheel transmission
and a larger fuel tank.
then they paint primer
onto the modified body shell.
they're now ready
for the rear transmission.
this will convert this
compact car to 4-wheel drive.
the technician bolts
the transmission
to the rear floor panel.
upgrading from 2-wheel drive
to 4-wheel drive adds traction
and allows the car to handle
more precisely.
now the seats.
they're individual survival
cells made of carbon fiber,
a virtually indestructible
material.
it's also extremely light,
and this helps offset
the extra weight
added by the rear transmission
and roll cage.
the new dashboard fascia is made
of lightweight fiberglass
and covered
with a velvety fabric
to block
the reflection of light.
with the dashboard in place,
the car gets the steering column
and wheel.
the car is now ready
for the fiberglass bumper.
it's been redesigned slightly
to accommodate new fenders
that are flared
for bigger tires.
the technician
then equips the rally car
with heavy-duty dampers
to absorb the shock
of high-speed bumps
on the rally course.
he slides the stiff spherical
bearings into the car shell
and secures them.
he links the dampers
and the driveshaft
to the hub carrier
and bolts them into place.
he inserts brake pads into
lightweight aluminum calipers
and mounts them to the rotors.
this braking system is extra
large for serious friction,
allowing the rally car to be
slowed efficiently when needed.
using a crane, they now lift
the engine into the chassis.
this is the original
1.6-liter engine,
but seriously ramped up
to boost performance.
they've upgraded
the pistons and camshafts,
among other things,
and added a turbocharger.
this takes
the compact-car engine
from 90 horsepower to 300.
instead of a metal fuel tank,
they install a rubber one.
it's pliable and expands,
so it's unlikely to split
or crack in a crash.
the rubber fuel cell fits
perfectly under the trunk floor.
strapped to that floor
is this little tool kit.
they've lightened these tools
by drilling holes
into the handles.
as the race heats up, so will
the engine and its fluids.
they custom-designed
this u-shaped radiator
to keep
the power-steering oil cool.
they tie it to the front of
the supersized engine radiator.
without this substantial
radiator system,
overheating could kill
the engine,
and that would be the end
of the rally for this car.
the mechanics of the rally car
have now been
completely rebuilt.
they now install windows.
they use double-sided tape
to bind the rear side windows
to the car.
taping the windows means
they can be easily kicked out
in the event of an accident.
the windows are made
of shatterproof plastic.
so there shouldn't be
any cuts or scrapes
when busting them out.
instead of painting the car,
they glue on graphics
from bumper to bumper.
the graphics are made
of plastic film
that is much lighter than paint.
the crew saves about 11 pounds
by not painting the rally car.
saving weight and redistributing
it for better handling,
while adhering
to tight weight regulations,
is just part of the challenge.
and a good finish
in the rebuild shop
could lead to a strong finish
in the rally.
narrator: british pork pie
is made of chopped pork
and pork jelly
nestled inside a crust pastry.
mass-produced versions contain
cured pork in a soft pastry.
premium pies are handmade
with fresh, uncured pork
inside a pastry that's hard
and crisp on the outside,
soft on the inside.
among the best-known
premium varieties of pork pies
is melton mowbray,
named after an english town
which has produced this british
snack since the 19th century.
only manufacturers situated
within a defined radius
of the town
can legally call their product
melton mowbray pork pie.
and they have to follow
the traditional recipe,
which begins with blending
hard bread flour.
then workers put lard
into a pot of cold water...
...sprinkle with sea salt,
then bring the water to a fast
boil, dissolving the lard.
then they add this hot mixture
to the flour.
they blend for a few minutes
until the ingredients form
a medium-soft golden dough.
unlike dough made
with cold water,
which bakes soft throughout,
hot-water dough bakes
hard on the surface,
but soft within.
they roll the dough into balls
of approximately
half a pound each...
...then roll half the balls flat
into a layer
roughly 2/10 of an inch thick.
with a round pastry cutter,
they slice circles.
each one will be a pie top,
called a lid.
the other dough balls
will later become
the base of the pie,
called the case.
the pie filling is made
from fresh pork shoulder,
white pepper, and sea salt.
they prepare the filling
in small batches
in order to better control
the distribution of ingredients.
after cutting the pork
into small chunks,
they sprinkle
with salt and pepper...
mix by hand...
...then form balls the same size
as the pastry balls.
in the assembly area,
workers lay a plastic sheet
over the hoop of a pie press
to prevent the dough
from sticking.
they put a pastry ball
in the hoop
and cover it
with another sheet...
...then plunge a round metal die
into the hoop to form the case.
now they drop
a pork ball inside,
pushing it down to force out
some of the trapped air.
they brush water onto the edge
of the case to make it sticky.
then they apply the lid, lightly
thumb-pressing all around
to adhere it
to the sticky edge of the case.
then with
a different hand press,
they score the perimeter
of the pie...
and gently run a wooden block
across the top.
this removes the excess dough
without unsealing
or ripping the pie.
a ventilation hole in the middle
lets just enough steam escape
to prevent pressure
from building up
and bursting the lid.
the steam that remains
helps tenderize the pork.
a pie decorator
crimps the edge inward.
then the pies go
onto a baking sheet
and into the oven for an hour
at just under
400 degrees fahrenheit.
earlier, workers prepared
the pork jelly
by boiling pigs' feet
in a large pot of water...
then simmering for nine hours
to release the natural gelatin
from the bones.
now they strain
the pot's contents
to isolate this natural jelly.
they've timed this perfectly
so that the jelly is still warm
when the pies
come out of the oven.
when they do, their pastry crust
is a golden color.
the pork, as meat tends to do,
has shrunk during cooking,
creating empty spaces
inside the pastry.
it's into those voids
that workers now inject
the warm pork jelly
until it starts bubbling out
the hole at the top.
this indicates the jelly
has filled
all the nooks and crannies.
the pies go immediately
into a fridge
set at 43 degrees fahrenheit.
they remain inside for about
90 minutes until the jelly sets.
from now on, the pork
will remain moist
thanks to this congealed jelly
surrounding it.
each pie is wrapped
in a see-through package
bearing a "best before" date.
kept refrigerated, a pork pie
stays fresh for about a week.
you take it out of the fridge
and let it warm to room
temperature before digging in.
no self-respecting brit
ever warms up pork pie.
narrator: a floating fountain
adds visual interest
to a pond or pool.
it continuously shoots water
several yards high,
producing ribbons
of cascading water.
a submersible pump
generates the effect.
and all you have to do is just
sit back and enjoy the show.
a floating fountain
is a pleasant sight,
but it's also practical.
the constant pumping action
aerates the water,
preventing stagnation
that breeds mosquitoes
and causes algae growth.
production begins
with the floatation ring,
which they cast
a section at a time.
a worker pours a measured amount
of plastic powder
into the bottom half
of a clamshell mold.
the mold is attached to an arm
that swings it into an oven
and rotates it on two axes.
the mold heats up.
the powder melts
and adheres to the walls of
the mold, forming a hollow part.
the mold now moves
into a cooling zone,
where it first rotates
in front of a fan,
then under a cool spray
of water.
the constant turning minimizes
sagging or buckling
in the plastic
as the hollow part cools
and solidifies inside.
the mold opens,
revealing a quarter section
of the flotation ring.
stainless-steel inserts
for attaching it to the
other sections
have been embedded
into the plastic.
they now mechanically push
the hollow part underwater.
this is a test.
they pump air into it
and check for bubbles
that would indicate a hole.
the fountain ring
must be leakproof
because water will eventually be
added to it to level it.
a worker now bolts
the four quarters together
using brackets
and the steel inserts molded
into the plastic earlier.
next, they focus
on the framework
for the submersible pump.
a mechanical saw cuts the
stainless steel parts to size,
and a welder pieces them
together.
another worker now attaches
the completed framework
to the brackets
protruding from the bottom
of the floatation ring.
using a press, they bend steel
to create brackets
to hold the fountain's lights.
they bolt the light brackets
to the pump frame
in a position to illuminate
the upward spray of water.
they slide
the long, tubular casing
for the pump and its motor
through brackets on the bottom
of the frame.
this is the pump.
it's open to display
the inner workings.
those steel disks
are the impellers
that will force water upward.
the next employee
applies pvc glue
to attach a flange
to the pump assembly.
the flange will be used
to connect the pump
to the fountain's plumbing.
he now inserts the pump and
motor assembly into the casing.
the motor has been hermetically
sealed to keep water out.
using a special gripper,
he pulls the assembly
all the way through the tube
to complete the installation.
he spreads more glue
onto the flange
and attaches a pvc elbow
that links it to the rest
of the plumbing.
the entire assembly
is painted black
so the fountain workings will
seem to disappear underwater
when viewed from the surface.
with the assembly
now flipped right side up,
they install the lights.
then a worker screws a circle
of eight brass nozzles
onto a pvc base.
these nozzles will split
the flow of pumped lake water
into a eight sprays
and configure them in a circle.
he tightens each nozzle
to ensure the connection
will withstand the powerful
and perpetual pumping action.
he places the nozzle assembly
on the plumbing
protruding
from the fountain raft
and twists
the threaded ends together.
the connection must be
extremely tight.
another worker then rolls
a sheet of perforated steel
to build a tubular screen
to filter the water
as it flows into the pump.
the screen fits perfectly
onto the intake end of the pump
and motor tube.
with the floating fountain
now complete,
it's ready to be wired
to the control panel.
this panel
will be positioned lakeside
for onsite activation
and programming of the timer.
the floating fountain is
now ready for launching.
this particular one is
a larger version
of the one we saw being built,
but big or small, it's all about
going with the flow.
narrator: artificial stone
is a cast material
that looks just like
sculpted natural stone.
since the early 18th century,
manufacturers have cast stone
in molds,
producing beautiful garden
and landscape ornaments,
as well
as architectural components
designed to enhance buildings.
classical-style statues
and other garden ornaments
came into fashion in england
in the 1700s.
it was trendy
for the upper classes
to tour italy and admire ancient
roman art and architecture.
not every noble
was wealthy enough
to haul home a solid stone
antiquity by stagecoach,
so english factories
began producing facsimiles
in artificial stone.
the production process today
is much like it was then,
beginning in the studio,
where a sculptor makes
a plaster model of the ornament.
this one's a copy
of an antique bust of pan,
the greek mythological figure.
they use
this intricately detailed model
to make the production mold.
after coating the plaster
with a sealer,
they cover the entire model
with thin strips of clay,
making certain divisions
between strips
to create the production mold's
various sections.
over the clay, they apply
six or so layers
of fiberglass cloth
saturated with resin.
the resin cures,
producing a 3/10-inch-thick
multi-sectioned case
around the clay-covered model.
next they open the case
and remove the clay,
which leaves a gap
around the model.
they close the case
and fill that gap with their
specially developed rubber.
when the rubber cures,
they open the case
and remove the model,
revealing a rubber mold
that bears all the model's
intricate details.
they send this cased mold
off to the production facility
and put the model in storage
until the rubber mold wears out
and it's time to pour a new one.
the artificial stone is a
natural-looking off-white color.
it's made of fine sand,
white cement, and limestone,
plus plasticizers,
waterproofers,
and a few secret ingredients.
the factory adds stone pigments
into the mix
to produce terra cotta
and other colors.
a computer-controlled system
feeds the ingredients
into the mixer
in all the right proportions,
then adds
a small amount of water
to activate the cement
that binds everything together.
on the production floor,
a caster repeatedly shovels
a bit of stone mixture
into the fiberglass-encased
rubber mold,
then, using both hand
and pneumatic tools,
compacts it in the mold.
the quality of the ornament
depends greatly
on the caster's technique.
the trick is
to ram enough stone mixture
into every nook and cranny
of the mold,
but not compact too much
at a time,
as this mold would produce
unattractive layers
in the finished ornament.
they trowel the open side
of the mold by hand
and smooth the surface.
the stone mix takes 24 hours
to reach an initial set.
then, section by section,
they unbolt the case
and peel off the rubber mold.
this may be artificial stone,
but its surface texture closely
resembles carved limestone.
the final step
is a vapor curing.
the ornaments go
into a chamber overnight.
the steam forces moisture
into the pores,
curing the cement inside.
this type of artificial stone
is called dry cast limestone.
other ornaments are made
of wet cast limestone,
a mixture
of similar ingredients,
but in larger particle size
and containing much more water.
because you
can embed stainless-steel
reinforcement bars in it,
wet cast is the better material
for making objects
such as garden benches
or large fountain bowls
that require
structural strength.
wet cast doesn't have
to be vapor-cured
because of its high
water content.
however, unlike dry cast,
which is finished
when it comes out of the mold,
wet cast
does require finishing.
workers have to grind away
excess material
that sometimes seeps
out of the joints in the mold
and hardens.
the wet cast surface
is smooth and sealed,
so it's normally easier
to clean.
dry cast stone, by contrast,
has a textured surface
and weathers
to an antique look.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...