-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: tapioca pudding is a textural fusion
of creaminess and chewy tapioca pearls.
the recipe is at least a century old,
and there are conflicting theories
about when and where it was invented --
britain or the united states.
with its distinctive chewiness,
it brings something entirely different to the table.
today factories whip up tapioca pudding in big batches.
times have changed,
but the appetite for this pearly pudding hasn't waned.
the proof is truly in the pudding.
the tapioca pearls, of course, define this dish.
the opaque, little balls
are processed from a vegetable grown in south america
called cassava root.
the recipe also calls for more traditional baking ingredients
like whole milk, eggs...
sugar...
and vanilla.
they pipe the whole milk into a giant mixing kettle.
this kettle has steam-heated steel walls
to gently cook the ingredients while blending them.
as the milk froths, the cook measures the tapioca pearls.
the pearls arrive at the factory already processed,
formed by grinding the root vegetable into powder
and tumbling it to shape it into properly sized pearls.
as the pearls cook in the milk,
they will soften and swell to double the size,
just like rice.
but unlike rice,
they'll take on an almost jellylike, chewy consistency.
he adds sugar to sweeten the mix.
the cook then leaves the swirling and foaming mix
to cook for over an hour.
meanwhile, at another station,
they add tapioca starch to a different blender full of milk.
this blender is unheated
and has higher speed for mixing
that's fast and furious.
he adds eggs...
and he flavors the mix with salt.
the tapioca starch
acts as a thickening agent for this separate mix,
as the blender whips it to a frothy state.
they transfer the starch blend to the main mixing kettle.
the cook adds a natural food coloring
to make the pudding beige along
with some vanilla flavoring.
the tapioca pearls are just the right consistency.
this pudding is now fully cooked
and ready to move on to the filling line.
they pump it while it's still steaming hot
into single-serve plastic cups.
packaging the pudding while it's still hot
is an act of food preservation,
which, not surprisingly, is called hot fill.
the hot-fill technique locks in nutrients
and ensures freshness,
giving the product a shelf life
of about 70 days.
suctioning arms swiftly transfer
foil lids to cover the cups,
giving the pudding no time to cool down.
with the lids in place,
the filler moves the cups forward
to meet up with heat-sealer heads.
they fuse the foil lids to the plastic cup rims.
it's taken just seconds
to fill these cups with hot tapioca pudding
and seal them, effectively preserving them.
the pudding-filled cups
now funnel into a lane to position them single file.
then they travel between rubber belts that squeeze them.
if they can take the pressure,
it confirms that the cups are tightly sealed.
a printer sprays the expiration date
and other pertinent information
onto the cup.
after weighing to confirm there's enough pudding inside,
an x-ray machine scans the contents
to confirm that there are no contaminants.
then they're on the way to the chilling line.
inside the tubs,
the tapioca pudding is still hot and fluid.
the cups ride a system
of spiraling, refrigerated conveyors
bringing the pudding's temperature down
to about 100-degrees fahrenheit
and thickening it substantially.
the pudding-filled containers now pass through gates
that separate them into two lanes
and then arrange them in groups of three.
machinery places
one group of three onto another,
and then all that's left is the packaging.
mechanical arms
place the paperboard sleeve on the top three cups.
traveling through a narrow lane,
guides fold the paperboard down
around the bottom three cups
as a sprayer applies hot glue to the flaps.
a worker pulls off one pack of six
and sends it over to a panel of testers
for an inspection and taste.
they examine the pudding for color and consistency.
they also taste a little from each production batch
to confirm that it's sweet enough,
that the tapioca beads are the desired texture,
and that it meets all other quality requirements.
if they like what they taste,
the entire batch is declared ready for retail.
three hours in the making, this tapioca pudding
is now ready to add a little sweetness to someone's day.
narrator: a snowplow
is actually the big blade on a snow-clearing vehicle --
not the vehicle itself.
the first snowplows
were wedge-shaped wooden blades
drawn by horses.
as cars replaced horses, these gave way to metal plows
mounted to the front of trucks and other large machines.
a snowplow is a blade made of either stainless steel,
which is rust-proof,
or carbon steel,
which they coat in plastic-based
powder paint to prevent rust.
to begin making the blade,
they take a sheet of metal about 1/10 of an inch thick
and insert it in a press.
the press punches out holes for the bolts,
which attach the blade to the mounting structure.
next, they feed the sheet through a rolling press.
the rollers
apply 35 to 40 tons of pressure,
curving the sheet to the required shape.
workers check
that the front radius and top radius of the curve
meet the technical specifications.
next, using a machine called a press break,
they bend over the top of the sheet.
this bend will sit on the top bar of the mounting structure.
the mounting structure is made of several parts
cut from giant plates of carbon steel.
a computer guides the cutting machine,
which uses electrogenerated flames.
their intense, focused heat
slices through the steel literally by melting it.
the steel is too hot to handle
when the plasma cutting is done,
so workers lift off the parts with magnets.
then they bend key, load-bearing parts
in a press break to increase the structural strength.
they position the parts
for one section of the structure
in an assembly fixture and weld them together.
in a different assembly fixture,
they position the parts
for another section of the structure.
a robot welds those together.
back at the first assembly, they use pins
to attach a spring-loaded component called a trip edge.
it protects the vehicle from damage
by absorbing the shock through the springs,
rather than through the vehicle frame,
should the plow hit an obstacle on the road.
after welding the two sections together,
workers send the structure to the powder-coating area.
there, workers spray it first with powder primer
then with powder paint.
each coat is baked to activate the plastic base,
which produces an ultra-durable
shell over the metal.
once the structure cools,
workers install the springs for the trip edge,
then they attach the base of the structure
called the cutting edge.
it's made of a harder type of steel
because it scrapes the ground.
the structure is now finished and ready to receive the blade.
this one's getting a stainless-steel blade.
the bent top fits over the structure's top bar,
the bottom into a slot below.
workers secure the blade with bolts
then finish off the plow with a decal.
for this model,
they make two plows like this --
mirror images of each other.
they go side-by-side, connected
in the middle by a hinge
to form a v-shaped snowplow.
straight plows have a single blade
attached to a different type of structure.
all the parts, except stainless-steel blades,
are powder-painted and baked.
the v-plow articulates.
the driver can adjust the width
of the "v" to direct the snow.
another model combines a straight blade
with hinged blades for clearing snow in large areas,
such as parking lots.
when it comes to these types of machines,
there's clearly no business like snow business.
narrator: a paddle boat is a small recreational vessel,
perfect for a leisurely ride on a lake.
it gets its name from the rotating paddle wheel
that propels it.
you simply sit in the seat
and turn the paddle wheel by pedaling,
which is why this type of boat
is also called a pedal boat or pedalo.
steered by rudder and gliding on two floaters,
a paddle boat delivers a smooth, relaxing ride.
boat mechanics don't get much simpler than this.
in a typical two-seater, two sets of pedals,
each powering a paddle wheel at the rear.
the factory molds the top and bottom halves
of each floater separately.
first, workers spray the mold with gelcoat,
a type of polyester.
this is the floater's surface finish.
next, they cover the entire mold
with fiberglass cloth
then add a second layer in the front and bottom
where the floater will be a bit thicker.
then they lower a cover onto the mold,
latching it down securely to make the mold airtight.
they draw a vacuum to extract the air trapped inside,
then inject liquid resin.
the resin saturates the fiberglass cloth
and, within an hour, hardens, producing solid fiberglass,
a lightweight material
that's both impact-resistant and waterproof.
after extracting this half,
workers mold the other half of this floater
and the two halves that make up the other one,
then they apply fiberglass glue
to the edges...
...and carefully align and mate
top and bottom.
they position spacers
to put pressure on the base of the groove,
then clamp the perimeter for about 45 minutes
until the glue sets.
when the glue is completely dry,
they trim the perimeter to make
the edge neat and smooth.
to make each propulsion wheel,
workers rivet eight blades to a fiberglass hub.
these strong plastic blades do have some flex in them.
this ensures they won't break,
should the wheel hit a rock or other obstacle.
the part of the boat where you sit and pedal
is called the bicycle.
the two bike bodies, like the floaters,
are made of molded fiberglass,
then jazzed up with decals.
since the bicycle mechanics are routinely exposed to water,
they must be rust-resistant.
therefore, the pedal mechanism is made of chrome-plated steel
and the chains
of steel that's been treated with an anti-corrosion coating.
each bike has two chains --
the first linking the pedals to one side of a central gear,
the second linking the other side of the central gear
to the propulsion wheel.
so, once they're both hooked up,
pedaling moves the first chain,
which rotates the gear,
which moves the second chain, which turns the wheel.
final assembly is relatively simple.
first, workers connect the floaters
with three painted aluminum crossbars.
the paint is baked on to make it extra durable.
then, on one of the crossbars,
they install a pair of aluminum rudders,
the boat's steering mechanism.
they link the rudders with an aluminum bar
so that they move in unison.
a hitch pin locks the bar securely in place,
while this rubber cap prevents paint chipping
when the rudders hit the crossbar.
after mounting the first bicycle,
workers install a console in the center of the boat.
it contains
a waterproof storage compartment
and the handle, which directs the rudders.
it connects to the rudders
with a long bar called a tiller.
next they mount the second bike.
like the first one,
it's designed to snap securely onto the crossbars.
the adjustable fiberglass seats
slide onto aluminum rails.
the seats have fixed cushions and rugged, waterproof fabric.
the boat's retractable canopy
is made of the same fabric on an aluminum structure.
a paddle boat is virtually maintenance-free.
you just have to oil the mechanisms
a couple of times per season,
and from then on, it's smooth sailing.
narrator: every home needs a tough exterior.
fiber cement siding is a concrete option.
made of cement, sand, and wood pulp,
it's engineered to be fireproof,
insectproof, and weatherproof.
embossed with various wood-grain patterns,
it has a natural look that's big on the street.
fiber cement cladding is a century-old product
that was actually reinvented in the 1980s.
asbestos was removed due to health concerns
and replaced with wood pulp.
the pulp provides the fiber that prevents cracking.
production begins with silica sand.
a loader shovels it into an underground conveyor.
the sand particles, which are about the size of beach sand,
are about to be ground down to a fine powder.
the conveyor takes the sand up to a revolving cylinder grinder
called a ball mill --
so named because, inside, steel balls tumble around
to smash the sand particles into much smaller bits.
they pipe in water to keep the dust down
and eliminate the need for an exhaust system.
this also liquefies the sand,
making it easier to pipe it through the plant
during the various stages of processing.
but the sandy liquid needs to be thickened substantially,
so it's into a tank to drain off much of the water.
what's left is about 80% sand.
the next ingredient is wood pulp,
which gives the cement siding bending strength.
without it,
the fiber cement siding would be
brittle and crack easily.
they add water and stir to soften and liquefy the pulp
so it can be easily pumped around the factory
for processing.
at the end of the mixing,
the pulp looks like thick oatmeal.
next, they lower cylindrical sieves into position.
but first they blend together
the liquefied sand, cement, and pulp,
along with some additives, creating a fiber cement slurry.
they pipe the cement slurry into
a trough beneath the sieves.
as the sieves rotate through the slurry,
residual water drains through the mesh walls,
leaving a fiber cement film on the surface.
the film transfers to a felt belt moving overhead.
through the felt,
a vacuum mechanism sucks more moisture from the film
until it forms a solid fiber cement sheet.
rollers squeeze numerous sheets together.
they're still moist enough to stick together,
and they fuse into one thick board.
another roller then presses a woodlike pattern
onto the surface of the cement board.
a spray of high-pressure water
then slices the cement sheet into planks.
a robotic suctioning head gently
picks up the fiber cement planks
and transfers them to a pallet.
the planks are fragile at this point
and need to be handled with care.
loaded into a pallet,
the cement planks are now ready
for some toughening up.
they bake the fiber cement siding inside steel tubes.
they're autoclaves, high-pressure ovens.
inside, pressurized steam
enhances the chemical reaction between the ingredients
to cure the cement clapboard.
they then load the pallets
of cement siding onto a railcar,
and it's on to the next station.
here, machinery does something they call stack breaking.
during curing, the siding planks get stuck together,
so these hydraulic cylinders lift and jostle them
to separate them into individual boards.
they put a siding sample to the test.
with both sides of the board stabilized,
a rod bends it at the center to determine the stress point.
if it can take a lot of pressure,
the whole production line moves forward.
spaced apart now,
the fiber cement planks ride by sprayers
that paint the sides and the ends a nice shade of red.
the siding then enters a curtain of paint
of the exact same color.
the paint adheres to the front of the boards.
these mirrors expose any missed spots.
if there are any, they'll do touch-ups.
the transformation from a pile of sand and other ingredients
to something that looks a lot like wood siding
has taken just three days,
and once installed,
these wood-look cement planks could fool the neighbors.
after all, it's all about putting up a good facade.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...