>> narrator: this edible money
is a symbolic treat.
in some parts of the world,
chocolate coins are stuffed in
christmas stockings to celebrate
the charity of saint nicholas.
they're also handed out to
jewish children during the
festival of hanukkah to teach
them the value of money and
charity.
chocolate coins don't have any
purchasing power, but they do
buy a lot of appreciative smiles
from the kids.
they start with giant chocolate
bars.
each one is 10 pounds of pure
chocolate.
the worker transfers the big
bars to a kettle.
it's a kind of double boiler.
hot water bubbles and steams
inside a sleeve shell to heat
and melt the chocolate.
there are 2 1/2 tons of liquid
chocolate in this kettle.
the machine now pumps the
chocolate through a long pipe
with different cooling zones.
the chocolate thickens but not
to the point of
solidification -- a process
called tempering.
it causes the chocolate to form
a precise crystal structure for
just the right texture and
taste.
the thick liquid chocolate flows
onto a conveyer that brings the
chocolate under a broad blade.
the blade levels it to a
specific thickness and spreads
it evenly, creating a long sheet
of chocolate.
the chocolate now begins to
coagulate and harden.
to spur that process, it travels
through a refrigeration tunnel
that is approximately 15 yards
long.
this journey transforms the
liquid chocolate into a soft
solid.
next, they clean and prepare the
die.
it's a spring-loaded device that
works cookie-cutter style to
punch out round blanks.
there is one big difference.
each cutter is long and tubular,
so as it punches out the
chocolate blanks, they
accumulate inside.
the latticework of leftovers
journeys forward to be re-melted
into the process...
so not a crumb of chocolate goes
to waste.
at the end of the line, dozens
of coin blanks have stacked up
in each magazine.
and piles of leftover chocolate
have accumulated in a bin that
will now be transferred back to
the melting pot.
now it's time to print some
chocolate money.
to do this, they wrap the
chocolate first and then emboss
both the wrap and the chocolate
blanks simultaneously.
here's how it works.
sheets of glossy gold foil
travel between rollers to
establish an even tension.
ahead, a forked arm moves two
chocolate blanks between the
foil sheets.
piston-like knives move in to
wrap, cut, and fold the foil
around the blanks.
the forked arm then delivers the
foil-wrapped blanks to a die
press.
it stamps designs on both sides
of the coins, making an
impression on the foil through
to the chocolate.
the chocolate, although solid,
is still warm enough to receive
the image.
removed from the machine, here's
what the die heads look like.
these are used to emboss
chocolate coins with american
penny markings.
as for the foil discards, they
don't end up on the scrap heap.
instead, they accumulate in a
bin to be sent out for
recycling.
they make 150,000 foil-wrapped
coins a day.
to change the currency type,
they simply switch die heads.
chocolate coins can be made in
many sizes with a range of
different illustrations.
the coins now spill out onto a
conveyor that takes them to a
bin.
all that's left now is the
packaging, which will be the
traditional mesh bag.
from start to finish, it takes
less than an hour to make a
chocolate coin.
gold dollars or $5 poker
chips, every day, it's a
jackpot of chocolate money at
this factory.
so there's never any shortage of
edible cash, only decisions to
be made -- poker chip or
chocolate penny?
you could always flip a coin.
>> narrator: in-floor heating
systems are hardly a new
concept.
the ancient romans heated the
floors of their bathhouses.
today's systems use either
electric cables or hot-water
pipes installed beneath the
floor's surface.
as the floor warms up, the heat
radiates to people and objects
in the room.
for electric radiant heating
systems, installers affix
installation gauges to the
subfloor, then wind electrical
cables around those gauges.
when there are no objects such
as bathtubs to work around,
installers can roll out a
fiberglass mat that has the
cable embedded.
once the cables are in place,
the installers lay down the
floor.
radiant heating systems can be
installed under most types of
flooring.
it's up to 28% more energy
efficient than forced-air or
baseboard heating.
at the core of those electric
heating cables are copper or
copper-alloy wires called
conductors.
an unwinding system feeds each
spool of conductor to an
extrusion machine.
extrusion machines force molten
plastic through a die to form a
particular shape.
they load the raw plastic
pellets into a receptacle called
a hopper at the top of the
machine.
the pellets drop down into a
heating device that quickly
liquefies them.
the machine then forces the
molten plastic through a round
die, forming a plastic jacket
around the conductor passing
through.
this jacket insulates the bare
wire.
a water bath cools the
still-warm plastic to prevent
sticking as they wind up the
conductor on a spool.
the next machine takes two
insulated conductors and twists
them together into a single
strand.
this forms a paired conductor.
then the next machine braids 16
spools of triple-strand copper
wire around the paired
conductor.
this copper braid is the ground.
the ground will capture any
electrical leak should the cable
get damaged, preventing
electrocution.
the cable's internal wiring is
complete.
now they run it through an
alignment jig that straightens
and smooths everything out in
preparation for the next
extrusion process, which coats
the wiring in a final plastic
jacket.
then they wind up the cable on a
spool to prepare it for
packaging...
and put one end into a machine
that cuts off an inch or so of
jacket.
after soldering the two
conductors to each other so that
the electrical current goes out
on one and returns on the other,
they insulate this connection
from the braided ground with
transparent heat-shrink plastic.
then they pull the ground over
the now-insulated end and cover
it with a black heat-shrink
plastic.
this seals the end of the cable
so that water can't seep in and
short out the wiring.
another machine produces the
cable that brings power from the
wall-mounted thermostat to the
heating cables under the floor.
it's called the cold lead
because it leads to the heating
cable, yet itself doesn't heat
up.
this machine cuts the average
production run of 8 1/2 miles of
cold-lead cable into several
cables of standard length,
either 2 or 3 yards long
depending on the product format.
the cold lead is comprised of
two conductors and a separate
ground wire.
workers connect it to the
heating cable by fusing
conductor to conductor and
ground to ground.
they protect this junction with
a hard plastic cover called a
mechanical joint.
this, too, must be sealed to
prevent any water infiltration.
after all, heating cables are
often installed under floors in
wet environments such as
bathrooms.
so, they seal the joint by
injecting enough polyurethane to
fill every nook and cranny.
the polyurethane takes three to
four minutes to dry, then
another 24 hours to fully
harden.
this machine assembles the
other format -- the roll-out mat
with heating cable embedded.
first, it winds cable the same
way an installer would onto
installation gauges.
then it secures it to an
adhesive-backed fiberglass mesh.
three strips of adhesive tape
above and below reinforce the
bond.
the mat format is sold by the
roll, while the loose cable is
packaged in a kit with
installation gauges and glue
sticks to adhere the gauges to
the subfloor.
narrator: it looks like a car
and it drives like a tricycle --
a child-size version of a
motorized three-wheeler vehicle,
popular in the early
20th century.
instead of gas, pedal power
propels this replica forward.
based on actual vehicles, a wave
of nostalgia has put pedal cars
on the road to a comeback.
an old-style pedal car is a
snazzy toy with a sleek metal
body and real rubber tires.
highly collectible, owning one
is a trip down memory lane.
production starts with the pedal
car's wood floor.
the worker places a metal
template of the floor under a
sheet of ash plywood and
transfers the two to a router
table.
with a pin in the template below
to guide him, he moves the
plywood as the router cuts it.
this produces a part that's the
precise size and shape needed
for the pedal-car floor.
using the same system, he cuts a
slot for the pedals and another
one for the rear wheel.
he evens the edges with a hand
router, giving the pedal-car
floor a finer look and feel.
he glues supports for the
backrest close to the rear of
the floorboard.
he props the backrest against
the supports and screws it into
position.
he installs the dashboard
framework further towards the
front.
next, they varnish the laminated
ash dashboard a deep, rich hue,
to replicate the look of the one
in the original three-wheeler
vehicle.
and now for the body of the
pedal car.
a welder tacks together the two
parts of the aluminum shell and
seals them with special
adhesive.
they then screw the wooden
framework to the aluminum body.
after a thorough cleaning, they
paint a primer coat onto the
metal.
then it's in to the paint booth
for a glossy coat of automotive
paint.
in the meantime, the metal
chassis of the pedal car
comes together.
a worker mounts a dummy twin
engine to the front.
in this pedal-powered replica,
the engine's purpose is purely
decorative.
the headlights, though, are
real.
he attaches those to the
chassis, complete with the
hooded framework distinctive to
the original, full-size
three-wheeled car from a century
ago.
he then fits the tires to the
chassis.
they're cycle tires,
child-sized, to fit the scale of
this toy-car replica.
a quick spin confirms they're
operational.
he mounts the fenders to the
frame just above the tires and
secures them with metal
brackets.
the fenders will guard against
splashing mud and water.
he now transfers the car body to
the three-wheeled chassis.
he aligns it with fixing points
on the chassis and then screws
it into place.
next, he hooks up the exhaust
pipe.
like the engine, it's an
imitation, but it looks real.
he fits an aluminum grille
to the front of the pedal car,
just behind the mock engine.
he installs a small windshield
in front of the pedal-car
cockpit.
and now he pops the dashboard,
equipped with a speed dial, into
place.
it fits into the pedal car's
hooped frame perfectly.
he wires the battery-operated
headlights to the dashboard
switch.
he attaches the hand brake to
the side of the cab and runs the
braking cables to the rear
wheel.
he threads the steering-wheel
column down through the
dashboard to steering arms on
the front wheel axle.
he clamps it to the steering
arms...
and makes some adjustments to
precisely position the column to
the shaft.
he fits the padded leather seat
into the cab, and this completes
the construction of this
pedal-powered replica car.
it takes about 40 hours to make
one of those retro toys.
when it comes to the authentic
touches, dave spared no expense
and expended great effort.
it's time for a spin to the
playground and some good
old-fashioned fun.
narrator: some people enjoy
playing combat games on video
systems, while others prefer to
exchange the controller for a
fake weapon, dress up in
costume, and act out the fantasy
with those who share the same
passion.
it's called live-action
role-playing, and there's
typically a medieval or
apocalyptic theme to it.
these weapons sure look like the
real thing -- so much so that
this company also sells them as
film and theater props.
but as menacing as these axes
and swords appear, they couldn't
even hurt a fly because they're
blades are made of latex.
in the weapons workshop, they
begin the sword-making process
by constructing the blade.
after tracing a template on a
4/10-of-an-inch-thick piece of
flexible waterproof foam, they
cut out two blade halves with a
utility knife.
after slitting one of them down
the middle, they glue in a rigid
4/10-of-an-inch fiberglass core.
this makes the sword blade stiff
enough for combat, yet flexible
enough to not break.
next, they glue a strip of
durable polyester fabric over
the core.
this acts as reinforcement,
preventing the tip of the core
from poking through the foam.
now they glue the second blade
half over the first one,
sandwiching the core.
the glue is a rubber-based
adhesive that bonds with
pressure that they apply with a
heavy marble rolling pin.
next, using a band sander, they
sculpt the blade's cutting
edges.
then they remove the foam
residue with a rotary tool.
next, they take a wood-burning
iron and melt the foam in select
spots to create the look of
battle scars.
then they spray on five to six
coats of latex rubber.
this forms a protective shield
over the foam without hindering
the blade's flexibility.
next, using an air brush, they
apply two coats of acrylic-based
latex paint -- first black, then
silver.
they brush on a thick coat of
black paint, then wipe it off.
this wash, as it's called,
creates the look of aged metal.
and finally, they lightly dab
some silver acrylic paint over
select spots to highlight
details.
from foam to main component of a
lethal weapon in just a few easy
steps.
they finish off their handiwork
by stenciling on the company
logo in gold acrylic paint.
now for the sword's handle.
they drill a hole lengthwise
through a cylinder made of
walnut and glue a steel tube
inside.
then they glue leather around
the wood...
and wrap a leather ribbon around
it for decoration.
to give it a worn appearance,
they lightly sand parts of the
surface.
to make ornate handles, an
artist first sculpts a model out
of lindenwood.
using that wooden model, they
cast a silicon mold.
then they pour rubber into the
mold to cast a handle.
for that leather-covered wooden
handle, they cast only the
components above and below it in
rubber.
after trimming off the excess
rubber, they paint it to look
like metal.
to assemble the sword, they glue
the handle components onto the
core, which protrudes from the
base of the blade.
first, they position the guard.
it stops the opposing sword from
sliding down past the blade and
cutting your hand.
next, the handle.
and last, the pommel.
it blocks the end of the handle
to prevent the sword from
sliding out of your hand.
each sword this workshop creates
comes with a scabbard, a
protective leather sheath.
they boil and wax the leather
to make it rigid.
the workshop also makes daggers
and other realistic-looking
weaponry -- all you need to
bring out your inner warrior.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...