--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today, on "how it's made"...
in the music industry,
winning a grammy is the ultimate accolade.
the national academy
of recording arts and sciences
has been awarding grammys for recording since 1958.
every year, the winners
are honored with a golden gramophone trophy.
the grammys are to the music industry
what the oscars are to movies.
the coveted trophy is made of gold-plated grammium.
but don't look for that metal on the periodic table.
it's a proprietary zinc alloy specially formulated
and trademarked by the artisan who makes the grammys.
to make the base of the trophy,
they heat the grammium to 644 degrees
and pour it into a bronze mold.
they immediately pour out the excess molten metal.
what remains quickly solidifies in a thin layer
against the walls of the cavity,
creating a hollow cast.
they also cast the gramophone's cabinet
and tone arm in grammium.
they remove mold seams, excess metal,
and smooth out the surface of each cast component
with a belt sander.
then, they file by hand the areas the belt can't reach.
finally, they polish the metal
with an abrasive compound on a buffing wheel.
they make sure there are no surface imperfections.
now, they work on the gramophone's iconic horn.
using a metal shear,
they cut a disc of malleable bronze.
they mount the disc on a lathe.
as the lathe spins, they use a series of tools
to transform the flat disc into a horn.
then, they spin the horn on a different lathe,
pressing an abrasive cloth against the surface
to remove any tool marks.
before they connect the tone arm to the cabinet,
they brush on some flux,
a chemical that makes the stationary solder flow
into the tiny gap between components.
now, they bolt the tone arm to the cabinet, then solder.
they submerge this part of the trophy
in a degreasing solution for a few minutes,
then in water.
gold doesn't adhere to zinc, so they plate it with copper.
they run a positive electric charge through the trophy
and a negative charge through a piece of copper
also suspended in the plating tank.
this process dissolves the copper,
then draws the particles through the water
and onto the trophy.
they repeat the electroplating process in a different tank,
this time with nickel.
nickel creates a sufficiently hard base
to support the gold plating.
it also makes gold appear brighter.
after another rinse, it's back into a tank
for the final plating with 24-karat gold.
to prepare the trophy's base for painting,
they smooth the surface with a belt sander,
then fine-sand by hand.
they spray on an epoxy primer,
let it dry for a day then wet sand it with fine sandpaper.
they repeat these steps with a black primer,
then paint the base with high-gloss,
chip-resistant black paint.
once it dries, they can finish assembling the trophy.
they bolt the polished gold-plated cabinet and tone arm
to the painted base.
then, they take the horn,
which has been gold-plated and polished,
and screw it into the tone arm.
after 15 hours of craftsmanship,
this grammy is ready to be awarded.
but this trophy won't be handed out during the award show.
the grammys handed out on stage
are actually props
that are used year after year.
the winners receive a personalized trophy
a few weeks after the show.
the base has a brass plate
engraved with their name and musical category.
narrator: the first bicycle lights
were modified kerosene lamps fixed to the handlebars.
the concept was truly trailblazing
and made it possible to cycle at night.
a century later, the technology has changed,
but the concept remains the same.
bicycle lights are still showing us the way.
these bicycle lights
are battery-powered with energy-efficient l.e.d. lights.
mounted to handlebars or a helmet,
they make it possible
for a cyclist to see and be seen at night.
a bicycle light starts with a design for the canister.
in this case, it's for a handlebar-mounted trail light.
following that plan,
computerized tools carve blocks of aluminum
into a two-part mold for the bicycle light reflector.
they secure the mold in an injection molding machine.
then, they load white acrylic pellets
into the machine's hopper.
the machine grinds
and melts the acrylic pellets into a thick liquid.
then, it pushes the liquid
into the crevices of the mold.
the acrylic quickly solidifies
into the shape of a reflector.
an aluminum finish makes the acrylic shiny and reflective.
then, it's over to a different injection-molding machine.
this one uses molten rubber to form four on/off buttons.
a worker sets an l.e.d.-studded circuit board on a switch
cradled in a fixture.
she trims wires
from the switch that protrudes through the board.
she solders those wires to copper pads on the board,
securing the switch and making an electrical connection.
she removes the assembly from the fixture
and threads the battery cord through the board.
she attaches the board to a vented heat sink,
which will draw heat away from the lights,
allowing them to run more efficiently.
she installs the reflector over the tiny l.e.d. lights.
the reflector will focus the light forward,
creating narrow beams.
another member of the team
places a tray of reflector covers in a laser etcher.
he closes the lid and activates the laser.
it etches through tape that's been applied to the metal.
the tape has a blackening agent on it.
the laser transfers that blackening agent
to the etched number,
making it stand out.
the number indicates the lumen power of the light.
lumen is a measure of the total amount of visible light
emitted by a source.
back on the assembly line,
a worker snaps the cover onto the bike light.
then, she attaches an open guard to the heat sink
to protect the cyclist
from the heat generated by the l.e.d.s.
this bicycle light is ready to be put to the test.
a technician turns it on
and inserts it in a device called a lumen sphere.
a computer analyzes the light
and finds that it meets standards.
next, an employee builds a smaller bike light
for a cyclist helmet.
she inserts the l.e.d. assembly in a canister,
then attaches the on/off button.
she attaches the light to a circuit board
with three l.e.d.s.
she tucks the circuit board into the housing
and inserts a rechargeable lithium battery.
she puts the assembly aside
and attaches a red reflective panel
to an aluminized reflector.
she snaps the assembly into a clear plastic case,
completing the rear light lens.
she returns for the front helmet light
and installs the reflector over the light.
she screws on a glass cover that's framed by a metal bezel.
she joins the rear lens
and the l.e.d. assembly, encasing the electronics
of this bike light.
she switches on both lights to confirm
that they're fully operational.
these bicycle lights are ready to illuminate a rider's path,
whether it's a shadowy mountain trail
or a dark city street.
narrator:
installing a pool above ground
costs much less
than installing one in ground.
this is because there's no excavation required.
you can build an elevated deck around the top
to give it an in-ground appearance,
or you can simply climb
up a ladder and jump right in.
no hole to dig, no underground pipes to install.
just a day or so of on-site prep and assembly,
and you can take to your above-ground pool
like a duck to water.
at the factory, a computer-guided machine
cuts vinyl panels for the pool's water-retaining inside surface.
the vinyl comes in a wide choice of printed designs.
it's tear-resistant, u.v.-resistant,
and is treated with an antifungal coating.
the wall panel is rectangular,
and the floor panels are curved to fit the pool's perimeter.
the wall panels go through a welder that fuses a bead
to the top edge.
a bead is a flexible, "u'-shaped, thermoplastic strip
that is used to attach the pool wall to the liner.
a hot welding tool slightly melts both the bead
and the liner edge, so when they cool and solidify,
they're bonded.
the liner is ready to be assembled.
workers use a manual welding machine
that generates heat with radio frequencies.
they overlap the edges of adjoining panels,
then fuse them together.
after connecting the floor panels to each other,
workers complete the liner by
joining the wall to the floor.
a quality-control inspector checks every soldered seam
to make sure they're solid.
meanwhile, workers manufacture
the pool's structural components.
they feed a continuous strip of painted, galvanized steel
through a roll former.
the strip is shaped to a specific profile.
a punch press cuts the components
to the required length and shape.
four different structural components are made this way --
the pieces that form the top
and bottom tracks of the pool,
the vertical posts that support the pool wall,
and the ledges running along the top of the wall.
the wall is also made of painted galvanized steel.
a roller impresses a corrugated pattern to give the wall
more vertical strength.
then, a press punches out openings
for the pool's water inlet and filter.
after folding each end of the wall over itself
to form a strong edge,
they punch holes for the bolts that will join the edges.
a stamping die progressively shapes strips
of galvanized steel into connectors.
the connectors join the vertical posts
to the structure's bottom track and top rail.
an injection molder
makes the plastic covers that will hide those connectors.
workers then box the liner
and structural components for transport
to the installation site.
on-site, they lay crushed stone around the perimeter
to support the bottom track
under the weight of the water.
next, they unroll the pool wall
and place it in the bottom track.
they place a vertical post over each bottom connector
and secure it with screws.
inside the pool wall,
they lay down a base of sand and compact it.
then, they lay down landscaping fabric.
they cut a hole for a central bottom drain.
then, they begin spreading out the liner.
they hook the bead
over the top edge of the wall,
then lock it in place with the top rail.
once the liner is fully attached,
they suction out the air to draw it tight against the wall.
they seal the liner to the bottom drain.
they hide the top rail under the ledge
and the connections under plastic caps.
they run pipes to connect the
filtration system and skimmer.
then, with an ordinary garden hose,
they fill the pool with water.
narrator: foldable solar panels were invented in the 1990s
for american soldiers in the field.
they use them to recharge electronic devices.
the panels have environmental and tactical advantages,
conserving both electricity and physical energy.
today, foldable solar panels
are not just for the military.
these lightweight panels can be folded up
and tucked into a backpack,
allowing anyone to escape to the wilderness
but stay plugged in.
production starts with a roll of thin plastic film.
it's the same material used to make flat-screen tvs.
a worker loads it into machines that distribute thin layers
of aluminum and silicon onto it.
the aluminum acts as an electrical contact.
the silicon produces electricity when exposed to the sun's rays.
next, lasers carve vertical and horizontal lines into the film.
these lines define the solar cells.
an automated squeegee applies black ink through a screen
and into the lines.
the ink will act as an electrical insulator.
it also makes it possible
to cut through the film without damaging it.
uv light cures the insulator ink.
an employee pours a generous amount of metallic silver ink
onto a pattern.
a squeegee forces the ink through to the solar film.
this creates a conductive grid on the film.
a camera magnifies the grid for inspection.
the solar film travels through a chamber
where heat cures the silver ink.
a laser now connects the solar cells,
linking the bottom aluminum layer of one cell
to the top silicon layer of the next.
the laser ties them together
similar to how a soldering tool would.
this establishes electrical connections
and increases the voltage significantly.
a different camera magnifies the connections
to check the alignment.
now, a worker loads
the solar film into a machine.
it deposits a transparent oxide onto the film
that will increase conductivity.
these solar cells are now fully functional.
the next machine tests each one.
it also applies a conductive foil tape at certain points.
another machine
rolls a clear sheet of plastic
onto the solar cells.
the plastic adheres to the cells,
waterproofing and encapsulating them.
a die press cuts out solar panels
along the black insulator lines.
the press uses computerized cameras for accurate cuts.
a robot transfers each panel to the next station
using suctioning heads.
a computerized camera
scrutinizes the panels for defects.
after more testing,
they deposit the panels on a piece of fabric.
a laser cuts the fabric around the panels.
heated rollers bond the plastic panels to the fabric.
now, an employee burns through clear plastic film
to reach the conductive foil.
he solders wire to the foil
at these points to connect the positive and negative leads.
the wire is flexible and will bend with the fabric
when it's folded.
a seamstress now stitches strips of fabric
over the wires, enclosing them in a protective pocket.
another member of the team solders a connector
to a circuit board that's been attached to protruding wires.
he squeezes silicone into a plastic cover
and places it on the assembly.
the silicone solidifies around the components to protect
them from water damage.
finally, he rivets the cover to the fabric.
this foldable solar charger is ready to be bundled up
and placed in a backpack.
it can power a laptop or a smartphone,
keeping the user connected anywhere in the world.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...