--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today, on "how it's made"...
l.e.d. stage lights...
...apple cider...
...chemical tank trailers...
...and ornate stone floors.
in the world of stage lighting,
traditional incandescent or halogen bulb spotlights
are making way for l.e.d.s.
l.e.d.s are light-emitting diodes
controlled by electronics.
they use less energy, emit less heat,
and can produce a wide array of colors
without the use of filters.
incandescent or halogen stage
lights produce just one color.
the only way to create more is to shine the light beam
through colored plastic called gel filters.
however, this l.e.d. stage light
uses seven different colored l.e.d.s,
which can be blended into a variety of different hues.
this computer-guided machine places all the components
on the stage light's circuit board,
which contains 60 l.e.d.s in 7 different base colors.
another machine measures
and cuts pieces of insulated electrical wire.
then, the machine strips the insulation off the ends
and crimps on terminals.
the machine processes up
to 26 feet of wire per second.
workers manually assemble 10 wires and two connectors
into a control harness.
the harness will connect the light's control board
to the l.e.d. array.
on the factory floor,
they paint the stage light's two-part cast-aluminum housing.
the paint process is electrostatic.
this means the housing and the black powder paint
are laced with opposing electrical charges.
this spreads the paint evenly over the housing.
then, the housing goes through an oven,
which bakes on the paint.
back in the assembly area,
workers install the stage
light's electronic components,
starting with the lcd screen.
it displays the current settings and modes
and the menus for changing them.
after covering the screen with a protective plastic shield,
they install the control panel.
it has an opening for the screen.
this plastic cover protects the lcd.
it also directs outside air
into the housing to the light's cooling fan,
which they now secure in place with this bracket.
the fan dissipates the heat the l.e.d.s generate.
this block of aluminum, called the heat sink, absorbs
and quickly dissipates some of that heat.
they mount the l.e.d. array
on top of this twofold cooling system.
then, they install the optic assembly.
this plastic component focuses the individual l.e.d.s.
they construct
the stage light's mixing tube,
lining its interior
with adhesive-backed aluminum mirrors.
the mirrors mix the seven l.e.d. colors
into a single color.
the assemblers now join the two halves of the mixing tube,
adding a glass lens on the front.
the lens focuses the light
produced by the 60 l.e.d.s into a single beam.
then, they install the tube over the optic.
next, they mount the control card
to the side of the mixing tube.
the control card is the stage light's onboard computer.
it processes the commands the lighting technician enters.
commands can be entered from the control panel
or remotely from a computer.
after installing the main power supply,
they plug a dmx cable into the control card.
dmx is the digital network
through which the console or computer
communicates to the stage light.
they join this completed unit to the rest of the housing,
which has the dmx and power connectors.
this stage light is now finished
and ready for a thorough quality control check.
they plug it into a testing machine,
which powers it up and verifies several functions.
the machine also calibrates every color
to ensure consistency in every stage light they manufacture.
then, they run the stage light at full power
for three hours nonstop
to simulate strenuous operating conditions.
once the light passes these tests,
it's ready for its stage debut.
narrator: apple cider is also known  a
it's darker and cloudier than conventional apple juice
because tiny bits of apple are not filtered out.
these flavorful fragments
are what makes this fall beverage unique.
when the apples on the trees are ripe,
it's time to produce apple cider.
they process the apples within days of the harvest
to produce a beverage that tastes both fresh and sweet.
it starts with the right mix of apples.
some varieties are sweet,
and others are tart.
this mix of flavors will spice things up.
the apples float to the surface of a water-filled pit
and drift onto a conveyor
that takes them into the cider mill.
inside the mill, the apples spill into a washing station.
water sprays the apples as they
bounce across rolling brushes.
next, the apples take a trip up to a grinder.
inside, a steel arm pushes the apples against a grater.
it shreds them, pits and all, into a pulp.
this pulp is known as pomace.
the pomace lands in a funnel.
from here, a pump moves it through pipes across the plant,
where it arrives at a press.
the apple pomace
flows between two porous belts
that wind around rollers.
the rollers apply pressure to squeeze out the juice.
the juice drips through holes in the belts.
the process strains out most of the pulp,
but some remains as the juice spills from the press
into large catch pans.
then, they pump this chunky apple liquid
into a holding tank.
from the tank, it
flows through a revolving drum
that filters out more pulp, pits, and apple stems.
the fluid seeps through the perforations in the drum
and flows into a large trough.
after one more screening,
only fine bits of apple and sediment remain.
this gives it the desired cider consistency and flavor.
the cider now flows into channels
between hot steel plates.
the heat destroys pathogens and bacteria
that would convert
the natural sugars to alcohol.
this ensures that the cider is both safe to drink
and nonalcoholic.
it's now ready for bottling.
a worker slides plastic jugs into position under nozzles.
the nozzles descend and pump the boiling-hot apple cider
into the jugs.
they're filled to the brim so air can't get inside.
air causes the cider to deteriorate.
next, the conveyor
moves the jugs forward to a capping station.
plastic caps funnel toward the jugs as they approach.
the caps land on the rims with perfect timing.
spinning wheels tighten the caps as the jugs ride by,
hermetically sealing the hot apple cider,
giving it a shelf life of approximately a year.
the jugs then head into a tunnel,
where sprayers douse them with cold water.
next, machinery pulls the liner
off of adhesive-backed labels.
an electric eye detects the approaching jugs,
queuing rollers to apply the labels.
the filtered-out pomace
from earlier is cooked four to five hours.
this caramelizes the sugars in the apples,
turning the pomace into a highly concentrated spread
known as apple butter.
they bottle it while it's piping hot to preserve it.
although not technically butter,
this fruit spread has a similar consistency.
it takes a full day of processing
to produce both apple butter and apple cider.
it's time to raise a glass
and enjoy the sweet bounty of the harvest.
narrator: chemical tank trailers roll down our highways
they haul liquid chemicals for
manufacturing and other needs.
chemicals could be hazardous if
released into the environment.
making a chemical tank trailer is serious business.
chemical tank trailers are built
to ensure that a potentially harmful cargo arrives safely.
their design is tightly regulated
because safety is in everyone's best interest.
they build the chemical tank from scratch.
they start with a big sheet
of heavy-duty stainless steel.
pressurized rollers curl it into a cylinder
that will become half of the tank's inner vessel.
using a crane, they transfer the 20-foot-long rounded section
to a welding station.
here, an operator controls a semi-automatic welder
with a joystick.
the welder joins the two sides of the sheet
to complete the cylinder.
they bring two cylinders together
to form a 40-foot-long inner vessel.
this seam is near the midpoint.
it will be subject to significant bending stress
in transport.
it's critical that this weld is perfect.
the team caps the end with metal discs known as heads.
they tack-weld the heads to the vessel first
and assure that the fit is exact.
then, a semi-automatic welder does a permanent weld.
next, they weld three long half pipes along the bottom,
again doing tack welds first and then final welds.
the three pipes serve as a heating panel,
keeping the chemical cargo at a liquid state.
this is important because, when some chemicals solidify,
their purity is compromised.
the team slides the first of many metal rings
onto the tank and clamps each ring to the shell.
these rings stiffen the structure and act
as an exterior skeleton.
a worker does the initial tack welds.
then, a semi-automatic welder makes the full welds.
after attaching a steel framework to the bottom,
a crane transfers the inner vessel to the trailer.
a worker tucks insulation between the vessel
and the trailer.
he secures the tank to the trailer
with intermittent welds known as stitch welds.
another member of the team
wraps strips of rigid foam around the steel vessel.
he spaces the foam evenly apart
and pulls them tightly against the vessel with metal strapping.
this creates compartments for fiberglass insulation.
he tucks the insulation into the spaces,
blanketing the vessels
so the chemical freight will stay warm and fluid.
the team now builds the outer shell.
they pull stainless steel sheets
around the inner vessel using thick nylon ties.
these sheets are made of thinner steel
than the kind used
to construct the inner vessel.
they easily conform to the cylindrical shape.
a worker welds the sheets in place,
completing the outer shell.
once a manhole
has been installed at the top,
the crew builds a metal platform around it.
this platform allows a person to access the manhole
without slipping or denting the outer shell of the tank.
a worker attaches a ladder to the tank.
it will be used for accessing the manhole.
another member of the team
connects l.e.d. taillights and inserts them in light boxes
at the back of the trailer.
he secures the lights to the light box with screws.
it takes about five days to
build a chemical tank trailer.
they last for 30 years or more,
so this trailer should be good for the long haul.
narrator: centuries-old churches and palaces
have ornate stone floors
that took craftsmen decades to create
with chisels and other hand tools.
today, factories can produce similar elaborate designs
in a matter of hours thanks to computer-guided machinery.
these floor designs are so intricate,
it's hard to believe that each component
is an individually cut piece of marble,
granite, or other natural stone.
whether the design covers an entire floor,
or it's a single decorative insert,
the starting point is a stone slab.
it's massive but extremely thin,
so it's actually quite fragile.
workers use a pneumatic suction hoist
to position the slab onto a cutting machine table.
the machine is entirely computer-guided.
it cuts with a jet of water.
the water contains particles of garnet,
an extremely hard gemstone.
the jet cuts by eroding the stone
rather than by sheer force, which would crack it.
workers rinse away the stone grit and abrasive residue
once the cutting is finished.
they use suction cups to remove the cut pieces one at a time.
they've cut squares for this design.
some will go into the floor as-is,
while others go onto a smaller water jet machine,
which cuts them into intricate shapes.
workers extract these smaller pieces
with tweezers.
every component of the design has a number.
workers label the back of the corresponding piece accordingly.
then, they print out a life-size
version of the numbered design
on a sheet of durable polyester film.
they tape it to the assembly table to serve as a template.
then, they lay one piece at a time front side
down onto the template.
like a puzzle, the design slowly reveals itself.
once the design is fully laid out,
they tack the pieces together with glue.
this keeps them from shifting or separating.
they lay fiberglass mesh over the entire assembly.
then, they prepare an epoxy resin
specially formulated for stone setting...
...and spread it evenly over the mesh.
they let it set overnight.
and the next day, they sand it flat.
the cut stone design is now bonded together in a solid unit.
now, they can safely flip it face-up.
the final step is to fill the joints with epoxy grout
then wash off any excess with a wet sponge.
this ornate cut-stone floor insert is finally finished.
this is just one of several components
of a large, elaborate design.
workers assemble them together
to do a quality control check.
then, they take the design apart
and package each component separately for shipping.
stone must always ship upright on its side
because it can crack
when transported horizontally.
however, the cut-stone floor
will be sturdy enough to walk on
once it's properly installed.
just be careful not to bump into anything
while you're admiring the art beneath your feet.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at
sciencechannel.com/howitsmade.