--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: gingerbread houses
are a holiday tradition.
it used to take
a fair amount of time
and baking expertise
to make one.
but today, there are kits
and even pre-assembled
gingerbread houses
that make the process a
breeze.
there's something about
this edible edifice
that makes the holidays
seem more special.
with a kit,
you can let the factory
handle the tricky part and
just
have fun with the trimmings.
to make a gingerbread house
kit,
the factory starts
with baking soda.
then a worker adds
a scoop of salt,
measuring the ingredients
by weight.
he transfers the baking soda
and salt to a mixer.
he measures the spices --
cinnamon, ginger, nutmeg,
and allspice.
there's actually
a lot more cinnamon
than ginger in gingerbread.
but the flavor of the ginger
is more pronounced.
he closes the mixer,
and the system adds water,
molasses, and sugar.
at the top of the mixer,
he tosses in a block
of vegetable shortening.
the mixer combines
all the ingredients
and blends in the flour.
the result is
a putty-like dough.
a spiraling machine helps move
the dough onto a conveyor.
a roller flattens the chunks
so they won't fall off
during the steep climb.
the conveyor delivers
the chunks of dough
to a machine called a sheeter.
it gets this name
because it rolls the pieces
into
a seemingly endless sheet.
a large cookie cutter
comes down.
it punches out
the various shapes needed
to form the gingerbread house.
the cookie cutouts land
on moving rubber-coated wires.
separators between the wires
trim the excess
gingerbread dough,
which is captured
and mixed into the next batch.
then the cookies transfer
to a mesh conveyor,
which takes them
up to a baking sheet belt.
the cookies travel slowly
through a long convection oven
that's heated to
just over 160 degrees.
here's an inside look.
at any time,
there are parts for 150
gingerbread kits in this oven.
the baked gingerbread
exits the oven
and transfers
to a spiral conveyor.
after a 30-minute ride,
the dough is cool and firm.
workers stack the pieces
for one gingerbread house
onto a piece of cardboard.
they're ready to be packaged
with the rest of the kit.
factory workers
assemble the houses
for certain retailers.
they glue the gingerbread
structure together
with royal icing
made of confectioner's sugar
and egg whites.
it dries fast,
giving this gingerbread house
instant structural integrity.
for the customer,
all that's left
is the decorating.
elsewhere in the factory,
they make the icing
for the kits.
plastic packaging moves toward
hot jaws that seal the bottom.
then a robot grabs a package
and opens the top.
a fill nozzle
pumps icing into it.
another robot applies
an applicator tip
and heat-seals
the plastic around it.
the tubes of sugary icing
fall on to a conveyor.
a worker places them in a box
for transfer
to the kit-assembly station.
these gingerbread houses
are ready for retail.
decorated with icing and
candy,
they look good enough to eat.
narrator: livestock should be
transported in a vehicle
that keeps them comfortable
and protects them
from injury and stress.
the best way to haul
cattle and horses humanely
is in a livestock trailer.
they're designed to be easy
to load, unload, and clean
out.
a proper livestock trailer
keeps its passengers
as comfortable as possible.
it's built to reduce rattling
and other stress-inducing
noises.
it lets in natural light,
which has a calming effect,
and it has openings along
the sides to circulate air.
a designer builds a 3-d model
on a computer
then breaks it down into units
for assembly.
the factory orders long pieces
of extruded aluminum
designed for the trailer model
then cuts them
to specific lengths.
to construct the floor,
workers
slide planks into end rails.
they pull the planks
tightly together
using ratchet straps
then weld them to the rails.
they weld two flat aluminum
bars
across the planks
as floor supports.
the floor is upside down
during
this part of the assembly.
once they flip it over,
these supporters
will be under the floor
planks.
next, they install the axles,
two or three
depending on the size
and style of the trailer.
these steel axles
are mounted to a steel frame
that provides structural
support
for the trailer.
to attach the frame,
they drill holes
for lock bolts and lock
collars.
they use a special tool
to squeeze the collar
down into the bolt.
this ensures the bolt
won't loosen with vibration.
now they flip the floor over.
they weld the reverse side
of the rails to the floor
planks
using a track welder.
to construct the trailer
walls,
they weld together
horizontal slants, uprights,
and a top rail.
they connect the wall to
the floor then weld it in
place.
this trailer is designed
for a warm climate,
so the side walls have
openings
at the top to improve air
flow.
several parts of the trailer
are cut from
sheets of textured aluminum
called tread plate.
after welding on
a large piece of tread plate
for the trailer's front wall,
they attach the gooseneck
nose.
this nose connects the trailer
to the back of a pickup truck.
it can also transport
tools, feed, and baby animals.
trailers that don't have
a gooseneck
are called bumper hitches.
they connect
to the back of a tow vehicle.
workers attach the gooseneck
using welds and lock bolts.
they build
the trailer's access gates
the same way as the walls --
cutting aluminum extrusions
to specific lengths,
assembling them,
then welding the parts
together.
they mount the gates
by welding the hinge plates
to the wall structure.
the roof can either be
a sheet of aluminum
or a sheet of translucent
woven glass fiber.
they pull the sheet taut
then rivet it
to the top rail of the walls.
they add an aluminum strip to
secure the roof in high winds.
workers install reflective
tape
and l.e.d. lights
where transport regulations
require them.
a rubber grommet
around each light
reduces vibration
and prevents water
infiltration.
workers complete the assembly
by mounting the wheels and
tires
onto the axles.
they add a spare tire
under the gooseneck
and a vinyl graphic decal
on the side wall.
after a thorough inspection,
they give the trailer
a mild acid wash
to remove any grease
and handprints.
the factory can customize
any trailer design.
this includes higher windows
for horses
or installing troughs
so the driver can give
the animals food and water.
every trailer is designed
for easy cleaning,
which includes
unloading the livestock,
removing the bedding material
and manure,
as well as pressure-washing
the floor.
narrator: a hangar
is a closed building structure
designed for storing aircraft
or spacecraft.
they provide protection
from direct sun exposure
and bad weather.
as aircrafts grew bigger,
so did their hangars.
many hangars today
use giant bottom-rolling
doors.
the bottom-rolling hangar door
moves along rails
embedded in the floor
and top guide beams
built into the ceiling.
they use several smaller
panels
to construct
the 184-foot-wide hangar door.
an oxy fuel cutter
carves door parts
out of a carbon-steel plate.
the torches heat up the metal,
then blast it with oxygen.
this creates iron oxide,
which melts and flows
out of the cut.
the operator uses an iron rod
to lift the machined parts
off of the burn table.
he cleans up the edges
with an electric grinder
and removes any iron oxide
left
over from the cutting process.
the machined parts
go to a cnc mill,
which turns each round blank
into a wheel.
a carbide insert carves
the rail's tread profile
into the steel.
the machine sprays coolant
to prevent overheating,
which would warp
the finished wheel.
next,
a machinist uses a smaller
blank
to make an upper-guide roller.
the mill runs at a speed
of approximately
200 rotations per minute.
it quickly turns the round
blank
into a finished roller
ready for assembly.
a worker starts fitting
rollers
inside the upper guide head.
he inserts them
into machined holes
in the steel housing
and tack-welds them in place.
he positions the larger
rollers
outside the upper guide head
housing.
these rollers
will bear the load of the
door.
using a metal sheet as a
gauge,
he sets the clearance between
the roller and the housing
then welds the parts together.
a cnc drilling machine
prepares to make
the outside frame
of the door panels.
a pressure sensor on the drill
moves its carbide insert
back automatically as soon as
it pierces the surface.
meanwhile, two welders
assemble
the bottom door truck
on a welding jig.
they weld a spacer
to the main beam
using an electric mig welder.
they tack-weld the tube in
place
then bring in the side channel
of the door truck assembly.
they clamp the side channel
tightly against the spacer
tube.
then weld the spacers
to the beam,
making a clean, continuous
weld.
a worker sand-blasts
the door truck assembly.
he blows compressed air and
sand
to prepare the metal surface
for painting.
using a spray gun,
a worker applies
corrosion-resistant metal
primer
on the door truck
and leaves it to dry.
workers assemble the panels
before the door leaves the
shop.
they use high-strength
structural bolts
to assemble the parts.
workers install
the unitized operator
assembly.
it contains the engine
powering
the bottom roller wheels.
a worker bolts
the electrical control panel
to the operator assembly
frame.
he puts the cabinet door
in place and secures the
hinge.
tightened brace cables
keep the door square
and prevent racking.
they mount the upper guide
on a telescoping assembly.
they add the door's
corrugated exterior panels,
and it's ready to ship.
at the push of a button,
the assembled door slowly
opens.
each panel rolls
on the bottom rail
and hangs
from the top guide rail.
the door opens wide enough
to let the aircraft through.
narrator: playing make-believe
is a common pastime
for children.
research shows that playing
with dolls and toy figurines
can improve a child's
creativity,
communication,
and social skills.
this includes
problem solving and
empathizing.
whether it's an animal,
person,
or fictional creature,
a toy figurine can be a
passport
to a fantasy world
where imagination rules
and the story plays out
in the child's hands.
the toy company designers
study
photographs or drawings
of the creature
they plan to create.
then they prepare
a sketch of the figurine
showing
the physical characteristics,
such as size, colors,
and textures.
once the sketch is finalized,
they use specialized software
to transform it into
a 3-dimensional model.
then a 3-d printer
creates a plastic model.
the company also employs
traditional wax modelers.
it may look like a slow
process,
but an experienced wax modeler
can often sculpt
a model faster than a
computer.
the company's engineers
determine whether
the toy should be produced
in one piece or multiple
parts.
then the modeler makes a wax
or plastic model accordingly.
this particular dino is
divided
into four parts --
head, body, jaw, and tongue.
for each part,
workers create a silicone
mold,
which will be used to make
several copies in hard
plastic.
workers place the model
of the dino's head
in a box
then fill the box with
silicone.
it takes about 12 hours
for the silicone to cure.
then they cut it open
and extract the model.
they use the vacated cavity
to cast several
hard-plastic copies of the
part.
the art department uses most
of them to sample paint
colors.
one copy, however, goes to
the company's tool makers,
who use it
to make the production mold.
they bury the copy
in putty up to the midpoint.
they leave the top half
of the copy exposed.
next, they set
the half-buried copy
in a metal form
and fill it with plaster.
once the plaster hardens,
they cure it in an oven
for about an hour
then they extract the copy.
what's left in the plaster
is a cavity in the shape
of half the dinosaur.
they fill the cavity
with molten zinc,
alloyed with copper,
aluminum, and magnesium.
once the metal cools
and solidifies,
they break the plaster,
revealing one half
of the two-part
metal production mold.
they repeat the entire process
to make the other half.
workers mount
the two-part dino mold
in an injection molding
machine.
the machine shoots
hot, molten plastic
into the metal mold cavity.
the machine
immediately cools the plastic
then releases the figurine.
the plastic is solid
but still soft,
so they dip it in cold water.
this hardens it further.
next, artists hand-paint
the figurines
using both traditional
and airbrushes.
the paint is nontoxic
and very durable.
it's designed to flex with
the plastic to prevent
cracking.
it also withstands abrasion
because children often drag
these toys along the ground.
once the paint dries,
they assemble the toy.
a worker glues the dino's
tongue
into the hinged jaw,
snaps the jaw into the head,
then glues the head to the
body.
the company performs
safety testing
on every new figurine
designed.
this tensile test makes sure
a child
can't pull or bite off
a piece of the toy.
chemical analysis confirmed
both the plastic and the paint
are completely nontoxic.
so this dino may look
dangerous,
but in reality,
he's perfectly harmless.
this ferocious beast
is ready to hit the
playground.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...