--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: the binding is
the most important component
of a downhill ski.
it attaches the ski boot
to the ski.
it prevents injury by
releasing
the boot if the skier falls.
also, an integrated brake
engages upon release,
stopping the ski
from sliding down the hill.
every downhill ski binding
has a toe and heel piece.
the toe usually
releases sideways in a fall,
and the heel releases upward.
the earliest bindings were
made
of heavy stamped steel
and had no safety release.
today's bindings are made
of lightweight material,
such as extruded aluminum
and fiberglass-reinforced
plastic.
using 3-d software,
the research
and development team
designs the binding
along with the molds and dyes
used to manufacture
the components.
the team produces
a prototype of each component
and uses three-dimensional
measuring tools
to verify the specifications.
workers paint the visible
aluminum and plastic
components
then cure them in an oven
for 40 minutes.
they also dry them
at room temperature
for 24 hours.
this company produces
high-end racing models,
as well as less expensive
models
for beginner
to intermediate skiers.
this aluminum housing
is for the toe piece
of a racing binding.
they screw on plastic tabs
to keep the metal from
damaging
the plastic ski boot.
then workers assemble
the indicator,
which is used to adjust
the release setting.
the release setting determines
how much torque is needed
to trigger the binding
to release the ski boot.
the torque is generated
by the weight
of the skier falling.
they place
a bronze and aluminum ball
joint
in the metal base.
the ball joint acts
as the rotational center
of the toe piece
when it releases.
they lubricate the ball joint
with grease
before putting the base
in an assembly fixture.
then they add
the toe piece housing...
...and a plastic cap
with a white line on the side.
as they screw down the cap,
it compresses
the spring underneath.
they test
the finished toe piece.
this machine stamps
the company logo
on the heel piece of a binding
that's designed
for beginner
to intermediate skiers.
this one is made of
fiberglass-reinforced plastic
with a clear polyurethane
protective cover.
you press the heel piece
with the ski pole
to get in and out of the ski.
next, they mount a heel piece
to a base
and assemble
the internal mechanism.
this includes a screw-down cap
that sets the internal spring
to a specific release setting.
an automated machine
tests each heel and toe piece
to make sure the mechanism
functions correctly.
another machine
unscrews the cap halfway
to lower the release setting
to the midpoint.
next, a metal pin
connects the pivoting top
of the heel piece to the base.
this setting tool locks the
pin
in its lateral position.
now, workers mount the ski
brake
to the heel piece.
the ski boot maintains
pressure
on the brake
to keep it in the off
position.
in a ski accident,
the fall releases that
pressure,
triggering the brake.
after the binding
has been adjusted
to the length of the ski boot,
workers insert a notching pin
that locks the heel piece
to the mounting plate
of the ski.
these plastic caps hide the
heads of the lateral metal
pin.
finally, workers connect
this lever to the notching
pin.
you simply
pull it up and back
to disengage the pin
and adjust for boot length.
the company subjects random
samples from the production
line
to rigorous
quality control tests.
bindings are made
to international standards.
these standards dictate
how they're supposed to react
to falls.
provided the binding
is correctly set
for the skier's weight,
boot size, and skiing ability,
these standards ensure
the ski boot releases
in an accident
but doesn't
inadvertently release
if the skier hits a big bump.
narrator:
removing oil, heavy soils,
scale, or rust stains on
a piece of metal can be tough.
this is where
industrial cleaning
technologies
come in handy.
immersion parts washers
use degreasing
and descaling compounds
to clean metal.
they also use ultrasound
to literally shake off the
muck.
an immersion parts washer
agitates water mixed
with an industrial detergent
to clean a mechanical part
or piece of metal.
a pneumatic lift mechanism
moves the platform
up and down inside the tank
as the water heats
to about 150 degrees.
a robot loads stainless steel
into a laser cutter,
using suction cups
to manipulate the sheet metal.
a cnc cutter uses
a 2,500 watt laser
to cut the steel,
following a layout
entered in a cad system.
the layout maximizes
the number of parts
made out of a single sheet.
the machine parts come out
on an unloading platform
where an operator performs
a visual inspection.
he takes the parts
to a cnc folding table.
the machine bends
the sheet metal
to form the outside shell
of the immersion parts washer.
this is also called
the tank skin.
a hydraulic bending machine
makes flanges in the sheet
metal
to reinforce the tank walls
and provide a surface
for welding.
this high-end
sheet metal-forming technique
allows workers to produce
a series of parts
for multiple units.
a worker assembles
the machine parts
on a welding fixture.
he uses clamps
to hold the pieces in place
as he welds them together
using an electric mig torch.
welding such a thin sheet
of stainless steel
is a tricky job
because it's more susceptible
to warping from the heat.
the tank goes through
a 24-hour leak test
before painting.
a painter applies
epoxy and acrylic hybrid
electrostatic powder coat.
the coat combines
the protective strength of
epoxy
and the resilience of acrylic.
the painter places the tank
in a massive curing chamber...
and sets the oven time
and temperature.
the baking process
gives the powder coat
a grainy, textured finish.
a worker grinds down
the weld profiles
and polishes the top tank
walls
with fine sandpaper.
another worker
brings in the lift arm
and inserts it in the tank.
he puts the bearing support
mechanism in place
and bolts it onto the tank.
he inserts the rollers
that will support and guide
the lift arm...
then drives a shaft
through the bearings.
he installs
the pneumatic cylinder
behind the bearing support
and pins it
on top of the lift arm.
he brings in the agitator pump
and installs its
3/4-horsepower electric motor
next to the bearing support.
a plumber installs the
fittings
for the tank filter.
the filter removes
contamination and debris
from the cleaning solution.
a worker installs the platform
and bolts it on the lift arm.
he installs a rack
on the platform.
it's made of grainy fiberglass
to prevent the pieces
from shifting
during a cleaning cycle.
after testing the movement
of the lift arm
and platform assembly,
workers install
the steel lid on the tank...
and attach its hinge.
then they check
the fit of the lid.
an electrician makes
the connections
for the heat
and timer controls...
...and screws the electric
panel
onto the side of the tank.
he closes the electric box,
then tests the lift arm,
the lid, and the agitator
pump.
as the lift arm moves up,
the platform lifts clean parts
out of the water.
washers like this one
can clean anything
from automotive castings
to printing press parts.
narrator:
in an underground mine,
ventilation is critical
for the safety of the miners.
above-ground fans
can either blow in fresh air
or they can suck out toxic
gases
using ventilation ducts
suspended from the ceiling
of the mine shaft.
the black ventilation ducts
are made of fiberglass.
the yellow ducts
are made of vinyl
reinforced with steel wire.
both are designed to withstand
negative pressure
when drawing out gases
and positive pressure
when blowing in air.
to manufacture
sections of fiberglass duct,
they use a steel mandrel.
workers wrap plastic
around the mandrel
to prevent the fiberglass
from sticking.
they also wrap cardboard
around
one end of each duct section
to increase its diameter.
next, they start up
the fiberglass winding
machine.
it draws
29 strands of fiberglass
roving
through a bath of resin,
then winds them
in a helical pattern    u
building up a layer between
3 and 10 millimeters thick,
depending on the application.
the regular end is called
the spigot.
the wide end is called the
bell.
the spigot of one duct section
fits snugly
inside the bell of the next.
this way, multiple sections
can be connected to each
other.
workers embed d-rings
at regular intervals
along the top.
these rings are used
to suspend the ducts
from the mine shaft ceiling.
once the winding is finished,
workers cut the roving...
...and roll
the fiberglass-covered mandrel
into a large oven for curing.
it takes about 30 minutes
to cure the resin
on a duct this size.
once it's cured,
they extract the mandrel.
they saw through the middle
of the fiberglass duct
to divide it into two
shorter ducts of equal length.
each has a bell end
and a spigot end.
workers use a hand saw
to cut and shape some pieces
into fittings.
fittings are angled
or "y"-shaped pieces
that connect two
straight pieces,
allowing
the route of the ducting
to turn or branch out.
they connect the cut pieces
with galvanized metal tape,
then they seal the gaps
with strips of fiberglass
cloth
saturated with resin.
to make spiral duct,
they weld together
sheets of vinyl
to create a wider sheet.
on one end of the tube,
they weld in a ring
made of galvanized wire rope.
at the other end of the tube,
they weld in
an adjustable coupler.
to connect duct sections,
the ring of one section
fits into the coupler
of the next one.
they mount the tube
on the guide bar
of the spiral winding machine.
the machine applies steel wire
to reinforce the vinyl.
it also enables the duct
section
to collapse into a compact
hoop.
as it works its way
down the tube,
the machine covers the wire
with a strip of vinyl.
it welds the vinyl to the
tube,
forming a pocket
that both locks the wire
in position
and protects it from wear.
when the machine reaches
the opposite end of the tube,
they cut the wire
and remove the duct section.
the last step
is to attach hangers
at 2-foot intervals.
the hangers are used
to suspend the ventilation
ducts
from the mine ceiling.
spiral ducts
are the easiest type
of ventilation to transport
and install
because they're collapsible
and lightweight.
however, they can get damaged
in high-traffic work areas,
so mines prefer to use
sturdier fiberglass
ventilation ducts.
narrator:
before the pencil sharpener,
people used knives
to sharpen the tips of
pencils.
it was in the mid-19th century
when a french inventor
came up with a clever tool --
a little box with a blade
and a cone-shaped opening.
just twist the pencil into it,
and it makes
a very precise point.
the pencil sharpener has been
a favorite of pencil pushers
for over 150 years.
with a few twists,
it can hone
the graphite tip of a pencil
to a very fine point.
to make pencil sharpeners,
they start with
high-carbon steel for th
the steel unwinds
through a straightener,
then a feeder serves it up
to a punchcutter.
it cuts out five blades
in one action,
complete with assembly holes
in the center.
it also embosses
the company logo onto it.
this machine can generate
well over
100,000 pencil sharpener
blades
in an hour.
a worker distributes the
blades
onto a conveyor
that will take them to an
oven.
the temperature inside
is 1,500 degrees.
the blades slowly circle
in the oven.
this step takes
15 to 20 minutes.
exposure to the intense heat
and a quick cooldown in oil
harden the blades,
but it also
leaves them tarnished.
so they drain the oil
by spinning the blades
in a perforated drum.
then they add a mix
of dried corn
and polishing paste
to the blades.
the drum tosses the blades
in the polishing medium
for six 6 to 12 hours.
this restores them,
as we see
in this before-and-after shot.
a circular feeder sorts them
into a single file
and racks them on a metal rod.
once on the rod,
a machine grinds a cutting
edge
into all of the blades at
once.
next,
they manufacture the housing
for the pencil sharpener
blades.
a circular saw
cuts a ridged magnesium bar
to the correct length.
the magnesium blocks
tumble into a feeder,
which funnels them
into a stamping machine.
the machine stamps
the company logo
onto the top
and lower side of the blocks.
machinery moves
the pencil sharpener bodies
forward to a drill
that bores cone-shaped,
pencil-sized holes into them.
a second drill
carves holes in the top
for screwing the blades into
the pencil sharpener bodies.
a little metal rod shoves
the pencil sharpener bodies
out of the machine
and into a bin.
a worker plunges
the pencil sharpener bodies
into five chemical baths.
each bath has
a different formula.
the chemicals soften the edges
of the magnesium bodies,
making the surface shinier.
a worker spreads
the pencil sharpener bodies
across a mesh conveyor.
the conveyor takes them
through a dryer
to remove any residue
left behind
by the chemical solutions.
these pencil sharpener bodies
are now ready to receive
blades.
a feeder system delivers them
to an assembly station.
the screws funnel
into an automated screwdriver
at the assembly point.
a mechanism slides the blades
into the pencil sharpener
bodies
as they arrive.
the pencil sharpeners fall
into a bin, ready for retail.
it's taken
many different processes
to produce these magnesium
pencil sharpeners.
here's a recap of the process.
over a century and a half
after its invention,
the manual pencil sharpener
is still making life easier.
and in modern factories,
the concept has been honed
to a fine point.