--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
early fishing lines were made
of vines and braided
horsehair.
but today, fishermen
rely on braided synthetics
to reel in their catch.
with a higher tensile strength
than steel,
these lines are unlikely to
snap
when they hook the big one.
this fishing line may be thin,
but that doesn't mean
it's not strong.
it's made of a synthetic
called
ultra-high-molecular-weight
polyethylene.
this same synthetic is used
in milk jugs, water pipes,
and even bulletproof vests.
to make these fishing lines,
numerous microfibers are
braided
into a single, tight cord.
an employee starts by
threading
fibers through needles.
she pulls the needles
through spring-loaded devices.
the devices keep the fibers
at an even tension as they
unwind onto small bobbins.
these bobbins are designed
to fit in the braiding
machines.
the machines are called
maypole braiders
because the spools spin
like dancers around a maypole.
as they spin,
they weave the strands
into a tight braid.
there are 4,500
braiding machines in operation
at this factory.
producing a tight braid
is slow work.
it takes about 10 days
to braid a 7,500-foot section
of fishing line.
big spools overhead
slowly revolve to take up
the braided polyethylene line.
at the same time,
a worker fills a metal tank
with hot water...
and adds yellow dye to it.
a pump at the bottom of the
tank
keeps the water moving
to evenly distribute the dye.
he stirs it a bit while
he inspects the mixing job.
they heat and pressurize the
dye
in a tank
filled with fishing line.
the dye penetrates all of the
strands for an even dye job.
these fishing lines
go through a different
process.
they unwind
through metal eyelets
into a tray
of yellow silicone resin.
this proprietary resin makes
the line abrasion-resistant.
it will be less likely to
break
if dragged across a surface
like a rock.
next, the line
travels through an oven
to cure the resin.
it travels over a series
of tensioning rollers
as it exits.
then, the line
goes through an abrasive
eyelet,
which removes
external contaminants.
finally, it's rolled up
by a spool.
now it's over to a test
station.
a technician clamps a piece
of fishing line
in a testing apparatus.
it pulls the fishing line
from both ends until it
breaks.
a gauge measures
the line's breaking point.
it snaps at 118 pounds
of pressure,
exceeding requirements.
with the test piece
of fishing line approved,
an automated system
now transfers the line
to retail-sized spools.
it loads about 450 feet
of line onto each one.
a worker applies a label
with product details
and packages it
in a cardboard box.
it takes about 17 days
to braid, color,
and process a single spool
of synthetic fishing line.
strong but very thin,
it can be cast
and reeled in with ease.
if the fish take the bait,
they
may not be able to get away.
narrator: the applications
for industrial-grade mixers
are limitless.
from construction and
recycling
to food processing
and medical supplies,
mixers chop, crush, and blend
any combination
of dry and wet materials
into a variety
of products or compounds.
this mixer consists of a bin
called a u-trough
and an agitator.
it's controlled
by an interface module
with simple start
and stop buttons.
the agitator shaft
is the main component.
its arms and paddles turn
at a speed
of 10 to 50 rotations
per minute.
a discharge valve
underneath the u-trough
controls the unloading
of the mixture.
first, a hydraulic 40-ton
press
roll-forms a carbon steel
sheet.
the sheet rolls back and forth
under the press
until it takes a "u" shape.
an overhead crane brings
the sheet over to the end
plate
for welding.
a worker spot-welds the sheet
to the end plate.
then, he makes a continuous
weld
on the end plate
along the inside
and outside of the sheet.
a high-definition plasma
cutter burns paddle shapes
into a stainless-steel plate.
the extreme heat of the plasma
cuts right through the steel,
making very precise lines
and angles.
then, the paddles
go to a forming press.
the 150-ton press
pushes the plate down on a
die.
steel is a formable metal,
so it can bend
without cracking or breaking.
a slight curvature
in the paddles
will maximize the lifting
and scooping effect
of the agitator.
a machinist turns the agitator
main shaft.
it takes a very hard
and resistant material
to machine
such a massive steel shaft.
this tungsten carbide insert
can resist high temperatures
and maintain
a sharp cutting edge.
the machinist
measures the diameter.
he cuts a groove into the end
of the shaft
using a stagger-tooth
side-mill cutter.
this groove, called a keyseat,
is designed
to lock the agitator
to the mixer's drive gearbox.
machining of the agitator
requires extreme precision.
the shaft must fit
into the drive gearbox
and match its drive key slot.
a worker assembles arms
and paddles to an agitator
shaft
mounted inside a u-trough.
he bolts the arms
onto the shaft.
he tightens the nuts
with a pneumatic torque driver
and assembles paddles
to the arms.
both the paddles
and arms are angled.
machine slots in the paddles
allow clearance adjustment.
next, a worker rotates
the assembled shaft and arms
to check the clearance
between the paddles
and u-trough walls.
a welder creates a solid
stainless-steel agitator shaft
for a larger mixer.
he welds the base of the arms
to the shaft
and grinds down
the welding profile
to obtain a uniform shape.
welded agitators are often
used
in food processing
because they
make cleaning easier.
now, workers attach an
electric
motor to the mixer.
they mount the drive assembly
on the agitator shaft.
a taper bushing centers
the drive gearbox on the
shaft.
fasteners secure the bushing
in place,
locking the agitator
shaft into the drive.
a worker installs a safety
grate
on top of the mixer
and closes the covers.
then, he installs
air-pressure regulators.
these supply air
to the main shaft seals.
air purge seals prevent
product loss or contamination.
air lines connect
the pressure regulators
to both ends
of the main shaft agitator.
the mixer fits on a support
frame for easy access
to the discharge valve.
it's equipped
with clamps, safety latches,
and a control panel,
which includes
an emergency stop button.
narrator: baking soda
is a white crystalline powder.
when added to dough,
it reacts with the acidic
ingredients to form bubbles,
giving cakes and cookies
a light and fluffy structure.
it's also used
in livestock feed,
fire extinguishers,
and detergents.
baking soda is also known
as sodium bicarbonate.
it can be produced
through a chemical process,
or it can be mined
from the ground.
large mineral deposits
exist in northwest colorado,
left behind as lakes
evaporated
millions of years ago.
mine operators
dissolve the sodium
bicarbonate
underground using hot brine.
the brine is a mix
of the minerals and water
left over from prior
processing.
they pipe
the higher-concentration brine
to a processing facility
about a mile away.
the brine collects
in a holding tank outside
and flows through pipes
into the facility as needed.
inside, a technician
tests the liquid
and confirms that the level of
sodium bicarbonate is
adequate.
then, the brine
flows through several tanks,
where heat exchangers
gradually cool it.
this causes
the sodium-bicarbonate brine
to crystallize, making
the granules larger and
heavier.
the crystals sink
to the bottom of the last
tank.
this forms a mixture
of brine and crystals.
they pump this mixture into
a device called a hydroclone.
the hydroclone spins out
the brine through the center.
the crystals gravitate
to the sides
and sink to the bottom.
this creates
a sodium-bicarbonate slurry.
it has a meringue-like
consistency.
the slurry is about 40% sodium
bicarbonate at this point.
a lot of water has been
removed,
but there's still
work to be done.
as the dewatering continues,
the system recaptures
spent liquid
and pipes it back into the
mine
to dissolve more minerals.
the slurry goes for another
spin, this time in a
centrifuge.
it wrings out more water,
transforming the slurry
into something called wet
cake.
wet cake is
95% sodium bicarbonate.
next, the wet cake travels
to a mixer
that blends dry sodium
bicarbonate powder into it.
the dry powder brings
the moisture content down to
3%.
next, the wet cake makes a
quick
trip through this dryer
to remove
the remaining moisture,
leaving pure baking soda.
the baking soda now
shakes through three tiers
of vibrating screens.
the crystals are sorted by
size,
producing
several different grades.
from brine to powder,
it's been quite a journey.
it's time to determine
how this naturally mined
baking soda measures up.
a technician dissolves some
of the baking soda in water.
he adds an acid to neutralize
the sodium bicarbonate.
this allows him
to measure its purity.
he also places the different
grades of baking soda
in a screening device.
it vibrates to shake the
granules through perforations,
verifying that the crystals
have
been correctly graded by size.
with the lab's approval,
this baking soda
is ready for the marketplace.
a robotic arm picks up the bag
and transfers it to a fill
station with a scale below.
the scale signals
when there's 55 pounds
of baking soda in a bag,
prompting the fill nozzle
to shut off.
these 55-pound bags will be
sold
to commercial bakeries
and companies that use large
amounts of baking soda daily.
it will no doubt
rise to the occasion.
narrator: when an 18-wheeler
has an accident
or construction equipment
breaks down,
you need to call in the big
guns
to haul it away for repair.
large tow trucks are equipped
with specialized tools
to recover
and transport massive
vehicles.
this tow truck
can haul a vehicle
as large as a semitruck.
the towing apparatus
is called the underlift.
this is one of four
outriggers.
these legs stabilize
the tow truck
when the using
the recovery boom.
this extendible boom is
equipped
with dual-wire ropes and hooks
to retrieve a vehicle
that's gone off the road.
these hydraulically powered
towing and recovery machines
are made up of 2,500 parts
cut from steel sheets.
the parts are cut
by one of two types
of computer-guided machines --
a high-pressure water-jet
cutter,
as we're seeing here,
or a laser cutter.
workers position the parts
in an assembly fixture...
then tack-weld them together.
tack welding is an initial
welding in select spots,
just to hold the parts
together
until a robot
does the final welding.
next, workers
sandblast the welded
component.
this preps the surface
for painting.
they apply one coat
of epoxy primer...
then one coat of polyurethane
automotive paint.
the paint dries
in about two hours
and fully cures
in about two days.
workers hook up all of the
hydraulically powered
components
to this testing machine.
if everything
functions properly,
workers connect permanent
hydraulic lines.
to assemble the recovery boom,
they install hydraulic
cylinders
that will move it up and down,
a winch that winds and unwinds
the thick wire ropes,
and an enormous ring gear
that enables the boom
to rotate 360 degrees.
then,
they attach the extendible
boom.
it's secured
with massive steel pins.
workers also attach he
underlift
at the back
and the four stabilizing
outriggers underneath.
this completes the towing
and recovery unit.
now they attach it
to a prebuilt truck.
steel mounting plates
are bolted to the truck's
frame.
the towing-and-recovery unit
is then welded to those
plates.
workers bolt aluminum tool
cabinets
to the side
of the truck's frame.
inside the cabinet,
they make the wiring
connections
for the emergency lights
and other electrical
components.
they install the electronic
control panel
that the driver uses
to operate everything.
the control panel monitors
oil temperature,
hydraulic pressure,
and other important
indicators.
they also install a set
of control handles
to give the driver
the option of manual
operation.
once everything is hooked up,
they perform a quality
control inspection.
this factory
makes several models,
ranging from a light-duty
tow truck...
...to one like this, designed
to haul the heaviest trucks
and machinery.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at
sciencechannel.com/howitsmade.