[ beeping ]
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator: spiral stairs
were part of a strategy
to defend the towers
of medieval castles.
attackers had to
climb single-file
and couldn't storm
the castle all at once.
and at the top of the stairs,
the guardsmen could more easily
maneuver their swords,
giving them the upper hand.
spiral stairs take people
to the next level
without taking up
a lot of space.
they're compact, and with
their corkscrew curvature,
they can also be
architectural features.
production starts with
the steel hubs
cut to the desired riser height.
a worker files
the sharp edges smooth
and drills a threaded hole
which will be used to fasten
the treads in place.
a computer-driven plasma system
cuts through a sheet of steel
to produce the pie-shaped
stair treads.
a worker nestles a tread
to the hub
and clamps them
in a weld fixture.
he also clamps
structural supports
to the base of the tread.
with everything in
the right configuration,
he welds the supports
to the tread and the hub.
he'll make 12 of these hub
and tread assemblies.
he chips off the weld slag
for cleaner seams.
a team slides the hub
and tread assemblies
on to the center pole
and rotates them
to the correct position.
the design geometry
dictates the rotation.
once rotated correctly,
the workers fasten the hubs
to the pole
and add a platform
for the top step.
a baluster spins in a lathe,
as tools cut it to length
and round the end
to the correct diameter.
the operator measures
the diameter.
he inserts the rounded end
in a dye
that carves the thread into it.
a worker welds a steel cup
just above the threaded part
of the baluster.
this cup will support
the baluster
once it's been installed
on the thread.
he grinds the weld scale
from the cup.
he inserts the baluster
through holes
in a metal spacer in the tread.
he screws a nut on to the end
to secure it.
using rollers now, another
worker twists long strips
of metal into spiraling
hand rails that match
the rise of the stairs.
he fits the rail
to the top balusters
and clamps it in place.
he then welds the balusters
to the rail.
he adds more railing until
it spirals all the way down
to the first step.
the team secures it
to the platform.
the spiral staircase's metal
structure is now complete.
it's ready for
the wooden accents.
a worker applies glue
to pieces of red oak.
he'll use two of them
to make one stair tread.
he clamps two tread sets in
a fixture while the glue sets.
he inserts a shim
and tightens the clamp
to apply downward pressure.
once the glue has cured,
a planer shaves the tread
perfectly flat
and to the desired thickness.
after refining the profile,
a worker rounds the edge of
the stair tread using a router.
after gluing strips of wood
together to create
a curved railing,
he sands the excess adhesive,
and with a file,
removes more of the glue.
he turns the railing over
and carves a groove in the wood.
this will enable the railing
to be installed
over the metal rail support.
he adds some detailing
along the edge.
a team then fits
the wooden railing
to the metal support structure.
all of the rail sections
fit together perfectly.
after the pre-fit,
they remove the railing
and sculpt the edges
to be rounder.
the rounded edges complement
the overall spiral design.
a worker pre-fits the wooden
treads to the metal structure
and then disassembles
the entire spiral staircase
for painting and staining.
the spiral stairs are then ready
for reassembly in the building
they were designed for.
they'll definitely add a certain
twist to the interior design.
♪
narrator:
originating in the middle east,
pita bread has been around
for thousands of years.
today, its popularity continues
to grow around the globe.
part of its appeal
is its versatility.
people can stuff
their pita's pockets,
use it as a sandwich wrap,
or slice it for dipping.
pita bread may be flat,
but that doesn't mean
it's boring.
anyone can use pita
to make any number
of interesting
lunchtime combinations.
making pita bread starts
with silos full of flour.
a blower system delivers the
flour to an automated sifter.
the sifter shakes the flour
through three levels of mesh
to filter out impurities.
magnets extract
any metal contaminants.
workers prepare a pre-mix
of sugar, salt, yeast,
and preservatives.
they combine these ingredients
with the sifted flour
in a big mixer and add water.
the mixer is equipped
with numerous bars
that rotate horizontally
to blend the ingredients.
the operator opens the mixer
and spins it one more time
to eject the dough into a bin.
he rolls the bin
to the next station.
here the pita dough
goes into a hopper.
and from there,
it drops into a machine
called a dough divider.
♪
this machine turns big chunks
of dough into many small blobs.
to do this, it forces the dough
through a round hole,
and a guillotine blade chops it
to the correct thickness.
the dough blobs ride a conveyor
and pass under a roller
that flattens them.
flour from an overhead sifter
dusts the dough blobs
to keep them from sticking
to the machinery.
each one of these flattened
dough blobs
will eventually become a pita.
the round pieces of dough
now ride
a conveyor up to a warm zone.
over a period of 15 minutes,
the yeast ferments,
causing the dough to rise.
out of the fermentation station,
a roller flattens
the pita dough segments again.
they're now ready
to be rolled very thin
in a process known as sheeting.
the next roller presses
the pita dough much thinner.
rolling it in one direction
makes the dough segments
oval-shaped.
the oval pitas ride by a pusher
that now shoves them
towards the final roller.
it rolls the dough in the other
direction to round out the shape
and make it even thinner.
perfectly round and thin,
the pitas now travel up to
another fermentation operation.
inside, the temperature
is toasty.
it's warm enough to reawaken
the yeast
and cause the dough
to rise again.
conveyors move in criss-cross
directions to take the pitas
back and forth.
this zig-zagging journey
lasts about 15 minutes.
when the pitas emerge
from the chamber,
they have thickened up
substantially.
they head into an oven
where the magic happens.
the oven's temperature is
between 750
and 930 degrees fahrenheit.
they spend just
15 seconds in it.
this flash-baking causes
the water in the dough
to turn to steam.
the steam puffs the pitas,
creating pockets inside.
the pitas then travel
on conveyors
for a 20 minute cool down.
as they cool, they deflate.
the process has created pockets
in the pitas.
once sliced open,
the pockets can be stuffed
to create sandwiches.
workers stack the pitas
six high for packaging.
the next conveyor delivers
the stacks into the clutch
of an automated arm.
just ahead, a burst of air
opens a bag
and the arm inserts
the pitas into it.
at the same time, it pushes
the bag on to the next conveyor.
moving forward, another device
automatically twists
the open end of the bag.
the device applies
a plastic lock tab
to the twisted end of the bag,
sealing the pita breads inside.
the bags pass by
a metal detector,
and then they're on their way
to the supermarket.
this pita bread has taken
45 minutes to make and package,
but it should enable lunch
to come together very quickly.
♪
narrator:
installing exhaust headers
will add extra power
from a car's engine.
they bolt on to the engine,
giving each cylinder
its own exhaust pipe
leading to the collector,
which connects to the car's
main exhaust pipe.
that's more efficient than
having all the cylinders exhaust
into a common manifold.
a header draws out significantly
more spent exhaust gasses
after combustion, leaving room
for a greater amount
of new gas and fresh air
to enter the cylinder
for the next combustion cycle.
headers are made of steel
or stainless steel.
a worker uses a roll cutter
to slice tubes into nearly
6-inch-long pieces
for the header's collector.
a forming tool on a press
stretches one side
of the collector outward.
then the worker places the same
side on an end-forming machine,
which shapes it like
a four-leaf clover.
he slips a flange over
the unshaped side
and widens that side to create
the ball portion
of the gasketless ball
and socket connection
to the car's main exhaust pipe.
meanwhile, another worker
roll cuts narrower tubes
into 32-inch-long pieces to make
the header's primary tubes,
the ones that attach at the top
to engine's cylinders.
a worker slides a tube
on to a mandrel,
then the computer-guided
mandrel bender
bends the tube in four places.
the mandrel fills the inside
of the tube
just up to the bend point,
preventing the tube from
compressing or collapsing
under pressure.
the header they're making here
is for a four-cylinder engine,
so it has four primary tubes.
an eight-cylinder engine
requires a pair of headers,
whereas a six-cylinder engine
requires a pair
of three-tube headers.
a worker trims the bent
primary tubes
to the required length
with a bandsaw.
the sawed edges of the tube
are ragged,
so the next step
is to grind them smooth.
♪
after grinding, the edge
no longer looks like this.
♪
workers heat the top end
of the tube
with a torch
to soften the steel.
♪
they place the end
into an end-forming machine.
the machine shapes the end
to match the top profile
of the cylinder,
to which the tube
will be mounted.
cylinder profiles vary
from engine to engine,
so workers simply change
the forming tool on the machine.
a worker clamps the header
flange with its four
exhaust ports on to
an assembly jig and positions
the top end of
a primary tube in each port.
he inserts the bottom ends
into the four-leaf-clover-shaped
collector.
he then welds the top end
of each tube
to its exhaust port
on the header flange.
then he welds a tag
with the company name
on to one of the tubes.
finally, he welds
the bottom end of the tubes
to the collector.
♪
the header's three sections --
flange, tubes,
and collector -- are now fused.
the worker grinds down the weld
around the ports
until it's nearly flush.
the remaining bit of weld
material encircling the port
will act
as a seal to prevent leakage.
during the welding,
some welding material drips
into the header flange's
openings,
so a worker reams
the bolt holes with a drill
and grinds
the edges of each port.
he mounts the header on
the corresponding engine's
cylinder head to make sure bolt
holes are sufficiently cleared.
then he runs a torch over all
the joints to check the welds.
the flame would shoot through
any hole in a weld,
alerting them to repair it.
this factory applies one of two
finishes on its exhaust headers.
the basic one is a coat
of black water-based paint
sprayed on and air-dried.
it prevents surface rust
from forming
while the part is warehoused.
the higher-end finish is an
aerospace-grade ceramic coating,
available in black or silver.
this baked-on finish protects
the headers from rust
for many years
of high-performance driving.
♪
narrator:
this may look like ivory,
but it's actually limestone.
it looks as though
it's a sculpted work of art,
but it's actually molded.
how does one mold limestone?
200 years ago, some people
in france figured out how,
and their descendents are still
molding limestone artwork today.
this unique art form exists
because, two centuries ago,
a family in france discovered
springs amid volcanic rock,
springs with water so rich
in calcium carbonate
that it petrified into stone.
that is limestone.
the family carved out caves,
then invented a way
to capture the calcium carbonate
and mold sculptures with it.
the descendents of the family
continue that tradition today.
the springwater contains
two grams of calcium carbonate
per liter and a lot
of iron oxide,
which makes the water orange.
the original troughs
direct the water
on to a bed of wood shavings.
the shavings trap
the iron oxide,
and the calcium carbonate floats
to the surface.
in the workshop,
the owner of the company --
the seventh generation
of the founding family --
makes the mold.
he heats something called
gutta-percha
in a pot of water
to soften it up.
gutta-percha is a natural latex
made from the sap
of the gutta tree.
once it's soft, he weighs out
the required amount
using the workshop's
original scale.
then he kneads it to force out
trapped air
and make it more malleable.
after forming it into a ball,
he places it in an old press
made my his great-grandfather.
the press shapes
the gutta-percha
into a rectangle measuring
7-by-10 inches.
after cooling in the press
for 30 minutes,
the gutta-percha has hardened
just enough to maintain
the rectangular shape.
he removes it from the press
and places a silicone-designed
template on top.
he cuts the gutta-percha
to the shape of the template.
♪
he places the gutta-percha
on top of a pattern
created by an artist.
he places the template
on the gutta-percha,
then a plank of wood
on top of that.
he puts the entire assembly
under an old screw press.
an hour later, he removes
the assembly from the press
and gently separates the layers.
the artwork design is now
transferred from the pattern
to the gutta-percha.
he sets it aside to cool
to a hard state.
when the work of art
is either too wide or high
to fit into
the traditional screw press,
the artisan then sculpts
the pattern out of clay.
once the clay hardens, he coats
it in silicone to make the mold.
this modern mold-making
technique is a bit trickier
because silicone
can't be reheated
and reworked like gutta-percha.
the silicone takes about
24 hours
to harden into a flexible mold.
a silicone mold can be used
only once.
and because it's so flexible,
it has to sit on a support tray
so that it doesn't buckle
when filled or moved.
now it's time to mold
the limestone.
a craftsman positions
the molds under these
liquid limestone waterfalls.
the carbonic gas in the liquid
gradually evaporates,
leaving accumulating deposits of
calcium carbonate in the molds.
an artisan moves every mold
to a new position daily
so that the dripping water
hits all parts of it.
artwork just one 1/5 of an inch
thick requires
six months under the fountain.
artwork 4/5 of an inch thick
requires two years.
to extract the limestone artwork
from a traditional mold,
the artisan immerses it
in hot water
to soften the gutta-percha so
that he can gently peel it off.
every intricate detail
of the design
in the gutta-percha
is now replicated in limestone.
this molded rock is as strong
and hard as marble.
to extra the artwork
from a silicone mold,
an artisan removes the support
tray and lifts off the silicone.
the company has more than 500
artwork patterns in stock
dating back to 1821.
not all the molded limestone
looks the same.
the artisans can tailor
the shade from white to ivory
by controlling
how much iron oxide
they remove from the water.