♪♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: in the first half
of the 20th century,
power steering
was not an option.
prototypes were too expensive
for production.
during world war ii,
the british and american armies
began to use power steering
in heavy vehicles
like armored cars,
and auto makers soon began
adding it to passenger vehicles.
these hydraulic steering pumps
are the steering muscle
in muscle cars,
providing a power assist
to give the driver more control.
using computer software,
manufacturers design the pumps
to fit specific
classes of vehicles.
they print a plastic model
using a 3-d printer.
this is a time-lapse
video of the process.
the designer removes the
plastic model and he sends it,
along with the computer design,
to a casting facility,
which produces aluminum
pump-housing parts.
back at the factory,
a worker mounts
12 of the castings in a machine
with computer-controlled
tooling.
he activates the system,
and it moves the rack
of castings into position.
the tools machine
the face of the castings.
they bore center-bearing holes
and drill
threaded holes for bolts.
this is precision work,
which will now be double-checked
by a device known as
a coordinate measuring machine.
a worker clamps the pump
housing in the machine.
then, a ruby-tipped probe
scans its dimensions.
the machine analyzes
the information.
it verifies that every part
of the housing meets
the precise specifications.
♪♪
with that confirmation,
he unclamps the part.
this is the pump housing in the
various stages of production.
♪♪
other tools turn a solid
aluminum dowel
into a fitting for
the pump's pressure bore.
they sculpt the circumference
and carve a complex
geometry in the center
for controlling the flow
of power steering fluid.
another tool carves the thread
to screw the fitting
into the pressure bore,
and the final one drills
the fluid bypass hole.
a blue anodized coating
protects it from corrosion.
a worker now locks the pump
housing in a honing machine.
the machine floods the pressure
relief bore with lubricant
as the stone hones the inner
diameter to a precise tolerance.
he then transfers the pump
housing to a press.
he inserts a bearing and shaft
in the center bore.
he places an aluminum tool
over the bearing and shaft
to align them correctly
as he manually presses
them into the bore.
once the bearing has been
solidly entrenched,
he removes the tool.
he inserts a metal
snap ring in a groove
to retain the bearing and shaft.
he turns the power steering pump
over an installs o-rings
to seal the pressure section.
♪♪
then the worker
installs the cam ring
and the rotor with the veins.
as the rotor spins,
the veins will move in and out,
collecting hydraulic fluid.
this process adds pressure,
taking the load off
the steering wheel.
the worker installs
this critical sub-assembly
in the pump housing.
he screws the device in place
in the four corners.
♪♪
he turns the power
steering pump over
and seals the end
of the pressure bore
with an aluminum plug
and copper washer.
♪♪
he now tucks the pressure
relief valve
in the open part
of the pressure bore.
he secures it with the special
flow fitting
we saw machined earlier on.
♪♪
he tightens the fitting
with a torque wrench.
he turns the power
steering pump onto its side.
he attaches a fitting
to the intake port
for the hydraulic fluid.
the power steering pump
is now equipped
with all the working parts.
here's a look at
the transformation.
a display model with a cutout
offers a peak inside.
at the test station,
a technician makes
all the connections
and runs it as if it was
in an actual racecar.
a computer measures its
performance and confirms
that it meets all
the technical requirements.
the power steering pump
is now ready for the twists
and turns of
professional racing.
♪♪
narrator: across asia,
rice bowl meals
are an enduring tradition.
by combining protein
and vegetable elements
with rice in a bowl,
people have a meal.
it's asian comfort food,
and somehow it just tastes
better in a bowl.
and people around the world
are discovering
the appeal of these
one-bowl meals.
asian bowl meals
start with the rice.
then people add
whatever they want.
at food bars like this,
there's any number of choices.
the bowls can be served up fast,
and the food is healthy.
because there are many
possible combinations,
these one-bowl meals
never get boring.
preparations start
with the rice.
this food worker measures
enough for 40 portions.
after rinsing the grains
repeatedly,
he adds it to a rice cooker.
he then measures the water
for cooking.
he adds it to the cooker.
it will steam the grains so they
cook uniformly for one hour.
while the rice is cooking,
the food worker
then pours peeled garlic cloves
into a food processor.
he adds a half cup
of vegetable oil.
the garlic will flavor several
dishes in the asian food bar.
the food processor chops the
garlic to a fine consistency.
using a mandolin
vegetable slicer,
he slices slivers of carrots.
along with chopped onions,
the carrots will enhance
the flavor of fried rice.
he now removes some rice
from the cooker,
in order to make fried rice.
he separates the grains
so they'll fry more uniformly.
♪♪
the food worker
is now ready to fry.
he heats the wok
to a very high temperature.
he adds cooking oil,
and it starts to sizzle.
he tosses in the carrot slivers,
chopped onion, garlic
and frozen peas.
he constantly stirs
the ingredients,
and the flavors
sweeten and deepen.
he turns down the heat
a bit an adds the rice.
he mixes the rice with the other
ingredients as the cooking
continues at
a slightly lower temperature.
he measures the temperature.
for food safety reasons,
it needs to be over
143 degrees fahrenheit.
the food worker pours soy sauce
onto the hot wok.
it trickles down
to permeate the rice,
adding flavor and color.
that completes the fried rice
component of the food bar.
next up are the vegetable
and protein choices.
the food worker cubes
sushi-grade tuna.
it will be marinated
with a spicy saucy shortly.
he places the tuna
in a food bar container.
he peels cucumber
and then juliennes it.
the cucumber will be a raw
food choice
that will offset
the strong flavor of the tuna.
the food worker then prepares
the tuna's spicy marinade.
he adds chili sauce
and a smaller amount
of chili oil to mayonnaise.
it's hot stuff.
♪♪
a seaweed salad dish
is another refreshing choice
that will cool the palate.
he adds the chili
mayonnaise to the tuna.
and he turns up the heat
a little more
with some extra chili oil.
a thorough mixing completely
saturates the raw fish
with the spicy sauce.
next, the food worker
prepares the dressing
for a cabbage salad.
he starts with
a white miso paste.
a generous amount
of soy sauce follows.
sushi vinegar and vegetable oil
are the next ingredients.
after adding some sesame oil,
he blends all the components.
he coats the shredded cabbage
with the miso dressing.
he sprinkles black sesame seeds
onto the cabbage salad.
teriyaki beef
is the next option.
the main ingredients are shaved
filet steak, chopped ginger,
and shredded onion.
the food worker sautés the onion
and ginger
to provide a flavor base.
he adds the shaved steak,
and as it cooks,
it takes up the essence
of the onion and ginger.
♪♪
the soy-based teriyaki sauce
provides
the final layer of flavor.
with this dish now complete,
it's time for the fun part --
mixing and matching components
for the asian food bowl.
narrator: there was a time
when an elegant walking cane
was a status symbol
for fashionable gentlemen.
today, a cane is no longer
considered an accessory,
but rather a utilitarian
medical aid
for people with mobility issues.
however, one can
still find canes
which combine both
function and fashion.
walking canes can indeed
be stylish,
with straight or crook handles
made of exotic wood or bone,
elegant knob handles,
or elaborate figurative handles.
this family enterprise
has been hand-crafting
walking canes since 1909.
making a crook handle requires
bending the handle material.
after heating a curved steel
form in a fire,
workers insert a square stick
of ebony in a steel spring
and mount it on the central
axis of the machine.
the clamp the machine's
guide wheel against the form,
then clamp the part of the stick
that will remain straight.
using their body weight,
the worker forces the
machine's lever forward,
wrapping the top part
of the stick
around the hot,
curved form.
♪♪
it's critical to do this slowly
to prevent the wood
from snapping.
workers then lock the bent stick
against the form with a brace...
and remove it from the machine.
♪♪
they set it aside for a week.
one week later, they remove
the brace and spring
and mount the curved
stick on a lathe.
as the stick spins,
a carriage moves a saw down
the straight part of the cane,
known as the shaft,
reducing the diameter
and rounding it out.
this is the shaft before
and after this step.
♪♪
a worker runs the handle
against a coarse grit
sanding belt to pare it down
and begin rounding it out.
he uses a router to refine
the shape and works on the
harder-to-access inner
part of the curve.
♪♪
once the handle is rounded,
and its diameter equal
to that of the shaft,
he performs
a final fine sanding.
♪♪
then he polishes the entire cane
with polishing compound
against a cotton buffing wheel.
♪♪
slowly but surely, this makes
the ebony sleek and lustrous.
♪♪
all wooden canes --
these here are made of maple --
warp a bit during woodworking.
another worker heats the cane
to make the wood flexible,
then inserts it
in a v-shaped holder
and peers down
the length of the shaft
to assess the direction
of the deformity.
then he manually
straightens out the cane.
these canes undergo a final step
to add a decorative feature.
a worker sands off some wood
on the crook handle,
creating a flat, oval surface.
he applies glue, then he adheres
a piece of cow horn.
once the glue dries,
he grinds the horn flush
with the surrounding wood.
♪♪
the result is a horn inlay.
wooden canes
also need protection
against moisture and wear.
the factory submerges them
in varnish for a half hour,
so that the varnish
deeply penetrates
the pores of the wood.
hanging the canes to dry
would leave varnish drip marks,
so the factory uses this
ingenious pulley-driven
contraption that dates back
to the 1900s.
with its wood wheels
and leather belts,
the machine continuously
rotates the canes
to prevent the wet varnish
from dripping as it air dries.
that's how to make
a wooden crook-handled cane.
as you'll see next,
fancier walking canes
require additional steps.
narrator: whether it's decorated
with ornately carved wood,
sleek horn or gleaning metal,
brandishing a fancy walking cane
is like wearing
a bold pair of eyeglasses.
what might otherwise
be a bland necessity
can be elevated
to a fashion statement.
elegant canes can have
horn or knob handles,
or silver-plated
figural handles.
the figural ones are molded
two at a time.
after placing a screw
mechanism in each cavity,
a worker closes the mold
and places it in
a centrifuge machine.
as the mold spins,
he ladles pewter into a funnel
that feeds the channels leading
into the mould cavities.
the centrifugal force shoots
the pewter onto the cavity walls
in an even layer,
where it cools and solidifies
in about five minutes.
then he stops the machine
and removes the mould.
the worker opens the mold
and extracts
the two pewter castings,
each with it's screw mechanism
securely embedded.
one is a cobra handle.
the other is a dog
and boar handle.
they require
a bit of refinement,
so the next step is
to remove the excess metal
with a rotating wire brush.
a worker then shines
up the surface
with some polishing compound
and a cloth buffing wheel.
♪♪
he washes off the
polishing compound
and silver-plates the pewter.
the handle will top an equally
elegant ebony shaft.
a worker places the square stick
of ebony in a lathe,
which rounds it.
♪♪
the shaft goes through several
sanding and polishing steps.
then a worker drills
a two-inch-deep hole
in the top of it.
he puts some glue in the hole
and screws in the handle.
♪♪
if silver-plated cobras
aren't your style,
how about a handle
made of white cow horn?
first, a worker heats all but
the tip of the horn in a fire.
this destroy the nerves in the
bone inside the horn's shell.
this horn will be shaped
into a crooked handle
using the same bending machine
the workers use
for wood crook handles.
the base of the horn is hot,
so they use a small block
of wood as a buffer.
after clamping the machine's
guide wheel
against the middle of the horn,
they use their body weight
to move the lever forward,
and wrap the top half of the
horn against the curved form.
♪♪
before heating the horn,
the worker drilled
a small hole through its tip.
now he inserts a thin steel wire
through that hole and ties
the wire tightly around
the opposite side
to hold the horn
to the round form.
he sets it aside for a week.
a horn handle undergoes the same
multi-step sanding process
as a wood handle, however,
a worker drills
a hole into the bottom
and screws in an aluminum rod.
this makes the handle easier
to hold while sanding.
♪♪
the worker removes the final
traces of the outer layer
with a router and finalizes
the crook's shape.
♪♪
he removes the handle
from the metal rod
and finishes it off
with a fine sanding.
the horn surface is now
as smooth as silk.
♪♪
he then polishes the handle
on a cotton buffing wheel
using a polishing compound
specially formulated for horn.
that brings out
the color and sheen.
then the worker screws
and exotic-wood shaft
into the same hole
used for the metal rod.
this fashionable cane, which has
taken 4-6 hours to craft,
is ready to be modeled
on the walkway.