[ beeping ]
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator: the use of glass
as an artistic medium
dates back to ancient egypt.
despite the obvious fragility
of glass sculptures,
this art form
has an enduring appeal.
the transparency of glass
often has a ghost-like quality.
they're tangible works of art
that are skillfully crafted.
with this glass sculpture
of a horse,
the artist's two passions
come together --
art and horsemanship.
the artist takes inspiration
from her horse,
observing the swell
of his muscles as he romps
in order to create the same
sense of movement in glass.
she then draws a series
of sketches of the horse
in different stances.
these sketches are
an artistic study.
they help her work out
the sculpture's form
before actually creating one.
she cleans solid glass rods
to prepare them for sculpting.
this is borosilicate glass,
which is more resistant
to thermal shock
than other kinds of glass.
she brings the glass into the
flame of a torch to soften it.
once softened, she can fuse
two of the rods together.
then using tweezers and flat,
knife-like tools,
she sculpts the glass
into the shape
of the horse's hips and legs.
she works quickly so the glass
doesn't have a chance
to cool and fracture.
she adds a smaller piece of
glass and forms it into a tail.
she constantly turns the glass
as she works it to make sure
it looks good from all angles.
she melts glass in front of
the hips to build up the body
and shape the horse's belly,
back, and chest.
this is intensive
and precision work.
the piece must be exposed
to a well-adjusted flame
and constantly moved
so it doesn't become too hot
and melt too much.
she adds glass to the front
and sculpts the shoulders
and part of the front legs.
she removes a little piece
of extra glass.
she deposits the sizzling,
unwanted bit in water
to cool it down
and dispose of it safely.
she does more work
on the front legs.
she'll refine them and form
hooves later,
but now she bakes the partially
sculpted glass horse in a kiln.
this is the first annealing,
which realigns molecules
to prevent cracking.
she forms the head and mane
separately from the body.
this is more intricate work.
the features are
much more detailed,
so she uses smaller tools.
once she shapes the eye sockets,
she melts little blobs
of black glass into them.
she sculpts the eyes
with a flat knife.
she carves creases above them
to create an eyelid effect.
she adds glass for the ears.
then, using a tool called
a masher,
she pinches the ears
to squeeze them thinner.
she heats them again.
this process can cause the ears
to stick together,
so she cuts them
to separate them.
she curls the ears
using tweezers
and tweaks their position
on the horse's head.
she melts the base
of the head to the body,
and they become one.
she fuses more glass to the back
to craft a mane,
and after another annealing,
she returns to the legs.
she softens them with
a flame again
and adds definition
to the fetlock joints.
she cuts the tips to create
a more level surface.
she melts black glass
on to the ends of the legs
and sculpts it into
the shapes of hooves.
with a series of tools,
she tweaks each hoof
until she's satisfied
this glass horse
will stand
the way she wants it to.
after another annealing,
she shines a polarized light
through the sculpture
and examines it for stresses
that could compromise
its structure.
finding none, this galloping
work of glass art is complete.
it's been made with great care
and caring.
♪
narrator: to turn a regular car
into a race car,
one needs to change the pulley
system mounted to its engine.
factory-installed pulley systems
are heavy,
and their pulley-size ratios
are designed for driving
at low speeds.
a racing pulley system
is lightweight
and has pulley ratios
for high-speed driving.
replacing the factory-installed
pulley system on a car engine
with one of these
racing pulley systems
is like putting
a car on steroids.
the components of this system
are determined
by what the engine
already comes with.
for example,
if the engine's water pump
is too heavy for racing,
this company makes
a lightweight one
along with a size-appropriate
pulley to go with it.
to make a pulley,
an automatic saw
cuts a patty off
an aluminum bar.
workers then mount the patty
on a computer-guided lathe.
as the lathe spins,
multiple tools shape
the patty into a pulley.
the first two tools drill
a hole in the center
and machine the overall shape.
then, this tool bores
the hole to a precise diameter.
this tool carves grooves
along the perimeter
for the pulley belt.
this broaching tool makes
17 vertical grooves
inside the bored hole
corresponding to grooves
on a shaft, locking
the pulley in place.
a worker removes
the partially-formed pulley
from the lathe and mounts it on
a computer-guided mill.
the mill's first tool drills
six round holes.
the next tool reshapes
those holes into triangles
known as windows.
this reduces
the pulley's weight.
the factory sends all pulleys
out to a plating shop
which coats the aluminum
with the hard,
black protective finish
known as anodizing.
this is a different type
of crankshaft pulley.
to make it, the automated saw
first cuts a patty
from a smaller aluminum bar.
then, a worker mounts it
on a computer-guided lathe.
after the first tool
evens out the surface,
this tool drills a hole
through the center.
the next tool enlarges
that hole.
the next tool cuts a female
pattern inside the hole.
a female pattern has grooves
which receive
corresponding protruding areas
of a male pattern.
the lathe then transfers
the patty to another spindle
to expose the opposite side
for machining.
the first tool shapes the back.
♪
the next one cuts
a male pattern.
with a female pattern on
one side and a male pattern
on the other, multiple pulleys
can be stacked and interlocked
to accurately align the system.
the final tool cuts straight
teeth for a square-tooth belt.
when an original engine
component is replaced
with a new, smaller, and lighter
one suitable for racing,
the factory must also make
a smaller, lighter bracket
to mount the new component
to the engine.
a computer-guided mill shapes
a rectangular piece of aluminum
cut by the same automated saw
that cut the patties
for the pulleys.
brackets, like pulleys,
go out for anodizing.
when they come back
to this factory,
they get laser-printed
with a brand name and model.
here's how the pulley system
assembles on this
particular engine.
first, the technician bolts
an adapter
to the harmonic balancer.
the harmonic balancer
is a component
on all engines
that lessens vibration.
next, he installs
the new crankshaft pulley
on to the adapter, attaching it
with a long central bolt
that extends beyond
the harmonic balancer
and into the engine's
crankshaft.
he installs a new lightweight
water pump,
which has a new mounting bracket
for the alternator
attached to its left side.
then, he bolts on a new
water-pump pulley,
which has grooves for two belts.
after mounting a new
lightweight alternator,
he connects the water-pump
pulley to the crankshaft
and power steering pump pulleys
with one belt
and to the alternator pulley
with another belt.
this allows simultaneous
steering, battery charging,
and water circulating
to cool the engine.
♪
narrator: coiled copper devices
called inductors
provide storage
for electrical circuits.
as electrical current
flows through the coils,
a magnetic field is produced.
the inductor stores
the electromagnetic energy
until the circuit
is ready for it.
they're one of the most
important parts in the circuit.
inductors come in many
shapes and sizes.
conductive windings surround
an iron-based core
to provide
temporary energy storage
and to regulate the current
flowing through a circuit.
to make an inductor,
manufactures use
plenty of flame-resistant
insulating material.
they cut sheets of it
to the desired dimensions.
an operator programs this
an automatic shear
to cut the electrical
insulation into long strips.
the hydraulically driven blade
makes clean, straight cuts.
these strips will be used
to insulate the inductor core
and coils.
a worker folds a rectangular
piece of insulation
around an aluminum form
to start the inductor coil.
she tapes the ends together.
she pulls a strip of copper foil
to the insulation.
she's pre-soldered a terminal
to the end of the foil,
and she tapes the terminal
to the insulating material.
she begins to wind
the copper foil
around the insulating
material and stops.
she places one of the long
insulating strips
under the copper foil
and resumes winding.
this prevents short circuits.
she clamps the copper windings
tightly together
and tucks an extra piece of
the insulation under the copper.
she hammers the copper
to flatten any kinks.
she solders a second terminal
to this end of
the copper foil windings.
these terminals will be used
to connect the inductor
to the electrical circuit.
she holds the terminal in place
with a metal dowel
and the soldering iron
until the solder solidifies.
she then cuts the copper strip
along the edge of the terminal.
she applies fiberglass tape
to the soldered terminal joint.
she removes the clamp
and adds more tape
to keep the terminal in place.
she then winds fiberglas tape
around the inside
of the inductor coil.
this outer wrap will prevent
shocks to anyone who might touch
the inductor when it's part
of an electrical circuit.
using a tough nylon block
to absorb the impact,
she hammers the inductor coil
to make it more rectangular.
she removes the coil
from the winding machine.
next up is this hard,
polyester-infused fiberglass.
manufacturers will
ultimately use it
to insulate the core
and fill the gaps.
with a hydraulic shear,
a worker cuts the fiberglass
into strips
that will fit in the core.
another worker clamps two of
the insulated copper windings
side by side.
she inserts a c-shaped
iron core
in one end of
the copper windings
and flips the inductor
assembly over.
she connects
the protruding terminals
with a tin-copper jumper.
she inserts insulating spacers
into both cavities.
these fiberglass spacers will
fill the gap
between the two iron "c's."
she installs the second
half of the iron core.
when alternating current is
applied to the copper windings,
it will create a magnetic field
in this core,
and this is how
the energy will be stored.
she tucks a couple of fiberglass
insulating spacers between
the iron "c's" and the coils.
she drives them deeper
into the inductor.
she loops a stainless-steel band
around the iron core
and pulls it tight
with pneumatic tensioning tool.
she solders the ends of the band
to secure it.
workers immerse the inductor
in a vat of varnish
under vacuum pressure.
the varnish completely seals
the inductor
against dirt and moisture.
this instrument detects any
problems with the insulation.
it's one of several
tests conducted.
if the inductor passes them all,
it's ready for
the electrical circuit.
♪
narrator: a medicine ball has
nothing to do with medicine
but everything
to do with health.
this heavy ball is an effective
workout tool,
available in a variety
of sizes and weights.
it can be used for a wide range
of exercises to improve
strength, coordination,
and cardiovascular fitness.
medicine balls are mass-produced
in a variety of materials.
this company is one
of the few remaining
which craft traditional leather
medicine balls entirely by hand.
the craftsman uses shoe leather,
which is thicker and sturdier
than garment leather.
he places a pattern on top
and cut loosely around it
with the utility knife.
this steel-cutting die
precision-shapes the panel.
the craftsman places it
on the rough-cut panel.
then, with a press, forces the
sharp die through the leather.
the ball is made up of
seven panels like this one.
once he has cut all seven,
he repeats the process
with the circular pattern,
then a circular die.
this cuts two leather circles --
one for each end of the ball.
he cuts identical pieces
from nylon cloth.
these pieces will line the seven
panels and two circles.
for the circle linings,
he first hand-cuts squares.
then he cuts those squares
into circles with the die.
♪
he clamps each lining
to its corresponding
leather piece
and sews them together
with heavy-duty
polyester thread.
this industrial sewing machine
is known as
a cylinder bed machine
because the sewing surface
is cylindrical rather than flat,
which enables working
with a three-dimensional shape.
he takes two of the lined
panels, and one at a time,
puts them back on the press,
this time using a different
cutting die.
it cuts a notch
in eight lace holes.
he then places one of these
panels in an embossing press,
which heat-stamps the brand name
into the leather.
using different dies,
he cuts pieces of vinyl
to reinforce the lace holes,
then sews them to the panels.
this is the only area where
the bright red thread
will be visible.
he sews the panels to each other
until he's formed
a closed circle.
♪
however, he doesn't
yet stitch together
that notched area between
the two sets of lace holes.
first, he sews the lined
leather circles to the ends.
the ball's leather shell
is complete,
but inside out and with a gap
between the lace holes.
the craftsman hands it off to
a colleague
who inverts the shell
and presses the seams against
a metal rod to stretch
and round them out.
now it's time
to stuff the shell.
the worker takes shredded
scraps of leather,
inserts them through the gap
between the lace holes,
then compresses the scraps
with a thick wooden dowel.
once the ball is fully stuffed,
he makes sure the ball
has reached the target weight.
weight precision, however,
is less important
than perfect roundness.
to close up the ball,
he threads a thick rawhide lace
through a large brass needle
and threads it through
the lace holes, pulling tightly.
this is the same sturdy
lacing configuration
that's used on footballs.
♪
he uses two large, thick nails
to properly size the end loops.
♪
then he snips off
the excess lace.
and pokes each end
inside a lace hole.
now he can safely remove
the nails.
with a final pounding here
and there to perfect the shape,
this medicine ball is ready
to pull its weight
in someone's exercise regiment.