♪♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: in the early days of basketball,
players used a soccer ball to play the game.
in 1894, a special basketball was designed.
it was laced and larger, with a circumference
that was about 4 inches greater than the soccer ball.
for players, the new ball was a game changer.
basketballs have evolved,
but one manufacturer still makes
them the old-fashioned way.
these laced brown leather balls
honor the beginnings of the game.
to make this traditional basketball,
a craftsperson cuts eight panels
out of tough american cowhide.
these are rough cuts.
the shape will now be more precisely defined.
he places a sharp steel die on one of the panels.
using a tool known as a clicker press,
he applies pressure to drive the die through the leather
and punch out the shape, cookie-cutter style.
♪♪
he now cuts strips of nylon to a workable size
using a utility knife.
the craftsperson then stacks up
a dozen of the nylon strips.
using the clicker press and same die, he cuts out patterns.
because nylon is softer than leather,
he can punch out many more at once.
he places one of the nylon patterns on the underside
of a leather one and stitches them together.
the nylon backing stabilizes the leather,
preventing stretching.
he now punches lace holes and notches in the nylon-padded
leather panel.
using a template, the craftsperson locates the spot
for an air-valve hole and nicks it with a sharp tool.
♪♪
he places a punch on the nick and strikes it with a hammer
to cut out the air-valve hole.
he clamps a stamp of a company logo in a heated press.
as the stamp heats up, he moves
it into a downward position
and then slides the leather panel under it.
he lowers the hot stamp,
and it burns the company logo into the leather.
♪♪
next, with the liner side up, he sews the basketball panels
together, two at a time at first.
doing this right takes practice.
the craftsperson then trims the polyester thread
and then pounds the thick seam flat with a hammer.
♪♪
he sews vinyl reinforcements to the two panels
that have lace holes.
this will give the laced area of
the basketball more structure.
the stitching will also frame the lace holes
from the leather side to define
and accentuate the lacing.
he adds another strip of vinyl.
this one will protect the inflated bladder
inside the basketball.
he assembles the panels four at a time.
he leaves the section around the lace holes open to provide
an entry point for the inflatable bladder.
he stitches the two halves together,
again working from the inside of the ball.
this completes the basketball's outer casing.
the next craftsperson places the basketball casing
on a steel post and pulls and tugs the casing
to turn it right side out.
he now inserts the synthetic rubber bladder
into the basketball.
he manipulates it so that
the bladder's air valve lines up
with the corresponding hole in the leather.
♪♪
using needle-nose pliers, he grabs the air valve
and pulls it through the hole.
the craftsperson then rearranges
the inner flap so that
it's in a position to protect the bladder from the lacing.
he partially inflates the bladder.
using a thick brass needle, he pulls a rawhide strip
through the holes to neatly lace up the opening.
♪♪
he then fully pressurizes the basketball,
and the pressure from the bladder
holds the laces in place.
♪♪
he simply clips the end of the lace and tucks it in.
a replica of the original,
this leather basketball is ready to bounce back.
narrator: floodgates are sliding gates
that are engineered to resist rushing floodwaters.
when installed at wastewater or water treatment plants
they can be used to control the outflow and inflow of water
in order to make operations more efficient.
that's why floodgates aren't just for emergency situations.
♪♪
sliding floodgates close to varying degrees
making these sliding gates
starts with a stainless-steel plate.
a crane lifts it over to
a conveyor in front of a chamber
that has a laser cutter inside.
the crane releases its suctioning grip,
and the conveyor takes it into the chamber.
it's dark inside, but the laser doesn't need
overhead lighting to do its work.
computer software guides the laser
as it cuts out parts for the floodgate frame.
it also precisely locates holes
for assembly purposes.
workers stack the laser-cut pieces and number them
to categorize them for the next
operation, called forming.
a worker inserts a part in a press brake numerous times
to make multiple bends.
he shapes this particular piece
into the bottom frame
of the floodgate.
♪♪
after forming the side frames the same way,
a worker evenly spaces reinforcements
along the entire length of them.
he tack-welds the reinforcements
to the frame.
using a carpenter's square,
he measures the angle of the
reinforcement to the side frame.
satisfied that each reinforcement
is perfectly perpendicular to the frame,
he does the full welds.
then the worker joins the two side frames
and the bottom rail and welds the structure together.
♪♪
he positions a stainless-steel ceiling frame
at the midpoint of the structure
and welds it in place.
another worker tucks a polyethylene strip
into the frame to seal it.
the strip also has a groove in it
to accommodate the gate's sliding door.
he clamps the strip to the frame
and then taps it with a hammer
to entrench it more firmly into the frame.
he drills through holes in the side frame
to make corresponding holes in the polyethylene strip
and inserts the bolts in the holes.
he screws nuts onto the ends
that protrude from the outside of the frame.
♪♪
he now inserts a polyethylene strip
in the horizontal ceiling frame,
and he marks the strip to indicate the location
for bolt holes.
he removes the strip and drills tapered holes
for countersunk bolts
in the locations he's marked.
he inserts a silicone strip in a recess in the seal,
and he bolts it all together.
♪♪
once the frame is complete,
another worker installs the floodgate's sliding door.
it will be raised and lowered using crank-operated gears.
the next worker closes off an opening used for an unneeded
drive gear with silicone glue and a plastic stopper.
he slides a washer and bearing on the center shaft opening.
he places the upper housing on the bottom one
to enclose the gears.
he secures the gearbox housing with numerous long bolts.
♪♪
next, powerful ridged rollers press a thread
into a very long stainless steel rod.
this rod will serve as the floodgate's operating stem.
it's ready for installation.
a worker bolts one end of the stem to the slide gate
while the other worker threads the gearbox onto the other end.
♪♪
with the crank not yet installed,
he uses a drill to spin the gears
and test the operation of the sliding floodgate.
♪♪
he confirms that the floodgate meets design specifications.
then workers flood the surface below the floodgate with water
and verify that nothing seeps through.
this proves that the floodgate is watertight
and ready to hold strong in the event of an emergency.
narrator: before artists put their brush to their blank canvas,
they have to choose what type of canvas to use --
rudimentary, economical cotton or finer,
more expensive linen, unstretched, or pre-stretched?
if pre-stretched, affixed to a wooden frame
or glued to a wooden panel?
this type of artist canvas is made of fine-weave linen.
it's stretched over and affixed to a wood panel.
the hard backing prevents the linen from flexing
under the paintbrush.
the face of the panel is made of a quarter-inch-thick
baltic birch.
after cutting a piece with the dimensions of
the finished canvas,
a worker cuts pieces of sturdier
basswood for the cradle.
after cutting a long strip in the required width,
he measures and marks the lengths
of the cradle's five parts,
which include four perimeter pieces and a cross brace.
then he cuts the parts.
♪♪
he miters the edges of the perimeter pieces.
that means cutting the ends at a 45-degree angle,
so the pieces mate
when assembled into a rectangle.
♪♪
to assemble the cradle, a worker spreads wood glue
on the mitered edges of the perimeter pieces,
then joins them to form a rectangle,
clamping two of the corners to a 90-degree block
to ensure the angles are perfectly square.
he reinforces the corner joints with v-shaped nails.
♪♪
he removes the clamps and squares
and glues the cross brace across the middle.
♪♪
once the worker checks that the cross brace
is installed squarely,
he nails it to the perimeter.
he applies a line of wood glue on top of the cradle perimeter
and cross brace.
then he places the panel onto the cradle.
the worker sets clamps all around the perimeter,
then puts the cradle aside overnight to let the glue dry.
♪♪
the next day, the worker sands any panel overhang flat,
rendering the edge of the panel
flush with the cradle.
♪♪
they burn the manufacturing information
into the back of the finished panel.
the linen they're using for this
canvas is portrait grade,
the finest and smoothest weave.
it's been primed with linseed oil to allow oil paint
to penetrate enough to adhere but not absorb into the fabric.
he measures and marks the wood panel's dimensions,
adding about 4 inches all around
to have extra linen to wrap around the cradle.
then he cuts along the lines.
the worker centers the cradled panel upside down on the linen
and traces a line around it.
♪♪
he flips the panel right-side up
and coats the surface
with special ph-neutral archival glue
because ordinary adhesives contain acid
which degrades the linen over time.
♪♪
he flips the panel upside down again,
carefully positions it within the trace lines
and presses the panel firmly against the linen.
♪♪
he mounts the assembly on a stretching machine.
canvases must always be stretched
to prevent contraction and expansion
due to changes in humidity.
starting with the longest sides first,
the machine yanks the linen tight
and folds it over the edge of the cradle.
a line of staples secure
the stretched linen to the wood.
after stretching and stapling both long sides,
the worker folds the corners
neatly and staples them as well.
♪♪
then he rotates the canvas to stretch the short sides.
once those are stretched and stapled,
the wood-panel canvas is finished,
and now it's the ready recipient
of artistic inspiration.
narrator: the oldest shoe archaeologists have ever found
is a 5,500-year-old leather hide moccasin
with leather-cord laces.
today we don't have to go hunt an animal to lace our shoes.
we can buy our shoelaces ready-made
in a variety of materials,
styles, lengths and colors.
♪♪
this company produces shoelaces
and shoelace-type drawstrings
in a wide range of materials,
including cotton, rayon and acrylic.
this run is producing polyester shoelaces.
a worker installs cones of fine polyester thread
on what's called a creel,
which feeds the bobbin-winding machines.
she groups the strands from eight cones
and feeds them through one side of one machine
and onto a bobbin.
then she groups the strands from another eight cones
and feeds them through the other side of the machine
onto a second bobbin.
each group of eight strands
will produce one thicker polyester thread.
she programs the machine
to wind a specific length of it.
each cone holds enough fine thread to wind
a 71-mile-long thick thread.
for this particular shoelace, the machine is programmed
to wind 8,200 feet of thick thread per bobbin.
another worker installs 20 of those bobbins
on a braiding machine.
for each one, she passes the end of the thread
through three eyelets,
the second of which regulates the tension of the thread.
♪♪
she gathers half the threads and ties knots in them
so that they'll catch when
she feeds them into the machine.
she starts up the braiding machine.
it draws in the knotted threads,
which pull in the unknotted ones.
then the machine begins braiding a continuous
round shoelace cord.
these wheels apply tension
to pull any loose braids tighter
so that the corrected diameter is uniform.
the finished cord, which is about a mile long,
collects in a barrel.
some shoelaces are made of knitted,
rather than braided, cord.
the cones of thread feed the knitting machine directly.
the machine's four latch needles can perform two types
of knitting stitches to produce round cord.
once the knitted, or braided, cord is ready,
a worker adjusts four metal pegs
of a winding device
to the shoelace length they're making.
then she winds the cord
around the pegs up to 250 times,
depending on the cord diameter.
she cuts the end and ties the cords together
so that she can easily transfer them
to what's called a tipping machine.
♪♪
she runs the center of each cord
over an acetone-saturated felt pad,
then inserts it in the machine's die.
the die wraps a piece of acetate
film tightly around the cord,
then cuts it in the middle,
producing a shoelace with a stiff tip,
called an aglet, on each end.
this press applies a nickel-plated steel tip,
a kind used on bag drawstrings.
the worker manually positions two tips directly on the cord
with a slight gap in between them.
she activates the press to force them on,
then cuts the cord in the gap.
this factory also makes rickrack,
a flat zigzag trim that's sewn onto clothing.
these rickrack-braiding machines are 120 years old.
each one holds from 13 to 73 bobbins of thread.
the more bobbins used, the wider the rickrack.
there are two ways to make multicolored rickrack
or braided shoelace cord.
mount different shades of solid color bobbins
on the braiding machine
or wind multicolored thread on each bobbin.
and for multicolored knitted shoelace cord,
mount different shades of solid-color thread cones
or multicolored thread on each cone.
to produce different shapes and sizes,
this manufacturer uses different types of braiding
and knitting machines,
varying the number of bobbins or cones
from eight to as many as 73.
an even number produces a round shoelace.
an odd number produces a flat one.
with so many possibilities,
shoelaces can be fashionable as well as functional.