♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪
narrator:
in the late 19th century,
it was considered immoral
for unmarried women
to enter a man's bedroom.
william murphy couldn't
bring his date back
to his one-room apartment,
so he invented a bed
that folded up into the wall,
converting his bedroom
into a parlor
to host his love interest.
a wall of cupboards and closets
suddenly opens up to reveal
sleek comfortable
sleeping quarters.
the wall bed is a great way
to economize on space
without sacrificing
comfort or style.
to build the mechanism casing,
a worker begins by
placing the steel plate
in a powerful bending machine,
which is capable of
exerting 55 tons of force.
using the square and calipers,
the worker verifies
that the bend
is a perfectly uniform
right angle
and the flange depth
does not exceed
the specified parameters.
once the bending machine
has folded
all four sides of the plate,
the worker then mounts it
onto a locator pin
in a second press,
which descends
and creates a small depression
around the central opening.
this depression will facilitate
the welding process.
using another locator pin,
a welder clamps the plate
into a purpose-built jig.
he then begins welding all
of the necessary components
in place.
he uses a bolt
to correctly locate
an internal reinforcement plate
and also welds in
the crucial pivot pin
on which the mechanism
will hinge.
the casing plates
are mounted on spacers
to help speed
the drying process.
then a worker spray-paints
them black.
once dry, he removes
a protective cap from the pivot.
it's now time to manufacture
the wall-mounted
spring mechanism.
a worker uses a drill press
outfitted with a countersink
to create a beveled recess
around the openings.
a worker then uses
a specially-designed press
to install a brass bearing
in one of the openings.
the mechanism
is nearly complete.
however, there are still several
steps to go in the process.
next, a worker brushes grease
onto the interior
of two mechanism casings.
he then flips them over
in order to apply
a specially-formulated
grease to the pivot pin.
he slides the bushing over it
and applies a c-shaped
locking washer.
an s-shaped stop will lock
the mechanism in place
until the bed is installed.
the spring-unit assemblage will
provide the resistance required
to help smoothly raise
and lower the bed.
a locking pin secures one end
of the spring unit in place.
the worker adds the bottom
plate of the unit,
which includes a threaded bolt.
a nut threaded onto it
can be tightened or loosened
to adjust
the mechanism's tension.
the wall-mounted
spring mechanism
is ready to be installed.
it's designed to connect
to this bed-mounted component.
once mounted to the bed,
the two components
work together,
allowing the user to easily
raise and lower the bed.
a worker quickly installs
the bed-mounted component
using pre-drilled holes,
bolts, and locking nuts.
he installs the wall bed's legs
in the same way,
following a pre-drilled
hole pattern
to locate the component
and attach it with bolts,
locking nuts, and screws.
the legs fold down when
the bed is being used
and tuck out of the way
when the bed folds up.
the manufacturers
can now package
the fully-assembled wall beds
for transport
to their destinations.
installing the wall bed
requires some muscle,
but once the two components
of the spring mechanism
are connected,
lowering the bed
onto its fold-away legs
is a piece of cake.
this s-shaped stop
ensures the mechanism
won't accidentally flip up.
once it's removed,
the bed easily rises.
the legs tuck into position,
and the bed neatly folds away
into its hiding spot,
as though it were never there.
♪
narrator:
several american towns claim to
be the birthplace of the sundae.
sundaes first appeared
in the 1880s,
when the sale of ice cream sodas
was banned on sundays.
instead, soda-fountain operators
poured soda syrup on ice cream,
added toppings, and called
this new treat the sundae.
♪
today, ice cream sundaes come
pre-made and frozen
in individual servings.
there's no need to wait.
this decadent dessert can be
served up in an instant.
at the sundae factory,
productions starts
with something called
the white base mix.
it's a pasteurized blend
of fresh cream, milk,
and a variety of sweeteners.
a worker adds a blend
of yellow coloring
to the white base mix,
and this takes it
from bright white
to an off-white.
a generous helping
of pure vanilla extract
lends a distinctive flavor
and adds extra color
to the cream base.
after a final stir, the mix is
ready for a freezing process,
during which, air will be added
to turn the mix
into soft ice cream.
it's time to cue the containers.
two at a time, individual-sized
sundae cups move forward
on the production line.
they meet up with
the ice cream dispenser.
it automatically pumps
precise amounts
of the soft vanilla ice cream
into the cups.
it fills the cups
to the 3/4 mark,
leaving plenty of room
for toppings.
it's now time to prepare
the next layer
of deliciousness --
the chocolate fudge sauce.
a worker mixes skim milk
and sweeteners
to a frothy consistency,
and then adds several large bags
of dark rich cocoa.
the mixer paddle agitates
the ingredients to distribute
the cocoa evenly throughout.
the chocolate fudge is pumped
into a plastic tote
to cool overnight.
during cooling,
the sauce thickens up
substantially.
it's now a rich
chocolate fudge syrup.
velvety smooth, the chocolate
syrup flows out of the tote
and into a big tank.
from there, nozzles dispense
the chocolate fudge syrup
onto the vanilla ice cream
in the cups.
next, a worker pours
a liquid-topping blend
into a high-speed mixer system
that beats it
to a whipped consistency.
nozzles deposit
the whipped topping
onto the syrup-covered
ice cream.
now it's time to add
some chocolate crunch
to the smooth, sweet sundae.
the system sprinkles
semi-sweet chocolate chunks
onto the whipped topping.
it's the final touch.
these single-serve
chocolate sundaes
have been prepared
almost entirely by machines.
a conveyor now sends them
through an icy blast of air
for a quick freeze.
exiting the freezer, the frozen
sundaes travel forward,
shielded by overhead guards
for food-safety reasons.
the sundaes funnel
into a single-file lane.
this positions them
to receive lids.
the lids slide down a chute
and land on top
of the ice cream sundae cups.
rollers press the lids
down on the rims.
a revolving apparatus deposits
plastic collars around the lids.
moving forward, the machinery
sorts the sundae cups
in row of two.
this allows a robot
with suctioning arms
to pick up six at a time
and pack them
into a cardboard box.
the boxes travel under and over
packing tape
to seal the tops and bottoms.
incredibly, this factory
produces 1,440 ice cream
sundae cups every 15 minutes.
and it's all thanks to
the magic of mechanization.
this company also produces tubs
of flavored ice cream,
so there are many
mouth-watering choices
to be made
at dessert time.
♪
narrator: digital painting is
a relatively new medium.
it's an artistic hybrid that
marries modern
computer technology
with traditional painting
by hand on canvas.
today, some photography studios
offer digital painting
as a way to transform
photographic portraits
into painted portraits.
this specialized photographer
offers digital painting
to enhance original portraits
and cherished snapshots.
his studio also specializes
in creating life-story collages.
the in-house artist assembles
photos and illustrations,
depicting elements
of the subject's lifetime.
she scans and digitizes photos
which are not already digital.
she manually retouches
every image with a digital pen
and tablet
to maximize the quality.
then she begins working
on the layout of the collage.
once she has finalized
the layout,
she blends the edges
of each image
so that the elements
flow seamlessly
into each other.
now the artist begins
digitally painting.
she chooses from a selection
of brush shapes and sizes,
and from a myriad of colors.
she applies digital paint
to blur the hard lines
of the photographs
to make them look more
like painted images.
this painting process
takes several hours
of painstaking work.
she sends the digital painting
to the lab technician
who prepares to print
the work onto a canvas.
first, he tweaks
the entire painting,
balancing the brightness
and the colors.
he prints a small test sample
on canvas.
both the technician
and the artist
meticulously examine the sample
under magnification,
looking for any painting
or printing errors.
if everything is perfect,
the technician installs a large
canvas roll on the printer.
the machine prints,
not with regular inks,
but with archival pigments,
which last for centuries.
after each pass,
the head waits six seconds
to let the pigments dry.
this prevents them from smearing
on the next pass.
a digital painting this size
takes five hours to print.
the pigments must dry
for 72 hours
to ensure they're embedded
into the canvas.
then the technician applies
a coat of stabilizing lacquer
to protect
the surface from damage
caused by ultraviolet rays
or handling.
the lacquer takes about
an hour to dry.
then they can safely
mount the canvas
on a stretcher frame.
the workers pull it tight
with special pliers
and then staple it down.
they cut the corners
to facilitate framing.
the artist applies a white gel
with thicker brush strokes
in some areas
and thinner ones in others.
this gives the print
the texture of a painting.
the gel turns clear
as it dries for 24 hours.
then the artist paints
the entire printed canvas
with acrylic paints.
as she applies shading
and creates depth,
the painting gradually
comes alive.
when she finishes,
she signs her work.
in about an hour,
the paint is dry
and the digital painting is
ready for framing.
she inserts a personalized
certificate of authenticity,
stating that this is
a one-of-a-kind work,
and applies the photography
studio's label
on the back of the canvas.
whether it's a
creatively-crafted collage
or produced from
a simple photograph,
a digital painting
immortalizes precious moments
captured by the camera lens.
♪
narrator: at some point
in 19th-century england,
a new game evolved
that took its name from
the duke of beaufort's
badminton house.
badminton soon became
all the rage
among british officers in india.
today, fans believe the game is
faster and harder than tennis,
its long-time rival.
to create
the carbon-fiber shafts
of the badminton racquets,
the manufacturer
follows a series
of meticulously-defined
production steps.
the process begins
by tightly wrapping
a carbon-fiber fabric,
called prepreg,
multiple times around
a metal cylinder.
a worker encases
the fabric in plastic
to hold the prepreg in place.
then he suspends the cylinders
from a rack
and rolls them into an oven.
the heating process transforms
the wrapped prepreg
into solid lightweight
and super-strong
carbon-fiber material.
this specialized device
removes the cylinder
from the carbon fiber,
leaving a hollow shaft.
here, we can see the stages
of production required
to create the hollow
carbon-fiber shaft.
in the next stage of production,
a worker begins the process
of manufacturing
the racquet frame.
she starts with
a different formulation
of prepreg material,
which she folds
into thin strips.
the key is to make sure
each strip is identical.
in the next phase,
a worker wraps the strip
around a purpose-built mold
to create the shape
of a racquet frame.
she introduces the carbon-fiber
shaft into the mold.
the racquet is taking shape.
another piece of carbon fiber
forms the joint between them.
the frame-shaped
prepreg carbon fiber
then goes into
a shaping machine,
and the lid closes.
the shaping machine heats
and then cools the prepreg
over the course
of about 30 minutes.
a worker lifts the lid
and removes the fully-formed
racquet frame,
which has excess resin.
resin holds the carbon fibers
together
before the curing process.
heating expels the resin,
which must then be removed.
a narrow bit drills
the first sequence of holes
in an offset pattern
to make the racquet
easier to string.
a larger-gauge bit drills
holes large enough
to permit two strings
to pass through.
quality-control inspectors
choose a racquet frame at random
to test how much
pressure it can bear
before it reaches
the breaking point.
it's finally time to add
the wooden handle
and cap to the shaft
and put everything together.
the racquets head for
the painting department,
where they receive a base coat.
then workers meticulously apply
a series of decals.
the decals soak in water
to make it easier
to remove the backing.
a worker slides each hole
over a pin
at the base
of a nailing machine.
the machine nails
specially-designed grommets
into the holes.
the grommets are slightly
too long to ensure
they can be cut perfectly flush
to the frame by this machine.
in a two-part process,
this pressing machine heats
and then presses the cut side
of the grommets
to smooth them out.
a worker carefully clamps the
racquet into a winding machine
and brushes glue
onto the handle.
she then secures one end
of the handle wrap at the base,
and uses a foot pedal to begin
turning the racquet.
maintaining the steady tension
at the correct angle,
she winds the wrapping
all the way up
to the beginning of the shaft.
she secures the top end
of the wrapping with tape.
a laser quickly and accurately
burns the product i.d. number
into the shaft.
a quality-control inspector
clamps the completed racquet
into a precision-
engineered device,
designed to measure its weight,
swing weight,
and balance point
with incredible accuracy.
the racquets made
by this manufacturer
come in different sizes,
suited to every level
of badminton player.
♪