♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: in glass extractors,
solvents capture liquids
from solid
or semisolid materials.
for example, oils can be
extracted from plants to obtain
the essence of their
fragrance and flavor.
the plant oil can then
be bottled for use
or incorporated into products.
inside this glass apparatus,
extraction happens.
solvent continuously treats
a solid material
to extract an oil
or other component of interest.
making an extractor starts
with glass tubing
of various lengths
and diameters.
a glass worker uses this one
to form a standard taper joint
in one end of
the extractor tube.
he heats the end to soften it
and places a forming tool
over it.
in its softened state, the glass
conforms to the profile.
after controlled heating
removes internal stresses,
he grinds the joint
to the final dimension.
the grinding gives the joint
a frosted appearance.
another worker widens one end
of the main extractor body
and forms it
into an outer joint.
this end will connect
to the condenser.
the other end connects
to the lower extractor body.
a worker joins them together.
then, using
a glass support tool,
he inserts an inner siphon tube.
he melts a hole in the lower
extractor body
and attaches the inner
siphon tube to it.
he makes another hole
in the extractor's main chamber.
♪
he then fuses another
siphoning tube
to the outside of
the main extractor body
and bends it into a "u" shape.
he connects the other end of
the "u" to the inner siphon tube
and melts the connecting point
all the way around
to seal the glass.
he burns another hole in the
lower end of the extractor
and installs a tube
for solvent overflow.
he bends it into
a vertical position.
he forms another hole near the
top of the main extractor body
and connects
the overflow tube to it.
♪
moving on to the condenser now,
a worker shapes the end
into a joint
that will fit into
the top of the extractor.
he pumps air into
the condenser tube
to expand the heated glass
within a forming tool.
another member of the team
applies an aggregate compound.
he inserts in it a spinner
that grinds the compound
against the glass
to refine the profile.
he tests the fit of this
inner joint
against a standard outer one.
blowing air into one end,
he heats the condenser tube
in three locations.
the air gravitates to the heat
and forms bulbs in the part,
increasing the surface area
inside to improve efficiency.
he opens up one end
of the condenser tube.
continuing to heat the end,
he inserts a reamer tool
to widen the opening.
he carefully slides the
condenser into the outer body
using a piece of cardboard.
the worker burns a hole
in the bottom of the outer body
and fuses the end
of the condenser to it.
he then connects the stem
that will eventually carry
the condensed solvent
to the extraction chamber.
next, he makes a hole
in the top of the condenser
and seals a stem to it.
this top stem opens the system
to the atmosphere
to prevent pressure buildup.
he also equips the condenser
with connectors
for cooling fluid hoses.
a worker moistens a decal
of the company logo
and places it on
the condenser unit.
then he places the unit into
an annealing oven to gradually
ramp up the temperature
to 1,040 degrees fahrenheit,
and then slowly brings it down.
the process both
strengthens the glass
and bakes the decal into it.
heated, evaporated
and then condensed,
the solvent in the extractor
will separate liquids
from solids.
after more than a century
of use, it's still a neat trick.
♪
narrator:
the perfect chandelier
can be the cherry
on the decor sundae.
there's no shortage
of fabulous fixtures
in lighting stores and online,
but when customers have
a unique design in mind,
or want someone to design
something special,
they have to go to
a lighting manufacturer
that does custom work.
this striking chandelier
is a unique custom design.
a rustic faux-wood-finish
exterior contrasts
against a shimmering
gold-leaf interior
and has handblown,
ribbed glass globes
suspended like colored jewels.
a worker constructs the frame
for the chandelier's drum shade
out of flat bars
of cold-rolled steel,
steel whose composition
makes it flexible enough
to be bent without heating.
after bending two bars
into rings,
the welder connects them
with four vertical ribs
made of the same type
of steel bars.
he tack welds
the pieces at first,
then verifies with a level to
make sure the ribs are straight.
then, he fully welds the frame
and grinds every weld flat
to make the joints invisible.
the manufacturers laser cut and
weld sheets of cold-rolled steel
to make the light kit that
contains the lights and wiring
and supports the shade
with four crossbars.
turning the kit upside-down, the
bottom is spray painted gold.
the workshop's custom painter
applies adhesive
and begins gently laying down
delicate sheets of gold leaf.
he flattens the leaf
with a soft-bristled brush,
working the entire surface.
once he's sure the gold leaf
has adhered everywhere,
he brushes away the excess.
once the gold-leaf adhesive
is dry,
he sprays on a coat of clear,
high-gloss lacquer,
then removes the masking tape
covering the side and top.
the painter also gold leafs
the inside
and rim of the light housings.
an assembler now installs them
in the light kit,
then installs an led bulb
in each housing.
to make the shade, manufacturers
mold two half drums of acrylic
and paint them black on one side
and gold on the other.
another painter brushes
white lacquer-based paint
on the black side.
once the paint dries, he applies
a coat of diluted brown paint
in uneven striations to create
the look of wood grain.
he doesn't let this coat dry
because he wants
overlapping colors
to bleed into each other,
so he quickly applies
the third coat.
he immediately applies
the fourth and final coat,
diluted gray.
he spreads it with a cloth
using small gentle strokes.
he compares his work
to the design sample
to make sure it matches.
then, he lets the paint dry
thoroughly overnight.
the next day, the first painter
applies gold leaf
to the reverse side
of the painted drum halves.
again, he coats the gold leaf
in clear lacquer
and lets it dry overnight.
the next day, an assembler
takes the drum-shade frame,
which has since been
painted black,
and installs
the two half shades,
locking them into a lip
on the top and bottom rings.
a worker completes the light kit
by splicing the nine wires
coming from the led lights
to a central wire
coming out from the center
of the kit's top cover.
then, workers line up the kit's
four crossbars with the shade's
four ribs
and insert each crossbar through
a notch at the top of the shade.
they screw the top ring
to the crossbar.
globes are crafted by
a local glassblower.
the assembler strings each one
on a stainless-steel
braided cable
with a brass check ring on top.
he sets spring-loaded
ball grippers above
and below the globe
to lock it on the cable.
the grippers make the globe
vertically adjustable.
this chandelier
has seven cables,
each one suspending
one to three globes.
a brass connecter at the top
of the cable screws
securely into a small
threaded hole in the light kit.
with its creative trio
of faux-wood, gold and glass,
this custom-designed chandelier
makes an illuminating statement.
♪
narrator: strength training is
an important component
of a fitness regimen.
one way to build strength
is to lift weights
or exercise on machines
that provide resistance
when users pull, push or lift.
typically, weights produce
that resistance,
but some machines use
a completely different system.
this exercise machine
doesn't have the typical
stack of weights.
instead, the handles
are connected
by a rope-and-pulley system
to a pneumatic cylinder
which creates resistance.
this computer-guided laser
cuts many of the parts
out of sheet steel.
it can make complex cuts, which
are accurate within 100 microns,
the width of two human hairs.
the parts go into
a vibrating tumbler
filled with ceramic
stones and water.
the stones rub
against the parts,
removing what's called scale,
a flaky substance produced
on the surface of the steel
by the heat of the laser
and oxygen in the air.
a worker clamps the parts
for the trainer's power module
onto a welding fixture.
the fixture is
on a robotic cell.
the cell rotates, delivering
the parts to the robot,
which proceeds
to weld them together.
welding the power module
takes 14 minutes.
when the robot
completes the welding,
the cell returns
the fixture to the worker,
who inspects
the module thoroughly,
then transfers it
to the finishing area.
a worker grinds the welds flat,
then, with a finer
grinding disc,
smoothes them out
so that they won't show
once the steel is painted.
after washing the module
in iron phosphate,
a worker applies a positive
electrical charge to the module
and a negative one
to the powder paint.
opposite charges attract,
drawing the paint particles onto
the surface in an even coat.
then the worker bakes the paint
onto the steel in an oven.
elsewhere in the factory,
another worker drills
a 12-inch-deep hole
into a cylinder rod.
the rod is steel, the piston
on its end, aluminum.
he inserts the cylinder rod
into the cylinder,
also made of aluminum,
then carefully inserts
a sensor rod
into the cylinder rod's hole.
the sensor relays
the cylinder's position
to the machine's computer.
snap rings hold
the parts together.
after a paint-job inspection,
the trainer
is ready for assembly.
first comes the decals.
the assembler wets the surface
with soapy water,
then applies them.
once the decals are
partially dry,
he gingerly removes
the transfer tape
and inspects
for bubbles or gaps.
♪
next, he installs
the machine's computer.
it calculates the power produced
with each pull on the handles.
then, he installs what's called
the accumulator tank,
which stores the air for the
return stroke of the handles.
he installs the cylinder.
the bottom is assembled
to a central pulley
that connects to both handles.
the top connects to
the accumulator tank
with an air hose.
the amount of force
is determined
by how much air pressure
the user lets in
when pushing the yellow
resistance-control buttons.
the buttons are attached to air
hoses and wired to the computer.
the assembler routes
a 26-foot-long rope
through the central pulley
and through the machine's
12 additional pulleys.
the configuration
is designed to enable
a wide range of exercises.
after closing up the power
module with a cover panel
and installing the two
height-adjustable arms,
the assembler installs
a swiveling pulley on each arm
and ties what's called a clevis
to the end of each rope.
the clevis holds a wide range
of other attachments.
once assembly is complete,
an inspector checks
for any aesthetic
or functional defects.
he sets a resistance level,
then pulls on the handles
to make sure the cylinder
sensor is reading correctly.
pulling a handle pushes the rod
into the cylinder,
forcing the piston against
the incoming air pressure
supplied by a compressor.
because this power trainer
uses air, rather than weights,
to produce resistance, users can
work out at faster speeds,
which producers higher power.
♪
narrator: single-serving
coffee pods provide
almost instant gratification.
the concept has changed
the way coffee is prepared,
no need to wait around for
a whole pot of coffee to brew.
by simply inserting the pod
in a compatible machine,
it brews the coffee in seconds.
these coffee pods are designed
to be composted after use.
they offer the convenience
of a quick coffee
without long-term
landfill consequences.
the process of making coffee
pods starts with bags
of unroasted beans from
different parts of the world.
these beans will be combined
to create specific blends,
but first, they must be
thoroughly tested and graded.
a technician inhales the aroma
to sniff out defects.
he examines the physical
condition of the beans.
he's looking for insect
damage or fragmentation.
if he finds too many defects,
the lot will be rejected.
too much moisture would be
another indication
that the coffee beans
are substandard,
so he measures the water content
using an electronic analyzer.
he roasts samples of the beans
in these mini roasters.
this unlocks the flavors
and aromas
in the green coffee beans.
the color deepens.
the beans harden
and double in size
due to the release of gases
and water vaporization.
for lighter, milder beans,
he does a shorter roast.
for darker, more intensely
flavored beans,
he roasts them a little longer.
he inspects the color
frequently, and when satisfied,
he empties the beans
into receiving trays.
fans underneath cool the beans
and stop the cooking.
roasting has transformed
the bitter green beans
into something
entirely more flavorful.
the technician grinds small
amounts into different glasses
in order to prepare for a flavor
analysis known as cupping.
the q grader takes over.
he's a certified coffee taster.
he inhales the bouquet
of the coffee and assesses it.
he then pours hot water onto
the coffee and lets it steep.
the grounds float to the surface
and form a thick crust.
he breaks the crust with a spoon
and inhales again.
then, after skimming off
the grounds,
he slurps the coffee and ponders
its flavor, body and acidity.
he grades the samples
accordingly.
the highest-grade beans will now
be made into coffee pods.
big batches tumble in
a computer-controlled roaster.
the computer slowly increases,
and then drops,
the temperature
for the desired result.
the roaster ejects the beans
onto a perforated pan,
and rotating paddles mix them
to dissipate the heat.
in this industrial grinder,
rollers pulverize the coffee
beans to a specific granulation.
too fine, and the coffee
will taste bitter.
too coarse, and the full flavor
won't be extracted.
to test the granulation
and density,
a technician dispenses
some of the coffee
into a 1-pint container
and then weighs it.
if the coffee is too heavy
and compressed,
water won't flow easily
through the coffee pod.
once it passes the density test,
the coffee is packed into pods.
the filter material unwinds
through tensioning rollers
towards the assembly machine.
the pod rings, made from
plant-based plastic,
head in the same direction.
a pusher moves the rings
into slots on a revolving drum.
the system pulls the mesh filler
material over the pod rings.
heated devices descend
as the drum turns
and seal the mesh to the rings.
formers stretch the mesh
to shape it into filter cups.
as the drum continues to turn,
depositors fill rows of the mesh
filter cups with coffee.
paper lid material unwinds
from the other side,
and heat sealers
fuse it to the pods.
at the same time, the ceiling
heads punch out the pods,
separating them from the mesh
and the excess lid paper.
the coffee is now
encased in pods.
exiting the drum, an overhead
system moves the pods forward
to be weighed.
this mechanized system produces
220 coffee pods a minute.
each will provide a quick,
caffeinated pick-me-up.