[ signal beeping ]
♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
fish rubbings.
♪
clay shooting machines.
almonds.
♪
and high-end motorcycles.
[ sign squeaks ]
fishermen like to exaggerate
about the size of their catches.
in 19th century japan,
fish rubbings were used for actual documentation.
fishermen coated the fish with non-toxic ink
and rubbed it on paper to transfer the image.
they called this form of record-keeping gyotaku.
♪
over time, the practice of fish rubbings
has evolved into an art form.
why paint a picture when you can
print one using the real thing?
the artist traces the outline of the fish onto a foam block.
following that outline, he cuts
out a fish-shaped cavity.
he sets the fish in the cavity.
the foam will keep the fish level
and stable during printing.
he tucks paper wadding into the mouth
to keep it open for a more interesting print.
♪
he also inserts wadding under the gill flaps
to impede the flow of fluids from the fish.
he props up the fins with pins
and leaves them to dry overnight
in this elevated position.
this will give the rubbed image
the illusion of action.
he wraps cosmetic sponges around wine corks
and tapes them at the base.
these improvised ink applicators
will eventually provide a smooth
finish with no brush strokes.
he makes one for each color, plus a few extra for blending.
next, he selects different ink colors
to create a bluish green shade
that's close to the one on the bluegill.
he adds poppyseed oil to thin the inks a bit
and blends it all with a palette knife.
♪
with the fins now dry and stiff,
he removes the pins.
with a metal probe, he pulls up a fin
that hadn't been raised earlier.
he places a paper towel between the foam support block
and the fish.
♪
he pats a greenish black color onto the gills
and tail using a foam brush.
this process leaves some smears
on the paper towel,
but that's what it's there for.
switching to one of the improvised applicators,
he applies the bluish green ink
to the upper part of the fish's body.
he dabs a yellow color onto the belly of the fish.
♪
he adds a bit of red to the chest
because during spawning,
it usually turns this color.
♪
he places a piece of paper under a fin
as he coats it with green ink.
then he removes the paper towel
that has protected the foam support block from smudges
and places the fish back in the cavity.
he lightly sprays a sheet of rice paper with water.
this makes it easier to manipulate,
as he drapes the damp paper onto the inked fish.
♪
he rubs the paper onto the inked
fish to transfer the image.
this takes skill and the right touch.
once he's finished,
the artist peels the paper away from the fish
and examines the rubbing.
after the ink has dried,
he lightly sprays the rubbing with water
and then a water-based dye.
the dye provides background color
but doesn't affect the oil-based ink guard.
♪
he brushes wheat paste onto a second piece of rice paper.
this paper will serve as an extra layer of reinforcement
for the fish rubbing.
♪
he wets the rubbing thoroughly.
an assistant slowly lowers the wet print onto the paper
as the artist smoothes the rubbing,
ensuring there are no wrinkles as it adheres.
the image of the fish's eye
doesn't transfer during rubbing,
so he paints one.
he defines the pupil with black watercolor
and paints the iris yellow.
the painted eye adds a soulful expression to the print.
the fish rubbing is now ready to be mounted
to a more rigid paper backing for extra support.
he trims the borders, ensuring that they're symmetrical
and the correct measurements.
♪
he then tapes the fish rubbing to the mounting board
and signs it.
with numerous and extensive dryings between steps,
it has taken several weeks to produce this fish rubbing.
♪
narrator: clay shooting machines
launch the flying targets
used in the sport of clay pigeon shooting.
the saucer-shaped targets are called clay pigeons
because they replace the original targets, live pigeons.
shooting machines can launch the targets
at various intervals, angles and velocities.
♪
this company has been building
clay shooting machines since 1927.
older models like this one were heavy steel clunkers
that ran on high voltage,
were difficult to move around and weren't terribly precise.
today's machines weigh from just 88 to 220 pounds.
not only are they easily portable,
they run on just 12 volts
and perform with great precision.
the machine's sturdy base
is constructed from thick steel.
its parts were cut by a computer-guided laser
then welded together.
♪
the base design enables the machine
to move both laterally and vertically.
the first component the worker attaches to the base
is the frame.
made of durable epoxy-coated cast aluminum,
it supports all the machine's key components.
one of them, the main shaft assembly for the throwing arm,
is already installed.
♪
a technician connects the frame to the base
with heavy-duty bolts.
♪
this slot in the frame allows the machine to tilt vertically,
up to 65 degrees.
♪
he attaches a steel extension for the throwing plate
across which the throwing arm moves the clay pigeon.
this extension enables an optimal
positioning of the throwing plate.
before installing the throwing plate,
he installs the indexing shaft assembly.
the indexing shaft is the finger
that moves the carousel forward
one column at a time.
he mounts the steel throwing plate.
it has three steel springs on its underside.
one goes over the bolt,
attaching it to the far end of the extension.
the other two go over the bolt,
attaching it to the frame.
these springs keep the arm parallel to the throwing plate.
♪
next, he screws the throwing arm
to the main shaft assembly.
♪
he checks the gap between the arm and plate
to make sure the arm makes contact with the clay pigeon
at just the right level.
if the alignment's off, he
adjusts the height of the plate.
♪
then he manually turns the main shaft
to make sure the throwing arm rotates smoothly.
the machine runs on a powerful electric motor
that has an integrated gear train.
♪
the technician installs the motor on the frame
beneath the main shaft assembly.
next, he attaches the steel arming spring
which can withstand up to 440 pounds of pull force.
its sudden release generates the propulsion
to launch the clay pigeon
of a flying speed of more than 62 miles per hour.
he mounts the support base for the carousel
that holds the clay pigeons,
then he screws the arming spring
to the main shaft assembly.
as the shaft swings back and forth,
it stretches and releases the spring.
he links the indexing shaft assembly
to the motor's gear shaft.
he installs the carousel, made of cast aluminum,
on the support base.
♪
this model has a different type of motor design
that enables the base to pivot automatically,
launching random trajectories.
this patented system increases the carousel's capacity.
by clicking retractable extensions
onto the rods that separate the columns,
the operator can stack 50 percent
more clay pigeons in the carousel.
when the operator presses a button on the remote control,
the throwing arm rotation begins.
when the arm passes a specific point,
the stretched arming spring releases, launching the pigeon.
as the arm continues its rotation,
the linked indexing shaft moves the carousel forward,
dropping a new clay pigeon onto the throwing plate.
when the arm comes full circle,
re-stretching the arming spring,
a sensor cuts power to the motor
until the next press of the button.
this entire cycle takes just 2 seconds.
♪
narrator: almond consumption dates back to biblical times.
they're even mentioned in the old testament.
around 100 a.d.,
the ancient romans showered newlyweds with almonds.
this ritual came from the belief
that they increased fertility.
but today, it's the nutritional
value of almonds
that keeps us coming back for more.
♪
almonds are a guilt-free snack.
they're full of vitamins, minerals and protein.
more than 80 percent of the world's
almonds come from california
where growing conditions are ideal.
upon arrival at a processing facility,
the almonds are still encased in leathery hulls.
they flow through equipment that combs out debris.
the next machine, called a destoner, targets any rocks.
air blows through it to separate the lighter
almonds from the stones.
the almonds travel between a rubber roller and belt.
this spins off the hulls and releases the almonds.
the operator periodically examines the de-hulled almonds.
vibrating decks with slots sort the almonds by size.
the system also shakes off
hull material and vacuums it up.
the almonds head to a gravity table for finer separation.
the spent hulls and other material float to one side
while heavier contaminants float to the other.
the in-shell almonds tumble down channels.
cameras examine the shells for imperfections
and look for contaminants,
then a blast of compressed air knocks them out of the flow.
these are some of the contaminants
that have been removed.
at another facility, machinery will now grade the almonds
according to the condition of their shells.
once again, the almonds fall through the open air,
and a computerized camera scans them for broken shells
and other flaws.
♪
a compressed air gun then knocks the flawed almonds
out of the mix.
the almonds bounce along a vibrating grid
and any kernels or missed shell fragments fall through.
finally, people sort through the almonds
and reject any that don't have perfect shells.
they also toss out any contaminants
the mechanized sorting system missed.
some buyers will pay a premium for the best nuts.
♪
the almonds with broken shells will have the shells removed.
these raw almonds are also sorted by size.
they flow onto a vibrating conveyor.
further along, the conveyor has holes.
the smaller almonds fall through
these holes and into bins.
the larger almonds continue forward.
these larger kernels are worth more
and will be sold separately from the smaller ones.
♪
as with the in-shell almonds, good looks are important.
a camera photographs the cascading almond kernels,
and a computer scans the images.
the system knocks the less-than-perfect almonds
out of the production stream.
♪
next, the almonds head towards a robot.
along the way, another camera sends the images
to a computer scanner.
this one has been programmed to find chips,
scratches and even small broken bits.
the computer sends the coordinates
of the damaged almonds to the robot.
the robot then finds them and plucks them out of the mix.
a human inspector now picks out any imperfect almonds
that the robotic system missed.
their flaws are just superficial.
they still taste the same,
so these almonds will be processed into chocolate bars,
almond butter or milk, baked goods and cereals.
the perfect almond kernels travel forward.
just ahead, machinery moves cardboard boxes
into an open position on a packaging carousel.
sprayers apply glue to the bottom flaps,
and pushers close them, sealing the boxes.
the almonds now arrive at a scale.
it releases them into the boxes
in approximately 50-pound batches.
♪
these big boxes of almonds will
be shipped to other facilities
to be processed into other products.
smaller amounts will be packaged for consumer use.
a snack anyone can crack or enjoy pre-cracked,
almonds are a natural and nutritious choice.
no wonder they're consumed by the handful.
♪
narrator: during the great depression,
motorcycles were an inexpensive
transportation option.
they were a cheaper way to get around town.
but these days, a motorcycle can be an expensive machine.
not for the penny-wise, high-end
motorcycles are engineered
and crafted for the rider with discriminating tastes.
♪
this is not a standard mass-produced motorcycle.
this performance cruiser takes
things in a different direction.
the high-end design is executed with precision,
with most parts machined specifically for this bike.
production starts with a conceptual layout.
the designer draws
the motorcycle on a digital pad,
producing a blueprint for the manufacturing process.
the manufacturer uses aircraft-grade aluminum
to make most of the parts.
computerized tools carve the solid aluminum
into the desired shape.
this part will be the motorcycle's belt drive cover.
the carved patterns make it more visually appealing,
and they reduce the cover's overall weight.
the company builds the exhaust system using stainless steel.
a technician welds the exhaust pipes together.
he then attaches several spring hangers
to the steel pipe assembly.
the next part is an ignition coil mount.
a ruby probe scans the part to find the center.
once it's been located,
a software-driven cutter descends,
and etches brand information and artwork
into the black anodized aluminum.
this steel structure will serve
as the motorcycle's skeleton.
the technician installs the 100-horsepower,
fuel-injected v-twin engine.
he then mounts the six-speed transmission system
to the engine.
it's equipped with a high torque shaft
that's shorter than usual
to make the system more compact.
he bolts it in place.
the steering stem has a framework at the base
with three openings known as the triple clamp.
he slides the stem into the tube on the frame
and screws a bearing onto the top.
he fastens it with a nut
that will keep the bearing pressurized.
he installs a second triple clamp
on the top of the assembly.
the center hole fits onto the nut.
he secures it with a steering head nut.
he inserts the suspension fork into the other two openings
in the triple clamps and makes some adjustments.
he places a carbon-fiber wheel between the fork tubes.
he installs the axle that links the suspension
to the front wheel hub
and tightens the titanium nuts on the axle for a better fit.
♪
next, he connects a six-piston brake system
to the suspension fork
and tightens the bolts that hold it in place.
this completes the front wheel assembly.
he now attaches the handlebars,
complete with dashboard gauges,
controls and side-view mirrors.
he makes the final connections for the electronics.
he encases the gauges and wiring with a part
called the front cowling.
the shape diverts air over the rider
and away from his or her face.
a two-piece gas tank will provide more capacity.
the tanks have been carved from a solid aluminum bar,
a process that's taken over 60 hours.
the tank on the right side
becomes part of the frame structure,
providing additional strength.
♪
he loops belt drive pulleys around shafts to transfer power
from the transmission to the rear wheel.
the motorbike is now ready for the belt drive cover
we saw produced earlier.
while protecting the belt drive,
this cover also gives the motorbike a distinctive look.
he mounts the left foot peg
to the frame through a hole in the pulley cover.
this high-end motorcycle is now
ready to hit the open road.
making it has taken 2 weeks.
preproduction fittings with the client
have dictated the position of the foot pedals,
handlebars, and the seat.
it's been tailor-made for a precision ride.
it costs more than many mid-range cars,
but this high-end bike isn't for the budget crowd.
it's for those who want a one-of-a-kind ride.
♪