-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: a dive light is essential when scuba diving at night,
but can also be used for daytime dives
to explore
underwater caves and shipwrecks.
the deeper you dive, the more water absorbs
certain colors in the light spectrum.
when you use an artificial light,
you can see the underwater world
in true color.
the dive light is waterproof to a depth of 295 feet.
it's brighter than a car headlight,
with six outer l.e.d. lights for floodlighting
and three inner l.e.d.s for alternate spotlighting.
the dive light begins as a conceptual drawing.
the mechanical designer sketches out its basic features
and a few proposed shapes.
then the company creates foam models.
scuba divers test these models
and provide feedback on the comfort of each shape.
this market research results in the final design --
a compact, hand-mounted dive-light
with a user-friendly operating switch
and three l.e.d. battery-life indicators.
the housing's components are
made of durable plastic pellets,
reinforced with glass fiber.
workers load the pellets into an injection molding machine.
the machine melts them and shoots the molten plastic
into the proper mold for the component they are making.
the machine then cools the plastic to a solid state
and injects the newly formed part.
this is the reflector.
it combines the light from the six outer l.e.d.s
into a single beam.
it's coated in aluminum
to increase
the amount of light it reflects.
a 3-d printer produces prototypes
for all of the parts before they are manufactured.
guided by a computer,
the printer shoots out plastic to build the part
in three dimensions from the bottom up.
once the prototype is approved,
they make a mold for mass production.
this part is called the light pipe.
it has oval covers for the three
l.e.d. battery-life indicators
and a waterproof seal.
once all the housing parts are molded, assembly can begin.
they insert the light pipe into
the main body of the housing.
then they attach a switch,
which turns the light on and off.
it also toggles the light
between spotlight and floodlight modes.
they don't need to pierce the housing to connect the switch.
the switch slides a magnet over
the outside of the housing.
the magnetic field communicates
through the housing
to sensors inside.
next they insert and connect the circuit board...
...then the lithium-ion rechargeable battery.
they plug its connector into the circuit board.
this cover holds the internal parts in correct alignment.
a silicone o ring forms a watertight seal
between the main body and the light head.
they snap the reflector over the nine l.e.d.s,
which are attached to a round circuit board.
the circuit board is metal
so that it will absorb the heat
the l.e.d. lights generate.
the screw-on aluminum bezel
makes contact with the circuit board,
transferring the heat out of the housing
and into the water.
they conduct the first quality-control test in water.
the dive light is turned on
to verify that it will run
for 65 minutes on a full charge.
in the second quality-control test,
they submerge the dive light in a pressurized tank.
this simulates the pressure the light would be subjected to
at an underwater depth of about 300 feet.
that's over twice the diving depth
of a typical recreational dive.
if the light doesn't spring a leak, it passes the test.
they fully recharge the battery,
which takes two and a half hours.
at full charge,
all three indicators light up green.
as the charge drains,
the indicators change from green to orange to red,
then to flashing red,
so scuba divers are never in the dark
about how much juice is left in their light.
narrator: interchangeable sandals come with numerous ties
that can be used to customize the look of a pair of heels.
the mix-and-match possibilities
are endless.
the wearer can try out many different styles
on a small budget.
with interchangeable footwear,
you can change the look without
actually changing your shoes.
with a variety
of cloth and leather strappings
to choose from,
a pair of sandals can be made to look different
each time you wear them.
to make a pair of interchangeable sandals,
they start with a piece of hardwood,
like cherry, walnut, or maple.
the employee cuts the wood to a workable size.
then computer-driven routers
carve the rough shape of the sandals' heels,
making two heels from a single block.
the router sculpts a cup for the wearer's heel
and carves a supportive structure
for the arch of the foot.
the router then shaves the sides of the heels
and exposes the grain of the wood.
then a worker takes over,
cutting away excess wood with a band saw.
she rounds the back of the heels
and further refines the structure.
she now has a pair of heels.
another team member brushes rubber cement onto the soles.
they are made of both natural and synthetic rubber.
she applies glue to the heels, too.
she presses the heels to the rubber soles.
the glue takes 40 minutes to dry.
faux leather, backed by cushy padding,
is used to make the footbed.
this material is similar
to what is used to make flip-flops.
the worker transfers the footbeds
to a silk-screen work station.
she lowers a stencil with the company's logo on it.
she applies acrylic ink
and squeegees the ink across the stencil
to transfer the imagine to the faux-leather footbeds.
another employee threads strong nylon cording
through the holes in the footbeds
to create loops for the interchangeable ties.
he presses rivets into the footbed
to hold the loops in place.
then he attaches the second part of the rivets
to the protruding shafts.
using the special press,
he flattens the rivets to secure them to the footbed.
the loops are now firmly attached
and should hold up to frequent tying.
another worker now glues the
footbeds to the soles and heels.
next, she glues the rubber heel caps
to the bottoms of the shoes.
the caps provide tread and make the shoe more durable.
a worker then sands the sides of the sandals,
blending all the layers together.
he buffs the sides against a fine grit abrasive
to give the surface a nice sheen.
then he rubs an oil-based sealer
into the wooden heels.
this protects the wood from moisture
and also accentuates the grain.
it's time to test the ties.
she threads the ribbons through the loops.
they're good to go.
with many colorful ties to choose from,
these interchangeable sandals are many shoes in one.
narrator: racecar simulators
help train racecar drivers off the track.
they provide realistic visuals and sensations --
bumps, jolts, swerves --
whatever movement you'd feel
if you were sitting in the driver's seat
of a real racecar.
this racecar simulator can be programmed to produce
a range of racing scenarios and weather conditions.
it can replicate any car on any track.
first, a computer-guided laser
cuts many of the simulator's parts from steel sheets.
after workers sand the rough areas,
a machine reads the final shape
with a laser
to make sure the part meets specifications.
if a part requires bending, it is done with a press.
this is one of the side brackets
for the driver's seat.
the simulator's main structure
is made primarily of steel tubing.
they saw the lengths required.
then a computer-guided mill drills holes
for the bolts that will later be used
to attach the simulator's components.
once all the steel tubes are ready,
a welder puts them in a jig
to align them correctly for assembly.
the structure's tubular parts are welded together.
then the worker adds the simulator's sheet-steel parts
and sprays the structure with industrial-grade paint.
now they mount an audio speaker and amplifier
for the vibration system.
motion controllers that move
the steering wheel and driver's seat
are also added.
they install the power distribution block
and a sub-controller for each of the two actuators.
they install the cables required
for the simulator's components
and plug them into a usb hub.
then they install the computer
and plug it into the usb hub, as well.
they cover the top of the structure
with a textured aluminum panel.
they bolt the bottom of the actuators to the structure
and plug them
into the sub-controllers inside.
then they mount the driver's seat
and bolt the top of the actuators to the back of it.
a worker installs the seat belt,
along with the spring mechanism
that yanks the belt back
when you hit the brakes.
they close in the sides of the main structure
with aluminum panels.
next they assemble the simulator's three pedals --
gas, brakes, and clutch --
and mount the clutch mechanism to it.
the pedal assembly is installed
to the base of the steering frame.
they mount the dashboard to the top of the frame.
it's made of carbon fiber
and contains the computer and audio controls.
they attach the steering frame to the main structure.
then they assemble the steering wheel.
inside its base is a circuit board
that controls the buttons on the wheel and gear shift.
it's called the shift paddle.
they mount the shift paddle to the base...
...then flip it over to attach the wheel.
next workers assemble the display frame.
it holds the simulator's three monitors
and three front speakers.
then they roll in the rest of the simulator
and plug the monitors and speakers into the computer.
finally, the steering wheel is mounted to the dash.
it snaps in and out, allowing the driver
to easily switch between steering wheel models.
the simulator is run through several days of test drives
before it ships out.
amusement parks also purchase these simulators
to offer visitors a racecar driving experience.
they can even link multiple simulators together
to race against each other in virtual replicas
of the world's most famous racetracks.
narrator: in the 1980s,
fiberglass doors came on the market.
they were well-insulated
and didn't warp in humid conditions
like wood doors.
however, they lacked the beauty
and texture of real wood.
that's now changing with technology
that can make fiberglass doors look much more inviting.
fiberglass doors trick the eye and fool visitors.
even up close, they look like real wood.
it's an illusion made possible with the help of technology.
a wood-grain fiberglass door starts with a real wood door.
a computerized cutter carves various panels.
an employee sands away any marks left by the cutter.
he gently scrapes the wood
with a wire brush to expose the grain.
he then assembles the panels
of the door within a special fixture.
another team member scans the wood door with a laser
to confirm its dimensional accuracy.
with that confirmation,
they're ready to use this wood door
to make a fiberglass one.
next the worker pours a special
silicone mixture onto the wood
and leaves it to cure overnight.
this step was demonstrated using
a smaller section of the door.
the silicone picks up all the definition of the wood grain,
creating an exact copy of the door.
next an employee injects a different silicone mixture
into a thin gap
between the recently created silicone copy
and a sheet of steel.
the second silicone door copy is thinner,
allowing for a better transfer
of heat during the next process.
they load the door copy, still on the steel sheet,
into a chemical deposition chamber.
the chemical heats the steel and the silicone,
causing a nickel-vapor shell to form.
the nickel shell has all the detail
of the original wood door.
an employee files the edges
and adds a protective fiberglass cover
over the top of the shell.
workers then lower the nickel shell into a mold base.
they remove the protective cover
and are ready to use the nickel shell
to mold fiberglass door veneers.
there are many nickel molds
and a variety of door styles at this factory.
the fiberglass material now unwinds into a cutting station.
a worker slices it into uniform strips.
the fiberglass has a dough-like
consistency at this stage.
he places a stack of fiberglass
strips on the nickel door mold
and lowers a hot press.
the press squeezes and melts the fiberglass.
it flows into the crevices of the mold.
the fiberglass solidifies quickly.
an employee removes it from the press
and sands the ragged edges.
another member of the team
confirms that the width and thickness of the panel
are on target.
they stain every first-run fiberglass panel
to expose the transferred wood grain.
this is a test.
if the grain is good,
it means there are no defects in the nickel door mold.
it's time to assemble the fiberglass door.
rollers apply glue to external framing wood.
the team builds a frame around the fiberglass door skin.
they join the wood to plastic casing
at the top and bottom of the door.
they place a second
fiberglass door skin on the top.
then they feed the door through rollers
that squeeze it together.
this activates the glue for a strong assembly.
the glue takes over 24 hours to dry.
next they load the hollow fiberglass doors
into an insulating press.
the press closes, holding the doors tightly in place.
a worker fills the hollow doors
with polyurethane insulating foam.
when foam begins to overflow through the vent holes,
the worker knows the doors are full.
he caps the fill hole...
...and runs a finger along the
doors to remove any excess foam.
energy-efficient and stable,
fiberglass doors
are a great alternative to wood.
with eye-catching wood grain, they're convincing imitations.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...