-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: skeletal replicas
are excellent educational tools.
while real bones are fragile,
these reproductions are made of a synthetic resin,
which is very tough.
these models are scientifically accurate
and can withstand repeated handling
in classrooms or museums.
this facility is dedicated to producing skeletal replicas...
...everything from ancient humans to prehistoric animals.
cast from real skeletons, these models
are virtually indistinguishable
from the original.
the process starts with a real skull.
this one is
of a prehistoric sabertooth cat.
using a wire cutter,
a worker slices up blocks of clay,
placing the pieces on the skull.
he presses the clay evenly around the skull.
he soaks a sponge and uses it to moisten and smooth the clay.
he inserts a plastic tube that will come in handy later.
now, he saturates strips of fiberglass
with a polyester resin
and drapes them around the clay.
left overnight, the fiberglass and resin cure
into a rigid shell around the clay.
he repeats this process
to create a second, identical fiberglass shell.
with the skull and clay in the bottom half,
he bolts the second shell on top.
he pours silicone into the plastic tube,
filling the space
between the skull and the top fiberglass shell.
after repeating this process on the other side,
he opens the shell.
he removes the skull
and examines the two-part silicone mold.
he places the two-part mold back into the fiberglass shell
and straps it to a spinner.
he pours polyurethane resin into the mold.
at just over a pound, the weight
matches the original skull.
the spinner spirals at a controlled speed,
evenly distributing the resin throughout the mold.
after the resin has solidified,
he removes a replica skull from the mold.
the specially formulated resin
has the look and texture of bone.
the craftsman scrapes away the ragged bits.
this part is the jaw.
using a special grinding tool,
he cleans up the surface and does a bit of contour work.
with a sharper tool,
he better defines the area around the teeth.
then he grinds the rough bits away from the cheekbone.
this is the jaw before and after
the improvements.
now it's over to the paint department,
where a worker airbrushes the skull using acrylic paint.
he layers shades of brown, black, and red
to make this replica look more authentic.
he inserts the saber teeth in the upper part of the skull
and drills little holes in both of them.
he pushes nails into the holes
to secure the teeth in the sockets.
an inspector now scrutinizes the skull
and compares it
to the original one on the left.
just like the real sabertooth cat skull,
it looks ancient.
it's difficult to tell the difference
between the 12,000-year-old skull and the new one.
the skull is now ready
for the rest of the skeleton body.
it takes five people three weeks
to build a skeletal replica like this one.
narrator: the roman emperor nero
is believed to have been the first
to chill wine in containers of ice.
despite the convenience of modern refrigerators,
ice buckets and servers are still used today.
they add presentation value to any occasion,
whether the host is
on a champagne or a beer budget.
this ice server's simple design
drains melted ice,
so food stays cold without getting wet.
an automatic guillotine blade
chops large sheets of high-grade stainless steel
into rectangles.
a worker takes each rectangle to a punch press.
the press cuts a pattern of holes into the steel.
the pattern is geometric
and will drain melting ice efficiently.
next, it's over to a deep-drawing press.
it uses 110 tons of force
to transform the rectangle into a pie-style plate.
a punch cutter removes the excess steel from the rim.
the worker now has a perforated ice tray.
he transfers it to another punch press,
which cuts finger holes for lifting it from the base.
the next worker places a larger steel rectangle
into a different press.
this will shape the bowl the ice tray rests in.
he returns to the tray and buffs
the rim to a mirror finish.
after polishing the outside of the bowl to a high gloss,
he welds two screws to the bottom.
with the screws firmly in place,
he connects the two steel legs to the bowl.
he attaches a steel platform to the other end of the legs.
this ice server is complete and ready to chill.
but before they uncork the champagne,
they need an ice bucket.
the bucket starts with a pre-cut steel disk.
an employee places the disk in a more powerful press.
it uses 165 tons of force
to transform the disk into a basic bucket shape.
next, another press applies over 175 tons of force
to deepen the bucket and reduce the diameter.
stretching the flat disk twice has made the metal fragile,
so it's exposed to induction coils
that are heated to over 1,800 degrees.
after cooling,
the steel's strength is restored,
and it's ready to be shaped again.
the final press gives the ice bucket
a cone-like shape.
the ice bucket spins on a table
that moves through six different
polishing stations.
the brushes at each stop are progressively thinner,
and this gradual polishing
gives the stainless steel bucket
a high sheen.
with the help of a template,
the worker welds handles to the steel bucket.
then the bucket is set upside-down
on a revolving table.
a pressurized sprayer shoots fine mineral particles
to give the interior a smooth finish.
this is the result.
a filler head now dispenses acid
and then plunges into it
and applies an electrical current.
this removes the surface metal,
resulting in a brilliant finish.
after the acid has washed off,
a worker inserts a perforated plate for drainage.
this ice bucket is now ready for a party.
narrator: it's not enough
for a dining chair to look inviting.
it also has to be comfortable and sturdy.
the secret to manufacturing a quality dining chair
is to use hardwood
and traditional furniture construction techniques.
this company makes dining chairs
out of hardwoods,
such as birch, walnut, oak, and ash.
they dry the wood until its moisture content is 7%,
so the chair size stays consistent after construction.
first, workers stand planks of wood
on a conveyor belt to apply glue.
then they align the planks' glued edges...
...and clamp them tightly together in a heated press.
after a few hours of heat and pressure,
the glue is dry, and they release the press.
the planks now form a large panel
from which to cut the chair parts.
a computer-guided band saw cuts the preliminary shape.
these are chair legs.
the next machine, the profiler,
finalizes the shape
and sands the wood surface on all sides.
workers now mount the parts on
another computer-guided machine.
this one drills slots called mortises.
these mortises will receive pins called tenons
protruding from adjoining parts.
before assembly, workers sand all the parts
so they can be stained later.
to make a curved chair back, they have to bend the wood.
they need the wood to have a 15% to 22% moisture content.
any drier, and the fibers would snap when bent.
they steam the wood for an hour
to soften it and make it more flexible.
they place the steamed wood in a curved mold on a press.
then they dry it with a device
that generates heat using radio frequencies.
after about an hour,
they release the press and remove the wood.
the moisture content is now 7%,
which maintains the curve shape.
parts that need tenons go into this automated machine.
its rotary knife shapes the tenon in about one second.
workers glue the mortises
in the two vertical sides of the chair back,
then brush glue onto the tenons
of the chair back's horizontal pieces.
they align the tenons and the mortises
and secure them in place with a mallet.
they put the chair back into a press
to force the tenons in place.
they reinforce each mortise-and-tenon joint
with staples designed for wood.
they continue to assemble the chair parts
with mortise and tenon joints.
this method is key
to the chair's strength and stability.
now for the final stage of construction.
they attach the front-leg assembly to the chair back.
the chair is placed in a press
to completely secure the tenons.
then they attach a support piece
in each corner.
in the finishing department,
they spray a light coat of stain,
wipe off the excess so that the color is even,
spray on a sealant, lightly re-sand the wood,
and apply a coat of protective finish.
finally, they add a seat cushion,
which screws into the chair from underneath.
now you're sitting pretty.
narrator: the first pools were built
by the ancient greeks and romans
in the 19th century.
large cities like london
started building indoor pools for sports and recreation.
backyard residential pools became popular in the 1950s.
today, residential in-ground pools
are available in a variety of shapes and sizes.
their parts are made to order in the factory.
the first step is to design the pool
according to the client's specifications.
computer software then determines
exactly which components must be built.
the side panels of the pool are made with galvanized steel
plated with zinc to prevent rusting.
they die-cut "v"-shaped notches
on the top
and will cut similar ones on the bottom later.
these little dimples in the metal
will hide the heads of bolts.
they punch out holes
on the remaining ends of the panel.
these will serve to join multiple panels
to create the perimeter of the pool.
they insert each panel in a powerful metal folder.
it firmly clamps the sheet of metal
and pushes up the edge to create a 90-degree angle.
taking a flat, metal sheet
and turning it into a three-dimensional object
makes it stronger.
they fold the notches at the top
and bottom ends of the panel.
they also die-cut a large hole for the clean-water inlet.
to make a curved panel, they place it on a fixed-radius jig.
they insert a metal profile called a stiffener
and bolt it in place.
they use a custom flat head bolt and nut
that will lodge themselves in the metal dimples.
next, an automated clamp
bends the panel to fit the jig's curve.
the "v"-shaped notches allow the panel to bend easily,
but workers must install radius
belts to maintain this shape.
they fasten the radius belts permanently
using hydraulic rivet guns.
all in-ground pool panels are made to order
and shipped as soon as they are ready.
in the thermoforming department,
they use a fixed sheet of a.b.s. plastic
to make the in-ground pool steps.
the sheet is firmly clamped in a frame
and goes into an oven.
the oven heats the plastic
to around 350 degrees for five minutes
until it gets soft and pliable.
as the plastic comes out of the oven,
a fiberglass mold is pushed up,
forming the main shape of the steps.
a rigid cage seals the sides,
and a powerful vacuum sucks out the air,
forcing the plastic against the mold.
a series of fans cool down the plastic.
when it has hardened enough, it's removed from the mold.
they prepare the vinyl liner for the inside of the pool.
there are about 30 designs to choose from.
workers unroll the vinyl on a cutting table,
where a conveyor will keep pulling on it.
a computer-controlled rotary knife
zips over the moving vinyl...
...cutting effortlessly
to create all the required sections.
the cutting process generates little waste,
and the materials are fully recyclable.
workers carefully fold each section of the liner.
all sections will be assembled in another department,
according to the assembly plan.
on-site, they assemble the steps,
the side panels, and the piping
for the filter and heater.
they pour concrete around the pool
to form a foundation.
then they pour some inside the pool
to create the bottom.
they smooth the surface and let
the concrete set for two days.
a worker unfolds the vinyl liner.
it has a semi-rigid pvc edge
that hooks into the top of the pool.
they fill the space around the pool with gravel
and pour a concrete sidewalk on top.
all that's left to do is add paving stones or a deck,
some plants and furniture,
and you'll have your own, personal paradise.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...