-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: in the days
of the american wild west,
you didn't leave home
without a gun.
both the sheriffs and outlaws
carried guns and ammunition.
it was important to have
your gun easily accessible.
wearing a holster
around the waist
putts a gun in the perfect
position for a quick draw.
these handcrafted
leather belts and holsters
are modeled after those made
in the late 1800s.
they're made for movies,
cowboy shooting competitions,
and historical reenactments.
a craftsman starts by using
a press
and a series of dies
to cut out out the holster
and belt components.
this is
vegetable-tanned leather,
the only type of leather
that's flexible enough
to carve or stamp.
he lays a paper template over
one end of the holster piece
and marks tiny dots with an awl.
he connects the dots
with a straight line
using a small knife.
he punches a hole at each dot.
the lines and holes form
two wide loops.
next, he carves a groove
for stitches along
what will be the main seam
of the holster body.
he sprays water onto the leather
to soften it.
he makes decorative lines
with a compass.
then, he imprints a design
into the leather
by striking a stamp
with a mallet.
because the leather is moist,
it compresses easily,
assuming the shape of the stamp.
these stamps are
modern-day copies
of the ones used
in the late 19th century.
a rosette is a common motif
of that era.
he uses one tool
for the outline,
one for the petals,
and another for the center
of the flower.
then, he adds details with
a small chisel-edged knife
and stamps on his maker's mark.
he shaves any sharp corners
and smoothly finishes the edge.
the holster piece is now cut,
embellished, and finished.
the next step is to sew it.
he marks the stitch holes
across the bottom
where he will later sew
the toe plug.
then, he pierces the holes
with an awl.
he soaks some sheep's wool
in neatsfoot oil and rubs it in.
this nourishes and conditions
the leather,
preserving the impressions
and enhancing the color.
once the oil is soaked in,
he applies a smoothing solution
onto the edges
and rubs them
with a piece of canvas.
now the sewing can begin.
he folds one end of the holster
piece to form a pouch.
then, he sews inside the groove
he cut for the main seam.
stitches sunken in a groove
are far stronger
than surface stitches.
when he completes the seam,
he burns the end of the
polyester thread with a lighter.
then, he sews on the toe plug
and inserts the pouch
into the double loops
at the other end of the piece.
next, he works on the belt.
after piercing stitch holes
in the main belt strip,
he sews on a thinner,
flexible strip,
bending it
into loops to hold ammo.
he glues on a leather lining
to make the belt more durable.
then, he sews on the billets.
they're the pieces that go on
each end of the main belt strip.
one billet has the buckle,
and the other has
the adjustment holes.
after applying some decorative
nickle studs known as spots,
he threads the belt
through the holster...
...and inserts the ammo.
this double-loop holster is
a copy of an 1880s holster
designed to hold
a single-action army pistol.
the craftsman can make
several different
authentic styles from this era,
customizing the holster to carry
a weapon of any size or shape.
narrator: from ocean wildlife
to shipwrecks,
the undersea world is
breathtaking.
many recreational scuba divers
want to capture what they see
on video.
they can do this with
an ordinary video camera,
encased in a specially designed
watertight housing unit.
this underwater housing
has remote camera controls
and a built-in monitor
that shows you
what the video camera sees.
at the factory,
a computer-guided mill uses
a variety of bits to shape
a tube of extruded aluminum.
the machine prepares the ends to
receive front and back pieces.
it forms a groove
for a rubber o-ring
to keep water out
and makes attachment points
on each side
of the housing for handles.
then, the mill cuts
the front and back pieces
out of two blocks of aluminum.
the machining process leaves
tool marks,
so they polish the housing parts
by putting them in a tumbler
full of ceramic stones.
after about an hour
of rubbing against the stones,
the aluminum is smooth and ready
to be anodized.
this process etches, dyes,
and seals the metal surface,
protecting it from the corrosive
effects of salt water.
next, a computer-guided laser
etches in
the manufacturer's logo.
laser etching is
far more durable than printing
because it bleaches
the black anodized surface white
so the lettering can't rub off
over time.
several parts of the housing
are made of plastic.
workers pour plastic pellets
into an injection-molding
machine.
the machine melts the pellets,
then shoots the liquefied
plastic into a mold.
after about 15 seconds,
the machine opens the mold
and ejects a newly formed part.
this part is a latch
that allows you
to open the housing
to insert a video camera.
the handles are made
of rubber-covered aluminum.
each of
its camera-control buttons
has an o-ring around it
to keep out water.
the controls are powered by
two lithium batteries
that sit inside
a separate sealed compartment.
when you press a control button,
the post underneath it makes
contact with electronics inside.
this produces an infrared signal
that communicates
with the camera
through tiny glass windows.
the back of the housing has
a built-in lcd monitor,
which displays
what the camera sees.
both the monitor and camera plug
into the same circuit board.
the handles fasten
to the housing
with a threaded ring.
there are also holes
on top of the housing
for attaching a carrying handle.
before attaching the front
and back of the housing,
they apply rubber o-rings
to keep water out.
then, they install
the flip filter.
it attaches magnetically
to a pivot
on the inside of the housing
and is operated by
an arm on the outside.
this filter is essential
because water absorbs
certain light wave lengths,
eliminating the appearance of
red, orange, yellow, and green,
depending on how deep you go.
to restore these colors
in the video,
the diver flips the filter over
the camera lens.
the factory tests every housing
to make sure
it's completely watertight.
the tester inserts
a video camera
and submerges the housing
in a water-filled tank.
he pressurizes the tank
to simulate
the underwater pressure
the housing will experience
at a depth of about 300 feet.
the housing passes the test
only if all the seals hold up
and no water leaks inside,
ruining the camera.
in addition to a flip filter,
divers sometimes use lights
to counter the muting effect
that underwater depth has
on colors.
the housing has
attachment points on the handles
for mounting lights,
enabling the video camera
to capture
the true vivid colors
of the undersea world.
narrator: soy beverages
originated in china
centuries ago,
long before lactose intolerance
and dairy allergies.
recently,
this dairy-free drink
has become a popular alternative
to milk,
allowing people to order
a latte, but hold the lactose.
it's not milk,
but it's a good substitute.
a soy beverage is made from
liquefied soy beans.
it has the look and consistency
of animal milk,
but is
an entirely different product.
it starts with a specific kind
of soybean,
one that has
just the right amount
of protein and carbohydrates.
they harvest these soybeans
when the plants are dry.
less moisture means the beans
will be less prone to spoiling.
they dehull the soybeans
and crack them into small bits.
a lift carries the heavy bag
of bean bits
to a scale
to weigh them for processing.
the operator cuts open
the bottom of the bag,
releasing the cracked soybeans
into a hopper.
here, augers move the cracked
beans up to two large grinders.
the system pipes in hot water,
and the grinders whip
the beans and water
into a creamy
soy-beverage concentrate.
the beverage travels
through steam-heated pipes.
this kills off any bacteria that
may have come from the field.
then, it's into a vacuum chamber
for a cooldown.
most of the manufacturing
equipment is sealed from the air
to prevent contamination.
the soy-beverage concentrate
leaves the vacuum chamber
and enters a centrifuge.
it spins out much
of the chunky insoluble fiber,
leaving smoother,
thinner liquid.
the soybean fiber
won't be wasted.
it will be used in food products
and animal feed.
the soy liquid flows
into a big blender.
they pipe in filtered water,
add refined sugar,
vanilla extract,
as well as various vitamins
and minerals.
he closes the lid
while the blender mixes
the ingredients
into a frothy soy beverage.
the soy beverage exits
the blender
and flows
into a huge storage tank,
where an agitator
keeps the various ingredients
well-mixed.
the tank is refrigerated
to preserve the beverage
while it's held for testing.
the operator takes a sample
to test
the consistency and nutritional
value of the beverage.
with his approval, the beverage
is released from the tanks.
it flows through pipes
injected with very hot steam.
this kills off any
microorganisms that may remain.
after a quick cooling,
the soy beverage
goes into a homogenizer.
it pushes the beverage
through small holes
to break down the fat,
reducing the size
of the particles.
the soy beverage accumulates
in a sterile tank
until it's ready to be packaged.
the soy beverages are packaged
without any exposure to
contaminants in the environment.
the packaging material is
made of a polyethylene laminate.
machinery takes the laminate
up to a steel ring
that forms it
into a tubular shape.
hot jaws seal
the sides and bottom,
then inject the soy beverage
and seal the top.
the cartons land on the conveyor
on their side.
they're liquid-tight
so nothing spills.
then, a conveyor transfers them
to a revolving wheel
that turns them right-side-up.
now that they are oriented
correctly,
they ride a windy conveyor
to a capping station.
plastic caps land on spouts
that have been molded
to the packages.
a system of rubber belts screw
the caps onto the spouts.
this packaging can preserve
a soy beverage for up to a year.
it probably won't be
on the shelf for that long
because someone is
always looking
for a dietary alternative.
narrator:
dogs and cats have round nails,
while humans have flat ones.
special trimming tools
have been developed
to give them
the perfect pedicure.
guillotine-style clippers have
a hole for the pet's nail
and a sliding blade that cuts it
so the pet will be back
on its feet in no time.
long nails can damage
a dog's foot pads,
so they must be trimmed
from time to time.
pets usually don't like
having their nails done,
but a guillotine-style trimmer
can make the experience
less of an ordeal.
its sliding blade trims
their nails quickly
so it's over
before they know it.
production of guillotine-style
pet-nail trimmers
starts with a feeder system.
the feeder system
uncoils a strip of steel
into a punch press.
the press cuts out
two handle blanks at once.
it also makes holes
for screws and rivets,
as well as a hook for a spring.
a second press rounds the handle
to make it easier to grip.
here is a large handle
before and after the shaping.
the handle now goes
into a third press.
this one folds the tabs down to
create a pocket for the blades.
here is a handle
before and after this forming.
next, a narrow strip of steel
unwinds into a press.
the press cuts and shapes it
into the main sliding blade.
the half-moon-shaped end will be
the cutting edge.
a worker slides the blades
onto a rack
with the half-moon edge
facing downward.
this makes it easier
to load the blades
into a grinding fixture.
she places two in each slot
with the half-moon facing up.
a carriage moves the fixture
back and forth
under a grinding stone.
it grinds the entire row
of blades at once.
this improves the strength and
sharpness of the cutting edge.
she inspects every blade
to confirm
that each one has been ground
to the correct profile.
on the left is a blade
before grinding
and on the right is one after.
she dips the blades
in a cleaning solution
and rinses them.
this cleaning removes
lubricating-oil residue
and metal filings.
she transfers the blades
to a perforated tray.
she spreads them evenly,
switches on an overhead fan,
and leaves them to dry
for several minutes.
heat treatment hardens
the blades,
and polishing finishes them.
next up is the retainer blade.
it's the one with the hole
for the nail.
she arranges the circular blades
on a magnetized tray.
the blades cling to the tray
as a carriage moves them
back and forth under a grinder.
the grinding sharpens
the front of the blades
and removes scale
left by a heat treatment.
this is the retainer blade
before and after grinding.
the pet-nail-trimmer parts
are ready for assembly.
the employee rivets a metal link
for the sliding blade
to the smaller handle.
once the parts have been
chrome-plated,
another worker hinges the large
handle to the smaller one.
he hooks one end of a spring
to the metal link.
he inserts the sliding blade
into the track
in the large handle,
lifting the link to hook it
into the blade.
he adds
the circular retainer blade.
he places a metal plate
over the track
and screws it in place.
this secures the top blade,
while allowing the link to move
the sliding blade.
he hooks the other end
of the spring
to the larger handle
and bends
the circular blade slightly
to give it the correct profile.
now a worker tests the trimmer
on dried buffalo hide.
dried buffalo hide is
tougher than pet nails.
with his okay, this cutting tool
is ready for the paws and claws
for our furry friends.
the main blade can be replaced
if it becomes dull,
which means
this pet-nail trimmer
can be used
for many years to come.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...