-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: cars that don't have fuel-injection systems
have carburetors.
they're an integral part of the engine
that mixes air and fuel in specific proportions,
vaporizes them, then sends the mixture to the intake manifold.
the manifold transfers the mixture
to the engine cylinders, where combustion occurs.
filtered air enters the carburetor
and mixes with fuel.
when you press the gas,
the carburetor opens conduits
for the air-and-fuel mixture to flow to the engine.
two metering blocks control the proportion of fuel to air.
computer-guided precision tools
machine them out of aluminum.
meanwhile, workers install components called boosters
in the carburetor's main body.
these boosters spray the fuel-and-air mixture as a mist
into tapered conduits called venturi.
those lead to the intake manifold,
which transfers the mixture to the engine's cylinders.
another computerized machine
makes each throttle shaft from a bar of steel.
these shafts turn when you press on the gas,
pivoting the butterfly discs
that open those conduits to the intake manifold.
the tooling machine bores screw holes
for attaching the butterflies
and carves grooves to prevent fuel from leaking out.
workers install the throttle shafts
in the carburetor's baseplate.
one side of this plate will bolt to the main body
and the other to the intake manifold.
the butterflies are made of aluminum, steel, or brass,
depending on the carburetor model.
he flips the baseplate and flares the bottom of the screws
to prevent them from vibrating out
and falling into the engine.
after installing an adjustment screw
for tuning the carburetor and using thread-locking fluid
to ensure the components don't loosen,
it's time to assemble the levers
that turn the throttle shafts.
a washer and cotter pin hold it all together.
a few pulls on the levers
ensure that both throttle shafts
move freely and smoothly,
turning the butterflies
perpendicular to open the conduits
and flat to close them.
next, the accelerator pump arm --
it shoots an initial burst of fuel when you start the car.
the carburetor's cast-metal fuel bowls
go into a vibrating tumbler
where metal balls smooth their surface.
then they receive a protective coating.
now a worker installs a float
to control the fuel level inside each bowl.
this is essential because too little fuel
would prevent engine start-up,
and too much fuel would overflow
and cause a shutdown.
a gasket sandwiched between the main body and the baseplate
will prevent fuel from leaking out and dirt from seeping in.
as a precaution, they coat the baseplate screws
with thread-locking fluid so they won't loosen over time.
now the baseplate that contains
the throttle shafts and butterflies
is connected to the main body that contains the boosters.
next come the metering blocks --
a gasket over each one, and then into a fuel bowl.
then one block-and-bowl unit
goes on each side of the main body.
just one final adjustment
to the accelerator pump lever and arm
and the carburetor is finished.
in the quality-control department,
every carburetor undergoes testing
with fluids similar to gasoline.
they check if the accelerator pump
squirts out enough fuel at ignition
and during the transition from idling mode to acceleration.
then, once everything's running
at regular speed,
they measure the amount of fluid
the boosters spray per hour.
once they pass quality control,
these carburetors will really be able to rev you up.
narrator: in an air conditioner,
liquid refrigerant absorbs heat
from inside the building,
changes into a gas, then flows outdoors.
it goes through a compressor, then a heat-exchanger coil
that transfers the heat to the outside air,
turning the refrigerant gas to liquid again.
the refrigerant then circulates
back inside the building.
this air-conditioner company
makes its coils entirely of aluminum,
which is five times more corrosion-resistant
than coils made of copper and aluminum.
to make the coil,
workers position an aluminum tube called the spine
in the middle
of this special winding machine.
then they feed in an aluminum strip.
the machine slits the aluminum strip
into thin teeth called fins.
then it folds and wraps
thousands upon thousands of fins
around the spine,
making the material they call spine fin tubing.
each tiny fin is a heat-transfer vehicle.
now to form the coil.
they hook the end of the spine fin tubing
to an automated winder.
it spirals the spine fin tubing
into a large cylindrical shape.
when they finish winding the coil,
they cut the end free from the feeder,
then apply hot glue to hold everything together.
the next machine presses the coil on all sides
to form it into the shape of the air conditioner.
a worker now cuts into the coil
and bears a row of tubing.
these cuts determine the circuits,
the term for the path the refrigerant takes
as it flows through the coil.
the pipes that feed these circuits are made of copper,
but copper doesn't fuse directly to aluminum.
so workers must first solder on
transition tubes
coated with a zinc/aluminum alloy.
then they attach the copper manifolds
that distribute the refrigerant
to the circuits.
once all the refrigeration components are in place,
workers subject the coil unit to an underwater pressure test
to make sure there are no leaks.
in another department, workers have assembled
the air conditioner's compressor.
they mount the compressor to a weather-resistant plastic base,
then cover it with a sound reducer,
a vinyl jacket filled with fiberglass insulation.
now they add the coil.
it sits between posts in the base.
for an air conditioner to work well,
it can't have air or moisture in its refrigeration system.
so workers hook up the unit to automated machinery
that completely evacuates the lines.
next, workers connect wiring and install corner supports,
then begin assembling the unit's exterior housing.
the top perimeter piece is shaped
to direct the airflow out of the unit.
a motorized fan pulls air into the unit.
a plastic grille lets air exit
and keeps debris from falling inside.
finally, they seal the refrigerant lines
by brazing shut a pair of tubes.
the housing parts are made of zinc-coated steel.
the factory spray-paints them
then bakes the paint for maximum durability.
air conditioners sit outdoors
so they have to withstand all kinds of weather.
the factory sends sample units
to a performance-testing laboratory.
it runs them in extreme heat, extreme cold, rain, and snow
to see if, under such harsh conditions,
they keep their cool.
narrator: next time you reach for the sugar bowl,
try to imagine that it was once
so rare and expensive
it was called white gold.
producing sugar from the sugarcane
first took place in india.
about 300 b.c.,
alexander the great's army reported seeing a reed
that gives honey without bees growing there.
this table sugar has many names --
mill white, plantation white, and crystal sugar.
but it all comes from the sugarcane.
it looks a lot like bamboo with fully grown stalks
that can measure up to 20 feet high.
here in the field,
a worker pares away the husk from a stalk of sugarcane,
then chews the cane's raw pulp
to extract the stalk's sweet juice.
this machine harvests the cane by cutting it at the base.
rotating scrolls feed the cane to the chopper drums inside.
as they chop the cane,
a fan blows the lighter leaves and tops back onto the field.
the heavier lengths of cane drop
into the base of a conveyor,
which feeds them into the transport bin
that follows alongside.
trucks rapidly transport the cut cane
to the sugar mill for processing.
once cut, sugarcane begins to lose its sugar content,
and damage to the cane during harvesting
accelerates this decay.
at the mill, trucks empty their
load onto a receiving table.
it feeds a belt conveyor
that takes the cane through two separate washes.
the cane must be as clean as possible
before extracting the juice.
but first, the cane's hard structure is broken down
inside this crusher,
where rotating hammers break the cane into small pieces.
a conveyor loads it into a milling tandem
designed to extract the sweet juice from the crushed cane.
in this milling tandem,
the cane passes through a series
of five or more consecutive mills.
large cylinders compress the cane fiber.
the juice pours out of the milling tandem
and diverts into a channel away from the bagasse,
the dry pulp that remains after extracting the juice.
a worker supervises the operation at each of the mills.
a vat collects the juice
that flows from the top and bottom of the mills.
now that the juice is extracted
from the sugarcane,
it's time to process it.
however, before turning the juice into sugar crystals,
a sample goes through a series of tests
at the sugar mill's laboratory.
first, a technician adds a thickener
that binds to impurities in the juice
and then filters it to obtain a clear, clean juice.
then he pours it into a polarimeter,
a machine that measures the concentration of sugar.
the juice from the mills
now falls through this 33-foot-high tower
as sulfur-dioxide vapors rise through it.
this process, known as sulfitation,
bleaches the juice.
then the juice flows
through a device that measures its p.h. level.
while at a separate vat,
workers add powdered lime to water,
preparing a solution to which they will then add the juice.
an agitator mixes the cane-juice-and-lime solution
for about six hours to complete
a process called alkalization.
it regulates the juice's
p.h. level and helps clarify it.
in reaction to the lime,
the juice's color changes from brown to yellow.
next, the juice goes into these clarifier tanks.
it takes over two hours for the juice to settle
and for the impurities to fall to the bottom of the tank.
a sample taken from the tank
shows how the sludge collects at the bottom,
while the clarified juice collects at the top.
next, we'll see how this clarified juice
transforms into flowing crystals
of white sugar.
narrator: christopher columbus never made it to asia
but discovered the caribbean
and later brought sugarcane plantings there.
sugarcane provides sugar
but also syrup, molasses, rum, and ethanol.
the many types of sugar available in stores
differ in crystal size or color,
depending on how they are processed.
workers filter the residue known as mud
from the clarifier tanks to extract any remaining sugar.
there's no waste here.
the mud will fertilize the cane fields,
and the bagasse will be burned as fuel.
the clarified juice collected from the clarifier tanks
now boils in a series of evaporators.
this brings the concentration of the sugar and the juice
up from 15% to 60%.
then the juice collects in 15-ton tanks
to clarify even more.
any sediment left in the juice floats to the top.
a rotating paddle skims this residue off
to the sides of the tank.
these tanks produce a type of syrup
that goes on for still more processing.
workers now pour
microscopic sucrose crystals suspended in alcohol
into the syrup.
this milky solution binds to the sugar present in the syrup
and helps draw it out.
next, it all boils in large vacuum pans,
forming sugar crystals.
as the water in the syrup boils away,
workers regularly check to see how the sugar is crystallizing.
the goal -- to produce a thick,
crystallized paste known as mesquite.
it then goes into
a high-speed centrifugal machine
to remove the sugar crystals from the uncrystallized syrup.
inside, the sugar spins
at 1,200 revolutions per minute.
this action draws the molasses
to the outer shell of the machine,
while the crystals remain in the inner basket.
sprays of water wash the crystals,
then the water is drawn out so that only the crystals remain.
this centrifuge works much the same way
as a washing machine set on the spin cycle.
it draws out moisture from the sugar
much like you draw out the wash
water from a load of laundry.
next, a conveyor belt carries the sugar crystals
out of the centrifuge.
this mill produces raw sugar,
which has a higher molasses color and is unbleached,
and plantation white sugar,
which has less molasses and is bleached a brilliant white.
the sugar on the conveyor now goes into a large dryer.
hot air blows into this dryer
to bring the sugar's humidity level down to .02%.
that's standard for table sugar.
the dried sugar pours out from
the dryer into a bag on a scale.
it's full when it weighs in at 2,200 pounds.
a hoist then carries the bags to a platform
at the far end of the packing facility.
at 3.3 tons, that's a heavy load.
it lowers each bag over a chute
that leads to the factory's main floor.
workers carefully open each bag in turn
and pour out the sugar directly into the chute.
it feeds an automated packaging machine,
which fills a series of 4½-pound plastic bags,
seals them, and separates them.
this packing facility produces 200,000 bags a day.
that means processing 400 tons of white sugar daily.
this fine plantation-white sugar
is available in a variety
of convenient packaging options,
and that should sweeten anyone's day.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...