-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: whether tightening
the wheels on your bike
or working on your car,
a combination wrench
can make the toughest jobs
safe and easy.
the best combination wrench
gives you reach and strength
and won't bust your knuckles
when you're working
in those hard-to-reach places.
a high-quality combination
wrench can last you a lifetime.
a combination wrench tightens
and loosens nuts and bolts
using its u-shaped open end
or its enclosed box end
with a hexagonal shape.
combination wrenches come
in imperial and metric sizes.
to start, a steel bar travels
into a die-cutting machine
that cuts it into lengths
called billets.
each billet
will become a wrench.
one by one,
a machine feeds the billets
into an induction heater.
it heats them to more
than 1,800 degrees fahrenheit,
then sends them
into a forging press,
where the first die creates
the wrench's general shape.
the second die
gives it its finished shape.
and the third
trims off the excess metal.
the wrenches
exit the forge press
and cool off on their way
into a collection box.
then a worker grinds off
the trim line,
a thin line of excess metal
created when the top
and bottom dies come together.
he loads the wrenches
into an automatic
edge-polishing machine.
using an 80-grit sanding belt,
the machine grinds the trim line
on both sides of the handle.
the wrenches leave
the edge-polishing machine
trim-line-free.
a worker then places each wrench
onto a 75-ton hydraulic press,
which stamps it with the brand
name, size, and part number.
this bend machine gives
the box end a 15-degree angle.
a vertical milling machine then
drills a hole into the box end,
using coolant to keep the drill
from overheating.
this is a hydraulic
hex broach machine.
the broach tool is what gives
the hole a hexagonal shape.
open-end wrenches also go
through a broaching operation.
in this case, the broach tool
shapes the open end
into the desired size.
a worker then grinds
the open end of the wrenches
and makes sure
they're perfectly smooth.
the wrenches now undergo
a three-stage
heat-tempering procedure
to harden and strengthen
the metal.
for some combination wrenches,
a sliding machine cuts
an opening out of the box end
that has the hex shape
broached into it.
this turns the wrench
into a flare nut wrench
that's ideal for working on
hard-to-reach bolts,
like on a hydraulic line.
ceramic stones
and a chemical solution
polish the wrenches
for eight hours,
giving them
a bright luster finish.
a machine then dips the wrenches
into a nickel-plating solution
that helps make them
corrosion-resistant.
this series of baths
then plate the wrenches
with trivalent chrome,
which is a safer,
more environmentally friendly
alternative
to traditional plating methods.
after a final rinse in water,
the wrenches come out
with a bright cosmetic finish.
combination wrenches are
available in a variety of sets,
all conveniently organized
and neatly stored.
since the 1920s,
this company has been making
combination wrenches
of all shapes and sizes
for jobs
of all shapes and sizes.
narrator: in a time
of health-conscious eating,
deli meats
remain a mealtime favorite.
almost everyone
loves a great-tasting sandwich
or sausage hot off the grill.
today, the best deli meats are
prepared from the leanest cuts.
they have no trans fat,
they are low in sodium
and saturated fat,
and contain no fillers.
some companies prepare
deli meats largely by hand
to maintain
that old-world tradition.
sausages begin as cuts
of fresh meats in a grinder.
the ground meat
falls into a collection tub...
which then deposits the meats
into a mixer.
adding ice
keeps the meats cold and fresh.
a worker then adds salt
and all-natural spices
and seasonings.
the mixer
blends it all together.
a worker
feeds a natural sausage casing
into a machine
called a sausage linker
that forms and links
the sausages.
a look inside the sausage linker
reveals where the meat is pumped
into the natural casing
and shaped
into the desired sausage size.
as the sausages
come out of the linker,
they hook onto
a conveyor system.
they're ready to go
into the smokehouse for cooking.
workers send the cooked sausage
into an oven
that destroys
any possible surface bacteria.
they pack the sausages
into plastic bags,
which are date-stamped.
then a machine
vacuum-seals the packages,
making them ready for the store.
an olive loaf begins
with a mixture of olives,
pickles, and pimientos.
again, a worker adds salt
and all-natural seasonings,
mixing it together with
blended fresh beef and pork.
this stuffer machine
fills loaf pans
with the season-blended meats.
another worker puts a rack
filled with
uncooked olive loaves
into a smokehouse oven.
after an initial cooking
that sets the loaf shape,
he removes the loaves
from the oven.
at this time, only the exposed
part of the loaves is browned.
after he takes them
out of the pans,
they will go back into the oven
to brown all sides.
it takes about 10 hours
to cook these special
european-style loaves.
another worker
loads pepperoni into a machine
called a revolving horn.
it stuffs a casing
with a mixture of beef and pork
seasoned with italian spices.
the horn stuffs the casing
with the precise amount of meat
and seals both ends.
the pepperoni
is then hung up on a rack
and taken into a smokehouse
for cooking.
another worker
prepares german bologna
by slipping
a natural beef casing
onto a machine
called a stuffing horn.
he stuffs the casing
with a mixture of beef and pork
and all-natural spices
and seasonings.
he seals the end of the casing
with aluminum clips.
another worker,
using a paddle with spikes,
perforates the casing to allow
air to escape during cooking
to ensure
even cooking and browning.
now it's
the german bologna's turn
for a stay in the smokehouse.
about eight hours later,
the german bologna
is evenly cooked.
using a guide, a worker slices
the sausage into even cuts,
which are then packed
and date-stamped.
from authentic german bologna
to all types of sausages
and distinctive deli loaves,
deli meats
are served around the world.
narrator:
scotland is the birthplace
both of golf
and the motorized golf car,
invented in 1946 by a dentist
named john "doc" keegan.
since the late 1950s,
golf cars have become widely
used on courses everywhere.
they're built low to the ground
to remain steady,
even over
the most uneven terrain.
this battery-powered golf car
has everything to get you around
in comfort and style.
it can't help you
with your swing,
but it can get you
to the next hole in a jiffy.
to make a golf car, the first
step is to build the frame
with lightweight
aluminum i-beams.
they go through
two separate machines
to bend them into shape.
metal forms
press down into vinyl
and stretch it into the shape
of the front and back seats.
workers cut and staple the vinyl
over a plywood base
covered with a layer
of foam padding.
they trim away the excess vinyl
and set the finished seats
aside.
now it's time
to assemble the power train.
here, workers place an axle
onto the differential,
which rotates the wheels.
they cover it
with a staff ring...
then bolt the car's
48-volt electric motor
onto the transaxle,
the assembled transmission,
differential, and drive axle.
they assemble the car's frame
on a fixture,
starting with the driver side,
then the passenger side...
then the center i-beam that
holds the two sides together.
they set the assembled frame
onto the power train
and bolt the car's front
suspension mechanism onto it.
as the car moves on
to the next assembly station,
a plastic underbody comes down
to cover
the front part of the frame.
workers now set in the
accelerator and brake pedal.
then they lower
the power compartment
that holds the car's battery
at the vehicle's rear.
they connect the battery to the
motor with four separate wires,
then hook them up
to the electric control module
that commands the engine.
now they can cover
the rear working parts
with the plastic underbody.
the underbody
provides the support
on which to install
the car's working parts,
like this pedal mechanism
or the steering column.
all the electric tools
that apply torque
are computer-monitored.
if the amount of torque applied
at any of the 130
assembly stations is incorrect,
the system prevents the car from
advancing to the next station
until they get it right.
this eliminates any problems
that might arise
with over-tightened
or loose bolts.
workers now tighten
the battery wires,
then check the accelerator.
golf cars may not attain speeds
higher than 15 miles per hour
in compliance
with industry regulations.
next, they set in
the front and back seats
that fit snugly into
the molded plastic rear body
and screw in the front fascia
that covers the underbody.
they set the brake rod in place,
make sure it moves
the brake pedal properly,
and tighten it.
the screen located overhead
indicates when they've applied
just the right amount of torque.
finally,
they hammer in the hubcaps
and set in
the front beauty panel,
also made of molded plastic.
the car's now fully assembled
and ready to roll.
the finished golf cars
offload automatically
from the assembly line
thanks to a hydraulic lift.
they get a final inspection
from every angle --
even under the seat.
finally, workers drive them
to an outdoor lot.
no worries --
their aluminum chassis
ensures they can endure even
the harshest weather conditions.
soon,
they'll carry eager golfers
across courses
throughout the world.
narrator:
an airship is basically
a large helium balloon
with an engine for propulsion.
the passengers and crew ride in
a gondola suspended underneath.
when there's an inside frame
supporting it,
the airship
is called a rigid type.
when there's no framework,
it's called a nonrigid type,
or blimp.
the envelope material
is made of five polyester-based
fabrics bonded together.
it's lightweight, yet resistant
to harsh weather and u.v. rays.
the crew inflates the envelope
with helium,
an inert, nonflammable gas.
at the back of the envelope
are a rudder and fins
for steering.
the factory constructs
each fin's frame
out of tough,
lightweight carbon fiber.
workers coat it with adhesive,
then apply
a polyester aircraft fabric,
adding extra adhesive
to seal the seams.
then, using an iron,
they heat-shrink the fabric
until it's taut.
they repeat this process with
two additional layers of fabric,
then paint it white.
they mount the fins
to the airship envelope
with a combination
of steel cables and rope.
the steel cables are rigid,
but the rope has some give when
the envelope flexes in flight.
a system of cables and pulleys
connect the rudder and fin
to the cockpit.
the pilot manipulates them
with yokes.
the flaps
control up-and-down movement,
the rudder, sideways movement.
engineers inspect the envelope
inside and out for pinholes
to ensure
no helium can leak out.
to repair a pinhole,
technicians first cover it
with a piece of tape,
then brush on some adhesive
in a circular pattern.
they apply a circular patch
made of the same five-layer
fabric as the envelope.
using a spatula, they push out
air and excess glue
to ensure airtight adhesion.
the airship runs
on two gasoline-powered engines.
workers hoist them
into the engine bay
at the back of the gondola.
the propeller's sharp blades are
encased in a duct for safety.
one propeller goes on each side.
the blades
of the propeller pivot
to move the airship in reverse
without having to stop
the engine.
the cockpit electrical panel
has gas-management gauges
because as the airship rises,
the helium expands.
so the pilot has to reduce
air pressure inside the envelope
to keep it from bursting.
in a pinch, the pilot can also
open a valve to vent helium.
to test the helium valve,
technicians
blow in pressurized air
while brushing liquid
along the edge.
any bubbles indicate leaks
that need sealing.
the valve opens and closes
with levers and cables.
unlike electronic controls,
cables can be repaired in midair
if something breaks.
inside the envelope,
they install air sacks
called ballonets,
the gray areas in this diagram.
the pilot deflates the ballonets
to rise
and inflates them to descend.
workers attach
the envelope and gondola
with cables, belts, and braces
and fill a ballast tank
under the gondola with water.
in an emergency,
the crew can dump the water
for a boost of buoyancy.
the gondola also has
compartments for shot bags,
22-pound bags of lead.
before takeoff,
the pilot checks the weight
with passengers, equipment,
and fuel on board.
then the crew
loads enough shot bags
to balance the airship.
to park the airship,
they lock its nose onto a mast.
just before flight time,
a truck tows the mast
out of the hangar.
then it's all hands on deck.
well, actually, all hands
on gondola, until takeoff.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...