-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: the jaws of life
were first used in 1963
to free racecar drivers
from car crashes.
it was so big,
it had to be suspended
from the back of a pickup truck.
today it weighs
as little as 33 pounds
and is small enough
for one person to operate.
it can free an accident victim
from a car in minutes.
in an emergency situation,
timing is everything.
a rescue tool has to pry open
a vehicle as easily as a tin can
or cut through solid steel
like butter,
because a few seconds
can make all the difference.
what gives the cutting blades
and the spreading arms
their power is hydraulic fluid.
the jaws of life begin
with a milling machine
that shapes the spreader arms
from a bar of solid
aircraft-grade aluminum.
the spreader arms then get
a protective coating.
a lathe now makes the cap that
fits on the end of the tool.
a high-speed carbide tip shapes
the solid aluminum
into a finished endcap
that is then drilled
and treated to a coat
of rust-resistant protection.
arms that both cut and spread
are made from tool steel.
a surface grinder ensures that
the two arms are perfectly flat.
a worker installs a seal
that prevents
the hydraulic fluid
from leaking out
of the cylinder.
he lubricates a piston
with hydraulic fluid
so it slides into the cylinder
without damaging the interior.
then he taps it in
so it will connect
with the link assembly.
he attaches a link assembly
to the piston
and secures it in place.
the link assembly relays power
to the cutting blades
or spreader arms.
he then attaches an assembled
end cap to the cylinder
and bolts it in place.
he connects the two hoses
that lead to the tool's
hydraulic cylinder.
he puts on a handgrip
that protects the hoses
and makes it easier
to work the thumbwheel.
he tightens the bolts
and completes the control valve.
he then attaches
the front handle
that allows the operator
to hold the tool safely.
this protective guard will keep
all the moving components
away from a rescuer's hands.
then he aligns the holes
in the blades to the tool
and inserts a steel pivot pin.
he puts on a locknut,
and, as with all fasteners
on the rescue tool,
he tightens it to a precise
engineering specification.
after mounting the blades,
he secures them
to the link assembly
with a steel-alloy pin
and a snap ring.
then he folds
the protective guard back
and finishes assembling
the tool.
a worker then tests the tool,
which has been filled
with fire-resistant
hydraulic fluid.
the fixture he uses is designed
to measure the pressure
at the strongest point
in the cutting.
the tool passes
the pressure test.
whether it's a rescue tool
that cuts through metal
or pries it open,
emergency-response teams
arriving on an accident scene
will have what it takes
to help save lives.
narrator: the quest
for the perfect tree
is a rite of the holiday season.
and ever since
the late 19th century,
people have been trying to come
up with an artificial version.
first,
there were feather trees
and, later,
trees made of animal bristles.
but by the 1960s,
the use of synthetics finally
gave us the perfect fake fir.
today's faux firs
can be several stories tall --
big enough for your town square.
you can get them
with many of the trimmings
so decorating
isn't such a stretch.
these big artificial trees start
with a steel skeleton.
rollers bend steel tubing
into arcs.
they'll be joined to form
the base of the framework.
workers weld vertical supports
to the arcs,
building the structure
in sections.
a spray of polyester powder
gives the welded metal
a smooth finish
that's actually tougher
than paint.
they bake the parts
to set the coating.
after a quick cooling,
it's time to assemble
all the pieces.
they fasten
the structure together
with u-bolts and a ratchet.
meanwhile,
a roll of green pvc plastic
winds its way towards a roller
equipped
with many circular cutters.
they slice it
into 4-inch-wide strips.
each of the narrow
plastic strips
then goes under a roller
with even more blades.
they shred it into
a needlelike configuration,
leaving a solid spine
at the center
to hold the simulated needles
together.
an automated spool then winds up
the fringed green pvc.
these artificial needles come in
an assortment of colors,
so if you want glitz,
you can really go out on a limb.
here,
streams of the fringed green
and a strip of brown pvc travel
over tension-control guides.
steel wire unwinds and merges
with the green and brown pvc.
this machine
twists them together.
the brown strip lands at
the core of the twisted fringe,
creating the illusion
of a stem among the needles.
this twisting technology
churns out a continuous supply
of artificial greenery.
giant scissors slice it
to the correct length.
to make branches
that appear snow-tipped,
this machine twists
and then frosts the pvc needles
with a spray
of white latex paint.
they use this ring fastener
to crimp the artificial foliage
together, branch by branch.
this creates a tightly knit
mass of greenery
that will be used to cover
the tree's framework.
they apply single garlands
on key parts
of the tree grid first,
using a handheld
pneumatic fastener.
they fill in
the sections between them
with the assembled branches.
this is easier than
attaching them to the framework
branch by branch.
they string the lights
and then plug them in
to check each bulb.
after all,
it's easier to change one now
than after the tree
has been erected,
especially since this one
will be a story and a half tall.
they also wire the ornaments
to the branches.
it's one less job
for the customer to do.
and now it's time
to put up the tree.
they bolt the cone
of wired greenery
to the lower framework...
...and then hook the panels
of artificial greenery
onto the rest of the structure.
it has taken just one day
for this artificial tree
to come together,
where growing a real one
this size
would take many years.
and the convenience is unreal.
narrator: soda crackers
are also called saltines,
originally a brand name that
over time became a generic term.
you can eat them plain
or spread something on them
or crumble them into soup.
doctors even recommend
eating soda crackers
when you're nauseous,
because they're dry
and easy to digest.
they're flat and bumpy
on the outside,
with a tasty texture
resulting from some interesting
chemical reactions.
workers first dump ice
into a trough
to prevent the dough from
overheating during fermentation.
the first ingredient
is a specific amount
of finished dough
to kick-start the fermentation
of this new batch.
to that, they add water,
wheat flour, yeast,
and enzymes
to help the fermentation.
a mixer blends the ingredients
for about 5 minutes.
they let the dough sit
for 16 hours
while the enzymes break down
the starch and the wheat
into simple sugars.
the yeast then reacts
with those sugars,
producing carbon-dioxide gas,
which makes the dough rise.
then they adjust
the fermented dough's ph level
with sodium bicarbonate
to produce the right flavor,
color, and shelf life.
then, for additional flavoring,
some salt...
malted barley flour...
and vegetable oil.
then the mixer remixes
the dough for about 5 minutes
to blend in
these new ingredients.
now they let the dough ferment
for another 6 hours.
the sodium bicarbonate
counteracts the acidity
this produces
and relaxes the gluten
so that the dough
now breaks easily
when stretched --
the perfect consistency
for soda crackers.
a machine then extrudes
the massive dough
into a sheet
that's 2 inches thick
and folds the sheet
over itself 3 times.
this folding creates
the light and flaky layers
inside the cracker.
the dough sheet then goes
through a series of rollers
that reduce it
to its final thickness,
about a millimeter.
a revolving die
cuts the cracker shapes,
perforations and all.
the little pins puncture
the dough
and push it firmly
onto the conveyor belt.
this keeps the dough
from deforming
when moisture and gases escape
during the baking process.
from there, the sheet passes
under a shower of salt.
the sheet
now takes a three-minute trip
through a long oven with
different temperature zones.
gas flames bake the dough
from above and below.
the heat transforms the
sodium bicarbonate in the dough
into carbon-dioxide gas,
which then breaks through
and escapes.
this drives out trapped moisture
and forms blisters
in the crackers.
as the sheet of baked crackers
exits the oven,
a roller breaks it into rows.
the rows then run from
one conveyor belt to the next,
stacking like roof shingles.
alignment wheels
keep them straight
until the next set of wheels
gently breaks the rows
into individual crackers.
each row makes its way
through a series of gates
that guide it onto a track
that leads
to the packaging equipment.
the crackers are upright now,
and the machine
begins dividing them
according to the number
of crackers per package --
in this case,
those little 2-cracker packs
you often get with soup.
the cracker pairs enter
the wrapping machine,
which sandwiches them between
a sheet of printed plastic film.
a wheel then
simultaneously seals
and cuts the wrapper
between each pair.
this all happens
at an astonishing rate
of 525 packages per minute.
and that's the way
the cracker crumbles.
narrator: ratchets come
in many shapes and sizes
and can tackle almost any job.
ratchets with socket attachments
deliver more power and speed
without slipping
or damaging the bolt or nut.
just snap an interchangeable
socket onto the ratchet,
and you're ready to get the job
done quickly and properly.
versatile and easy to use,
a ratchet tightens or loosens
nuts and bolts
in a continuous motion.
it uses removable sockets
that fit many different sizes
of fittings and fasteners.
to start, a steel bar travels
into a shearing machine
that cuts it
into specific lengths.
these pieces, called billets,
will be used
to make the ratchet.
a machine feeds the billets
into an induction coil,
which heats them to about
1,800 degrees fahrenheit.
a forge press then shapes
the soft billets into ratchets.
the first die creates
the ratchet's general form.
the second die gives it
its finished shape.
and the third die cuts off
excess metal.
the ratchets exit
the forge press
and fall into a collection box,
where they cool.
then a vertical milling machine
prepares the body cavity
to receive the internal
working parts of the ratchet,
called the gear assembly.
a worker then places the ratchet
on a hydraulic press,
which stamps the brand name
and the on-and-off indicator
on the ratchet's face.
a lathe cuts away the rough
forged metal from the handle
and trims off the end,
making it ready
to receive the handgrip.
a worker then grinds
any rough edges
off the machined ratchet.
then he crimps each side
of the smooth handle
so it will hold
a rubber handgrip in place.
the ratchets now undergo
a 3-stage tempering process
that hardens
and strengthens the metal.
ceramic stones
and a chemical solution
prepare the ratchets
for nickel and chrome plating.
a plating machine
cleans the ratchets,
then treats them to a nickel
and a trivalent chrome plating.
the two platings make
the ratchets corrosion-resistant
and give them
a bright cosmetic finish.
a worker then lubricates
the ratchet cavity,
puts in an on-and-off switch
and a spacer to support
additional components.
a worker sets a retention ball
onto a ratchet gear,
then a punch press
locks it in place.
next they fit a gear mechanism
into the cavity,
then attach
all the internal components
that control the movements
of the ratchet.
once completed,
the gear assembly allows
or restricts movement.
so, putting the assembly into
either the on or off position
is all it takes to tighten
or loosen a nut or bolt.
she then puts a rubber seal
onto a cover plate
and closes up the ratchet.
she makes sure the gear assembly
works properly.
finally, this machine
friction-fits a handle
on the ratchet's shaft.
evolving from a steel bar
to a finished product
in 10 steps,
the ratchets must undergo
a final test of strength
to prove they meet
the highest quality standards.
ratchet sets are available
in a variety of sizes.
they're used for big
and small jobs by handymen
and professional mechanics
alike.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...