-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: bit by bit,
the screwdriver makes the life of a handyman
a whole lot easier.
the screwdriver first showed up
in the early part of the 19th century.
it evolved from a flat-bladed
bit used in a carpenter's brace,
and its invention was a definite turning point.
these trusty tools come with different bits
to fit a variety of screwheads,
so all you have to do is apply the right torque,
and it's mission accomplished.
the job of making screwdrivers
starts with coils of specially formulated steel.
wheels straighten a thick wire,
and then it travels through an aperture.
on the other side, a machine rocks back and forth
as it cuts the wire to length
and forces it through four dies.
the first die narrows the steel
to the required diameter.
the others form a hexagonal bolster partway down.
this bolster will allow a wrench
to be applied to the screwdriver
to increase its turning power.
a quick shower washes away the lubricant,
and these screwdriver shafts are ready for inspection.
the technician examines them for defects
and measures the length and the dimensions
of the hexagonal bolster.
once he confirms that everything
is to specification,
the screwdriver shafts head into a machine
that will transform the tips into a slotted shape.
at the first two stations, the press flattens the tip.
the third one trims it and stamps the part number onto it.
the flat blade is probably
the most common of screwdrivers.
its chiseled tip turns a standard slotted screw.
after the screwdrivers are heat-treated
to increase their hardness,
they sand the tips to shave off
.1 of a millimeter.
they confirm that with this slotted guide.
then they insert the screwdrivers
into a different slotted device.
this one shuttles them over to a grinding wheel.
this wheel trims them to their final dimensions.
visually, the change is subtle,
but this fine-tuning will make a big difference
in the screwdrivers' performance.
now they twirl in a machine
that blasts the tips with mild abrasive.
this texturizes the surface
to allow this screwdriver to really grip a screwhead.
the texturized tip is the one on the right.
over at another station,
a different kind of screwdriver
is taking shape.
this is a phillips.
its tip has a beveled cross point
to correspond with a phillips screw.
this machine carves ridges into
the bevels of the cross point
to give it extra gripping power.
a press then slams into
the other end of the screwdriver
to create flanged grooves.
these grooves will allow them
to lock the screwdriver shaft into its handle.
it's time for some positive vibrations.
this vibrating feeder
causes the screwdrivers to chafe against each other,
and the action removes any waste material.
after they texturize the cross-point tip,
it's over to a laser machine.
it etches the part numbers onto
these polyurethane handles.
and now for the gripping part.
the assembler attaches the
handle to the screwdriver blade.
he then places the screwdriver in a machine
that applies mechanical force
to solidly entrench the shaft in the handle.
with the screwdrivers now on a tray,
they move through a curtain of plastic.
a machine heat-seals the plastic
around the edges.
the loosely wrapped tray then enters a special furnace,
and the heat shrinks the plastic around the tray
to neatly wrap up this job.
it has taken several days to make these screwdrivers,
and now they're ready for
the twists and turns of any job.
tools like these screwdrivers
are really an extension of the human hand.
a quality tool will enable you to work with more precision,
but, of course,
you have to grasp the fundamentals of your project.
and depending on what kind of handyman you are,
that could be a whole other story.
narrator: compact track loaders
move materials like dirt,
gravel, and even snow
into a dump truck or any other type of machinery.
the rubber tracks give them the traction to work hard
while treading lightly over soft
ground conditions like grass.
compact track loaders can be used year round.
compact track loaders give a smooth and stable ride
over all sorts of terrain.
their rubber tracks and suspension
allow them to turn on a dime
and work in places where other machines can't.
to start, technicians attach four sets of mid wheels
to a frame rail.
the wheels are made of plastic and rubber.
then they assemble the axle suspension
using rubber cords so the wheels
can flex up and down.
they tighten the bolts and mark them as done.
after they attach two more sets
of mid wheels,
what's called the frame-rail assembly is complete.
technicians then attach a turnbuckle to the frame rail.
the turnbuckle will be used
to tighten or loosen the rubber track.
next, they put together the drive sprocket assembly --
the part that drives the track.
they put a drive motor into a housing,
add the sprocket assembly, then
put on a heavy-duty bearing.
finally, they install a support plate
which completes the drive-motor assembly.
a technician then mounts the drive-motor assembly
onto the frame-rail assembly.
technicians install the rubber track
a little lubrication makes the track go on easier
until its molded lugs interlock
with the drive-sprocket assembly.
next comes a larger idler wheel,
which they install at the end of the track,
securing it on the axle.
he tightens the turnbuckle
to give the rubber track the correct tension,
completing the undercarriage assembly.
the track loader will ride on two of these undercarriages.
a technician installs the machine's main suspension
onto the chassis, then connects
the hydraulic-valve assembly.
it's the hub to which they connect all the hydraulic lines
and hoses used to control the machine.
using a crane,
the technician mounts the engine
to the chassis.
once the engine is secure,
he puts on the integrated fuel tank.
he installs a hydraulic cylinder
and connects its two fluid lines.
one cylinder goes on each side of the machine.
they are used to move the loader bucket up and down.
he then connects the undercarriage assembly
to the chassis using an undercarriage pin
and pneumatic wrench to secure it in place.
a technician now installs the loader assembly --
the part that holds the bucket or other attachment.
once installed, this machine can lift more than 3 tons.
he secures the assembly in place
using heavy-duty pins.
then technicians install the operator's station
that helps protect the driver from the elements
and from debris.
a technician makes sure the loader arm works properly,
then drives the track loader on a treadmill
to test all the systems.
he runs the engine at full speed
until it reaches the appropriate
operating temperature.
this shows that everything is working as it should.
finally, he affixes the company logo.
compact track loaders are strong and agile machines.
they work just as well on dry surfaces
as they do in wet and muddy conditions.
narrator: stepping onto
the scale at the doctor's office
is a moment of truth not everyone enjoys.
little has changed in the simple design of these scales
since the early 1900s.
cast iron has given way to steel and aluminum.
that means they've actually gotten lighter over the years,
unlike some of us.
this scale compares the weight placed on the platform
with a standard weight known as a poise
that slides along an off-center
waybeam until it balances.
a punch press forms sheet steel
into the head,
or top of the scale's column.
workers form the column from another piece of steel
using this press brake.
then they spot-weld the head and column together.
another machine stamps out lengths of steel
that will form the frame for the scale's base.
workers use the press brake again
to bend both sides of the steel lengths.
then they fold it by hand to form the frame.
they clamp the frame onto a base,
and this robot welds them together.
the robot moves on to weld other components to the scale,
such as the lever mechanism and the baseplate.
now workers place steel bearings
at each corner of the base,
where the lever mechanism will rest
then add the base frame.
next, they install the long lever...
then the short lever.
a c-clip joins them together.
once it's right-side up,
the lever mechanism hangs off the platform.
the columns receive a coat of electrostatically charged paint
that evenly coats the metal for a flawless finish.
once it's dry,
a machine silk-screens the brand name onto the column.
now for the final assembly.
a worker inserts a 4-foot steel rod
that will tie the waybeam to the levers.
he works the rod up through the column,
then, at the column's head,
he screws it to the waybeam's shelf.
another worker hammers the large poise
into position on the waybeam, then the smaller poise.
they screw on to the beam in two
parts so they can glide freely.
she applies a gauge onto the beam
that indicates the weight measured in pounds
from 0 to 350.
now she takes a zero-adjustment screw
and spring-loads it onto the beam.
this allows the beam to balance
when the poises are set at zero
and the scale is unweighted.
a retaining ring holds the screw in place.
at the assembly line,
workers fasten the scale's column to its base.
they cover the pivot to protect it from wear
and set down the waybeam that balances on it.
then they connect it to the steel rod
that comes up through the column
from the base.
once the waybeam connects to
the lever mechanism at the base,
the scale is functional.
now it's time to make sure it's accurate.
each scale goes to a weigh station
where workers check the readings
in 44-pound increments.
if the readings are off,
workers go back and remove some
lead from inside the large poise
so the scale calibrates perfectly.
just a few grams of lead
can make all the difference in accuracy.
finally, they place a plastic cover over the working parts,
and the scale is complete.
narrator: when the competition is stiff,
sometimes it helps to be a little flexible,
and that's the idea behind the carbon-fiber softball bat.
manufacturers can tweak the stiffness of carbon fiber
to produce a bat with some elasticity.
it's a striking innovation.
carbon bats are a high-tech way to improve your game.
incredibly, these hard-hitting bats
start with pliable sheets of carbon-fiber
infused with a special resin.
they crisscross the sheets
and then iron the side with a paper liner
to melt the layers at the seams.
a hot steel roller then applies
some serious pressure
to fuse the carbon-fiber layers together.
they slice it to size.
now they peel away that paper liner
and spiral the carbon fiber around a steel bat form.
by changing the angle of the weave,
they can fine-tune the bat's elasticity
to a league's specifications
or to an individual player's performance level.
they wind polypropylene tape around the carbon layers
to squeeze out the air between them.
they bake the carbon in an oven
for two hours.
this cures the resin impregnated in the carbon
so the many layers become one.
after they slice away the tape,
they slide braided weaves of carbon and fiberglass
over the fused carbon form.
they secure the braided tubing with tape.
they pull a layer of thick carbon over that,
followed by a superstrong synthetic weave called aramid.
one last taping,
and this softball bat is ready to take shape.
they place the carbon-wrapped forms in a mold.
as the mold closes around them,
they prepare an epoxy resin.
they then inject the resin into the mold.
it permeates the many layers wrapped around the steel form.
the mold applies hot pressure to bake the layers together
and define the contours of these bats.
it takes just a few minutes in the mold
to transform the many layers into a solid bat.
this 5-ton puller now extracts the steel form
on which the carbon bat was built.
they use this pneumatic equipment
to test its flexibility.
a lathe now spins the bat as a cutter moves in
and carves the hardened resin base into a knob.
the knob on the right
now meets league specifications.
now this carbon bat goes for another spin
so they can sand it from every angle.
they dip the bats two at a time in black primer
and hang them to dry.
the bat then takes on a more colorful appearance
with a variety of spray paints.
they transfer decals with production information
onto the barrel of the bat,
and a laser burns the company logo and serial number
into the painted carbon.
they cap the bat
by press-fitting a polycarbonate
plug to the barrel.
resin completes the seal, and they add extra
to adjust the bat's weight to league specifications.
they pump the resin in through a hole in the knob,
and it flows up to the barrel plug.
then they weigh each bat
to verify that it's within an acceptable range.
using a hydraulic ram,
they drive a steel pin into the
hole on the bottom of the knob
to achieve the correct balance point.
and it's time to wrap this carbon bat
with synthetic leather, making it easier to grip.
these high-tech bats are now ready
to team up with raw talent, and they could
blow the competition out of the ball park.
if you have any comments about the show
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...