--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
today on "how it's made,"
cartridge blades,
chocolate banana loaves,
vending machines
and dive computers.
developed in the middle
of the 20th century,
the cartridge blade
is an invention
with many cutting edges.
the plastic cartridge
houses up to five razor
blades.
with multiple blades,
fewer shaving strokes
may be necessary,
which results
in a faster shave.
for the multibladed
cartridge razor,
getting rid of stubble
is no trouble.
when the many blades
become dull,
the cartridge
can simply be popped out
and replaced
with a new one.
making cartridge blades starts
with coiled steel strips
that are a few miles long.
the strips unwind
around guide rollers
that orient them
for entry into punch machines.
revolving cylinders help feed
the steel strips to the
punches.
the punches cut holes
in the steel,
spacing them at
precise intervals.
these holes will
allow production machinery
to grip the steel
and move it through
the blade-making process.
machinery pulls the steel
ribbons through an oven,
which heats them to a searing
1,832 degrees fahrenheit.
the steel then enters
a cooling chamber,
followed by another oven.
the temperature extremes
change
the steel's molecular
structure.
it becomes harder and
stronger.
the steel rewinds
and then unwinds
between grinding stones
that hone the edge
into a very sharp
gothic arch profile.
they're now ready to break the
steel into individual blades.
a mechanical punch snaps it.
and it breaks cleanly.
with a skewer holding
the blades in alignment,
a technician scrutinizes
the edges for any defects.
after applying coatings
to prevent
rust and add durability,
they bake the blades
in a special furnace.
this binds the coatings
to the blades.
at another station,
they transform plastic pellets
into the razor cartridges.
this machine melts the pellets
and injects the liquid
plastic into molds
as pressure is applied.
the plastic solidifies
into the shape
of razor cartridges.
the cartridges bounce along
a circular feeder.
the feeder orients them
front-side-up
and then funnels them
into the next machine.
this one resembles an octopus
with numerous tentacles.
the tentacles are robots.
the first one places
the cartridges
in a fixture
on a revolving table.
as the table turns,
it serves up the cartridges
to the next robots
in the assembly line.
in quick succession,
these robots snap
a total of five blades
into the cartridges.
by now, the holes used
to move the blades
through the assembly process
have been trimmed off.
and it's a perfect fit.
they now place back casings
in front of the cartridges
and install pieces of metal
on the parts.
the metal pieces
are sacrificial anodes.
their sole purpose
is to be sacrificed
to corrosive forces
to save the blades.
after that, robots flip
the back casings
then transfer them
to the cartridge blades
and click them into place.
the cartridge blades are now
fully assembled.
the robotic system takes
them into a station
with more quality
control cameras.
if no problems are found,
the blades move into
another mechanized system.
this one installs
a temporary plastic cover
to protect the consumer
and keep the blades sharp
until it's time for a shave.
robotic arms pick up
the clear plastic protectors
two at a time
and place them in slots
in the assembly machine.
they then snap
the cartridge blades
into the plastic covers.
with the protectors in place,
the robots send the cartridge
blades down a chute
and into a bin.
they're now ready
for retail
and the business
of personal grooming.
narrator:
many schools today require
to be allergy-free
because so many children
have life-threatening
to peanuts,
tree nuts or dairy products.
often, these allergies
are so severe
that just touching
or inhaling the allergen
can cause a potentially
deadly reaction.
these kid-sized chocolate
chip banana loaves contain
no peanuts, tree nuts
or dairy products.
nothing else this company
makes contains them
either to eliminate
any possibility
of cross-contamination.
as a further precaution,
all the ingredients
come from suppliers
whose facilities are also
entirely peanut,
tree nut and dairy-free.
to make the batter,
workers first combine water,
canola oil and sugar.
then they add pureed banana
and mix until the ingredients
are well blended.
they add wheat flour,
then sea salt,
baking soda and preservatives
such as citric acid,
routinely used
in packaged foods,
to prevent the growth
of bacteria and mold.
the final ingredients
are eggs
and chocolate chips,
not milk chocolate
because these snacks
are dairy-free.
instead, chocolate chips
are custom-made
for this bakery
by a producer of certified
kosher pareve foods,
meaning the products contain
neither meat nor
dairy ingredients.
a pump moves the finished
batter
from the mixing bowl
to a large hopper
that feeds the
automated production line.
at the start of that line,
more than 620 loaf baking pans
pass under spray nozzles,
which lightly grease them
with canola oil.
this prevents the baked loaves
from sticking to the pan.
then the pans
enter the depositor,
which drops 1.5 ounces of
batter
into each loaf cavity.
this one batch of batter
produces 6,666 loaves.
the filled pans enter
a multilevel vertical oven
in which they zigzag up
and down 13 baking zones
of varying temperatures.
after 27 minutes,
the loaves are fully baked.
however, they can't
be packaged yet
because they're piping hot.
so the next station on the
line
is a multilevel vertical
cooling chamber.
its fans draw out the hot air
while blowers introduce
filtered cold air.
when the pans exit
the cooling chamber
about 25 minutes later,
the loaves are just
slightly warm.
a robot now descends
on two pans at a time.
it jabs the loaves
with needles to lift them out
then withdraws the needles
to drop them on a conveyer
belt
that's ventilated to help
the loaves finish cooling.
this belt transfers them
to a narrower one
that leads
to the packaging area.
there, workers line up
the loaves in single file
on a track that leads
to the wrapping machine.
each loaf is roughly
3 1/2 by 2 inches
and 1 1/2 inches high.
even though each one started
out
as 1 1/2 ounces of batter,
some moisture evaporated
during baking,
reducing the final loaf
weight to 1.4 ounces.
under the watchful
eye of a sensor,
the loaves enter
the wrapping machine
where printed transparent
film envelops them.
the two edges of the film
overlap slightly
underneath the loaves.
the machine seals the edges
with a combination
of heat and pressure.
then it simultaneously seals
and cuts the film
in between the loaves.
each chocolate chip banana
loaf
is now individually wrapped.
workers pack the snacks
into the retail packaging.
the box moves
into a glue machine,
which seals the flaps.
the bakery conducts
several quality control checks
throughout production,
for example,
testing the viscosity
and ph level of the batter.
it also tests
the finished product.
once per hour,
they cut up a loaf
and place the pieces
in a moisture analyzer.
the correct moisture
level ensures
that the loaf has
a proper cake texture
and isn't dry
because as much
as this snack needs
to be safe for kids
with allergies,
it also has to taste great.
narrator: vending machines
are a common sight
in public places.
the first modern
vending machines
in 1880s england
didn't sell food at all.
they dispensed postcards.
nowadays, automated vending
has
come full circle with machines
selling not just food
but electronics
and other consumer goods.
thirsty?
just select a drink.
enter its number
on the keypad.
the led monitor displays
what you've chosen
and how much it costs.
then insert the money.
the monitor shows your credit,
how much you've paid.
the credit resets to zero
when the machine
releases your drink
and returns any
change you're due.
the vending machine
has a welded steel body
onto which workers assemble
the other components
such as the see
-through refrigerator
and an lcd monitor
to display advertising.
workers assemble the machine's
payment and display system,
starting with the machine's
control board.
they install the led monitor
and the keypad,
which are integrated
into a single unit.
after bolting the unit
securely in its window
in the housing,
the workers screw the control
board securely in place,
then plug the led monitor
and the keypad into the board.
they install the coin
acceptor.
it can be set up to recognize
up
to 16 different types of
coins.
when a customer
inserts money,
the coin acceptor transmits
the value to the control
board,
which displays the amount
on the led monitor,
calculates it into
the purchase of the item
and directs the coin acceptor
to dispense any required
change.
next, workers install
the bank note acceptor.
it identifies the denomination
of an inserted bill
with an optical scanner and,
to make sure
the currency is genuine,
measures fluorescent ink
with uv light
and reads magnetic ink
printing
with
a magnetic scanner.
it sends the value of the bill
to the control board.
they plug the data
transfer cables
from the money acceptors
into the control board
along with a cable
for the controllers
that operate the machine's
product release motors
and the data transfer cables
coming from the two
coin hoppers,
which collect the inserted
coins
and dispense change.
then they close up
the machine with cover panels.
a worker constructs
the product feed trays
that go into the vending
machine's refrigerator.
the first step
is to attach partitions
to a back panel to form
columns.
each column's width is set
to the dimensions,
weight and type of packaging
of the product it will
dispense,
from small featherlight
bags of chips
to heavy glass beverage
bottles.
a feed tray can have up
to six columns.
the trays are constructed
entirely of stainless steel
because it withstands
refrigeration temperature
and doesn't rust
when exposed to moisture.
workers install a motor
at the back of each column.
once the tray's installed
in the fridge,
those motors plug into
the control board.
when the customer pays
for the selected product,
the board activates the motor
for the corresponding column
to release the product.
side-by-side columns
designed to be stocked
with the same product
have linked motors.
that way, if one
column sells out,
the linked one with more
of the same product kicks in.
each motor moves the product
with a steel drive spring.
there are seven different
sizes of springs.
workers install the size
that has the correct spacing
between the rolls
that corresponds
to the dimensions
of the product being
dispensed from that column.
once the customer pays
for the selection,
the motor rotates
the spring 360 degrees
to release the product
and move the one behind it
to the front of the line.
once all the product feed
trays are installed,
workers adjust the
refrigerator
thermostat and stock
the products.
then they test the machine.
first, they purchase a product
with paper currency.
they make sure
the bills feed smoothly,
that the bank
note acceptor sends
the right data
to the control board,
that the board calculates
the transaction accurately
and activates
the correct motor.
they run the same test
with the coin acceptor
to make sure its sensors
correctly detect the coin,
dimension,
weight and chemical
composition
and transmit
accurate information
to the control board,
all this to ensure
the vending machine customers
get exactly
what they paid for.
narrator:
dive computers help divers
these wrist computers
keep tabs on the time
and depth of the dive.
and they calculate
a safe ascent.
the journey back to the
surface
must often be done in stages,
or the diver could fall victim
to decompression sickness.
a dive computer is
something someone wears
when they're ready
to take the plunge.
strapped to the wrist
like a watch,
it provides critical safety
data during the dive.
they start with panels
of four printed circuit
boards.
a technician confirms
that the tracks
and pads are correctly
located.
a conveyor then takes one of
the panels into a machine
that precisely positions
a metal mesh
stencil over it.
an automated squeegee
spreads solder paste
onto the circuit boards
through the open areas
of the stencil.
the solder paste
will act as glue
for over 100 tiny
electrical components.
next, the circuit boards
receive
those electrical components.
a robot peels them
off plastic strips
and places them on
the soldered areas
at an impressive rate
of 13,000 pieces per hour.
the parts
include microprocessors,
sensors and memory chips.
then the circuit boards
head into an oven
with several different
heating and cooling zones.
as they travel
through these zones,
the soldering particles melt
to bond the components
to the circuit boards.
passing through
the cooling zones,
the solder hardens.
and this solidifies the bonds.
the circuit boards
have now received
all of the necessary parts.
a technician places
the panel of circuit boards
in an automated
optical inspection machine.
here, a camera takes
a picture of the panel
and sends it to a computer.
the computer scans
the circuit boards
for missing components,
positioning errors
and soldering defects.
if there are no flaws,
the panels move on
to a programming station.
here, a technician
positions them under probes.
the probes descend
and load software
into the microprocessors.
this brings them to life
and enables them to control
all of the board's functions.
another technician trims
and cuts the panels
using circular saws.
she then punches out
the four round circuit boards
and transfers them to a tray
that has an electrically
conductive surface.
the surface protects the
boards
from mechanical
and electrical shocks
until they're ready
to be assembled
into the dive computer module.
now the fabrication
of that module begins.
the technician places a buzzer
mechanism behind a backlight.
she transfers the two of them
to the reverse side
of a display screen.
she places a plastic
framework on top.
and she inserts rubber
connectors in it.
these little rubber parts
will make the connection
between the circuit board
and the digital display.
the next assembler inserts
the circuit board
into the digital display unit.
she installs a temporary
battery
and checks the digital monitor
to confirm
that it's functional.
satisfied that it's in good
working order,
she sets it aside temporarily.
in the next stage
of production,
the worker removes
any dust particles
from the screen
using blasts of compressed
air.
she snaps the dive
computer module
into a tough plastic case
that's designed to withstand
a lot of water pressure.
she cleans a glass face
plate and places it
over the digital screen.
this face plate will protect
the screen from water.
the next part
is a metal bezel.
it surrounds the face plate
and will be used
to secure it to the casing.
she flips the assembly around
and screws the bezel
to the case from the back.
she inserts the computer
battery
into a titanium back plate.
she then installs
the battery assembly
in the back of the module
and secures it with screws.
this completes the dive
computer module.
all that's left is
to attach the wrist strap,
and this dive computer
is ready to probe underwater
and provide
critical safety information.