♪♪
narrator:
wooden utensils may date back
to prehistoric times,
yet today, they're
a popular cutlery option
for the modern dinner table.
typically a high-end product,
handcrafted by artisans,
wooden forks, knives,
and spoons appeal to people
who are drawn
to the organic beauty
and warmth of wood.
traditional in material
but modern in design,
each of these wooden utensils
is meticulously handcrafted
from a single piece of maple.
maple is dense, so it
doesn't develop cracks
which can harbor bacteria.
it takes up to 28 steps
to make a utensil.
first, a worker planes a maple
plank to a specific thickness.
then, they cut it into blocks
the length of the utensil --
in this case, a fork.
the worker places each block
on a curved template
and traces the curve,
which matches the arc
of the fork's handle.
with a band saw, they cut
along the trace line.
the center of the curve runs
parallel to the grain
of the wood.
this makes the handle and tines
of the fork stronger
than if the curve would run
perpendicular to the grain.
they clamp the block
to another template and profile
the curve on a machine
called a wood molder.
then, with a band saw,
following the curve,
the worker cuts the block
into strips 1/4
of an inch thick.
the curve is quite pronounced to
give the fork an elegant line.
they clamp up to ten strips
at a time
onto this woodworking machine.
then, they start her up.
routers descend, and guided
by computer software,
simultaneously carve
the strips into forks.
♪♪
after seven minutes,
each curved strip,
while nowhere near
the finished shape,
does have a defined handle
and four tines.
♪♪
a strong squeeze snaps off
the excess wood.
♪♪
only small nubs of excess
wood remain,
which a worker now removes
by running the fork
against a sanding belt.
from this point on comes
finer detail work
that can be done only by hand.
starting on a balloon sander,
a worker adds or releases air --
adjusting the
inflation pressure --
to produce a soft surface
against which to sand
a curved utensil
and a hard surface against
which to sand a flat one.
once they've refined
the back of the fork,
a worker manually
sands the area
that motorized sanders
can't reach --
first beveling the tines
to sharp points...
...then sanding in between
the tines.
it's important to keep
the tines thick
so they won't wear out with use.
next, the worker sands
the entire fork
with a fine-grit sandpaper
to remove any faint ridges
left by the balloon sander.
they finish with
an ultra-fine sanding
to make the fork
feel silky smooth.
now that the fork
has its final shape,
the worker stamps the company's
logo into each handle.
to ensure the top
of the fork remains smooth,
they soak it in hot water.
this draws up the
wood's short fibers
so they can then be sanded down.
the final step is an intricate,
hand-applied
finishing process --
three coats of
a proprietary mixture
of food-safe plant oils,
waxes, and lemon.
lemon works like a solvent,
diluting the mixture,
so that it penetrates
deep into the pores of the wood.
after the last coat dries,
a worker manually polishes
the surface
with an ultra-fine abrasive pad,
sweeps off any dust,
then lets the finish cure
for 28 days.
the finish brings out the grain
and color of the wood.
it also protects against
food stains, abrasion,
and moisture over the lifetime
of the utensil.
wooden cutlery doesn't
just look different,
it sounds different --
no ting of metal utensils
on dishes as you eat.
when dining a la wood,
the only thing
you'll hear is conversation.
narrator:
the invention of transport
refrigeration units
in the 1940s changed
our food-consumption
patterns forever.
suddenly, florida oranges
were available in snowy regions
and frozen food could be
delivered far and wide.
previously, ice had been used
to preserve perishables
so the trucks
couldn't go far.
transport refrigeration units
are designed for the long haul.
when trucks are parked,
they can be plugged
into an electrical outlet
to keep the cargo cool.
production starts with this
computerized punch cutter.
it cuts holes and slots in
steel panels that will be used
for the housing
of the compressor and condenser.
a worker then serves up
the panels to a bending machine.
it folds them so they can be
assembled to each other
to form the refrigeration
unit's housing.
an automated machine
bends copper pipe to form it
into tubing for refrigerant.
each bend changes
the direction of the pipe.
it's an alternative
to using fittings for this job.
it means fewer seams,
reducing the risk of leaks.
a worker then joins the pipe
to create the evaporator coil
in which liquid refrigerant
is converted to gas
to draw heat
from the area to be cooled.
once the evaporator coil
is complete and he's
installed additional copper
pipes for defrosting,
a worker assembles
it to the housing.
the fan panel
completes the evaporator.
during operation, it will blow
cool air into the truck trailer.
the unit can be set
to refrigerate or freeze,
depending on
the trailer contents.
a technician puts
together the unit
that goes on the outside
of the truck.
it compresses and then
condenses the refrigerant
during the cooling cycle.
she secures the compressor
and the copper pipes
to the steel housing.
she places a motor in the
housing beside the compressor.
using a rubber belt,
the technician links
the motor pulley
to the compressor pulley.
she completes the connections
for the inlet and outlet pipes.
the condenser is next.
it transforms refrigerant
vapor back to liquid.
using more copper pipe,
the technician links
the condenser to the compressor.
she connects a pipe
to a little steel vessel
that will hold liquid
refrigerant not in circulation.
the technician
installs a filter unit
on the outside wall
and links the refrigerant
pipe network to it.
the mesh filter inside
will catch dirt
in the refrigerant gas
and will trap
any lingering humidity.
back to the compressor now,
the technician installs
a second motor.
this one will keep
the refrigeration system
working even
when the truck is shut off.
all the trucker will need to do
is plug the power cable
into an electrical outlet.
she attaches a pressure
sensor to the pipe.
the technician melts
metal filler into the joint
where the discharge pipe
links to the condenser.
this seals the connection.
the electronics for
the control panel are next.
the technician screws
the metal board
that holds them
to the housing.
then, she makes all
the electrical connections.
now, a safety test.
another technician connects
the compressor
and condenser unit
to a vacuum and activates it.
it suctions out air
in the system.
he then injects nitrogen gas
and traces of refrigerant.
if the gas escapes, it will
indicate a leak in the system.
to find escaping gas,
he uses a special leak detector.
it sucks in tiny amounts of air
and analyzes it
for the refrigerant.
this enables him
to pinpoint exactly
where any problem might be.
another technician powers up
the unit and confirms
that the control panel
is working
and that the compressor motors
are fully operational.
they fill the system
with nitrogen gas.
it's a temporary measure
to protect it
from oxidation during shipping.
the on-site installer
will replace
the nitrogen with refrigerant.
it has taken approximately
an hour to manufacture
this transport
refrigeration unit.
when it comes to keeping
food chilled or frozen,
it should deliver
for many years to come.
narrator: the indigenous people
of north america
invented moccasins
to protect their feet
from harsh weather conditions
and to provide
spiritual protection
in the form of symbols stitched
into the leather
to evoke sacred places
and things.
the idea was to protect both
the soles of the feet
and the soul.
today, moccasins
are mass-produced.
factories make their
own versions
of this traditional footwear.
this one generates up
to 100 pairs
of moccasin slippers a day.
production starts
with rabbit-fur pelts
that are a by-product
of the european
rabbit-meat industry.
the furrier places
a plastic template
over the pelt.
he draws lines through
the slats of the template.
this outlines stripes to be
used to trim the moccasins.
using a razor blade,
he cuts out the fur strips
and sets them aside.
one pelt will provide enough
trim for two pairs of moccasins.
using dies made of sharp steel,
the furrier cuts out
the suede leather parts.
a hydraulic press,
as known as a clicker,
drives the dies through
through the leather
to punch out the pieces.
the largest one will be
used for the bottom
and sides of the moccasins.
it's called the foot.
the other parts
are a sole to reinforce
the bottom
and the vamp,
which is the upper
part of the slipper.
next, the furrier cuts
out pieces of thick
polyester fleece
which will be used
to create plush liners.
he arranges the moccasin
components in the correct
sequence for sewing.
this is called a layout,
and it helps
the sewing process go faster.
the furrier presses
an adhesive-back size label
to the bottom
of the foot part.
the sewing machine
operator stitches
the sole of the foot
through to its fleece liner.
she also sews the label
to the leather
to fasten it more securely.
she folds the back sides up,
inside-out,
and sews them together to form
the heel of the moccasin.
the worker trims the fleece
that protrudes from the seam.
she then folds the heel
right side out.
now that the foot and sole have
been joined and the heel formed,
the worker turns her
attention to the vamp.
she sews beaded designs
into this moccasins' upper.
♪♪
these geometric designs
are a nod to the past,
but their purpose is purely
ornamental, not spiritual.
after lining the beaded vamp
with fleece, the worker stitches
a leather strip
around the edges,
creating a border
known as a welt.
the welt gives the vamp
a more attractive finish.
to sew the vamp to the rest
of the moccasin,
she uses a special
sewing machine.
it pleats the top of the foot
to fit the vamp as it stitches.
♪♪
the moccasins are now
structurally complete,
and they're ready
for the fur trim.
the worker stitches
the rabbit-fur strips
together to create
one long strip
that will fit to the moccasin.
the length of the strip
will vary depending
on the size of the moccasin.
she makes an initial
chain stitch
and then doubles back
to lock the stitch down,
in order to prevent
it from unraveling.
she aligns the fur trim
with the collar of the moccasin
and sews it to it.
after stitching,
the worker leaves
the fur tucked down
into the moccasin.
this makes it easier
to apply glue
around the top of the moccasin,
so that when the fur
is folded up and over it,
it stays in place.
with that,
this modern-day version
of traditional
indigenous footwear
is ready for its first steps.
narrator: an impact drill is a
power tool that's tough enough
to bore through hard materials,
such as brick, stone,
and concrete.
it can also drive screws
into softer materials like wood.
an electronic impact drill has
the added feature of a switch
that amps up the drill speed
if the job requires it.
an impact drill is comprised
of the drive unit,
the back part with
the electric motor,
and the gear unit --
the front part containing
the motor-rotated spindle
that turns the drill bit.
to make the housing
for the gear unit,
the factory furnace melts
down solid aluminum.
then, an automated
casting machine injects it
at high pressure
into a mold with
six housing-shaped cavities.
once the machine cools the mold
to re-solidify the aluminum,
a robot removes
the hot housings
and submerges them
in water to cool them.
the robot then places
the housings
in an automated
stamping press,
which cuts off
the connecting metal,
separating the housings.
a computer-guided
milling machine finalizes
the shape of each housing
and forms a collar for attaching
a second handle
that provides extra control
when drilling through
hard materials.
elsewhere in the factory,
a computer-guided
turning lathe shapes
a solid steel bar
into the drill spindle.
back to the gear housing now,
a worker positions it next
to a spindle assembly fixture.
she lines up a grooved wheel,
called a ratchet wheel,
over the housing and inserts
another one into
the spindle fixture.
then, she puts the spindle
through this second
ratchet wheel and inserts
the first ratchet wheel
into the housing with a press.
the worker inserts the spindle
with its wheel into the housing.
this makes the two
ratchet wheels,
so that they'll move up
and down against each other
when the spindle rotates.
after installing a seal
and retaining clip,
she completes the gear unit by
installing the gears
that rotate the spindle.
an automated
injection-molding machine,
meanwhile, produces
the plastic housing
for the electric motor.
the machine makes two
housings at a time.
the motor is made up
of a stationary component
called a stator
and a rotating component
called a rotor.
a worker inserts the stator
into the housing,
pushes it down into position
with a press,
then secures it with screws.
he mounts the electronic unit
that lets you regulate
the speed of the spindle.
after installing a flange,
the worker inserts the rotor
and presses it into position.
the rotor has a fan attached
to cool the running motor.
he connects the electronic
unit to the motor.
now, everything comes together.
using an assembly guide,
a worker positions half
of the drill's plastic handle
then wires the motor
to the switch
that's connected
to the electronic unit.
moving the switch increases
or decreases the drilling speed.
next, she takes
the drill's power cable,
applies a device that prevents
the cable from kinking,
then screws the cable
to the switch.
the worker closes it all up
by affixing
the other half
of the plastic handle.
this completes the assembly
of the back part of the impact
drill known as the drive unit.
a worker places the gear unit
onto the drive unit.
an automated machine
screws them together.
every impact drill this factory
produces undergoes
performance testing
and a critical safety test.
♪♪
if the tool passes
inspection,
the spindle gets
awarded its chuck.
the chuck is the component
that holds the drill bit.
a computer-guided laser engraver
marks the model number
and all the technical data
on the motor housing.
then, workers pack the
electronic impact drill along
with a second handle
and accessories
into a sturdy
plastic carrying case.
with this tool in your kit,
you've got license to drill.