--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
metal nail files.
birch bark canoes.
cruiser boat hardtops.
and high-voltage
circuit breakers.
throughout history,
people have wanted nice nails.
and they used whatever
they could get their hands on
to make them look good.
marie antoinette is said to
have
used a pumice stone file
to shape her fingernails.
by the end of the 19th
century,
metal nail files
became the norm.
can be used to grind
and shape fingernails
with a few strokes.
their abrasiveness is the
secret
to their popularity.
making metal nail files starts
with a thick spool
of stainless steel.
the steel unwinds
at a steady pace.
a punch press wields
88 tons of hydraulic pressure
to cut out nail file blanks.
the blanks spill into a bin
and accumulate.
the blanks bounce around
with ceramic stones
and a mix of water
and polishing solution.
this smoothes the rough bits
on the blanks
and also cleans them.
the nail file blanks then
slide
down a chute into a dryer.
this dryer doesn't use
hot air to do the job.
instead, a pulsating mass
of hot corn grain
soaks up the lingering liquid
on the blanks.
as the blanks exit,
some of the corn falls
through a perforated conveyor
to be reused.
the blanks continue on
and land in a bin,
ready for the next phase
of production.
it involves the cutting of
an abrasive grid on both
sides.
it's a three-stage process.
first, a worker places the
blank
under a sharp tool
that's angled at 52 degrees.
the tool pounds the blank
repeatedly
to cut angled grooves into it.
here is the blank before
and after the first cut.
he switches the cutting tool,
and it carves over the first
cuts on the opposite angle.
the third cut goes straight
across the other two.
the ridges and valleys
created by the cross cuts
make the surface of the blank
sharp.
the grid cutting has bent
the still-pliable steel
out of shape,
so the worker now bends the
nail
files in the opposite
direction,
using a round form as a guide.
this restores
their linear profile.
the carving process
has also caused steel to bulge
on the edges of the nail
files,
so he grinds them against
a fine abrasive sanding belt
to make the edges smooth
again.
next, he places
the metal nail files
in perfect alignment in a
tray.
he transfers the tray of files
to an oven.
the files bake for an hour
at a temperature of
1,832 degrees fahrenheit.
the intense heat begins to
alter
the physical properties
of the steel
and is the first phase of
a hardening process.
when the hour is up,
he takes the red-hot tray
of nail files
out of the oven using tongs
and then immerses them
in a vat of cold saltwater.
this is called quenching.
the shock of the quench
completes the hardening
process.
shielded by an enclosure,
he sandblasts each nail file
to remove stains
left by the hardening process
and to make the steel around
the triple-cut grid shinier.
he places the handle
into the nail file
beneath a plastic stencil.
a stamp applies acid to
the open areas of the stencil
to etch brand information
onto it.
some nail files
have plastic handles.
to make the handles,
this machine melts plastic
and injects it into molds.
the handles are stuck together
by hardened flow lines
or runners.
a few tumbles in this
revolving
drum knocks off the runners,
separating the handles
from them.
the worker places each handle
under an automated printing
head
that soaks up ink from a pad
and then stamps brand
information onto the plastic.
another worker heats the end
of each metal nail file
using copper elements.
she inserts the hot metal
into the plastic sleeve,
and the plastic melts a little
to bond to the metal.
these metal nail files
are ready for the grind.
narrator: for centuries,
the canoe was indispensable
to the indigenous people
of north america.
essential for hunting,
fishing,
transportation, and commerce,
indigenous people often
crafted
their canoes from birch bark,
which is lightweight, strong,
waterproof, and rot-resistant.
historically,
different indigenous tribes
constructed different styles
of birch bark canoes.
this one is the type crafted
by
both the algonquian
and eastern ojibwe.
even today, the canoe builder
crafts every component
from water- and rot-resistant
plant materials
found in the forest,
such as the exceptionally
strong
roots of black spruce trees.
after scraping off the bark
with a tool crafted from
a moose rib,
this craftswoman cuts a slit
in the top and pulls,
splitting the long root
into two strips.
she coils up each strip
and puts it aside to dry out.
the canoe builder
uses spruce root
to bind structural components
and lace together
sections of birch bark.
to build the canoe's
cedar structure,
the builder connects end
frames
at the front and back
with long strips of cedar
called gunwales,
then he lashes crossbars
called thwarts
to the gunwales
with spruce root.
to make each end frame,
he splits a piece of cedar
many times to let it bend,
soaks it in boiling water
to soften the wood fibers,
and binds the shape
with spruce root.
then the builder checks this
curved part, called the stem,
against the straight part,
called the headboard.
if the proportions are right,
he notches the bottom
of the headboard
to fit over the base
of the stem,
then lashes the parts to
each other with spruce root.
he laces together
several pieces of birch bark
to make a sheet large enough
for the canoe.
the builder saturates the
bark sheet with boiling water
and bends it up
around a wooden template.
then, on each side of the
canoe,
he sandwiches the top edge
of the bark
in between the two cedar
strips
that form the gunwale.
the builder shaves
pieces of cedar
to make straight,
vertically laid planks
and u-shaped
horizontally laid ribs
that line the inside
of the canoe.
he uses a gauge to make sure
each piece
is the required thickness.
he lays each rib piece
across the structure
and makes a mark on each side
in line with the bottom edge
of the floor.
that's where
he'll bend the piece.
just as he did to bend the
stem
portion of the end frame,
the builder ladles boiling
water
onto the wood
to soften the fibers.
he positions his knees
on the charcoal marks
and pulls up the ends.
he bends two ribs at a time,
as this reduces the chances
of them cracking.
after checking that he cut
and bent all the ribs
correctly,
the builder begins the process
of securing the birch bark.
he drills holes in the
gunwales
at nearly six-inch intervals.
then he takes pegs
carved from hardwood
such as ash or maple
and hammers one
through each hole.
then he pierces holes
through the bark
with a traditional awl
made from deer antler.
he threads spruce root
through the holes
to lash the bark to the
gunwale.
with an assistant's help,
he fully lines the canoe
with straight cedar planks
and installs the remaining
ribs.
the tight fit presses the
planks
against the bark,
stretching it taught,
which strengthens it.
the final step is known as
pitching the seams.
he melts down dried resin
gathered from scars
on spruce trees
and mixes in two ingredients
--
ground charcoal
and oil rendered from bear
fat.
he applies this hot mixture
to all the lacing holes
in the birch bark,
making the canoe water-tight.
the canoeist carries
a small supply of dried pitch
and lights a stick to remelt
and apply it.
the repair dries quickly,
so in about five minutes,
the canoeist can be
back in the paddle.
narrator: a hardtop encloses
the cockpit of a cruiser boat.
it provides shelter
from water spray, wind, and
sun,
and a roof on which to
mount antenna for marine
and satellite radio and gps.
on the inside,
it provides walls and a
ceiling
for recessed lighting
and other features.
this cruiser hardtop has
windows
that wrap around the front
and sides.
the tall one in the middle
is retractable
so you can walk through
to the front deck.
workers use two molds to make
the inner and outer parts
that form the hardtop.
first, they spray white
gelcoat
to a thickness of
just .6 millimeters.
next, workers shoot shredded
fiberglass strands into the
mold
along with a stream of resin
which saturates the fibers.
when the fiberglass is about
3/4 of an inch thick,
they let the resin cure
for an hour or so.
then workers apply bonding
putty
to the fiberglass
in the outer mold.
they mate the inner
and outer molds
and let the putty set,
which takes about an hour.
finally, it's time to extract
the fiberglass from the molds.
it comes off relatively easily
because prior to spraying
the gelcoat layer,
workers have applied a release
agent on the mold's surface.
the inner and outer parts are
built in the mold upside-down
so the gelcoat gives
the coarse fiberglass
a smooth and shiny
surface finish.
then they cut openings
for the windows
and for the various components
to be installed
into the hardtop.
they install
the retractable front window.
workers then position the
window
and mark the screw holes,
then remove it
in order to apply adhesive,
which also functions
as a sealant
to prevent water infiltration.
they reset the window
and screw it to the hardtop.
workers install
a non-opening window
on each side
of the retractable one.
after taping off the area,
a worker applies primer.
once the primer dries,
they remove the tape
and apply an adhesive-backed
foam gasket
that's about 1/4-inch high.
a worker applies a 1/4-inch
high
bead of adhesive sealant
next to the gasket
and sets the window.
the primer gasket
and adhesive sealant
are all black
to match the window frame.
on the roof of the hardtop,
workers install a thin
molded fiberglass cover.
the retractable window,
when opened, slides under it.
workers fill the gap
between the cover and hardtop
with sealant.
this adheres the cover
and makes it watertight.
at the rear, workers install
the radar arch.
this, too, is made of
molded fiberglass
but with a black gelcoat
finish.
they mount various components
on it,
such as the horn,
navigation light, and antenna.
inside the hardtop,
after passing wires
for lighting,
workers connect the wiring
to the retractable window.
the window comes
as a self-contained unit
with an incorporated motor
and intricate pulley system.
the hardtop is now ready to be
mounted to the cruiser's deck.
workers install
a windshield wiper
on each non-opening
front window.
the last step is to install
a large window
on both sides of the hardtop.
its middle section opens.
like a giant windshield,
the hardtop transforms
the cruiser boat's
otherwise open cockpit
into a weather-protected
lounge.
narrator: electrical
substations
play a critical role in the
grid
as they distribute electricity
to entire communities.
the circuit breakers
at these stations
routinely interrupt
short circuits
to prevent damage to the
system.
they perform the same function
as the ones in
a home electrical panel,
but on a much larger scale.
the size of a car
or even a large truck,
these circuit breakers
troubleshoot
high-current situations
at electrical substations.
this protects the grid
and prevents power outages.
making one starts with
a cast-aluminum tank
that has receptacles
for bushings.
a worker inspects the tank
for dirt or flaws
and then places
protective covers
on the bushing receptacles.
he installs bases
for current transformers
on these receptacles.
the worker applies adhesive
to the outside
of these metal bases.
he presses squares of plastic
insulation to the glued areas.
with the help
of an overhead lift,
the worker installs
the two current transformers
on the insulated bases.
these current transformers
will act as sensors,
enabling the circuit breaker
to detect short circuits
in an electrical system
in mere milliseconds.
another worker brushes
lubricant
on the moving part
of the interrupter
that will break the electrical
current when needed.
he inserts the exhaust tube
that helps direct the flow of
gas used to break the current.
he sets the interrupter module
in an upright position
on the floor
and returns to the workbench.
the worker dabs thread lock
liquid in the mounting holes
of the stationary
contact assembly
and installs a resin ring
in the base.
he inserts the stationary part
into the moving one,
leaving the end protruding.
the worker applies thread lock
to the assembly holes
of a large tube
that will shield
the entire interrupter
once it's installed in the
tank.
it will also direct the flow
of interrupting gas.
after assembling it
to the interrupter,
he inserts a synthetic
insulating tube.
then with the help of a lift,
he flips the module over
in order to
work on the other end.
he installs another
insulating tube in this end.
he then sets the module
to a stand to steady it
as he inserts
the contact assembly
that opens to interrupt
the electrical current.
he caps one end
of the interrupter
with the unit that houses
the bell crank.
he slides the bell crank
into the housing.
this crank will convert
the rotary motion
from the operating mechanism
to a linear motion.
he turns the crank to confirm
that it rotates freely.
he now clamps leads
to test probes
inserted in the interrupter
and applies 100 amps of
current.
the testing device measures
the interrupter's resistance
to the current to confirm that
it's within
an acceptable range.
with a lift bearing the load,
the other member of the team
guides the interrupter module
into the cast-aluminum tank.
he bolts the bell crank's
housing to the tank opening
and places cylindrical
electrical shields
in each of
the bushing receptacles.
he then encases the
transformers
at the base
with aluminum covers.
they'll protect
the transformer wiring
from rain, snow, or dirt.
lifts now hoist the
silicone-rubber-wrapped
bushings
into the receptacles.
the worker bolts them
in place...
...and caps the rear
of the tank.
this interrupter is now ready
to be mounted
to the steel support
structure.
each high-voltage
circuit breaker
will be equipped
with three interrupters.
the team connects
the bell cranks
to the operating system
in the control cabinet.
and workers equip each bell
crank with a pressure gauge.
a worker grounds
the circuit breaker
to the support structure
with copper cables.
this will prevent shocks
to anyone who touches it.
in one last test,
towering transformers
apply high voltages
to the circuit breakers.
these high-voltage
circuit breakers
are ready to
interrupt situations
before they become problems.