--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: the angle grinder created a major buzz
in the workplace when it was developed
in the middle of the 20th century.
this power tool could do it all --
cut, grind, and polish metal or stone.
just change the disk or brush attachment
to match the job,
and work gets done automatically.
with numerous attachments available,
the angle grinder
could be equipped for many different jobs.
that makes it one of the most useful things
on any job site.
making angle grinders starts
with these blocks of pure aluminum.
fired in a furnace,
the aluminum melts into a liquid form.
the factory casts the molten aluminum
to create gear housings.
a robot transfers one of the gear housings
to a milling station
and then retrieves a finished part.
the door of the machine closes,
and a computerized cutter carves threads
into the center bearing seat
and generally improves the profile of the part.
next up is the rotor for the electric motor.
an automated system pushes special cardboard end disks
onto the rotor shaft.
the part on the right is equipped with end disks.
the system now installs a part
called the collector on one end.
made of copper and plastic,
the collector will transmit power to the rotor
and ensure that the grinding or polishing attachment
can turn.
the part on the right has had the collector installed.
spinning arms wind copper wire
into grooves in the rotor at both ends.
the wire will serve as an electromagnet
and maximize power output.
moving forward, the system inserts covers
into slots in the rotor wall.
they both insulate the rotor
and stabilize the copper coil.
spinning devices wrap copper wire
around each half of the stater.
this stater creates the electromagnetic field
around the rotor.
a robot puts the two halves
of the stater together in a fixture,
and welds make the assembly permanent.
over to an injection molding machine now,
it forms plastic into outer casings for the grinder.
a robot transfers the casing to a platform for printing.
this stamp adds silver ink to the embossed company logo,
giving it greater visual appeal.
a worker then slides the plastic housing over the stater,
and a pneumatic machine press-fits the two together.
the worker then wires the on/off switch
for the angle grinder.
the gear housing has, by now, been equipped
with a drive gear and brake.
he installs the gear system on one end of the rotor.
he then inserts the rotor assembly in the stater.
an automated system screws everything together
to complete the angle grinder motor.
next, a nozzle fills the gear head with grease.
a worker places the spindle
and safety clutch over the gear head,
and a mechanized system screws it in place.
she then wires the electrical plug
to the angle grinder motor.
she encloses the electrical wiring with a plastic cover.
she locks the cover in places with screws,
using a metal template to aid in their placement.
this angle grinder
is now ready to undergo quality control tests.
this one depresses the angle grinder switch,
while a computerized system
analyzes the motor's performance.
if it passes all the tests,
the angle grinder is ready to take a chunk
out of someone's workload.
narrator: long before the development of pottery,
people looked to the forest for containment materials.
they made berry baskets from the bark of birch trees.
the baskets were lightweight and waterproof,
due to natural resins in the bark.
the making of these baskets
is a tradition that carries on.
for containing nature's bounty,
birch bark is a natural choice.
this berry basket is made entirely
from materials found in nature.
making one starts with birch bark
that's been carefully pried off the tree
to avoid damage to the inner layer of bark.
this cardboard pattern will be used as a template.
the basket maker examines the bark
for any holes or serious flaws.
he flips the bark over.
he'll use the inner side
for the outside of the basket.
he traces around the pattern,
using a scribe that lightly scores the bark.
this light scoring creates
a visible outline on the bark.
using scissors for cutting leather,
he follows the pattern lines
to cut the bark to the pattern shape.
the contours are harder to follow,
so he switches to scissors
with curved blades to cut them out.
he punches holes in the basket corners.
this will stop the bark from splitting in these spots
when it's folded.
using a pointed instrument known as a divider,
he now etches stitch lines around the perimeter.
he maps out the location for the stitch holes
by lightly piercing the bark along the etched lines.
using a ruler for support,
he bends the flaps of the pattern up,
creating creases that will become permanent folds later.
he punches out stitch holes
where he had lightly pierced the bark.
he drapes a damp towel over the birch bark
and irons it.
this softens the bark so that it doesn't split
as he now forms the final bends along the crease lines.
he overlaps the ends of the basket.
he clips the structure to hold it together
while he inserts wooden dowels in some of the stitch holes.
once the dowels are in, he removes the clips.
the dowels will keep the basket together for stitching.
but first, he tapers the stem
from a willow shrub using a wood plane.
he inserts the stem in a cylindrical container
and fills the cylinder with hot water.
the tapered stem soaks overnight.
it softens and becomes extremely flexible.
using a wooden form, he shapes the stem into a ring.
the tapered ends overlap for a consistent thickness
all the way around.
he clips the ring
to the inner rim of the basket
and also tacks it in place with a few stitches.
this willow ring will add support
to the lip of the berry basket.
next, he stitches the seams together
using the root of a spruce tree for thread.
its tapered tip serves as a needle.
he does precise backstitches
and ensures all the seams are tight.
moving back to the rim of the basket,
he punctures the bark just below the willow ring,
creating a row of holes
to loop the root around the rim.
this spruce root wrap protects the rim ring,
and gives the basket a more finished look at the top.
he slices a piece of cedar bark
into long, narrow strips.
he'll use these strips to make a handle for the basket.
he weaves the cedar into a five-strand braid.
he loops the cedar braid at the ends
and uses the loops to stitch the handle
to the berry basket.
it takes this artisan about a day
to craft a birch bark berry basket.
his efforts will no doubt
bear fruit for many years to come.
narrator: choosing the right
speakers for your sound system
depends on how you prefer to hear music.
unidirectional speakers radiate sound in a single direction.
omnidirectional speakers radiate in all directions,
so the sound bounces off the ceiling and walls.
this omnidirectional speaker system has four towers --
two main system towers and two subwoofer towers.
the towers contain the drivers
that radiate sound frequencies out of the speaker.
this computer-guided mill shapes brass sheets
into mounting plates for the main system towers.
each of the main system towers contains six drivers --
two tweeters, two mid-ranges, and two woofers.
each subwoofer tower contains six drivers
for the lowest human audible frequencies.
after the brass mounting plate comes off the mill,
workers grind the top surface smooth
to prepare it for polishing and chrome plating.
the mill then shapes brass rings.
these are bases for the woofers,
which fit an opening in the mounting plate.
brass is the metal of choice for these parts,
due to its acoustical properties.
for aesthetics, the rings are painted black,
and the mounting plates are electro-plated
with galvanized chrome.
in this part of the plant,
they build tweeters for the main system towers.
the first step is to lay strips
of resin-impregnated carbon fiber
in semi-circular molds.
after removing the protective film
that covers the carbon fiber,
they lay foil strips at each end.
these will direct heat from the oven
to the carbon fiber strips
and prevent the resin from flowing out.
they assemble the molds and clamp them shut.
they place the molds in an oven for 45 minutes
at a programmed series of temperatures.
this heats the resin in the carbon fiber,
stiffening and forming the strips to the mold shape.
using a punch press,
workers slice each carbon fiber strip
into several thinner strips.
they construct each tweeter
by gluing 24 of those thin strips
to the tweeter's voice coil,
a ring made of wound copper wire.
they brush silicone in between the strips,
coat the entire surface with more silicone,
then place an aluminum cover plate on top.
they construct each mid-range driver the same way,
but with carbon fiber strips
that are thicker and stiffer
and therefore radiate lower frequencies better
than the thinner, more flexible tweeter strips.
placing the strips with tweezers
and aligning them properly with a toothpick
requires a good eye, excellent dexterity,
and a lot of experience.
like the tweeter, the mid-range driver
goes into an oven for 45 minutes
through a specific cycle of temperatures.
once the driver comes out of the oven and cools,
they glue strips of sound-dampening foam
to the inside,
sealing the gaps between the carbon fiber strips.
this prevents sound from radiating inward
rather than out the speaker.
they solder the cables
that bring the incoming electrical signal
that carries the sound frequencies.
that signal moves the voice coil up
while the driver's magnet moves it back down.
the repeated up and down motion
flexes the carbon fiber strips,
radiating the sound frequencies.
after installing a center rod made of carbon,
workers stuff the hollow space inside the driver
with sound-dampening wool.
they pour lubricating oil
into a narrow gap in the driver's magnet,
then insert the voice coil into the gap.
the oil contains iron,
so it conducts the electrical signal to the coil.
they screw an aluminum mounting plate
to the magnet's posts...
...then apply a disk of a stiff sound-dampening material.
they install the tweeter's magnet on the mounting plate,
feeding the tweeter's electrical cables,
not yet soldered to the tweeter, through the center rod.
next they'll make the woofers.
narrator: the sound system's amplifier
that carries all the sound frequencies.
inside each main system speaker,
an electronic component called the crossover
separates the frequency ranges
and sends them, via designated cables,
to the appropriate driver.
they make each melon-shaped woofer
out of 12 aluminum segments.
they glue acoustic foam to each segment,
then trim the foam to the shape of the aluminum.
workers assemble the woofer upside-down
in an assembly fixture.
they glue the segments vertically
between this woofer's voice coil,
which has two cables attached to it
and a mounting plate.
the structural rod
through which they'll feed the other driver's cables
is in the center.
once all the segments are aligned and fixed in place,
they coat the edges with glue.
then they adhere rubber gaskets in between the segments
to block the gaps and prevent air from exiting.
they seat copper strips in the segment's grooves,
hooking the ends into holes at the top and bottom.
brass, aluminum, copper -- every type of material used
in these speakers has specific acoustical properties.
the combination produces a natural sound balance.
they fill the hollow interior space
around the center rod
with sound-dampening material.
first, synthetic insulating wool
with long, coarse fibers.
then, on top of that,
a barrier of cotton-insulating wool
to prevent those coarse fibers
from touching the voice coil.
next, they install the painted brass ring
they milled earlier,
which now has the woofer's magnet fixed to it.
they place a spacer, thread a screw,
pull the voice coil's two cables through the center,
then solder those cables,
together with the cables from the other drivers,
to a main cable that will plug into the crossover.
they flip the woofer right side up
and pour a liquid sound-dampening compound
into the center rod.
the cables inside are too delicate
to be shoving in insulating wool.
workers now begin assembling the speaker,
first soldering the two remaining crossover cables,
mid-range and high frequency,
to the respective driver cables.
the tweeter connection cables
are attached to the tweeter magnet,
installed earlier on top of the mid-range driver.
they now mount this unit on top of the woofer.
they install the connectors in the crossover.
its electrical components separate the frequency ranges
and send each one to a designated connector,
which sends it to the cable
leading to the appropriate driver.
after sliding the crossover onto the speaker's base,
made of milled brass,
they close up the top with the mounting plates,
between which they've since sandwiched
a thick piece of wood.
screw-in stainless steel support posts
hold everything together
and direct all the weight down to the floor,
rather than into the speaker structure.
they install an aluminum crossbar
for structural support,
then a second set of posts.
they fit the ring at the base of the woofer
into the mounting plate hole, securing it with screws.
they insert the tweeter's voice coil into the tweeter magnet
that's mounted on top of the mid-range driver
that's mounted on top of the woofer.
they solder the tweeter cables
to the two connectors on the tweeter cover plate.
this completes the lower trio of drivers.
now they install an identical upper trio,
but upside-down
so that the two tweeters face each other
in the middle of the tower.
they mount the crossover for the upper trio
and plug in the connector that joins the three cables.
that brings the correct frequencies
to the three drivers.
they run test tones through every completed speaker.
a microphone positioned just over three feet away
picks up the emitted frequencies,
which a computer analyzes for accuracy.
once the speaker passes inspection,
they install a decorative grill over each woofer voice coil.
the subwoofer tower radiates the lowest frequencies,
with six huge drivers and a built-in amplifier.