--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today on "how it's made":
potash,
leather bracelets,
wild rice
and hex key l-wrenches.
potash is used primarily
as an agricultural fertilizer.
it's extracted from underground by either conventional mining
or by injecting hot brine into the formation
to dissolve potash in salt crystals.
it then pumps the solution back up
and separates out the potash in settling ponds.
potash is potassium chloride,
the chemical compound kcl.
it can be processed into a granular agricultural fertilizer
or into a higher grade product for industrial use.
at this canadian potash mine,
the deposit lies just over a half a mile underground.
the ore is comprised of three materials:
kcl, clay and sodium chloride,
the chemical compound nacl,
better known as table salt.
the big machine manufacturers use to cut the face of the rock
is called a continuous miner.
it has two rotors, each with three arms.
each arm has six pairs of bits with carbide tips
that grind the face of the rock,
flaking off the ore.
the rotor arms sweep the ore into the machine,
which feeds it off the back onto bridge conveyors,
a series of conveyor belts
that lead to a main conveyor belt.
miners fasten sheets of polymer
to the rock above to erect walls
which direct the flow of fresh air
that's pumped down
into the mine for ventilation.
the bridge conveyors transfer the ore to a main conveyor.
at this particular potash mine,
up to 10 machines work
simultaneously at different locations.
all those main conveyors, nearly 22 miles of moving belts,
converge at the skip,
a gigantic elevator bucket
which hoists up to 49 tons of ore at a time
to the surface and dumps it into a storage bin.
a conveyor transfers the ore to the mill for processing.
first the ore tumbles down
a series of vibrating screens.
smaller particles drop through the openings
and move on to the next station
while larger particles stay on top
where they are whisked off
with the flow of brine into a crusher.
the finer particles flow to the fine flotation tank
while the larger ones sink to the bottom, drain out,
then travel to the course flotation tank.
the particles are treated with chemicals.
over the course of five minutes in flotation,
the chemical treatment makes the kcl particles attach
to air bubbles and rise to the surface.
in the course flotation tank
paddles skim the surface,
pushing the floating kcl into a collector.
the clay and nacl particles drain
out the other end.
similarly in the fine flotation unit,
the kcl particles attach to air bubbles
and rise to the top
where they overflow into a collector.
the collected potash
then goes through a centrifuge
and a dryer to remove all the moisture.
the dryer feeds this vibrating screening machine,
which separates the kcl particles into three categories.
oversized particles go back to the crusher.
undersized particles go to machines
which compact them into boards
then break the boards into new particles
which then go back to the vibrating machine
for another round of screening.
the final product size particles
go directly to the shipping warehouse.
this granular potash is the type
used as agricultural fertilizer.
it's kcl concentration is 95 percent
because there's some residual clay and nacl.
technicians regularly test product samples
to verify the kcl content.
they grind each sample into a find powder
and compress it inside a stainless
steel cap to form a pellet.
then the workers load the pellet
into an x-ray fluorescence analyzer.
the pelletized sample absorbs
that energy then releases energy as fluorescent radiation.
the analyzer measures the fluorescent radiation
to determine the sample's concentration of kcl.
the mill also processes potash
for industrial use.
this higher grade potash
with a kcl concentration of 99 percent
is a white powder
manufacturers make it by dissolving
the 95 percent kcl granular potash
in hot brine to remove more
of the residual nacl and clay.
then workers crystallize the potash
by evaporation and cooling.
the result, potash that's almost pure kcl.
narrator: handcrafted leather bracelets
are an unconventional jewelry choice.
traditional bracelets are chains
or bangles made of metal or stones.
but these fit like a cuff and are eclectic in design.
each one is an original.
so the wearer can express individuality.
handcrafted leather bracelets are substantial pieces
designed to draw attention to the wrist.
they can also complement an outfit in a big way.
making one starts with a strip of stainless
steel that will serve as the bracelet's base.
the artisan bends it by hand into a round shape.
using pliers she closes the gap a little more.
this bracelet is meant to be large,
so the loose fit seems right.
she sorts through a collection of leather pieces and ideas
for the design begin to take shape.
she selects a piece to cover the inside of the bracelet.
she draws an outline of the bracelet on paper
to create a pattern
and she cuts it out.
she sticks the pattern to the leather.
using a utility knife,
she follows the pattern to cut the shape in leather.
the edge of a triangular ruler
serves as a guide for a straight cut.
she peels the cut leather away from the paper pattern
and applies a textile adhesive to the back of the leather.
she curls the leather and inserts it, glued side down,
into the steel bracelet form.
she applies pressure for a strong adhesion.
for the bracelet's outer materials
there are many colorful options,
from dyed exotic leathers
to luminous semi-precious stones.
she sorts through the different leathers
and stones, looking for inspiration.
she selects a quartz stone
and a piece of fish scale leather.
once tanned, fish skins can be surprisingly tough.
she cuts the fish leather
to size using a paper template
of the front of the steel bracelet base.
she wraps it around the bracelet band
to check the fit.
she applies glue to the back of the quartz
and then positions the stone in the center of the leather.
the glue tacks it in place
while she now stitches a beaded surround
to permanently secure the stone to the leather.
she selects special beading needles for this.
the heads of these needles are tiny enough
to pass through the mini beads.
she'll use beading cord made of a tough polyethylene
to string and stitch the beads.
for the first three rows she uses silver beads
that are two millimeters in diameter.
she pulls the beading snug to the quartz stone
as she stitches the beads to the fish leather.
in addition to securing the stone,
the beaded surround also serves
as an embellishment to it's beauty.
she completes the three rows of silver beads
and switches to glass beads.
at 1.7 millimeters diameter,
they're a little smaller and trickier to work with.
she pulls the thread through the eyelets of the beads
a total of for times
to form a tight pouch around the perimeter of the stone.
she now applies strong glue
to the steel exterior of the bracelet base.
and it's time for the next decorative elements, black lace.
she glues the lace to the base
so that the flowery border overhangs.
she now spreads glue onto the back of the fish leather.
she wraps the leather around the lace-covered base
and presses it firmly to it.
she then stitches silver beads around the edges
to join the leathers and encase the steel base.
the beaded stitching matches
the quartz stone surround
for another decorative touch.
this handcrafted leather bracelet is now complete
and ready to add something completely different
to someone's jewelry collection.
narrator: wild rice is the grain harvested
from four species of aquatic grasses
that grow in many freshwater lakes
in northern united states and canada.
historically, indigenous people
harvested this plentiful and nutritious food
which they considered to be a sacred gift.
wild rice was a vital food source
for thousands of years.
it also became a valuable commodity,
which indigenous people exchanged with fur traders
who traveled the territory by canoe and needed
portable, nutritious food that didn't spoil.
beds of wild rice plants still grow today
in the shallow areas of rivers and lakes.
people still harvest the rice by traditional means,
in a canoe using two cedar flails
and winnowing baskets.
the baskets are made from bark pieces laced together
with dried roots of black spruce trees.
harvest time is usually in early september,
once the plants are protruding
from the water at least half a yard or so.
paddling through the rice beds would uproot the plants
so one person propels the boat
with a forked pole
while the other gently bends the plants
over the canoe with one flail
and gently knocks off the mature kernels
with the other.
the harvested kernels pile up at the bottom of the canoe.
harvesting wild rice is a delicate operation.
you have to knock just hard enough
to dislodge the kernels,
yet not break the plant stalks.
each kernel is comprised
of a fibrous hull encasing a rice grain.
back on land, harvesters transport the harvested kernels
by a winnowing basked or a grain sack.
the harvesters dump them
onto either birch bark sheets,
a tarp, or smooth bedrock
then spread them out to cure in the sun.
sun curing takes anywhere from several hours
to several days depending on the weather.
the next step is to parch
the kernels over an open fire.
this evaporates addition moisture,
enabling the rice to be stored
indefinitely without spoiling.
it also gives the rice a roasted nutty flavor.
for centuries indigenous people parched the kernels
on a woven willow rack above the fire,
letting the rising heat and smoke permeate the rice.
once the trade began with the europeans,
the indigenous people began using cast iron kettles set
directly on the flames.
fresh rice grains are green and flexible.
after parching they're brown or black
and snap cleanly into two when bent.
next comes threshing,
removing the grains from the hulls.
harvesters cool the kernels in the basket,
then pour them back into the parching pot.
before acquiring cast iron implements,
indigenous people would pour their kernels in a hole
in the ground lined with wood or animal hide.
threshing doesn't require
any special handcrafted tools,
just a pair of feet.
the pressure of each step forces
the rice grains out of their hulls.
this is what the rice looks like
before threshing and after.
the last step is winnowing,
separating the rice grains from the now-empty hulls.
there are two traditional techniques:
repeatedly flipping the rice in a single
winnowing basket like this
or pouring it from one basket to another.
the movement creates wind that blows away
the feather-light hulls.
eventually only the rice grains remain in the basket.
today, instead of deerskin pouches,
harvesters store wild rice
in containers or plastic bags.
the grains range in color
depending on the body of water
from which they were harvested
and how long after harvesting the grains were parched.
wild rice is high in protein in fiber,
low in calories in fat,
contains all essential amino acids
and is rich in b vitamins,
potassium and phosphorous.
narrator: hex key l-wrenches are designed
to turn screws and bolts
that would otherwise be tricky to reach.
they have ball-shaped hexagonal heads
that take an angled approach
to installing threaded fasteners.
the long arms of these l-shaped wrenches
also extend the user's reach into tight spots.
hex key l-wrenches often
come in sets to provide tools
for almost every job, big or small.
making these wrenches starts
with 13-foot long steel bars
formed to a hexagonal profile.
a technician tests the short piece to confirm
it could be bent without breaking.
the steel must be hard, yet elastic.
a diamond-tipped tool presses into another piece.
the depth of the indentation
is a measure of the steel's hardness.
after the steel passes all tests, workers slice
the just over 13-foot long bars
into smaller lengths using a die cutter
with a hexagonal profile
to prevent any distortion of the shape.
each steel piece then spins in a lathe
as a computerized tool carves a gentle slope into the end.
this is before and after the contouring.
a second computerized tool shapes the end rounder
to create a sphere shape
that retains the hexagonal angles.
an automated loader serves up the steel pieces
to a spiral copper heating element.
the element heats a specific spot
on the piece to 1,112 degrees fahrenheit to soften it.
a mechanized tool then bends the steel at this softened point
to give it an l shape.
the hex key l-wrenches have now taken shape.
in the next operation,
workers heat treat the wrenches
to make the steel even harder.
workers fire the parts in an electrical furnace,
quench them in oil
and then heat them in a second furnace
that's not as hot as the first one.
the heat treatment strengthens the steel but leaves a residue.
a wash and then a sand blast cleans them up a bit,
but the wrenches are quite tarnished looking
so it's into a vibrating machine
with ceramic stones and polishing solution.
this cleans and brightens the steel.
a magnetic conveyor extracts them from the mix
and takes them to a revolving drum.
here the wrenches bounce around with corn grains
that absorb residual moisture from the polishing.
what a difference the cleaning has made.
on racks now, the wrenches take a dip
in different nickel and chrome baths.
the rack delivers an electrical charge
to the parts,
which attracts the nickel and chrome.
the metals coat the wrenches
for a shiny rust-proof finish.
next a device spins the wrench in front of a sensor.
the sensor detects and crookedness
in the wrench's long arm.
if needed, he straightens
the steel with a special tool.
the wrenches are now ready for a spray of powder coat.
it will provide
a durable finish and the color
will indicate the wrench's size.
after powder coating a robot transfers
the wrenches to a printing station.
a mechanized tool nudges the wrenches forward
to put them in alignment.
another robot moves in.
it picks one of the wrenches
and moves it under a printing pad.
the pad stamps brand information
and a serial number on the wrench.
the robot retrieves the wrench and places i on a conveyor.
they now make the plastic holders for the wrenches.
this machine melts and molds plastic under pressure
to produce them in seconds.
a robot removes the plastic holders
from the machine
and deposits them in a bin.
a worker now places two of the holders under a laser.
he lowers the protective shield
and the laser etches company information onto the plastic.
another member of the team inserts the color-coded wrenches
into the correct slots in the holders.
they now have a full kit of hex key l-wrenches.
it should have all the angles covered.