--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today on "how it's made,"
macarons...
pine-needle baskets...
and micrometers.
meringue cookies with a flavored filling,
macarons were first produced in the eighth century
in venetian monasteries.
in 1533, the recipe came to france
with the pastry chefs brought by the italian noblewoman
who arrived to marry the king.
macarons have been considered french ever since.
macarons are as much a treat
for the eyes as for the mouth,
with colorful meringue shells sandwiching a flavorful filling.
to prepare what's known as italian meringue for the shells,
the bakers combine sugar and water.
they heat the mixture to precisely
222 degrees fahrenheit,
slightly above the boiling point.
in a mixing bowl, the bakers combine egg whites
with dehydrated egg whites.
using a combination of liquid
and dried egg whites reduces the amount of moisture
in the meringue mixture.
when there's less moisture,
it's easier to control the baking.
workers mix the egg whites
for about 8 to 10 minutes to make an emulsion,
then add the boiling water and sugar.
the combination mixes until the temperature
drops to 104 degrees fahrenheit.
no thermometer is necessary.
bakers can tell by the stiff texture
of what is now meringue.
the next step is to flavor and color the meringue.
workers weigh very precise
quantities of almond powder...
...then icing sugar.
they transfer these ingredients to the mixer...
...and blend them thoroughly.
the baker adds the blended almond powder
and icing sugar to a mixture of egg whites
and, in this case, red food coloring
because these will be raspberry macarons.
they resume mixing for another two or three minutes
until everything is thoroughly blended.
then the baker adds this mixture
to the meringue to color and flavor it.
five more minutes of blending, and the meringue is ready.
it's time to form the meringue shells.
a worker pours the meringue
into the feed vat of the depositer.
the depositer dispenses 5-gram disks of meringue,
60 disks per lined baking sheet.
using a micrometer,
a worker measures each disk to make sure
it's between 1.69 and 1.77 inches in diameter.
meringue expands with baking,
so this ensures each disk
will bake into a shell that's the correct size.
then, fans blow air to dry out the tops.
evaporating the moisture prevents
the top of the disks from rising
as they bake in the oven
for 15 to 20 minutes at 249 degrees fahrenheit.
when they come out of the oven,
the baked shells are set out to cool.
meanwhile, the bakers prepare the filling,
mixing chocolate with piping-hot 35% cream.
as the chocolate melts,
they blend the ingredients thoroughly.
then the baker refrigerates
the filling for 12 hours at 48 degrees fahrenheit.
when the filling comes out of the fridge,
it's firm but malleable enough to be scooped up
and put in a pastry bag.
with filling and shells now ready,
the baker can begin assembling the macarons.
they squeeze about 5 grams of filling onto each shell...
...then place another shell on top,
pressing gently to spread the filling outward.
the macarons fit perfectly
into the slots of plastic retail trays,
thanks to the careful measuring
of the meringue disks prior to baking.
the trays pass through a machine
which seals them in a pocket of plastic film
to keep out moisture.
then, each tray is packaged in a retail box.
this colorful selection features
five flavors of macarons --
raspberry, blueberry, lemon,
cherry, and exotic fruits.
narrator: when indigenous north americans   needed
they looked no further than the pine needles
that littered the forest floor.
they wove the needles into sturdy baskets
for their daily use.
the making of these coniferous containers
continues today,
ensuring that it doesn't become a lost art.
pine-needle baskets are beautiful examples
of resourcefulness.
they prove that something substantial can be made
from needles that would otherwise
just end up on the ground
and be trampled on.
the norway red pine in the northern united states
sheds needles in the fall.
just before they drop,
they can be easily plucked from the branches.
this forager also collects needles
that have fallen to the ground.
he tosses some pinecones into the bag too.
back in the studio, a craftsperson immerses
the needles in boiling water
and simmers them for five minutes.
this softens the needles
so that they're flexible enough to work with.
she selects a pinecone
and boils it for 15 or 20 minutes.
this causes the scales to close up,
and the cone shrinks.
here are the pinecones before and after boiling.
the shrunken cone will serve
as a handle for a basket lid.
after winding waxed linen thread
around the cone's base,
the craftsperson loops thread around the strands
to hold them firmly together.
she now coils a bundle of pine needles around the cone
and sews them to it.
she sets the cone aside for now.
next, for an effect that is simply decorative,
the craftsperson coils pine needles
around a colorful piece of stone
that's been sealed in acrylic.
holes around the edge of the acrylic envelope
make it easier to stitch the pine-needle coil
to the decorative center.
the craftsperson gives each stitch a gentle tug
to pull the coils snuggly
so that it encompasses the acrylic edge.
this decorative center is now ready to be used
as a starting point for a basket or a lid.
using another technique,
she crafts a basket center
using only softened pine needles and thread.
this will be a bit trickier.
using pliers, she pulls off the sheaths
that hold the groupings of needles together.
without the sheaths in the way,
it will be easier to work with the needles.
the craftsperson now takes a bundle
that's almost the thickness of a pencil
and forms a small loop.
she ties a knot at the cross point.
she stitches the bundle all the way around,
creating a spiral with a threaded pattern
that radiates outward,
like spokes on a wheel.
the craftsperson continually tucks more pine needles
into the tail of the spiral
to make it thicker and more even.
she then weaves a basket base
from the center spiral outward.
she stitches each coil of pine needles to the one before it.
and she aligns the stitching
to create a decorative pattern
that adds to the appeal of the basket.
the craftsperson now tucks in pine needles
with the black sheaths still on,
to add even more visual interest.
she artfully arranges them around the basket base
and stitches them to it.
from start to finish, it takes about 12 hours
to craft the entire basket.
after completing the lid with the decorative stone,
the craftsperson tests the fit.
for an alternative embellishment,
she weaves red dogwood twigs into a pine-needle basket.
it's another way to be creative with the materials
that nature offers up in abundance.
each one of these pine-needle baskets is an original,
handcrafted by an artisan.
and that makes them worth holding on to.
narrator: a micrometer is a handheld
typically used in manufacturing.
a toolmaker producing parts for factory equipment
or a machinist making parts for a product
would use a micrometer
to take precision measurements
to make sure the part dimensions confirm
to engineering specifications.
micrometers come in different types
and ranges of measurement.
this model is designed to measure
the outside diameter of an object.
the graduations are in imperial units up to 1 inch.
the micrometer's frame starts
out as a forged-steel part
that needs to be machined to the final shape.
workers secure the part on a mechanical milling machine.
the machine first squares the ends...
...then slices the part down the middle,
dividing it into frames for two micrometers.
a computer-guided mill profiles the frame.
this is the forged frame before this step and after.
another computer-guided mill reduces the inside
and outside diameters of the frame's hollow stem.
workers insert a nut in the stem,
then dip a piece of solder
into a soldering chemical called flux
and insert it through a hole in the stem.
they hold the stem inside a soldering coil.
the heat instantly melts the solder,
fusing the nut to the stem.
workers remove excess solder with a wire brush.
then, they grind the stem to finalize the diameter.
here's what the stem looks like
before this last grinding and after.
next, on the opposite end of the frame,
they mill a notch.
this is for the lock nut
that locks the micrometer against the object
while you read the measurement.
workers now sandblast the entire frame.
this removes all traces of metal dust and machining lubricant,
leaving the surface pristine,
a requirement for the next step --
electroplating the frame with chrome.
they complete the micrometer's frame
by laser-marking the brand name
and a reference chart of measurements
in fractions of an inch and the decimal equivalents.
this machine shapes a long steel rod
into the micrometer's inside shell,
which, in conjunction with the outside shell,
displays the measurement reading.
the machine first drills through the rod
to form a hollow cylinder.
next, it reams the inside
and grinds the outside to the required diameter.
the same machine also shapes a steel rod
into the micrometer's outside shell.
it carves a diamond pattern onto it called a knurl.
this textures the surface, making it easier to grip.
then the machines reams
the inside to the required diameter.
after sandblasting both shells,
workers hang them on a rack,
then dip the rack into a tank of chromic acid.
copper prongs on the rack
deliver a positive electrical current to the shells
while the chromic acid is charged
with a negative current.
this magnetically draws a chrome layer
onto the surface of the shells.
then a computer-guided laser marks the brand name
and the graduations on the inside
and outside shells.
this computer-guided mill shapes a steel rod
into the micrometer's key measuring component,
the spindle.
the machine first profiles the outside.
then it drills a hole 1/2 inch deep
and reams it to the correct diameter.
it's critical that the spindle not wear down
with long-term use,
as this would effect the micrometer's measuring accuracy.
to prevent this, they harden the steel through
a heat-treatment process.
first, workers put the spindles
in a furnace at a temperature of 1,526 degrees fahrenheit.
after an hour, they submerge the spindles in oil,
then freeze them overnight to stabilize the steel.
the next day, workers temper the steel
by putting the spindles back in the furnace for an hour,
this time at a lower temperature.
once the spindles cool,
a machining tool grinds threads into them.
the precision of that threading determines
the micrometer's measurement accuracy.
narrator: to use a micrometer,
you place the object you're measuring
against the stationary end
of the frame called the anvil.
then you rotate the spindle on the opposite end
until it's seated against the object.
you turn the nut to lock that position
and read the measurement.
the spindle for this model has 40 threads per inch.
so turning it one revolution in either direction
moves it 25/1,000 inch.
if the steel hadn't been hardened,
those threads would wear down over time,
causing inaccurate measurements.
for the same reason,
this disk they now prepare to solder
onto the face of the spindle
is made of tungsten carbide,
the hardest type of steel.
after fluxing the face of the spindle,
topping it with the disk of solder,
and positioning the fluxed carbide disk on top of that,
workers place the spindle inside the hot soldering machine
to fuse the carbide to the face of the spindle.
they grind the diameter of the carbide disk to reduce it
to the same diameter as the spindle.
after this grinding,
the disk becomes integrated
with the rest of the spindle.
they grind the face of the carbide disk flat.
then this lapping machine polishes the face
to perfect the flatness
and produces a mirror finish.
they perform a quality-control check
with an optical parallel made of sapphire.
it projects bands of light which detect flatness
to a degree the human eye can't perceive.
this second test reflects light off the mirror-finish face.
when rotating the spindle,
the light should stand still.
this indicates the face
is perfectly perpendicular to the diameter.
the micrometer's anvil,
the fixed surface opposite the spindle
against which you place the object you're measuring,
is also machined from carbide.
to assemble the micrometer,
a worker places a spring
in a recessed area of the frame stem,
then the inside shell onto the stem.
the spring applies enough tension
to hold the shell in place.
the inside of the stem will have female threads
to match male threads on the spindle.
this adjusting nut on the end of the stem
controls the thread engagement
between the two,
enabling the spindle to move more tightly or loosely.
the next step is cutting those female threads
into the inside of the stem.
first, a worker reams the stem to the required diameter,
then switch the reaming tool on the lathe for a tapping tool.
tapping is the term for cutting threads.
they put the stem back on the lathe
and tap 40 female threads per inch.
now, workers can assemble the spindle to the stem.
they mount the spindle
on an automatic lapping machine.
then a worker slides the stem over the spindle,
going back and forth multiple times
to fit both sets of threads together.
they lubricate the threads with instrument oil
so they'll glide smoothly against each other.
after assembling the lock nut in its notch,
the worker cleans the spindle face with alcohol
and glues the anvil to it temporarily.
then they rotate the spindle
until the anvil reaches its adhesive-coated position
at the opposite end of the frame.
when the adhesive sets,
the worker separates the spindle and anvil.
using an optical parallel, they check the spindle
and anvil faces to make sure
they're perfectly parallel to each other.
the worker completes the assembly
by fitting the outside shell to the frame.
it covers the end of the spindle that's protruding from the stem.
a steel ratchet locks it into position.
a final round of quality-control testing
ensures the device works smoothly
and measures accurately.
in this test, they measure
four different-sized measuring blocks.
in this one, they bring out those optical parallels again
to check flatness and parallelism.
they also perform a cosmetic inspection
and check that the graduations are all legible
because, of course, no one wants a micrometer
that doesn't measure up.