-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: abalone is an edible mollusk.
its shell has
a multicolored iridescent lining
that's been used since ancient times
to decorate jewelry and other prized objects.
more recently, abalone has been tapped
as a source of collagen,
a protein that supports the structure of bones,
connective tissues, and skin.
abalone collagen is a popular treatment in asia.
this farm and factory raises the abalones,
then extracts their collagen to add to drinks,
cosmetics, and medicine.
the abalones spend their first six months
in the farm's hatchery and nursery pond.
nocturnal, they hide
from daylight under cement tiles
that simulate their natural habitat
of rocks and coral.
their single shell has pores
that regulate various bodily functions
such as breathing and reproduction.
the main ingredient in their specially formulated food
is seaweed.
feeding time is once every evening.
♪♪
at six months of age,
the abalones graduate to the cultivation pond.
there are two types of growing methods.
in this one, before filling the pond with seawater,
workers lay cement tiles at the bottom,
along with underwater pipes that supply oxygen,
which abalones need to survive.
the other method houses the abalones
in stacks of polyethylene crates,
referred to as condominiums.
with 50 to 100 abalones in each condo,
the yield per square foot is significantly greater.
every second day, workers remove the condos
from the cultivation pond to rinse out the crates,
check the abalones, and feed them.
rather than wastefully using new seawater,
the pond water is regularly drained,
cleaned, and recirculated.
the cleaning system filters out feces
and neutralizes ammonia.
after six months to a year in the cultivation pond,
the abalones are mature and ready for harvesting.
workers remove them from the shell
and remove organs to be used for other products.
then, the workers prepare to extract collagen
from the meat.
first, they mash the meat in an industrial-sized blender.
the trick is to use an extraction method
that doesn't destroy the collagen
or diminish its effectiveness.
abalone collagen must have full potency when consumed
in order to stimulate the human body
to produce more of its own collagen.
since prolonged heating turns collagen into gelatin,
worker use a process called cold extraction,
stirring the meat in refrigerated tanks
for up to seven days
until the collagen separates
and rises to the top.
workers skim off the collagen,
then, to make this particular product,
blend it with mixed fruit juices.
then they heat the drink in pasteurization tanks
for three minutes to kill off any bacteria.
the drink contains 20% collagen
and 80% juice.
when it's time to package the product,
the conveyor belt moves glass bottles
to the cleaning station,
which washes them out with pressurized boiling water.
after washing, the bottles move to the next machine
which fills them with the drink.
the next machine seals the bottles
with an aluminum twist cap.
controlled by a sensor,
an inkjet printer applies the lot number on the cap
along with the product's expiration date,
a year away.
a worker visually inspects the bottles
as they make their way to the labeling machine.
the factory's on-site laboratory
conducts a series
of quality control tests on random samples.
in this test, the technician uses
a ph meter to ensure the product's acidity
is within a specific target range.
in another test, she places a few drops
on a device called a refractometer.
it measures to what extent
light passing through the liquid is bent,
which gives a reading of the sweetness.
while this drink is a skin enhancement product,
other abalone collagen formulations
are designed for weight loss, boosting immunity,
increasing bone density, and strengthening cartilage.
narrator: an essential component
of an audio system
is the digital-to-analog converter.
it receives data from a digital device
such as a computer, tv, or disc player
and converts that signal to analog,
an electrical audio signal
that the sound system can amplify
and play through speakers.
this digital-to-analog converter,
part of a product line of high-end audio components,
has four inputs for different digital devices.
it also has a built-in cd drive.
many of the converter's structural parts
are made by computer-guided machines.
this computer-guided lathe, for example,
rotates an aluminum bar,
which a cutting tool forms into one of four legs
that support the cd drive.
♪♪
this milling machine cuts
and shapes most of the aluminum parts
that makeup the converter's chassis,
the box that contains all the electronic components.
the parts come off the mill with sharp burrs
along their edges,
so the next step is to trim them
with a de-burring tool.
workers spray the trimmed chassis parts
with black powder paint,
then bake the paint in an oven to make it more durable.
then they print labeling on the chassis's front
and back panels by squeegeeing white epoxy paint
through a silkscreen stencil.
then workers put the panels
in the oven to bake the paint.
workers install them in between
the cd drive support base and each of the feet
to create a floating suspension system
that protects the drive from vibration.
next, workers install the cd drive
onto the support base.
they install the drive's protective cover.
it prevents dust from getting into the cd optical reader.
meanwhile, a technician tests
each of the converter's five circuit boards
to make sure they function perfectly.
this board runs the l.e.d. display
which shows the selected input
and other playback information.
once all the circuit boards pass inspection,
workers solder the l.e.d. board
to the front panel circuit board
which runs the converter's user controls.
the worker inserts brushed aluminum push buttons
into the front panel's labeled holes.
then they attach the front panel circuit board.
this aligns the push buttons with the corresponding contacts
on the board.
the worker assembles the chassis bottom,
side, and back panels.
they attach the front panel with its push button controls,
and in the center, an opening for the cd drive.
the technician visually inspects
the converter's main circuit board,
which converts the digital signal to analog.
if the main circuit board passes inspection,
they install it in the back of the converter
next to the power supply board.
next, a worker installs the cd drive.
this requires connecting three cables
into the main board --
one for the optical reader,
and two for the motors that open
and close the loading tray
and spin the compact disc.
before completing the converter
by closing up the top,
a worker tests the cd drive
as well as the four other digital inputs,
which are designed for connecting devices
such as audio components,
dvd or blu-ray players,
tvs, and computers.
the testing machine takes all kinds of measurements
to ensure the converter performs
to a list of technical specifications.
if the unit passes inspection,
they complete the assembly by attaching the top cover.
this digital-to-analog converter
is now ready to play its critical role
in this high-end audio system,
reproducing sound for the discerning ear.
narrator: embossed wood trim
can make factory furniture look handcrafted.
the technique was developed over a century ago
to mimic carvings on fancier furnishings
that were only available to the wealthy.
today, this trim is still giving furniture and cabinetry
the look of hand carving.
the purpose of embossed wood trim
is purely aesthetic.
it can transform a piece of furniture
and make it a beautiful thing.
making embossed moulding starts
with a rough piece of maple.
using a rip saw,
a woodworker slices the board into strips.
the first cut straightens
the edge of the wood to correct warps,
and the second one trims the strips
to the correct dimension.
♪♪
he then carves through the center of each strip
to get two pieces of trim from one board.
each strip is about 1/2 inch thick.
the strips are ready to be fed to the moulder,
a machine that shapes the flat surface to a specific profile.
the moulder has five cutter heads.
to prepare them, he inserts a spacer
and a blade into the steel head.
he uses a magnet to pull them into alignment.
the worker locks the blade and spacer
to the cutter head with bolts.
he slides the cutter head onto a spindle in the moulder.
the worker secures it with a nut,
using a special tool for the job.
once all the cutter heads are in place,
he turns the switch on the machine.
as the cutters spin, the operator feeds
the long strips of wood to them.
rubber and steel wheels move the board
from one cutter to the next.
the cutter progressively profiles the area
that's to be embossed
and creates decorative raised borders.
here's a side view of the contouring.
this trim is now ready for embossing.
some of the embossing wheels at this shop date back to 1908.
the oldest wheels are made of bronze,
and the newer ones are made of steel.
there are hundreds of patterns to choose from.
the worker selects the wheel with the desired pattern.
he mounts it to an embossing machine
that was built in 1908.
the worker locks the embossing wheel onto the shaft.
he ignites torches that heat the embossing wheel.
as the hot wheel revolves,
it presses the pattern into the moulded strip of wood.
the heat releases moisture from the wood,
preventing splintering during embossing.
a drive wheel below works in concert
with the embossing wheel to move the wood forward.
next up are rosettes
that are used to accentuate the corners of furniture,
windows, and doors.
using a sliding apparatus known as a sled,
the woodworker delivers a board
to the teeth of a saw.
he makes straight cuts and squares
to the desired dimensions.
the worker draws lines from one corner
of the wood square to another,
and from the opposite sides.
the lines intersect at the exact center of the square.
the worker clamps the square in a milling machine
with the cutting tool aimed directly at the center.
he activates the tool to make the first circular cut.
he removes the wood square to check out the cut.
the worker measures it to confirm
that it is in fact, dead center.
he returns the square to the platform
under the milling tool.
this time the cutter spins into the wood
to make a wider and deeper circular cut.
this further expands the pattern
in a radial fashion.
and it completes the rosette pattern.
the worker examines the quality of the cut
and measures the distance to the edge of the wood
to verify that it's to spec.
from a simple wood square to an elegant rosette,
this job is done.
the trim can now be used
to make furniture looked hand carved
without all the effort.
narrator: a stapler can instantly transform
a pile of papers into a document.
its story begins with the rapid
increase in the use of paper
in the middle of the 19th century.
the stapler was developed
because people needed something
better than string or pins
to hold the pages together.
plier staplers open and close like pliers
to tackle fastening jobs with quick precision.
♪♪
making these staplers starts with the cover plate.
a press wields up to 176 tons of force
to shape steel blanks to a slopped profile.
a robot inserts tracks into nickel steel casings.
these are the vertical staple tracks
for the front of the stapler.
tools bend tabs on the ends of the casings
to fasten the two parts.
another robot serves up covers for the stapler's magazines
to an automated welder.
the welder fuses an assembly attachment
to each cover.
a worker immerses some of the stapler's interior parts
in a solution of water and zinc phosphate.
this solution forms an anti-corrosion coating
on the surface of the steel.
these particular parts are pusher guides.
the top part has the protective coating.
the parts then take a ride
with ceramic stones and polishing solution.
this smoothes rough bits and makes them shine.
next up is the die plate.
this is the part that shapes
and closes the staple during stapling.
an automated system screws an iron "u"-bolt attachment
to the die plate.
a robot then inserts the spring block,
the part that allows the stapler
to spring back to its original position after use.
meanwhile at the next station,
a robot places a piece of precision-cut steel
on a mold.
a press drives it into the mold
to shape it into the stapler body
that holds all the working components.
more robots then work in perfect sequence,
to install thick metal pins across the stapler body.
these pins brace the stapler's structure,
but that's not all.
some of the stapler's working parts
will hook onto these pins.
other robots now fasten the die plate
to one end of the stapler body using rivet hinge.
in the process, they also fasten
the spring block securely to the die plate.
after cleaning and degreasing,
the stapler bodies head into a paint booth.
spray guns apply primer,
and a curtain of water behind the parts prevents emissions
from escaping from the booth.
the next sprayers coat the parts with green paint.
with the paint dry on the stapler body,
workers are ready to assemble all the working parts.
the assembler slides the front staple track into place
and inserts the staple pusher guide into the body.
she positions a metal plate over the guide
and screws everything in place
through holes in the body of the stapler.
the assembler clips a retaining
ring around each screw.
next up is the driver.
this part detaches staples
one at a time during stapling.
after installing it, the assembler inserts
the spring loaded pusher
and hooks the end on the staple guide.
another worker assembles the handle
that allows the stapler
to be wielded with plier-like accuracy.
he secures the handle with a rolling fastener.
this rolling fastener indirectly bears down
on the staples to apply pressure during stapling.
another team member then inspects the stapler.
satisfied with its fabrication,
she reaches for the cover plate
and hammers the wings to bend them for a better fit.
she slides the cover plate into the grooves of the stapler
and loads the staples to give it a trial run.
she staples paper repeatedly to confirm
that it's fully operational.
these plier staplers
are now ready for the workplace,
where with a few quick crunches,
they'll help keep the paperwork in order.