--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
endoscopes...
megaphones...
and uranium.
an endoscope is a tube with optical glass fibers
and lenses inside attached to a video camera.
doctors feed the endoscope through the patient's mouth
or other opening or insert it through a tiny incision
then watch what the camera captures on a video monitor.
an endoscope lets the surgeon see inside the patient
during an examination or surgical procedure.
its light-transmitting optical fibers work
like a flashlight inside the body.
the optical fiber manufacturer suspends glass rods
from the top of a tall oven,
which heats them to a melting temperature
of 1,652 degrees fahrenheit.
each rod drips downward in the form of a thin strand.
a guide wheel turns this glass fiber in a horizontal direction.
the fiber then winds on to a drum,
whose rotation speed stretches it
to a specific hair-thin diameter.
a worker combines several single fiber spools on to a large
winding wheel to make a bundle containing thousands of fibers.
to make the cable that connects a light source
in the operating room to the endoscope,
a worker inserts an optical fiber bundle
into a silicon cable sheathing.
this one has nearly 9,000 fibers.
she screws a stainless steel fastener,
called a ferrule on to each
threaded end of the sheathing.
after saturating the ferrules and optical fibers
inside with glue and curing the adhesive with heat,
the worker trims off excess fibers
and hands off the cable to the next station,
where a work polishes both ends.
polishing finalizes the dimensions
and enables light to shine through.
this quality control test, one of several,
ensures the fibers can
withstand a prescribed amount of pressure without cracking.
the optical fiber manufacturer
also supplies fiber spools
to the endoscope manufacturer
for the light transmission system inside the endoscope.
workers cut the bundle of optical fibers
to the length required
for the endoscope model they're making.
endoscopes vary in length and diameter,
depending on the part of
the body they're designed for.
after verifying that the diameter
of the bundle is correct,
they tie the optical fibers with string
to hold them together during insertion.
then workers insert the fiber bundle
between the inner and outer stainless steel sheathes
that make up the main body of the endoscope,
pushing the fibers down the length of the inner sheath.
they attach a stainless steel adaptor.
this will connect the light cable
from the operating room light source
to the endoscope,
transferring light to the optical fibers
inside the endoscope.
a worker inspects those fibers
under magnification for black spots.
black spots indicate broken fibers,
which would interrupt the transmission of light.
an endoscope transmits an image much like a telescope does.
optical lenses send reflected light, which produces the image,
from inside the patient
all the way up to your eye peering through the top.
the lenses in the endoscope are glass rods.
after cleaning them with chemical solution,
workers line them up in a fixture
with brass spacers
of various lengths in between.
depending on the length of the endoscope,
there are five to seven lenses.
the spacers create specific distances between them.
once workers have assembled
the image transmission system,
they gently slide it off the fixture
into the inner sheath of the endoscope.
then, they screw on an ocular cap
to hold it all in place.
a worker cleans the cap's glass top,
then attaches an eyepiece.
this gives the surgeon the option of either
looking directly into the endoscope
or looking at an operating room video monitor
which receives the image via a small camera
attached to the eyepiece.
this demonstration shows how it all comes together
in the operating room.
after securing the endoscope in a holding fixture,
the surgeon attaches the light cable
coming from the nearby light source.
the light travels down and out the endoscope,
illuminating the area that surgeon's working on.
the lenses reflect the image
to the top of the endoscope,
where a camera transmits it to a video monitor
that's mounted in front of the surgeon.
narrator: in the beginning,
megaphones were simply cone-shaped devices
that focused sound forward so it went further
and could be heard more clearly.
in the 20th century microphones, an amplifier and a speaker
were added to the cone,
and that really ramped up the volume.
with a megaphone, there's no need to shout.
just speak, and you will be heard.
this waterproof version is designed for coaching,
law enforcement, and military uses.
production starts with a panel
of four digital circuit boards
that have little gold pads on them.
an assembler places a stencil over the panel
and aligns the stencil holes with the gold pads.
he then squeegee's
solder paste down the stencil,
and it flows on to the exposed gold pads.
this is before and after the solder past application.
robotic arms install electrical components
on the solder-coated pads, creating circuitry.
various reels unwind to deliver these little parts.
the robotic arms suction them off liners
and transfer them to precise locations on the boards.
the parts will run the megaphone's sirens,
horns, and microphones.
a technician clamps
one of the completed circuit boards in a tester.
spring-loaded pins underneath make electrical contacts
with the components and probe their performance.
the system runs a full test of the circuitry.
at the next station, an assembler attaches
a part known as the front can
to the end of a flared speaker cone.
he then turns his attention to the speaker.
the assembler inserts screws in the base.
he threads wires from the speaker
through a hole in the cone
and through the front can.
the assembler then places the speaker in the cone,
and he screws it in place.
he attaches a connector to the protruding speaker wires.
the worker places a mesh metal screen
over a hole in the rear can.
the assembler taps a nut driver
with a hammer to force the mesh into the hole,
and this shapes the mesh into a microphone cover.
he removes the newly-formed mic cover and fits it to the mic,
manually crimping it around the sides for a snug fit.
he now tucks the microphone into a tube
that has a sliding inner sleeve.
the assembler inserts the tube into the microphone hole
in the rear can.
he slides the inside tube down
to push the microphone in the hole.
he secures the knob for turning the megaphone on
and for adjusting the volume.
the assembler installs a mini-circuit board
that's linked to the siren and horn button.
these small spring pins will mate to a battery
to power the megaphone's circuitry.
he tucks the pins into molded protrusions
inside the rear can
and waterproofs them with rubber o-rings.
this megaphone subassembly is now ready
for the main circuit board.
the assembler threads wires
for this switch trigger, microphone, siren,
and horn through holes in the board.
he then screws the board to the rear housing.
he fits a silicon o-ring around
the rim of the rear can to seal it.
the assembler then joins the rear can
with all the working parts
to the front can and cone assembly.
he connects the speaker wires to the circuit board.
this megaphone is now ready for a sound test.
the technician connects it to a temporary battery
and powers it up.
check, one, two. one, two.
check, testing, testing.
one, two, test.
more sensitive testing is needed.
he encloses the megaphone in an insulated chamber
to shut out background noises.
a computer runs the megaphone at different frequencies
and analyzes its performance.
once the megaphone passes these tests,
they install handles.
and now it's ready for anything you have to say.
narrator: uranium is a metallic element
that was discovered by a german chemist in 1789.
the significance of this discovery
wasn't understood for a century and a half.
in 1938, scientists figured out that uranium atoms
could be split to produce energy.
the size of a fireplace log,
this nuclear fuel bundle generates a lot more heat.
it's packed with enough uranium
to power 100 homes for a year.
to obtain the uranium,
the tunnel 1,640 feet underground
at this site in northern saskatchewan.
this mine is the largest source
of high-grade uranium in the world.
the uranium ore lies beneath a bed
of water-saturated sandstone.
to reach it, they use drill bits studded
with tungsten carbide buttons.
like knuckles on a fist,
the button bits punch into the rock face.
these first holes are for pipes
that will pull heat out of the ground
and freeze it around the ore.
the miner operates the equipment by remote control.
it transfers a new piece of pipe to the end of the drill
roughly every five feet
to penetrate 426 feet into the sandstone bed.
it takes up to eight days
to install just one length of pipe,
and there are 200 of them.
workers configure the pipes
so they surround the ore deposit.
these freeze pipes will stabilize the ground,
and they'll also turn high-pressure ground water
to ice, so it won't interfere with the actual mining.
a freeze plant above ground chills
calcium chloride brine
to minus-22 degrees fahrenheit
and sends it through the freeze pipes.
the brine absorbs heat as it freezes the ground
and loops back to be chilled again.
above the uranium deposits,
workers now gear up to mine the ore.
they'll use this bit to chew into the ore body
in order to make an initial small-diameter hole
known as a pilot hole.
the pilot hole maps out the drill route to ore,
and it creates an entry point for larger mining equipment.
from a raised position,
the bit bores vertically into the rock
to drill the pilot hole
and reach a specific level below the ore body.
they're now ready for the reamer bit.
the reamer has numerous
button-encrusted wheel tentacles.
as this animation shows,
the drill pulls the reamer up the pilot hole, widening it.
and the broken ore falls into what's known
as an extraction chamber.
here, a tram operated by remote control
scoops up the rock.
this remote control system keeps miners a safe distance away
from falling rock hazards.
it also minimizes their exposure
to the radioactive uranium in the ore.
as another precaution,
workers continuously ventilate the mine,
introducing fresh air every 20 minutes.
steered by the operator's joystick,
the tram delivers the ore to a scanner.
by measuring the amount of radioactivity in the ore,
the scanner determines
the uranium content is about 15%.
in much of the ore, the uranium content is even greater --
on average, around 18%,
and that's considered to be very high-grade.
the train now empties the ore into a chute.
cameras follow the rocks' journey to the next station.
then from a control room,
an operator manipulates a hydraulic hammer
to smash the ore to bits.
the broken ore then migrates to a mill
that grinds it into a fine sand.
they add water, and it becomes slurry,
which they then pump to the surface.
trucks then transport the uranium ore slurry
to a mill nearly 50 miles away.
they pull into a special off-loading facility.
the support for a vacuum system aligns with the tote
that encases the slurry tank.
once in position, a vacuum pipe drops into the tank
and suctions up the slurry.
cameras provide a live feed of the unloading progress
to a control room almost 23 feet away.
after a wash and a radiation check,
the truck leaves.
stay tuned for the transformation
of uranium into nuclear fuel.
narrator: just one fuel bundle of uranium contains
the same amount of energy
as just over 71,000 gallons of oil.
but uranium can't simply be chipped away
from the rock it resides in.
it must be chemically separated and processed
to make it into usable fuel for a nuclear reactor.
acid dissolves the uranium, but not the rest of the rock.
it settles to the bottom of these tanks.
the uranium-acid solution flows forward,
leaving the unwanted minerals behind.
using a series of chemical reactions,
they further purify the uranium.
they then roast it at 1,562 degrees fahrenheit.
this concentrates it into a jet-black powder.
the uranium powder flows into 55-gallon steel drums.
a worker taps the lip of the drum
to remove residual powder.
he then puts the lid on and activates a press
that secures it tightly to the drum.
as an extra precaution,
he seals it with a steel ring.
he labels it to indicate the drum's contents,
weight, and radioactivity.
workers stack the drums in a warehouse
to await shipment to the next processing plant.
there, the uranium goes from black to yellow
as they convert it to uranium trioxide,
an interim chemical form in the processing chain.
they ship the uranium trioxide in specially
designed inverted cones.
upon arrival at the next facility,
a valve opens at the bottom
and the powder flows into conveyor tubes
that take it into the plant.
inside, workers dissolve
the uranium trioxide powder in acid.
a worker takes a sample to test the density
and the chemistry and confirms that both are acceptable.
they then add a chemical to turn the dissolved uranium
back into a solid.
after more processing,
the uranium trioxide becomes uranium dioxide,
the chemical form required for nuclear fuel.
spinning the uranium dioxide mixes
the different sized particles
to make it a more homogenous blend.
the chemical processing has also caused the uranium
to change color again.
it is now a fine black powder.
using several tons of pressure,
tools shape the uranium dioxide into pellets.
a revolving wheel with protrusions
guides the pellets into a channel conveyor.
the conveyor takes the pellets into a furnace.
over 24 hours, the heat removes pores in the pellets.
the pellets shrink, increasing the density of the uranium.
the particles fuse together and harden into a ceramic.
here's a pellet before and after baking.
a robot arm now loads the pellets
on to a tray and levels them.
a conveyor moves the tray forward.
ahead, another robot places zirconium fuel tubes on a rack.
zirconium is a metal that's highly resistant
to both heat and corrosion,
but neutrons will pass freely through it
during the fission reaction.
the rack of tubes meet up
with a tray of incoming pellets.
a robotic loader pushes the stack
of 30 pellets into the tube.
another robot delivers the rods one at a time
to an automated welder that caps the ends.
the next robot retrieves the completed uranium fuel rods
and transfers it to an assembly fixture.
it arranges a total of 37 rods
in an upright position within the fixture.
after the rods have been welded
and the bundle capped at both ends,
a robot transfers it to a scale.
this weigh-in confirms
that there is the correct amount of uranium in the bundle.
prior to burn up in a reactor,
the amount of radioactivity emitted by nuclear fuel bundles
is very low, and they're safe to handle
as workers prepare them for shipping.
they're now on their way to the power plant,
where they'll be sure to generate a reaction.