-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: the word barbecue
seems to originate in haiti
where indigenous people
developed
a method of cooking meat
outdoors over a wooden structure
long before columbus arrived.
nobody knows exactly
when humans started grilling.
but it's safe to assume
that we've been
cooking outdoors
longer than indoors.
in thailand, many homes
and restaurants
have a popular kind
of barbecue.
it's a small portable
charcoal burner.
this new, more efficient
design has become
increasingly popular both
in thailand and abroad.
workers start by adding
the raw materials
to a mixer, beginning with clay.
they add a fiber derived
from ground-up rice husks.
this fiber reinforces the clay,
giving it added strength
and helping to prevent
the finished product
from cracking
at high temperatures.
the correct mixture is two parts
clay to one part husk.
once the mixer thoroughly
blends the materials,
it extrudes the resulting
compound in a thick ribbon,
ready for the next
phase of production.
a worker rolls the clay
in a small quantity
of a third material
also derived from rice.
this is rice husk ash.
and adding it to the clay
helps prevent mold growth.
a craftsman places
the clay inside
a specially shaped mold,
which sits on a potter's wheel.
as the wheel turns the mold,
the craftsman works
with a metal arm
and handheld tools to spread
and shape the clay.
he then removes
the fully formed clay pot.
having marked out
three locations
on the rim of the pot,
a craftsman now adds some husk
ask to a handheld mold
to prevent sticking.
he then packs the mold with clay
before pressing it
into the pot's rim
and inner surface.
he smoothes the clay
around them,
integrating them into the pot.
these three elements
will form raised supports
for cooking pots,
woks and kettles.
at this stage, the pot
has air dried enough
to safely remove it
from the mold.
the craftsman now uses
a handheld tool to define
and finish the edges
of the rim and supports.
he then uses a metal,
rectangular template to mark
and cut out a small vent for air
intake at the base of the pot.
an artisan prepares
a small disk of clay
for a different stage
of production.
he uses a cylindrical metal tool
to cut a series
of 62 holes in the disk,
creating a honeycomb pattern
that will allow
the passage of air.
he uses a small
beveled wooden tool
to help smooth
the edges of the holes.
when the pots
are fully formed,
workers transfer them
to the walk-in oven.
once there are
a total of 500 pots
and honeycombs inside,
it's time to fire up the oven.
the pots spend 8 hours
in the oven at nearly
2,200 degrees fahrenheit.
the firing process gives
the gray clay a reddish tinge.
to assemble the barbecues,
a worker starts by creating
a layer of rice husk
between the clay pot
and the zinc bucket.
this insulates the metal
from the barbecue's heat.
he cuts out the rectangular vent
that will allow air
to flow into the bottom
of the barbecue
and help fuel the fire.
he adds soil to the gap
between the pot
and the bucket to further
insulate the exterior
metal from the interior heat.
the craftsman now seals
all the gaps in the barbecue
with mortar in order
to keep the husk
and soil firmly in place.
the honeycomb disk
fits perfectly
into the bottom of the pot.
it will hold charcoal up
above the vent hole,
allowing air to flow up
through it,
fueling the fire,
while permitting ash to fall
down into the cavity below.
a worker carefully mortars
the disk in place.
this barbecue
is a low-tech
but highly effective
outdoor stove,
useful whenever it's too hot
to cook inside.
♪♪
narrator:
if you're scuba diving,
free diving or snorkeling,
you need a mask to maintain
a layer of air
between your eyes and the water.
without that barrier,
your eyes can't focus
under water.
fins are another diving
must-have
to let you push away more water
when you kick
and give you
stronger propulsion.
diving fins consist of
a foot pocket and a blade.
the blade has side arms
running down its length.
these strengthen the blade
and amplify the forward
thrust a kicking foot generates.
the parts are made
of thermoplastic.
to make the fin blade,
the manufacturers
mix clear thermoplastic granules
with a specific portion
of color dye granules
and drop them into the feed tank
of an injection molding machine.
the factory uses certain
types of thermoplastic
when making fins
with a stiff blade
and other types when making
more flexible models.
the machine heats the granules
until they melt then injects
the liquefied thermoplastic
into a blade-shaped mold.
the plastic quickly
cools and solidifies.
then the mold opens.
and extractors eject the blade.
a robot grasps the blade
with suction and removes
it from the mold.
as the robot lifts
the blade out of the machine,
the mold closes again
to receive another injection
to make the next blade.
the robot deposits
the blade onto a conveyer belt
which transports it
through a cold-air tunnel.
this cools
the thermoplastic enough
to enable the upcoming
component materials
to properly adhere to the blade.
the next robot picks up
the cooled blade
and moves it to another
injection molding machine,
which performs a process known
as over printing,
molding on additional parts
until the fin is completed.
the robot first
removes the previous
completed fin fresh out
of the over
printing injection mold.
this machine melted
down granules
of thermoplastic rubber,
a more flexible material,
and simultaneously injection
molded the side arms
and the foot pocket
onto the blade.
once the robot pulls off
this completed fin,
it loads the new blade
into the mold.
as the mold closes
for the next injection,
the robot deposits the finished
fin into a conveyer belt.
the over printing
process also applied
the manufacturer's name
and some decorative elements.
by changing the molds
on the injection machines
and using different
types and colors
of thermoplastic materials,
the factory produces
a wide range of fin models.
a diving mask is made up
of a flexible silicone
facial skirt attached
to a rigid frame
with lenses.
the skirt, which this injection
molding machine produces
from liquid silicone,
seals the frame to the face,
preventing water infiltration.
while thermoplastic must be
melted before injection,
then cooled to
a solid state,
silicone must be
injected combined
with a hardening agent
then heated to a solid state.
the frame is made
the same way as the fins
but using a more rigid
type of thermoplastic.
a worker begins
assembling the mask
by threading
a silicone head strap
through the frame's buckles.
they attach the silicone skirt,
first pressing the nose portion
into the bridge of the frame.
then the worker
connects the eye area.
the frame is designed
to enable the silicone skirt
to slot right in.
next, the lenses, which are
made of tempered glass.
while they're highly resistant,
they don't withstand
frontal impact.
so the diver shouldn't plunge
into the water face first.
the final step
is to clip in
rigid thermoplastic
lens retainers
and clamp each one securely
to the lens and frame.
the mask is now ready
for a final inspection
to make sure no water will seep
in when you wear it.
just like fins,
there's a wide range
of diving mask models
designed to see
through different
types of underwater exploration.