--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: after water,
tea is the most consumed
beverage in the world.
the different types
are determined by
the degree to which
the producer
lets the harvested leaves
oxidize
before drying them.
green tea, for example,
is barely fermented,
whereas black tea
is greatly fermented.
oolong falls
somewhere in between.
in chinese,
oolong means "black dragon."
it's a semi-oxidized tea
fermented more than green tea,
yet less than black tea.
its taste, aroma, and color,
from light yellow to dark red,
vary according to how
the tea leaves are processed.
this amber oolong
produced in thailand
has a rich, smooth
roasted taste.
like most teas,
oolong is made from
the leaves of
a flowering plant species
called camellia sinensis.
harvest time is during
the plant's peak growing
season,
which, in thailand,
is from may to november.
workers handpick
what's known as the flush,
a grouping of
two young leaves and a bud,
which grows
out the top of the plant.
at this time of year,
the plant produces a new flush
every 7 to 15 days.
an experienced tea master
directs
every phase of the processing,
the first step of which
is called solar withering.
workers bring the leaves
into a glass-roofed building,
then spread them out in the
sun
for 15 to 20 minutes.
this kick-starts the
oxidization fermentation
process
as the chlorophyll enzymes
inside the wilting leaves
start breaking down.
at the same time, the moisture
inside begins evaporating.
workers
keep moving the leaves around
to ensure
a thorough exposure to the
sun.
then they gather up the leaves
for step two --
indoor withering.
the leaves lie on bamboo trays
for six to eight hours,
where, gently stirred
every two hours,
they oxidize further.
step three -- disruption.
the leaves go into
a rotating drum.
as they tumble,
they bruise and tear.
this breaks down
the cell structures,
enabling oxygen
to penetrate deep inside,
greatly accelerating
fermentation.
this also releases
the leaf juices,
which help draw out
the taste of the tea.
when the tea master determines
the leaves
have sufficiently oxidized,
they stop the oxidation
process
by tumbling the leaves
in a gas-heated dryer
for 10 to 15 minutes.
this fourth step of the
process
is called fixation
because it fixes the
oxidization
at the desired level,
which can be anywhere from
8% to 85%,
depending on the
variety of oolong in
production.
this is the most critical
part of the process
because it determines the
tea's
taste, aroma, and color.
the next step forms the
tea leaves into tiny pellets.
first, workers shake the
leaves
on a sieve
to filter out
the dust-like particles.
then they bag the leaves
in a cotton cloth
and place them
first in a kneading machine,
then afterward
in a rolling press.
kneading and rolling the bag
twists the leaves inside
into tiny pellets.
forming these pellet shapes
intensifies
the flavor of the tea,
and, when the tea is
steeped in hot water,
releases that flavor slowly.
they repeat the sieving,
kneading, and rolling cycle
up to 35 times
until the tea master
is satisfied with the result.
then and only then
does the final step begin --
firing.
they transfer the tea
to an oven,
in which it undergoes
three drying cycles
of 20 minutes each
at a temperature of
approximately
210 degrees fahrenheit.
this dries the damp tea,
reducing the moisture content
to the target level of
less than 5%.
the firing
also brings out the fragrance.
the traditional way to
brew oolong is in a clay
teapot,
using about
2 teaspoons of tea per cup.
ideally, the water should be
190 to 210 degrees fahrenheit.
steeping time
is from 3 to 10 minutes,
and you can brew the same
leaves
up to five times.
narrator: originally crafted
from stone by the greeks,
finials are still on top.
perched on peaks and gables,
these roof ornaments
are a crowning touch
to any structure.
they can make
even an ordinary home
look a little more grand,
and after all,
every home is someone's
castle.
on many structures,
finials still rule the roof
and give people
a reason to look up.
the design of these
roof ornaments usually
reflects
the style of the building
and the owner's taste.
they're often custom made
for the client
and entirely hand crafted.
to make a copper finial,
the artisan first
draws the design on paper.
like many finials,
this one will have a point,
a central orb,
and skirting.
once the design has been
approved by the client,
he draws larger versions of it
onto poster board.
they'll serve as templates
for the copper parts.
here, he draws the patterns
for the elaborate scroll work.
to execute the design,
he gets creative.
he uses copper refrigerator
tubing to make the scrollwork.
it's malleable
and can easily be shaped.
he positions a pipe cutter
device at the cut line.
the device grips the tubing,
but can still be turned
to cut the pipe cleanly
at the desired location.
he flattens one end
with a sledgehammer
so it can be
tucked into a groove
in this large pvc plumbing
pipe.
with the end secured,
he physically
bends the copper tubing
around this pipe
to give it
the desired curvature.
he compares the curvature
to that of the pattern
and makes adjustments.
he continues shaping the pipe,
now using
only the scrollwork pattern
as a guide.
he'll make several of
these copper scrollwork parts
for one roof ornament.
with an etching tool,
he now traces
the shape
of the skirting pattern
onto copper roof sheeting.
he cuts reference points
for the bends
and removes the pattern.
he then extends the bend lines
with the etching tool.
he now cuts out
the skirting part
with standard hand shears
following the etched outline.
one last trim along the edge,
and the skirting is ready for
the sheet metal bending
machine.
he clamps it into place
and pulls a handle
to apply hydraulic pressure
and bend the part
along the etched lines.
he repositions the skirting
and bends it
at the next
etched marking point.
he continues until there are
six evenly spaced folds
in the copper.
this transforms it into
a hexagonal pyramid.
to seal it where the ends
meet,
he prepares the surface.
he applies an acid called flux
to clean the copper.
he ignites the torch
and melts solder into the
seam.
the solder
is half-lead and half-tin
and provides a good seal.
he sands the soldered seam
against a fine, abrasive belt
to blend it with the copper.
the finial skirting
is now complete.
he now drills holes
into a hollow copper orb.
he slides the orb onto
a long copper spike
that's been installed
in the base.
he cleans the copper
where the two parts meet
and solders them together.
he adds a second smaller orb
and the extravagant
scrollwork.
he now solders the spiked cap
to the finial.
this adds height and drama
to the rooftop ornament.
this finial is now complete
and ready for high places.
making one has truly been
a pinnacle achievement.
narrator: artificial flowers
have been used as decorations
for hundreds of years.
initially,
silk flowers made in china
were displayed in homes
and not commercially sold.
as far back as the 12th
century,
italian flower makers using
dye-colored silkworm cocoons
were the first to sell
their floral arrangements.
modern imitations of
natural flowering plants
are endless in variety,
stunning in color,
with realism so impressive,
they can look and feel like
the real thing.
since the '70s, most are
made of polyester fabrics.
a worker
places an iron cutter blade
on top of non-woven polyester
and then applies several tons
of hydraulic pressure
to complete the cuts.
the result is
20 layers of flower petals.
the worker wraps
piles of 100 petals
in elastic bands
and sets them aside.
another worker places petals
into a heated mold
to give the fabric texture.
using a glue gun,
a worker completes
the flower's petal structure
by assembling
two different shapes
of non-woven polyester petals.
this is part of the flower
head.
in the coloring department,
a worker paints the
pieces of non-woven polyester
using watercolor.
she paints
the edges of the flower heads
in bundles of 100 at a time.
the painted flower heads
go into a microwave
for two to five minutes.
the dried flower heads
now undergo silk screening
one at a time
using acrylic paint.
customers can choose among
more than 50 different
color patterns.
the flower heads
have been pressed
to simulate natural curving.
using a glue gun,
a worker
connects the flower head
to the petals of
this phalaenopsis orchid.
the goal is not only to
make the flowers
look as real as possible.
it's also to make them
feel as real as possible,
which takes us to
the next stage.
an employee
puts two flowers together...
...lines them up,
then adds a stick,
which will be held
in the next part of the
process.
she encircles them tightly
with an elastic band.
another worker
dips the two flowers in
polymer,
which helps make them
feel real to the touch.
she spins the flowers to
remove
as much excess polymer
as possible.
workers then brush
excess polymer from the
petals.
a worker
attaches flower buds to the
stem
using green floral tape.
she attaches
the petals and flower head
and continues to wrap the stem
in floral tape
until the entire length
is covered.
to make the leaves
feel real to the touch,
a worker dips them in polymer
and wipes off any excess
with her fingers.
after one hour of drying,
the worker
dips the same leaves
in green polymer.
again, she removes any excess
and sets the leaves aside
for another hour of drying.
once they're dry, another
worker
gives the leaves
a final coat of polymer paint.
she removes the excess
and sets the leaves aside
for yet another hour of
drying.
all the drying is done
at room temperature.
now coated with
several layers of polymer,
the leaves stick to each
other.
to fix that, a worker applies
a thin coating of talcum
powder
with a sponge.
the coating solves
the problem of sticky leaves.
with its many components
fully assembled,
this finished flower is
a rather dazzling recreation
of the cymbidium orchid.
shipping these flowers
requires careful packaging.
they wrap the glass vase
in clear plastic...
...and place it securely
inside a polystyrene base.
the flower is lowered
into the box upside down.
the base is snug enough
to keep the flower from
moving inside the box,
which the worker then
seals shut for shipping.
authentic looking and feeling,
these striking flowers are
sure to make any decor
blossom.
narrator:
higher-end cars typically co
rather than basic steel wheels
covered with a hubcap.
called mag wheels, because
when they first came out,
they were made of
an alloy of magnesium.
today's alloy wheels are made
of
an aluminum alloy,
which is far more durable.
aluminum alloy wheels
are not only
more attractive than
standard wheels.
they're also
a fraction of the weight,
and therefore
require less energy to rotate.
this contributes to
greater fuel efficiency
as well as better handling,
acceleration, and braking.
manufacturing them begins with
high-grade aluminum alloy
containing 97% aluminum.
a furnace heats the ingots to
over 1,300 degrees fahrenheit.
they liquify
in about 25 minutes.
the molten aluminum
then flows directly to a mixer
in which they inject argon
gas,
which enables them to
remove the hydrogen.
this increases the density,
making the aluminum
less porous when solidified.
after adding
powdered titanium, magnesium,
and other metallic elements to
further strengthen the
aluminum,
they blend in flux,
a chemical which
draws aluminum oxide
to the surface.
they skim off this impurity
along with the flux,
and the liquid aluminum
is ready for casting.
the wheel mold is made of
high-strength steel.
it's actually
a set of three molds --
the upper mold, which forms
the inside face of the wheel,
the 4-part side mold,
which forms the wheel's edge,
and the lower mold,
which forms the outer face.
that's the side with the
design,
so this is
the most intricate mold.
it takes three to four weeks
to produce a mold.
computer simulations check
the flow and temperature
of the liquid aluminum,
factors critical for
preventing casting defects.
the casting machine
is designed to
fill the mold from the bottom
by pressurized injection.
injecting upward
through the bottom,
rather than pouring downward
into the top,
reduces the risk of air
bubbles,
which cause defects.
right before casting,
the molten metal
flows through a filter sheet
made of
high-temperature-resistant
ceramic.
this traps
additional aluminum oxide.
once cast, the aluminum takes
about 7 to 10 minutes
to solidify.
then the mold
automatically opens,
releasing the newly cast
wheel.
workers
submerge it in lukewarm water
for a few minutes.
this cools it down enough
to be handled.
the wheel undergoes
a complex heat treatment
process
that takes 12 hours
from start to finish.
first, they heat the wheel
to 900 degrees fahrenheit.
this rearranges
the molecular structure,
strengthening the metal.
next, what's known as
quenching.
they submerge the wheel in
80-degree water for 30
seconds.
this locks in that new
strength.
then they reheat the wheel,
this time
to 180 degrees for nine hours
to further stabilize the
metal.
the wheel doesn't come out of
the mold in perfect condition.
the edges are rough, due to
some excess metal
that has to be trimmed off.
so they mount the wheel
on a computer-guided lathe.
it precision-machines the
sides,
refining them to
within 0.05 millimeters
of the measurements specified
in the technical drawings.
as for the more intricate
base of the wheel,
a worker manually
trims the edges with a blade.
the shape now finalized,
it's time to test the wheel
to make sure it's airtight.
while pumping air
into the wheel,
they submerge it in water.
should any air bubbles appear,
it would mean
there's a pinhole in the metal
or some shrinkage,
in which case,
the wheel would fail
inspection.
no air bubbles.
the wheel proceeds to
the automated painting line.
first, a base coat,
then a coat of color,
which can be anything from
classic silver or black
to a flashier shade.
then a clear coat to protect
the paint and prevent
corrosion.
from every 1,500 or so wheels,
the factory
randomly selects two or three
to test for
performance and wear.
workers install
the decorative cap
that covers the center hub.
it typically bears the
specific
brand's logo.
then a final
cosmetic inspection
to make sure
these aluminum alloy wheels
look as good as they perform.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...