--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: indycars are open-cockpit race cars
that compete in the annual indianapolis 500 race
in the u.s.
the cars are entirely custom-built.
even the driver's seat is specially contoured
to the driver's body shape
and position in which he or she sits
most comfortably in the car.
the custom-made driver's seat in an indycar
is made of fire-resistant fabric over impact-absorbing foam.
it has openings
at the shoulder, lap, and legs
for the safety harness.
to make the seat, they first have to produce a template,
which is, in itself, a two-day process.
technicians prepare,
then pour an adhesive into a bag full of foam beads.
the adhesive contains resin and a hardener.
once the adhesive seeps in,
they squeeze out the air and tie the bag closed.
they knead the bag to spread the adhesive
over all the foam beads inside.
next, laying the bag flat,
they spread the adhesive-saturated beads
in an even layer.
then they install a valve...
attach it to a vacuum pump,
and suction out most of the remaining air.
they shape a cavity in the middle to fit the driver's body.
once they vacuumed out enough air to make the bag tight enough
to hold the shape of this cavity...
...they place it in the race car's cockpit,
pressing the foam beads as snugly as possible
into all the nooks and crannies.
this ensures
the car seat will fit properly
and not shift under the driver.
the driver now has to sit in the car
so they can custom-contour the template
to his body in the driving position.
once he's settled comfortably
with hips and shoulders square
and wearing his helmet,
they begin taking measurements,
starting with the height of his head, critical for aerodynamics,
and of his sight line over
the hood, critical for safety.
both measurements must conform
with the racing association's strict regulations.
they also measure the distance
between his chest and the steering wheel
and ensure
there's adequate leg clearance
to enter and exit the cockpit.
the driver sits down, gets out, gets back in
several times
as the technicians measure and make adjustments.
the entire process takes about 40 minutes.
when it's all done, they run the vacuum for another four hours
and let the foam cure overnight.
the next morning,
they use a hot knife to melt a line through the foam
and dislodge the template from the cockpit.
the driver returns for a final two- to three-hour sitting,
during which the techs trim the foam as closely as possible
to his body contour.
the shape now finalized, they cover the entire surface
with cloth adhesive tape and a matte finish.
this creates a non-reflective background
suitable for laser scanning.
onto this dull surface,
they adhere positioning targets --
reflective dots spaced four inches apart
that create a grid pattern over the entire template.
the 3-d laser scanner
reads these reflective dots...
...that a computer translates into a 3-d image.
specialized software then converts this image
into a technical drawing,
which guides an automated router
to cut the seat parts out of polypropylene foam.
this precision-cutting process takes four to six hours.
the router cuts out six to eight sections,
which technicians then carefully glue together
into the full seat.
they cover the finished seat in fire-retardant material,
first applying the fabric with spray adhesive,
then trimming it to the shape of the seat.
this foam is quite elastic,
so it absorbs impact and protects the driver.
at the same time, it has memory,
so after a blow, it regains its driver-customized shape.
narrator: people have always been enchanted
by the beauty of flowers.
it's not surprising that these jewels of nature,
often in artificial form,
are used in decorative objects and arts and crafts projects.
paper flowers last forever,
and you don't have to remember to water them.
these flowers are made of saa paper.
the saa tree is a variety of mulberry
that grows abundantly across southeast asia.
for more than 700 years,
villagers in northern thailand
have been using saa bark to make paper.
the paper is used for crafting items
such as umbrellas, fans, and flowers.
they soak the dried bark in water overnight
to begin softening it up,
boil it over a wood fire for four hours,
then soak it again overnight.
all of this softens the bark into fibrous pulp.
next, they soak the pulp overnight
in hydrogen peroxide to whiten it,
then they rinse off the bleach,
which would interfere with the dying process later on.
workers discard any discolored pieces.
the goal is to make each sheet of paper evenly white
so that it absorbs colored dye uniformly.
now they load the pulp into a mill,
which grinds it up and mixes it with water.
this process, which takes about half an hour,
transforms the pieces into soft,
fluffy, and very soggy fibers.
what was once tree bark
is now ready to be processed into paper.
every single sheet
is handcrafted on fine mesh screens.
they submerge a screen in water,
then drop in roughly 15 ounces of fibers.
they manually stir the water to spread the fibers
in a thin layer across the screen.
they slowly lift the screen out of the water
and press the surface by hand to smooth it out.
the screen then stands in the sun for three to four hours,
flipped a few times
until the fiber's dry into a solid sheet of paper.
to color the paper,
they fill a basin with hot water and add a chemical dye.
they test the color,
and if it's just right, they submerge the sheet.
the sheet absorbs the dye instantly
in a consistent shade thanks to the uniformly white base color.
they hang the sheet outside to dry in the sun.
in three to four hours, the paper is ready to bloom.
they cut out flower shapes with a hand-operated press
that stamps a sharp metal dye through the sheet of paper.
each shape will be a layer of petals in a flower.
there are dyes in various shapes and sizes.
however, the petals they produce are flat --
not very lifelike --
so workers place one petal at
a time on a flower-shaped mold
and stamp it with a hot press.
this permanently shapes the petals
to the contour of the mold
almost the same way a hot iron presses clothes.
then it's assembly time.
to make a rose, they mount a white ball made of foam,
or flower and glue,
onto the end of a three-inch-long wire.
they fold the inner petals over the ball
and pinch them together to
create the center of the rose.
then they thread four to five petal layers of the same size
on the wire,
bending and pinching those, as well, to form the rose shape.
once the petals are complete,
they finish off with a green paper leaf at the base.
to make a daisy, they take a flat flower
and glue a brown paper dot in the middle.
then they glue another flat flower beneath it
and a leaf base beneath that.
to make another type of rose,
they gently twist the tips of the petals.
even though they're made from trees,
these artificial flowers are environmentally friendly.
the saa's severed branches and stripped bark grow back quickly,
providing a renewable supply of raw material
for crafting blooming paper bouquets.
narrator: weather-wise, these are turbulent times.
there are more storms and heat waves,
and that means an increased likelihood of power outages.
a standby generator
supplies emergency electricity
within seconds of an outage
so a homeowner can
ride out the storm in comfort.
in today's high-tech world,
staying plugged in
has never been more important.
wired to a home's electrical system,
a standby generator automatically powers up
in the event of an outage.
it assumes the electrical load
until the public-utilities system comes back online.
with your own standby generator,
a power outage is never a crisis.
production starts with a stator.
it's the stationary core of the alternator --
the part that converts energy
from the motor to electricity.
a press compacts 100 or more laminated steel disks
to create the stator core.
machinery unwinds steel banding and wraps it around the stack
to hold the core layers together.
machinery lifts the stator core out of the assembly device
and transfers it to the next station.
here, an automated system
insulates the numerous slots in the core.
as the core turns, a machine cuts, forms, and inserts
synthetic insulating fabric into each slot.
meanwhile, at another station,
an automated system winds copper wire onto a mandrel.
the slots in the mandrel are the same size
as the insulated slots in the core.
this configures the copper windings to fit the core slots.
but first, a technician slides the copper coils
onto a threading tool.
this tool maintains
the configuration of the coils
to prepare them for installation in the stator core.
they wind more bundles of copper wire.
once all the windings have been correctly arranged
on the threading tool,
the technician is ready to transfer them
to the stator core.
he places the stator on top of the threading tool
and activates a hydraulic device
that pushes the wires up through the tool
and into the slots of the stator core.
the device retracts, and he removes the stator.
the copper wires transform the stator into an electromagnet,
which is critical for electrical generation.
he trims the ends of the wires
and sets the leftovers aside for recycling.
he slides insulating sleeves onto the ends.
then it's into the lacing machine.
this machine crochets a string wrap around the bundles
to hold the wires together.
it also pulls in any loose strands
to keep them from snagging on generator components.
with the wiring precisely wound and wrapped,
this important generator component
is ready for the finishing touch --
a clear varnish.
the lid closes on the tank, and a vacuum pulls air out.
the tank then fills with clear varnish to coat the stators.
the varnish fills in any gaps in the windings.
they transfer the stators to an oven and bake on the varnish.
once hardened, the varnish
insulates the entire assembly.
the next technician
connects the stator lead wires
to a testing machine.
the machine applies high-voltage pulses to the wire windings
and monitors the output
for anything that could cause generator failure.
the stator passes the test.
a technician now positions
an outer casing and an end cap
on top of the stator,
followed by a steel pressing plate.
a hydraulic arm then provides the muscle power needed
to fit the casing and cap snugly to the stator.
coming up next,
the generator stator joins the rotor and engine,
and the result is purely electric.
narrator: the average home may contain
over 100 electrical appliances and devices.
when there's a power blackout, everything shuts down.
a standby generator restores electricity in seconds
to keep the refrigerator running and the heat on.
in an extended power outage, a generator can be a life saver.
to produce the alternator's rotating part, the rotor,
the technician stacks laminated steel disks
to the same height as the stator core.
he lubricates the opening in the center of the disks.
he inserts a shaft,
and a press pushes it into the stack
to complete the installation.
powered by the generator engine,
the shaft will spin the rotor.
the technician installs steel rods
to maintain the disks' alignment
and then removes the rotor from the assembly device.
he fits more rods to it on a slight angle.
they'll act as conductors
and stabilize
the rotor's electrical output.
he slides aluminum caps onto both ends of the rotor.
then it's over to an automated welder.
the machine grips the rotor at both ends
and slowly turns it
as a robot welds both caps to the rotor body.
welded in place, the caps secure the aluminum rods.
the aluminum solder used in the weld
is conductive and will create an electrical connection.
the technician unclamps the
rotor from the welding machine
and then tucks insulation into slots on the sides.
the rotor then goes for a spin
in a machine that winds bands of copper wire
around the insulated sections.
these wires will act as electromagnets
and help produce electrical current.
they tie string around the wire,
add bearings and a copper collector ring,
and bake an insulating varnish onto the entire rotor.
they're now ready to assemble the standby generator.
using a lift, the technician lowers the engine into position.
he joins the rotor shaft to the engine crankshaft.
to secure the assembly, he drives a very long bolt
through the rotor to the crankshaft
and tightens it to a specific torque.
next up is the stator.
it will provide a magnetic field
to advance the flow of electrons in the rotor.
the technician slides the stator onto the rotor.
a steel end bracket is next.
it aligns the rotor and the stator.
he forces the bracket into place.
to secure the alignment, he installs four long bolts
from the end bracket to the engine-adapter plate.
he anchors the stator and rotor to the generator base
and adds special rubber mounts under the supports
to buffer vibrations.
he attaches a motorized carbon brush
to copper rings on the rotor shaft.
the brush will collect electricity from the shaft
and transfer it to the generator controller.
he secures it to the end bracket with screws.
he connects the wiring harness
that moves electricity from the brush to the controller.
he links the other end of the harness to the engine.
he plugs in a sensor to monitor oil pressure
and makes all the other electrical connections.
next up is a panel through which he runs some of the wiring.
it acts as a separator to prevent entanglements
and also supports the fuel regulator.
other parts include a muffler to help dampen engine noise
and a controller that converts generated power
to the correct voltage.
the assembly of this
standby generator is complete.
the technician fuels up
and runs it first at partial capacity,
then to the max.
the test confirms there's no
wavering in electrical output.
once encased
in a neutral-colored corrosion-resistant shell,
the standby generator blends into the background,
but in a power outage,
its contribution will definitely be noticed.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...