--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
lace began as a fringe fabric.
back in the middle ages,
it was handcrafted by european
women to trim fashion finery.
the ladies' fingers got a
break
with the advent of lace-making
equipment in the 19th century.
with mass production,
lace moved from the fringe
to the mainstream.
in the material world,
lace used to be a luxury,
handcrafted for decorative
rather than practical reasons.
machines
now produce lace quickly,
and you don't have to be
wealthy
to afford it.
to manufacture lace,
hundreds of nylon
and polyester threads
unwind simultaneously
into a separator.
it arranges the threads in a
configuration for
manufacturing
and keeps them from tangling
as they move forward.
to maintain the formation,
the the threads pass through
a comb-like apparatus.
still
in that neat configuration,
the threads
wind around a large spool.
this spool is
known as a ground beam
because the threads on it
will be used
for the lace's ground, or
mesh.
these smaller spools supply
the threads for the pattern.
they all unwind
into the lace-making machine,
which will interweave them to
create a pattern on the
ground.
here's how it happens.
a long thick card
with holes punched into it
defines the pattern
and guides
a system of hooks and needles.
it's called a jacquard card,
and the technology has been
around for two centuries
and was actually the
inspiration
for computer technology.
each hole on the card
corresponds to one hook,
and the hooks are
attached to these guide bars.
if the hook encounters
a hole in the jacquard card,
it loops a thread,
and if it encounters
the solid card, it stops.
the guide bars
shuffle back and forth
to move the hooks
in concert with needles
and weave the design
on the ground.
this is the lace-weaving
action
in slow motion.
the punch-card system
allows for the same pattern
to be woven repeatedly
without error.
it's all
perfectly choreographed,
and this complex lace design
comes together quickly
with no snarls.
the result
is a thing of beauty --
an intricate floral pattern
on a mesh background.
the lace rolls by inspectors,
who scrutinize the needlework
for flaws.
it then heads into a station
with high-speed knives.
they cut the loose threads
that
run between the floral
patterns
on the front of the lace.
a worker finishes the job
by hand,
removing what the knives miss.
here you can see the
difference
the trimming makes.
the mesh between the
needlework
is now completely transparent.
they mend the lace when
needed,
and then it's into a dying
machine to add some color.
after rinsing,
the now bright-yellow lace
travels over bars under
tension
to wring out the water.
the lace, still damp,
lands and accumulates in a
bin,
which they wheel over
to a finishing machine.
the finishing machine
is equipped with rollers.
the first ones
remove the curl from the lace.
the others take it
through a chemical bath
for a treatment
that both softens the lace
and prevents shrinkage.
a trip through a dryer removes
the water from the fabric
and cures
the finishing chemicals.
now complete, the lace exits
onto a network of rollers.
the final one
swings the fabric to and fro
so that it lands neatly folded
for transfer
to the packaging line.
heavy industrial machinery
has produced this delicate
lace
in a matter of minutes.
they roll it and wrap it,
and it's on its way to the
fabric store or another
factory.
no ordinary textile,
the factory-made lace will add
beauty to things of necessity
like curtains,
a tablecloth, or a dress.
its sheer good looks
will add visual appeal
to these ordinary items.
narrator: it's important
that the frame around a
painting
be stylistically consistent
with the period in which
the artist created the work.
when you're dealing with a
centuries-old painting,
however,
the original frame
has often been replaced
with a newer one.
the solution is commissioning
an historically accurate
antique replica.
when a painting's original
frame
is lost,
a specialist can produce
an exact replica
or a historically accurate
alternative.
basswood is the wood of choice
because it's relatively soft
and even-grained.
first, they saw the length
required for the frame.
then they plane the sides
to smooth the rough edges.
next, they saw the piece
to the required dimensions.
once pieces for all four sides
of the frame are cut,
workers set up a machine
called a molding planer.
as its contoured steel blade
spins,
they run each piece against
it,
carving the blade's profile
into the wood.
the workshop
has thousand of blades,
each with a different profile.
they all began
as a flat bar of steel,
which the shop milled to shape
following a profile drawing.
once each side is contoured,
workers saw the ends
at 45-degree angles...
...then cut a slot in each
one.
they spread glue in the slot
and over the entire surface,
then insert a beechwood
biscuit.
the biscuit goes in
just halfway.
they insert the other half
into the glued slot
of the adjoining frame piece.
once the glue dries,
the master carver gets to
work.
with a pencil,
he draws the frame's design
onto tracing paper,
then lays the paper
upside down on the replica
and retraces the design,
which transfers it in graphite
onto the frame surface.
then he turns to his arsenal
of 40-plus chisels
and begins carving out
the design.
each chisel has
a different shape and sized
tip
and therefore makes
a very specific type of cut.
he first cuts straight down
along the outline
to sever the wood grain.
this prevents
the angled cuts, which follow,
from splitting the wood
beyond the outline.
interchanging chisels,
he repeatedly removes
small chunks of wood
until the design emerges.
he clears away the wood chips
with a wire brush.
now the master gilder
takes over,
brushing on
up to 20 coats of gesso --
a traditional mixture of
water,
calcium carbonate,
and a very flexible glue
made from rabbit skin.
flexibility prevents cracking
when the wood
expands and contracts.
he brushes on four coats
of another traditional mixture
called bole.
the ingredients --
ultra-fine particle clay,
water,
and, again, rabbit-skin glue.
bole provides background
colors.
it also provides a cushion
between the gesso layer
and the gold leaf.
next, a coat of what's called
gilder's liquor --
a combination of water,
alcohol,
and either gelatin
or rabbit-skin glue.
then he cuts
a piece of gold leaf --
a sheet of genuine gold a mere
1/10,000 of a millimeter
thick.
he applies it with a fine
brush
made of squirrel hair,
which he has lightly oiled.
as soon as he taps the frame,
the water in the gilder's
liquor
grabs the gold leaf,
pulling it away from the oil,
adhering it to the bristles.
this is the tricky part,
because too much oil
on the brush
or too little water
in the gilder's liquor
can hinder
this delicate transfer.
next, the master gilder rubs
select areas
with a polished agate,
a natural stone.
this burnishing process
compresses the gold leaf,
making it smooth and shiny.
now he'll make the frame
look old.
he removes some gold
from the high points
to create
the appearance of wear.
then he applies a tinted glaze
to simulate patina --
natural darkening
that develops over time
due to the accumulation
of airborne dust and dirt.
he works in the glaze
with a brush
to distribute it strategically
so that the fake patina
looks perfectly natural.
for this frame,
he uses 23-karat gold leaf.
gilders will also use 6-, 12-,
14, 18-, and 22-karat leaf
to achieve
different shades of gold.
the higher the karat,
the yellower the color,
due to the greater proportion
of gold in the composition
and lesser proportion
of copper and silver alloys.
narrator:
orchids are a standout.
their exquisite beauty
even caused a frenzy
in the mid-19th century
when wealthy british
collectors
hired orchid hunters
to search the world
for new species.
today, the fascination
with orchids continues,
and cultivating them
is a growing industry.
in thailand, orchids grow
wild,
but the wild orchids
have been tamed.
they've been
hybridized and domesticated
to satisfy a global demand
for this fantastic flower.
at this farm, cultivation
starts with bud cuttings,
mixed with nutrients and water
in glass bottle.
the bottle provides
a germ-free growing
environment,
keeping the cuttings
disease-free
as they grow into baby
orchids.
this takes a year or more.
when the plants have developed
a strong root system,
they're ready to come out
into the world.
the worker deposits the baby
orchids in a tub of clean
water
and swishes each one around to
give their roots a good rinse.
she transfers the baby orchids
to a perforated plastic
basket.
a wad of coconut fiber
soaked in water
provides
the next growing environment.
the worker places
the roots of each baby plant
in one of the wads.
she wraps the fiber snuggly
and ties the wad.
she places the fiber-wrapped
orchids in growing cells.
the team waters and fertilizes
them for four to six months.
the orchids grow to midsize,
and the plant's root system
flourishes.
the plants are now ready
for the next phase of growth.
they transfer the mid-sized
orchids to coconut husks.
the husks act as a kind of
plant
pot and growing media in one.
they absorb water to provide
a constant supply to the
plants.
the plants grow on the husks.
no soil is needed.
in nature, orchids flourish
on tree bark or cracks in
rocks,
and coconut husks
are the next best thing.
overhead, a nylon-fabric roof
diffuses sunlight
to simulate conditions
found in a shady rainforest.
too much light and
the heat would harm the
plants.
gardeners regularly observe
the growth of the orchids.
they're on the lookout
for disease or other problems.
not all of the plants
will thrive.
they'll lose
about 10% of the crop.
they fertilize and water
the orchids
over a period of several
months.
many of the plants are
hybrids,
created by crossing species to
achieve a certain color or
shape
or to improve the plant's
vigor.
with thousands of species
available in nature,
the potential combinations
are never-ending,
and the results
are always stunning.
with the orchids in full
bloom,
it's time for the harvest.
workers cut the orchids
at the base of the stems,
with an eye to making them
approximately the same length.
in the packing room, they
tweak
the length of the stems
until each bunch
is perfectly uniform.
they make this final cut
on an angle.
this creates a larger surface
for absorbing water
so the orchid
will stay fresh longer.
they sort the flowers
by the size of the bloom.
they insert the stems
in plastic capsules
that contain
a flower-food and water
mixture.
this should maintain
the orchids' freshness
during shipping.
it's time to wrap up
each stunning display.
the plastic sleeve will
preserve
them on the journey ahead.
this particular orchid is a
hybrid species known as
mokara.
extremely desirable,
cut mokara orchids should
bloom
for up to three weeks.
en route to the airport
in a climate-controlled truck,
they'll soon be
on an international flight.
thai orchids
are sold around the world.
chances are they'll end up
at the center of a big event
in someone's life,
and whether
it's a wedding or a birthday,
these stunning orchids will
add
something special to the
party.
narrator: the key part
of a wheel is its hub,
the central point to which
all the spokes attach.
it's comprised of a body
which receives the spokes
and houses an axle and
bearings.
if the wheel has a gear
system,
then those gears and a clutch
are also integrated
into the hub.
this is the only
commercially available
unicycle
with a gearing system.
located on the wheel hub,
it enables the rider
to push a button
to shift from regular gear
into high gear
and reach 25 miles per hour --
twice the speed
of a regular unicycle.
the geared wheel hub contains
six identical small gears,
rotating
around a large central gear.
the central one
is called the sun wheel
and the small ones,
planetary gears,
because they revolve
around the central gear
the way planets
revolve around the sun.
each of the small gears begins
as a disk-shaped steel blank.
a conventional,
1950s-era gear-cutting machine
cuts teeth into it
as a shower of oil washes away
the shards of metal.
the oil also cools
and lubricates the tool
so that it doesn't
overheat or jam.
after about 30 seconds
of machining,
the blank is
a fully shaped gear.
an even older machine,
circa 1930,
mills a larger blank
into the central gear.
however,
because this gear is bigger,
cutting the teeth into it
takes much longer --
about two minutes.
once all the gears are
machined,
they, along with the hub's
other steel components,
undergo a complex
heat-treatment
process to strengthen the
steel.
elsewhere in the factory,
workers assemble
the two halves of the clutch,
the component which locks
into regular or high gear
when the rider shifts.
using a cylindrical tool
called a broach,
the machine grooves
in the center of the clutch.
slots on the axle
will fit into these grooves.
next, they unscrew
the two halves of the clutch
and mount eight hollow pins
in each one.
in one half, they also install
three longer alignment pins
and a greased spring
inside each hollow pin.
then they thread the two
halves
of the clutch onto the axle,
aligning the axle slots
in the clutch's grooves
and the pins on one half
with corresponding pins
and holes on the other.
after fastening the halves
together once again,
they mount
the six planetary gears
on a ring called
the planet carrier,
then install it on the axle.
the spring-loaded pins
on the clutch
click into corresponding slots
on the planet carrier.
these slots are engineered
to fit the pins
with no more than
.01 millimeters of clearance.
after securing
the planet carrier to the axle
with a retaining clip,
they insert ball bearings
with a spring
in two holes
on opposite sides of the axle.
a retaining ring holds these
spring-loaded bearings in
place.
meanwhile, a laser engraver
etches the company logo
and product identification
on the wheel-hub body.
the body is made
of high-strength aluminum
that's undergone
an electrochemical treatment
to make it
corrosion-resistant.
they mount the hub body
on a hydraulic press
and insert the sun wheel,
surrounded
by a large ball bearing.
then they activate the press,
which forces the sun wheel
into the body.
they install the body
on the axle,
positioning the sun wheel
right in the center
of the planetary gears.
a cover protects the gears
from
dust, dirt, and precipitation.
on the opposite end of the
body,
they install additional
bearings
and affix a cover
with nine screws.
now the shift buttons --
a chrome-plated one
for shifting down,
a gold-plated one
for shifting up.
both screw into a shaft
running
through the center of the
axle.
the two spring-loaded bearings
workers inserted in the axle
earlier
hold that shaft in place.
this cross-section model shows
how everything comes together.
the shift button
moves the shaft,
which moves the clutch
to lock into the selected
gear.
in regular gear,
pedaling one revolution makes
the wheel turn one revolution.
when the rider shifts
to high gear,
pedaling one revolution
makes the wheel turn
1 1/2 revolutions.
the unicycle moves 50% further
as a result of the same
action.
riders use the regular gear
for climbing
and the higher gear
for flat or downhill terrain.
they hit the shift button
with their heel or ankle
while pedaling --
a quick, slight movement that
won't throw them off balance.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...