>> narrator: today on
"how it's made"...
paving asphalt...
marshmallow cookies...
loudspeakers...
and electronic door locks.
asphalt is a black, liquid
substance that's a by-product of
processing crude petroleum.
asphalt is a key component of
waterproofing and insulation
materials and roofing shingles.
but its best-known use is for
paving roads.
asphalt cement is a by-product
of crude oil -- the key
ingredient they mix with crushed
rocks and other minerals to make
paving asphalt.
so, production begins at the
paving plant's quarry, where
some 50 feet below ground,
workers driving heavy machinery
collect boulders of granite that
have been blasted off the rock
walls.
trucks transport the rocks to
the paving plant, which is right
on the quarry site.
they dump their cargo into the
primary crusher -- a machine
whose steel jaws crush these big
rocks into pieces smaller than
8 inches.
it takes mammoth force to crush
solid rock.
the fly wheels that amplify the
motor's energy weigh more than
6 tons.
the primary crusher empties onto
a mobile conveyor belt, which
transports the crushed rocks
to an outdoor storage area.
when it's time to make the
asphalt, the rocks travel, via
conveyer belt, from the storage
area to a screening building to
be classified by size.
there, the rocks tumble
downward over a series of
inclined screens whose largest
holes are 4 inches wide.
what's too large to drop through
goes to a secondary crusher,
that reduces the rocks to
4 inches or smaller, then sends
them to a third, or tertiary,
crusher that further reduces
them to 1 inch or smaller.
what's small enough to pass
through the screens bypasses the
secondary crusher and goes
directly to the tertiary
crusher.
after this last crushing stage,
the largest stones are 1 inch
in size.
everything smaller than 1/4 inch
goes in one pile -- that
includes stone dust created by
the crushing process.
stones that are 1/2 to 3/4 of an
inch go into another pile...
stones 1/4 to 1/2 inch into
another.
trucks transfer material from
each pile to separate
compartments called feed bins.
exactly what goes into the
paving asphalt depends on what's
being paved.
but, generally, these are the
four ingredients...
sand...
stone dust...
1/4- to 1/2-inch stone...
and 1/2 to 3/4 of an inch stone.
the ingredient proportions vary
according to what the paving
asphalt will be used for.
stones, along with sand and
stone dust as fillers, usually
make up about 95% of the mix.
the remainder, added later, will
be liquid asphalt cement.
each bin releases a specific
amount of material onto a
conveyor belt running under it.
the belts lead to a main
collecting belt that dumps
the ingredients, combined,
onto yet another belt that leads
to a drier.
the drying process, which takes
about a minute, removes all
traces of humidity.
this will enable the materials
to bond better with the asphalt
cement.
screening equipment then
reseparates the dried
ingredients, making it possible
to precisely weigh out the
required amount of each one.
everything then goes into a
mixer.
as this demonstration shows, the
mixer blends everything
thoroughly.
then it's time to pump in hot
asphalt cement.
oil refineries make asphalt
cement from what's left over
after they've processed crude
oil.
the paving mix contains about 5%
asphalt cement.
this is what happens inside the
mixer.
the hot asphalt cement binds the
ingredients in about 30 seconds.
the result is ready-to-lay
paving asphalt.
the mixer empties directly into
trucks destined for the paving
site.
there, a paving machine will
spread the hot asphalt on the
road bed.
then a compactor roller will
pack it down.
the asphalt cools and hardens in
about one hour, depending on the
weather.
>> narrator: the next time you
bite into a marshmallow cookie,
you can thank the ancient
egyptians.
they invented marshmallow
candy by thickening honey with
sap from the root of the
marshmallow plant -- a herb that
grows in salt marshes and along
large bodies of water.
modern marshmallow contains
gelatin instead of sap from the
mallow root.
the snap test -- to make sure
the coating is hard and thick
enough.
then, the taste test.
if you've got a sweet tooth,
doing quality control in the
marshmallow cookie factory is
your dream job.
to make a batch of dough for the
cookie base, they mix wheat
flour, salt, baking soda and
powder, cornstarch, whey powder,
and potassium sorbate.
then they add several liquid
ingredients.
this one causes a chemical
reaction, making the biscuit
lighter.
this cream-colored liquid is
vegetable oil shortening.
this transparent liquid is
glucose fructose, a sweetener.
the ingredient proportions are
also a company secret.
from the mixer, the dough goes
into a machine called the
chipper.
it shreds the big blob into
pieces about the size of the cap
on a highlighter pen.
this makes the dough more
manageable for the next machine,
called a rotary mold.
inside that machine, a large
roller flattens the dough
pieces, forming them into a
dense sheet about 1/2 inch
thick.
it then presses the sheet
against another roller whose
surface is a cookie mold.
the factory uses the rotary mold
machine for many different types
of cookies.
it simply installs the
appropriate roller for the
cookie in production.
for marshmallow cookie bases,
the mold cavities are round.
the bases exit the rotary mold
and make their way onto a moving
baking sheet.
that transports them to an oven.
the baking time and temperature
are, once again, top secret.
the baked cookie bases exit the
oven and move onto a conveyer
belt that transports them to a
cooling area.
once they cool to room
temperature, the bases go into a
machine called the base feeder.
it lines them up like marching
soldiers to receive their
marshmallow filling and
chocolate coating.
the process does require
military precision.
factory technicians have to
adjust this machine daily to
ensure accuracy to 1/32 of an
inch.
a portion of filling has to land
perfectly centered on each base,
finishing off in a curled peak,
this brand's trademark.
the company won't divulge how
much marshmallow filling goes
into each cookie, nor will it
reveal its marshmallow recipe.
but marshmallow is usually made
from either corn syrup or sugar
and gelatin.
and now for the final layer --
the chocolate coating.
not only are the marshmallow and
base covered in hot, melted
chocolate, the base floats in
it, which coats the underside,
as well.
built-in air jets blow off the
excess.
the chocolate hardens inside a
cooling tunnel.
how long that takes in the
tunnel temperature are -- you
guessed it -- classified
information.
as the cookies exit the cooling
tunnel, a quality-control worker
does spot-checks to ensure the
coating is thorough, hard
enough, and thick enough.
on the packaging line, the
cookies go into plastic trays.
to keep up to speed, the workers
have to grab four cookies in
each hand without breaking the
coating.
the trays pass through a machine
that wraps them in plastic film.
this keeps the cookies fresh and
also prevents them from falling
out of the tray.
meanwhile, another machine
assembles the boxes -- first
folding and gluing one end shut.
once workers load the trays, the
machine glues the open end
closed, as well.
then with the go-ahead from
quality control, the box's next
stop is the cookie aisle of your
local supermarket.
>> narrator: loudspeakers take
an electrical signal and turn it
into sound.
the key to it all is a magnetic
wire voice coil and a permanent
magnet that attract and repel
each other.
as the coil moves back and
forth, it rapidly vibrates a
flexible cone.
this vibrates the air in front
of the speaker, creating sound
waves.
loudspeakers contain at least
two magnet-and-cone assemblies
known as drivers.
they're typically housed in a
box called a speaker enclosure.
to build the internal magnetic
structure, the factory begins by
cutting two plates of iron, each
about 1/2 inch thick.
they go one at a time onto a
lathe.
first, the machining tool
smoothes and evens out the
surfaces, getting rid of the
marks the saw made.
then it cuts out a small hole in
the center of one plate and a
larger hole in the center of the
other.
next, they cut a smaller and
thicker round piece of iron
called the core.
a reamer bores a large hole
through it.
they apply superhigh-strength
epoxy glue to the core and to
the back plate -- the plate with
the smaller hole.
they glue and screw the pieces
together because the bond has to
be strong enough to withstand
intense magnetic pull.
they glue a foam filter in the
hole to ensure the vibrating
cone doesn't draw in dust and
cause internal damage.
now they spread the glue on the
narrow end of what's called the
metal basket, a die-cast
aluminum frame that will hold
the magnetic structure and cone.
they screw the front plate, the
plate with the bigger hole, onto
the glued surface.
then they glue the underside of
the front plate and one side of
a ferrite, a ceramic ring made
from the iron powder.
after adhering the ferrite to
the front plate, they apply glue
to the other side of the
ferrite, then flip the basket
over to attach the back plate.
the core fits through the large
hole in the front plate.
they insert shims to center it
while the glue dries.
after screwing terminals to the
basket, they put the entire
structure they've just assembled
into a magnetizing machine with
600 volts of direct current.
the machine creates positive and
negative poles, transforming the
magnetic structure into a
permanent magnet, meaning it has
a constant magnetic field around
it.
now they wind the voice coil --
the electronic magnet that will
interact with the permanent
magnet.
an electromagnet is an
object that generates a magnetic
field only when there's a
current running through it.
they wind enamel-insulated
copper wire, gluing it to a
rigid plastic sheet.
the positive pole of this
voice coil will be attracted to
the negative pole of the
permanent magnet.
the negative poles will repel
each other.
the key is that the voice coil's
poles are constantly reversing
position because the electrical
current running to the speaker
is an alternating current,
meaning it switches between a
positive and negative charge
several times per second.
this makes the magnets attract
and repel each other
continuously, causing the
voice coil to move back and
forth rapidly.
this vibrates the cone, which
creates sound waves.
after slipping the voice coil
between the front plate and the
core, they glue on the bottom
suspension -- flexible fabric
rings that move with the
voice coil and prevent it from
rubbing on the magnetic
structure.
next, they glue the cone.
it's usually made of cardboard,
plastic, or metal.
then solder the electrical
connections.
the current coming from the
amplifier travels by wire to the
two terminals.
the terminal wires connect to
the voice coil wires.
after making sure the cone moves
freely without rubbing, they
glue on a rigid cardboard cap
to keep out dust.
the last step is to take the
speaker for an audio test drive.
they connect it to a machine
that transmits different
frequencies.
they make sure the movement of
the voice coil and cone isn't
obstructed in any way.
then a computer device analyzes
the sound wave the driver sends
out.
two-way speaker systems have two
drivers in each enclosure -- a
woofer and tweeter.
a woofer has a large cone that
vibrates more slowly for low
frequencies.
a tweeter has a small cone that
vibrates quickly for high
frequencies.
three-way systems have a third
driver with a medium-sized cone
for the midranges.
>> narrator: at most hotels,
room keys are a thing of the
past.
you're more likely these days to
be given a key card.
when you arrive at the door to
your room, you swipe or insert
it to unlock the handle and get
in.
because the room number doesn't
appear on the card, this system
is far more secure than door
locks with a keyhole.
the metal case that houses the
door lock's mechanical and
electronic components is called
the housing.
to make it, they begin by
melting zinc ingots.
to melt zinc, you have to heat
it to about 734 degrees
fahrenheit.
die-cast machinery then injects
the molten zinc into molds.
between injections, sprayers
coat the empty mold cavities
with a release agent, the
industrial equivalent of
greasing a baking pan.
a built-in cooling system
hardens the metal.
then a trimming die cuts off
excess zinc around each piece
and in the openings.
meanwhile, the electronic
circuit board, the brain of the
lock, takes shape.
they call this the "pick and
place" machine.
it picks up the 60-odd
electronic components and places
them in the right position on
each board.
this computer-guided machine
installs 15,000 components per
hour.
next, the boards undergo what's
called wave soldering.
a mix of molten lead and tin
surges up from underneath,
fusing components in place and
creating electrical bonds.
then, both sides of each circuit
board get a coat of
silicon-based sealant.
this protects the components
against the elements.
back to the housings now.
workers lubricate them with
grease and apply what's called a
sleeve bearing -- a nylon
bearing that enables the handle
to turn smoothly.
next comes the drive tube onto
which the lever will be
assembled on the other side.
there are several clutch
components that link the lever
to the latch.
swipe the right card, and they
permit the latch to retract.
after applying more lubricant,
they install an override that
enables the hotel to open the
door with a key, if, for some
reason, the electronics
malfunction.
they install the circuit board
and connect it to the various
parts it controls, such as the
clutch motor, which they install
next.
now they close up the completed
housing with the steel
back plate.
this protects the components
inside from rusting.
the last step is to insert a
battery pack.
it holds three standard double-a
batteries.
the factory tests the lock using
a test key card because the lock
isn't yet programmed to work
with a specific card.
that's done after installation.
elsewhere in the factory, they
assemble the mortise -- the part
of the lock that goes inside the
door.
when you lock up, the mortise's
bolt comes out of the door's
edge and fits into the hole of a
receiving piece, called a strike
plate, in the door frame.
they close up the mortise with
the back plate.
this demonstration shows how
they install the mortise in the
door.
once it's in, they screw a
decorative plate on top.
this is what the finished
electronic door looks like.
key cards have instructions on
one side, a magnetic data stripe
on the other.
they use a generic card to test
every lock that comes off the
production line.
in the quality-control lab, they
subject every new design to
several rigorous tests.
they open and close 1 million
times.
they subject the lever, latch,
and lock to repeated impacts.
they also test lock function in
extreme temperatures.
these electronic door locks come
in several metal finishes plated
over the zinc and even in a
painted finish that simulates
wood.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.