narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
hockey gloves...
...snack cakes...
...remolded tires...
...and wastewater treatment.
ice hockey
can get pretty rough,
so wearing the proper equipment
is a must.
hockey gloves protect
the forearm, wrist, and hand.
a good glove has padding
in all the right places,
but is still lightweight
and comfortable.
it also has to be flexible,
so the player can hold
and maneuver the hockey stick.
the covering material
of a hockey glove
is called the outer shell.
it can be made of genuine
leather or synthetic leather.
there's even a new
synthetic material called carbon
that's tearproof,
even if a sharp skate blade
slashes it.
what it's made of is
a closely guarded trade secret.
one hockey glove is made up
of about 30 different parts,
depending on the model.
workers lay a die
in the shape of each part
on the outer-shell material.
a hydraulic press forces it down
like a cookie cutter.
workers then cut foam pieces
to line the glove.
this low-density foam is stiff
enough to provide protection,
but flexible enough
to enable the player
to grip the stick properly.
a seamstress now lockstitches
the outer-shell
and foam-lining parts together,
assembling each section
of the glove separately.
after finishing
the back of the hand,
called the back roll,
she pieces together the thumb.
she sews three sides closed.
one end stays open
so they'll be able to insert
more protective foam afterward.
these are the finger pieces.
the seamstress
uses a tacking machine
to sew up the sides and tack
the corners for added strength,
again leaving one end,
the top, open.
now they assemble the fingers
to the base of the glove.
they use what's called
a cylinder arm machine.
it has a narrow sewing surface
that protrudes,
making it easy to access
the fingertips.
next come the parts that make up
the palm and the gusset,
the piece that goes between
the fingers and the palm.
like before, workers cut
the parts using a die.
the palm and gusset
can be made of high-end
synthetic suede or leather
or even genuine leather.
the advantage of real leather
is that it can be treated
with an antibacterial product
that combats odor
caused by the hand sweating
inside the glove.
again, the seamstress uses
the cylinder arm machine
to sew the palm
to the glove base,
which already has
the fingers attached.
next, the glove
goes onto a machine
that's custom-made
for the hockey-glove industry.
using air pressure
to power a piston,
it injects pieces
of high-density foam padding
into the open end
of the fingers.
high-density foam is rock-hard,
so it provides
maximum protection.
but high-density foam is
too stiff to go into the thumb,
which needs some flexibility.
so instead, they make what's
called an armored thumb plate,
which is essentially
a plastic thumb shield.
a hot forge presses
a flat piece of hard plastic
onto an aluminum mold
in the shape of the plate.
then they wrap the plate
in low-density foam
and, with another machine
custom-made for this purpose,
inject it into the glove thumb.
the lower part of the glove
is now complete.
a seamstress finishes off
the edge with cotton tape.
all that's left is to do
is assemble and attach the cuff.
the standard cuff
is a little over 2 inches wide.
you can buy the gloves
this company produces
for retail stores,
or order customized gloves
with your name embroidered
on the cuffs.
professional hockey players
have the factory build gloves
to their own specifications
with extra protection
in key areas
or certain adjustments
that they feel give them
an advantage on the ice.
the most important part
of the glove is the palm.
that's the area that endures
the most wear and tear.
the sturdier the palm material,
the longer the glove will last.
but at the same time, the palm
padding can't be too thick.
that would make the glove
uncomfortable to wear
and take away the player's feel
for the hockey stick.
narrator: when marie antoinette
said, "let them eat cake,"
she probably didn't mean
those mini jelly logs.
still, in the realm
of treats for the sweet tooth,
snack cakes
have been revolutionary.
they're just the right size
for a quick snack
and individually wrapped
to stay fresh.
veteran snackers will recognize
this as a jelly log,
a sponge cake rolled up with jam
and a creamy filling.
first the factory bakes
the sponge cake.
it comes out of the oven
in continuous strips.
those moving arms align the
strips to receive the fillings.
one machine then does it all.
first it deposits an even layer
of cream filling...
then blobs of strawberry jam.
now the rolling begins.
one side of the cake strip
runs against a metal guide.
this lifts
and folds over the edge.
then the cake strips
run against a second guide
which rolls it over some more.
now the machine cuts
the continuous strip
into separate cakes.
then an automated roller
completes the logs.
the jelly logs
go onto a conveyor belt
that positions them
closer together,
aligning them for
the next phases of production.
they travel through a waterfall
of strawberry-flavored syrup.
this sticky coating
acts as a tasty glue
to adhere the shredded coconut
that showers them next.
the conveyor belt
shakes off the excess
which, like the excess
strawberry syrup before,
gets fed
through the machine again.
now, if all this doesn't have
your sweet tooth tingling yet,
the next snack cake will.
it's a chocolate cream cake
covered in a chocolate coating.
production begins in the mixer,
where they combine eggs,
a vegetable-oil mixture...
flour...
sugar...
water...
glucose, a liquid sweetener...
and cocoa powder.
the mixer blends the ingredients
at high speed for one minute.
then it pumps the batter
into a machine called
the automated depositor,
which squirts the batter
into cake molds.
the conveyor belt transports
the mold pans to the oven.
the batter bakes
for 7 minutes.
to achieve
just the right texture,
there's a very specific
heating pattern.
once the pans exit the oven,
a robot flips the cakes upside
down onto a conveyor belt.
it stacks the empty mold pans
onto another conveyor
that sends them back
for more batter.
now the cakes flip right side up
onto a wire conveyor belt.
air circulating between
the wires cools the cakes.
the next machine
aligns the cakes in position
for the next phases
of production.
first thin blades
saw the cakes in half.
then suction tubes
remove the tops
and place them
next to the bottoms.
next the machine drops
a portion of cream filling
on each bottom.
the cream is about
the consistency of margarine.
as the feeder tube
above each cake delivers it,
a wire cutter slices off a piece
about 1/4 of an inch thick.
then the suction tubes
put the tops back on.
now the cakes
pass through a shower
of hot,
chocolate-flavored liquid.
this coats the top and sides.
at the same time,
the cakes travel
through a bath of the liquid.
this coats the underside.
air jets blow off the excess.
the cakes pass
through a cooling tunnel.
this hardens
the chocolate-flavored coating.
then it's off
to the packaging department.
the cakes file into a sheet
of polypropylene film.
the machine seals, then cuts
the film between each cake.
this keeps each one fresh
until snack time.
narrator: if you need new tires
for your car or truck
and are looking to save money,
you might consider buying
retreaded or remolded tires.
retreads are worn-out tires
onto which the factory glues
new rubber treads.
remolds, on the other hand,
are actually rebuilt.
this company specializes
in remolding
commercial truck tires.
the worn-out tire
is called a casing.
this is a cross section.
that steel reinforcement rod,
called the bead,
won't be replaced.
but most of the rubber
around it will be,
along with most
of the tread area.
the steel belts
underneath the treads --
those dots -- will remain.
they begin
the remolding process
by thoroughly inspecting
the casing
to determine
whether it's indeed salvageable.
they consider its age,
whether it's had repairs.
they examine
the steel components
to make sure
they haven't rusted.
if the casing passes inspection,
it moves on
to the buffing machine.
there, sharp blades
spinning at high speed
shear off most
of the worn-out rubber tread.
buffing prepares the surface
so that the new rubber
will adhere well
and stand up to road friction.
buffing takes
about 6 minutes per tire.
it leaves just over 1/16 of
an inch of tread on the casing.
now they use a tool
called a skiver
to shave off any imperfections.
a rubber tire
is like a car windshield --
even the smallest crack
can spread outward,
so it has to be stemmed.
after excising problem spots,
they smooth them
with a grinding stone.
then they repeat
the buffing-skiving-grinding
procedure
on the sides of the casing,
but they use
a less abrasive grinding stone
because the sides don't need
such aggressive treatment.
unlike the tread area,
they won't be subjected
to road abrasion.
now, using a drill,
workers remove dirt and rust
from each spot.
then they work the area
some more with a grinding wheel,
so that the rubber
they'll use to patch it
will adhere properly.
now they glue the patch from
the inside with rubber cement,
pressing out any air bubbles
with a roller
to ensure full contact.
workers can now start
rebuilding the tire.
they feed a rubber strip into
a machine called an extruder.
first it heats up the strip,
making it malleable.
then it wraps it
onto the casing,
building up anywhere
from two to four layers
depending on how thick the
customer wants the tire to be.
that depends
on several factors --
for instance, how much traction
the tire needs to have
and whether the truck
will be doing mostly local
or long-distance driving.
now they apply a wider
rubber strip to the sides,
building up one to three layers,
the choice again depending on
the customer's thickness needs.
using a perforating roller,
they release the trapped air.
this enables the layers
to adhere well.
now they sprinkle the tire
with rubber powder,
residue from the buffing.
this will prevent the tire
from sticking to the mold.
the mold consists of sections
which allows it to open
wide enough to receive the tire.
the backward lettering inside
will imprint
the remolding company's
brand name on the tire.
the mold applies
about 220 pounds of pressure
as well as heat --
320 degrees fahrenheit.
this fuses the molecules
in the old and the new rubber --
a chemical reaction
called polymerization.
once the mold closes
to begin this process,
a tube inflates with air
and fills the void.
this provides counterpressure,
so that the tire
doesn't get crushed.
molding time
is anywhere from an hour
to an hour and 15 minutes
per tire,
depending on the thickness.
after extracting the tire,
workers remove the seams
of excess rubber
with a special comb.
this remolded tire
is now ready to hit the road
at considerable cost savings.
depending on the size and type,
a remold is 30% to 60% cheaper
than a new tire.
narrator: have you ever wondered
where all the rainwater goes,
or the snow once it melts,
or the water in your sink, tub,
and toilet after you've used it?
this wastewater flows through
the underground sewer system
to a treatment plant.
the plant removes
most of the pollutants,
then releases the water
into a lake or river.
the underground sewer network
feeds into
a regional interceptor,
which is a kind of sewer highway
that runs
to the treatment plant.
the action begins
at the plant's pumping station.
it doesn't look like much
from above,
but the building extends
some 15 stories belowground,
right through solid rock.
the wastewater collects
in huge underground wells.
it's not a pretty sight.
it's full of dirt, garbage,
and fecal matter.
it also contains high levels
of phosphorus,
a poisonous element
in the nitrogen family
harmful to waterways
because it promotes
the overgrowth of algae.
the water flows
from the wells to giant pumps
that force it to the surface.
the plant has backup generators
to keep the pumps working
in case of a blackout
and devices to prevent water
from backing up
should a pump have to be
shut down for servicing.
once the wastewater
reaches the surface,
it flows
through the pumping station
down discharge channels leading
to the treatment building.
along the way, it's sprayed
with either aluminum sulfate
or ferric chloride,
two chemical coagulants.
they gradually transform
phosphorus in the water
from liquid to solid
so it can be removed later on.
once the water reaches
the treatment building,
it flows through screens.
this preliminary filtration
removes any solids larger
than one inch in diameter --
such things as stones,
paper, and plastic.
giant presses
compact this garbage,
squeezing out the excess water.
trucks then haul the stuff to
a landfill, where it's buried.
the wastewater, meanwhile,
flows into large tanks
called grit chambers.
grit refers to particles
in the water such as gravel
that are inorganic, meaning
they don't decompose or burn.
these particles, some as tiny
as a grain of sand,
gradually settle to the bottom.
then they're pumped out
and trucked to the landfill.
to remove organic particles,
mainly phosphorus,
they add a polymer,
a type of chemical compound.
this demonstration
shows what happens.
remember, as the wastewater
left the pumping station,
it was sprayed with coagulant.
that transformed
the phosphorus in the water
into solid particles.
the polymer solution
completes the process.
it binds those particles,
forming what are called "flocs,"
masses of phosphorus
that look like snowflakes.
they're heavier than water,
so they sink to the bottom.
and that's exactly what occurs
in the plant's
clarifier tanks.
it takes about two hours for the
flocs to settle at the bottom,
forming a layer of sediment
called "sludge."
a system of rakes and pumps
collects the sludge
and transfers it to
the sludge treatment building.
unless testing shows a need
for additional treatment,
the clarified,
fully treated wastewater
now flows to what's called
the outfall,
a series of channels
that discharge into the river.
in the sludge-treatment
building,
they spray the wet sludge
with another type of polymer.
this further solidifies it,
so that filter presses can more
easily squeeze out the water.
most of the sludge goes into
giant incinerators to be burned.
the ashes go to a landfill.
the gas that the incinerators
emit powers several machines
that dry and transform the
remaining sludge into pellets.
these pellets are sold
as organic fertilizer.
when it arrived at the plant,
the wastewater
was full of contaminants
that harm aquatic life.
now, after treatment,
it contains 80% fewer suspended
solids such as fecal matter
and 75% less phosphorus.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc.
if you have any comments
about the show
or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...