-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc.
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
...cement...
...caskets...
...soft drinks...
...and glider rockers.
many people confuse the terms
"cement" and "concrete."
cement is a fine, gray powder
that's used to make concrete.
it's also an ingredient
in the mortar
that masons use
to lay brick and stone.
cement also goes
into soil cement,
a material that's used
in paving roads, building dams,
and lining reservoirs.
the action begins
at the limestone quarry.
the limestone near the surface
has a high content
of the minerals silica,
iron, and aluminum oxide.
deeper down,
the limestone is more pure,
containing less
of those minerals
and more calcium carbonate.
the plant
uses both types of rock,
altering their proportions to
make different types of cement.
workers drill holes
in the rock wall,
in which they plant
powerful explosives.
for safety, the workers
have to position themselves
behind the area
they're blasting,
maintaining a distance
of at least 150 feet.
after the explosion,
loaders move in.
they transfer
the limestone rocks
to 50-ton-capacity dump trucks.
the trucks then haul their cargo
to the cement plant nearby.
at the plant,
the trucks dump the rocks
into what's called
the primary crusher.
the rocks
can be as big as a piano.
the primary crusher reduces them
to about the size of softballs.
there's a constant spray
of water
to keep the dust
from billowing up
and settling on the chutes.
from there,
a conveyor transports the rocks
to the secondary crusher.
it reduces them further
to about the size of golf balls.
rock high in calcium carbonate
and rock low
in calcium carbonate
are crushed separately.
now it's time to mix the two.
the ratio varies
according to the type of cement
they're making.
this overhead machine,
called a tripper,
makes piles
of the required proportions.
they call this the raw mix.
then a reclaimer loads
the raw mix
into a grinding machine
called a roller mill.
depending on what minerals
are already naturally
in the crushed rock,
the factory adds
extra minerals
such as silica and iron.
certain types of cement
also require aluminum oxide.
the roller mixes and grinds
the ingredients uniformly,
producing a dry rock powder
called the raw meal.
now the powder
goes into a preheater.
the temperature of the powder
is 180 degrees fahrenheit
upon entering.
within 40 seconds, it gets
more that 10 times hotter.
this begins the process
of binding the minerals together
so that they'll later harden
when hydrated with water.
the preheater is equipped with
what's called a flash calciner.
in about 5 seconds, it removes
95% of the carbon dioxide
in the powder
through a chemical reaction.
this isolates the lime,
which is the most
important element in cement.
from there, the powder
moves into a rotary kiln,
a huge, cylindrical furnace.
it's set on an angle so that the
powder moves from top to bottom,
a distance of 160 feet.
the kiln rotates
about 2 turns a minute
to ensure the materials travel
through at the right speed.
the burner's gas flame
at the bottom
reaches a scorching 2,900
to 3,000 degrees fahrenheit.
as the powder approaching it
reaches the 1,500-degree mark,
it fuses into pieces
about the size of marbles.
these pieces are called clinker.
as the clinker leaves the kiln,
large fans cool it down
to between 140
and 180 degrees fahrenheit.
it's important
to cool the clinker quickly
in order to have quality cement.
from here, the clinker
goes to the storage area.
the last stage of cement making
is called finish grinding.
they add some gypsum
to the clinker.
the precise amount varies
with the type of cement
they're making.
gypsum delays
the cement's setting time,
so it can be worked for up
to two hours before hardening.
the cement mills
are called ball mills
because they contain
metal balls,
about 150 tons of them,
in the largest mill.
as the mill rotates,
the balls crush and grind
the clinker and gypsum
into a fine powder.
narrator:
the terms "casket" and "coffin"
are often used interchangeably,
but there are distinct
differences between the two.
coffins are actually
those eight-sided burial boxes
that are narrower at
the bottom -- think "dracula" --
whereas caskets are rectangular.
they can be made
of metal, plastic, or wood.
whether the wood is ash, oak,
mahogany, or something else,
the casket's construction
is generally the same.
first they run wood slats
through a machine
called a molder.
this profiles the edges,
carving a tongue on one side
of each slat
and a groove on the other.
a worker applies glue
to these edges,
then positions the slats
in a rounded vise
that locks the tongues
and grooves together.
the glue dries
in an hour and a half,
bonding the slats permanently
into a large, curved piece.
this piece will form the top
and long sides
of the casket's
rectangular cover.
to complete the rectangle,
a worker now makes
a v-shaped cut on each side
and glues in a triangular piece
of slatted wood.
while a press clamps
the components tightly together,
he secures the end pieces
in place with joint fasteners,
which are like
heavy-duty staples.
now a machine carves a groove
into the cover's underside
at the midpoint.
a worker glues in
a wooden piece,
securing it
with joint fasteners.
this piece is called the bridge,
and it's the point
at which the cover
will be cut in half later on.
they transfer the casket cover
to an automated machine
that gives it a rough sanding,
then a finer sanding.
the next step is to attach
a decorative molding
to the base of the casket cover.
this molding has a groove
on the inside
into which they'll later
tuck the edge
of the casket's
upholstery fabric.
a worker glues a small piece
of wood in the groove
at the midpoint
so the groove won't show
when the cover is open.
now he saws the casket cover in
two, right through the bridge.
meanwhile,
another worker assembles
the bottom of the casket,
called the box.
he glues together the sides
and applies a bottom molding,
securing everything
with joint fasteners.
at this point,
the box is upside down.
he attaches the bottom,
then flips
the box right-side up.
now it's time to join the cover
and box, using four hinges.
they spray the casket
with one of countless shades
of wood stain,
then rub it in equally
over the entire surface.
the casket goes into an oven
for an hour to dry the stain.
next a worker sprays
on two coats of lacquer,
with 40 minutes drying time
between applications.
this happens to be
a high-gloss finish,
but many models
have a duller sheen.
once the lacquer dries,
a worker attaches handles.
the more expensive the casket,
the fancier the features.
this higher-end oak model
with decorative corners
has wood
and metal swing handles.
other models
have all-metal swing handles
or fixed bars
made of wood, metal, or both.
the fancier caskets also have
an adjustable wooden bed inside,
with a mechanism
to adjust the height.
a worker covers the bed
in fabric.
the base-model bed
is made of absorbent paper
laid over a product
called wood wool,
which is simply shredded wood.
the upholsterer lines the inside
of the casket with foam,
covering it with either velvet,
satin, or silk polyester crepe.
by folding, nailing,
and stapling this fabric
a certain way,
she creates pleats, tufting,
and other design details.
generally,
the more expensive the casket,
the finer the fabric, and
the more ornate the upholstery.
a decorative trim
hides the staples.
fabric straps, or metal elbow
brackets, hold the cover open.
there's just no limit
to how beautiful and elaborate
caskets can be.
narrator:
the soft drink was born
at the drugstore soda fountain,
where pharmacists would serve up
various flavors
of carbonated water,
initially considered
a medicinal drink.
these sodas became so popular
that customers wanted to be able
to buy them in bottles
to take home.
that demand spawned
the soft-drink industry.
in 2003, almost 195 billion
liters of soft drinks
were sold around the world.
that's 30 liters
for every person on earth.
these 2-liter plastic bottles
have just arrived
from the bottle factory.
even though
they're brand-new bottles,
the soft-drink plant
still has to clean them
before filling them.
this rinsing machine
turns the bottles upside down,
then flushes them with water
the plant filters on-site.
once the water drains out,
the machine turns the bottles
right-side up again.
and they make their way
to the filling station.
meanwhile, in the mixing room,
technicians prepare
whatever soft drink
they'll be bottling
in this production run.
each recipe begins
with filtered water.
it makes up 86% of the drink.
the rest is syrup.
each syrup recipe
is a combination
of carefully measured
ingredients,
natural and artificial coloring
and flavoring,
and one or more various types
of sugar,
such as glucose or fructose
extracted from beets,
corn, or cane.
this machine releases
the right proportion of syrup
to filtered water,
creating the final soft drink
minus the bubbles.
the drink now travels
to a pressurized tank
called the carbonator.
there an injection
of carbon dioxide
infuses the drink
with gas bubbles.
the carbonated soft drink
now travels
to the reservoir
of the bottling machine.
the bottles arrive
and travel its carousel.
the machine removes the air
in each bottle,
then fills it with, in
this case, two liters of cola.
now on to the capping machine.
the caps come down a chute
propelled by filtered air.
the machine twists a cap
on the part of the bottle
called the crimp,
intertwining the threads
of the cap and crimp tightly
to hermetically seal the bottle.
next stop, labeling.
the machine's roller
applies cold glue
to one metal plate
after another.
each plate then grabs a label
and applies it to a bottle.
brushes smooth edges down,
ensuring the labels adhere well.
elsewhere in the plant,
a machine called the uncaser
unloads cases
of refillable glass bottles
that have come back
to the factory.
the cases continue
toward a case-washing machine.
the dirty bottles head toward
the bottle-washing machine,
where devices called cells
line them up in rows of 16.
each bottle tilts and enters
the washer neck-first.
inside, a combination
of powerful water jets and soap
remove dirt and germs.
then water jets
rinse off all traces of soap.
as they exit, they pass in front
of a neon inspection light.
workers pull any problem bottles
off the line.
now the bottles head to the same
bottling machine as before,
only now it's been adjusted
to fill each bottle
with 10 fluid ounces of drink --
in this case, orange soda.
this factory takes a sample
from each production run
for quality-control testing.
the lab technicians
check such things
as the dilution ratio
of syrup to water,
the carbonization level,
and the airtight seal.
they also analyze the purity
of the drink and container
by running the sample
through a paper filter.
they put the filter
in a petri dish
containing the nutrients needed
to grow micro-organisms.
then they incubate
at a precise temperature
and observe
if any bacteria grow.
these glass bottles
have old-fashioned bottle caps,
not the twist caps
the plastic bottles have.
as each cap drops down
onto a bottle,
the machine squeezes it tightly,
creating an airtight seal.
once the bottles
are filled and capped,
they go into shipping cases.
narrator:
a glider rocker combines
the back-and-forth movement
of a traditional rocking chair
with the gliding motion
of a swing.
parents often buy them
to rock their infants to sleep
or soothe them while feeding.
other models are designed
for people
who like to rock and glide
while having a conversation,
reading a book, or watching tv.
glider rockers
come in a few different styles.
some are made of solid wood
with a variety of cushions.
others have a metal frame that's
partially or fully upholstered.
the first step is to cut
the dried wood
to the required dimensions
using laser-
and computer-guided saws.
the species this factory uses
for its wooden models
are maple, oak, and ash --
hardwoods known for
their strength and durability.
then a computerized, industrial
router/shaper forms tenons.
a tenon is a projection
on the end of one piece
that fits into a cavity, called
a mortise, on another piece.
another shaper
profiles the seat-frame pieces
four at a time.
workers glue each tenon
and mortise together by hand,
then clamp the joint.
once the glue cures,
these joints will be
virtually indestructible.
with the glue dry,
the seat frame moves on
to the next phase.
another automated router/shaper
gives it the final contour.
next they smooth
the surface of the wood
using successively
finer sandpapers.
now they bore a series of holes
for attaching the armrests
and back of the chair.
precision is critical here.
they assemble those pieces
in a custom-made assembly jig
to ensure their exact position
and angle
before screwing them in place.
now they attach what's called
the multiposition mechanism.
this enables the glider-rocker
to lock in six different
comfort positions.
this part, called a trammel,
controls the angle.
ball bearings located at the top
and bottom of the chair's arms
are key to a smooth,
gliding motion.
secured solidly,
they'll last a lifetime.
workers assemble the parts
that make up
the rocking/gliding mechanism.
finally, they slide it
under the seat frame
and attach it
to the multiposition mechanism.
it's critical
that the fit be precise
for the chair
to operate properly.
meanwhile, work is under way
in the upholstery department.
there are many different styles
and colors of fabric available.
workers stack several layers
of seat-cover fabric
for a given model in a pile
to cut several in one shot.
the pile lies
on a textured rubber mat
held steady by a vacuum press
so it won't move
while the computerized cutter
does its work.
after the pieces are cut,
a seamstress sews
the zippered seat cushions.
another vacuum press temporarily
squashes the seat cushions,
enabling workers
to insert one in each cover.
the cushion
isn't a simple block of foam.
rather,
it's a triple-decker sandwich
composed of two different
densities of foam
glued together with
a multilayered polyester fiber.
the fiber gives the cushion
more depth and smoothness.
the different foams
maximize comfort and durability.
the plastic wrapping
has no structural role.
it's merely part
of the vacuum system.
relaxing in a glider rocker can
be a very soothing experience.
picture yourself
in front of the fireplace,
legs resting
on a gliding ottoman,
relaxing your back
after a long day,
reading, listening to music,
or just daydreaming.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...