narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
wood-burning stoves...
...orthoses...
...ballet slippers...
...and buses.
wood-burning stoves
do more than create
a cozy ambience.
they're also powerful enough
to heat an entire house.
more and more people
are installing a woodstove
as an additional heat source
in their home.
it's economical,
and the new low-emission models
are more
environmentally friendly.
every woodstove
has a fire baffle --
a stainless-steel barrier
above the burning wood
that shields the top
from the intense heat.
the baffle also slows down the
smoke exiting by the chimney,
which reduces the upward draft
that the rising heat creates.
production begins
with large steel sheets
that are 1/4 of an inch thick.
a computer-guided laser
cuts out pieces
that workers will shape into
the various parts of the stove.
the laser slices through
the metal quickly
and with extreme precision.
and because it cuts
with intense light
rather than punching force,
the pieces
have neat, smooth edges.
workers use a strong magnet
to lift and transfer the pieces
to the next production area.
the largest piece
becomes the surround --
the part that forms the sides
and back of the woodstove.
workers use a machine called
a press brake to shape it.
a computer guides
this large hydraulic press
to bend the flat steel
in exactly the right spots.
now they position the surround
in an assembly jig
to keep it steady
during welding.
after welding the front
of the stove to the surround,
they weld the air intake,
which allows oxygen to enter
the stove to feed the fire.
next they weld the top --
the fire baffle --
and air channels near the top,
which are also designed
to feed the fire with oxygen.
the quality of welding
in a woodstove is critical
because the joints have to be
able to withstand extreme heat.
now they weld the bottom
of the stove.
it has a hole in the middle
through which you sweep
the embers to an ash pan below.
now they weld the flue collar,
the steel ring that attaches
the stove to the flue pipe
that leads to the chimney.
workers now bolt the stove
to a pedestal.
the pedestal
is also made of welded steel.
meanwhile, the door takes shape.
they glue a fiberglass rope to
the perimeter of the doorframe
using a silicone-based glue
that's resistant
to extreme temperatures.
this cord prevents air from
seeping in through the door
and fueling the fire
out of control.
after installing
the locking door handle,
they weld the door hinges.
the stove's interior,
where the wood burns,
is known
as the combustion chamber.
they line it with bricks
to protect the walls from
warping in the intense heat.
bricks do deteriorate over time,
but it's easy to replace them.
the last steel part they install
is the cap for the ash pan.
now an automated conveyer
transfers the stove
to the paint station,
where a robotic arm sprays on
a coat of heat-resistant paint.
once the paint air-dries,
a worker removes the door
to install its glass panel.
this isn't your
run-of-the-mill window glass.
it contains ceramic,
which enables it
to withstand temperatures up to
almost 2,000 degrees fahrenheit.
with the glass panel in place,
workers can apply
decorative features
and information stickers.
then they put the door back on
and lock it shut.
they rivet on
the company logo...
...then install a fan
in the back.
the fan blows out the heat
that the stove generates.
when the wood-burning stove
leaves the factory,
its coat of paint is dry,
but not yet cured.
the heat cures it
when you fire up your stove
for the first time.
narrator: orthoses are devices
such as arch supports and braces
that address
a joint or muscle problem
in the back or extremities.
an orthosis can provide
artificial support,
prevent or correct a deformity,
or improve how a weak
or painful area functions.
you can buy an orthosis off the
shelf or have one custom-made.
producing a custom-made orthosis
starts with a thorough
examination.
a certified professional,
called an orthotist,
analyzes the problem area --
in the case of this patient,
the feet.
after a few manual manipulations
to test the range of motion
and pinpoint weakness or pain,
the orthotist
uses various instruments
to measure the angles of
the different parts of the feet.
then it's on
to specialized devices
that analyze foot position
and movement
during standing and walking
and how body weight
is distributed onto the feet.
in this scan,
the red areas show
that more weight is landing on
the left foot than on the right.
next, a 3-d impression
in foam.
it goes to the production
department,
where technicians fill it
with plaster.
once it dries, they extract
an exact model of both feet.
now they can construct
the orthosis piece by piece.
most of the components
are made of different types
of polyurethane,
a lightweight thermoplastic.
each type is designed
to produce a specific effect
at a different phase
of the patient's footstep.
for example, the blue base
is made of rigid polyurethane
that holds the foot
in the correct position.
at the front, dense, black
polyurethane helps propulsion
and reduces stress
on that side of the foot.
they cover the assembled
orthosis with a sheet of glue
and put it in a vacuum press.
the press applies heat
to activate the adhesive.
it sucks out the air
between the components
and compresses them
tightly together.
when the orthosis comes out,
they place it on the model
of the corresponding foot.
then it goes into
a different vacuum press
to mold it to the shape.
they add made-to-measure
corrective parts
with latex foam.
then, using hypoallergenic glue,
line the orthosis
with a soft polyurethane.
all that's left to do now
is buff the orthosis.
this smoothes all the surfaces.
to ensure the orthosis
fits correctly,
the patient redoes the key tests
while wearing it.
remember that scan
showing red areas?
they're gone now
because the patient's feet now
bear his body weight equally.
this patient has arrived
with a doctor's prescription
for a knee brace.
the orthotist
analyzes his mobility,
flection, and balance,
then sends the technical
specifications
to the production
department.
there, technicians make a model
of the leg.
they begin by positioning
the leg at a 12-degree angle
and wrapping it
in plaster bandages.
while waiting for
the fast-set plaster to harden,
the patient chooses
a decorative pattern
for the outside
of the brace.
the hardened cast
serves as a mold.
technicians pour in plaster, let
it harden, then remove the cast.
after smoothing the surface,
they draw technical markings,
then install the lightweight
aluminum joints
that will enable the orthosis
to bend.
now they run a sheet of plastic
through an oven.
this is high-memory plastic,
meaning that when you form it,
it remembers the shape
and maintains it.
the design the patient chose
comes printed on transfer paper.
they use a laser thermometer
to ensure the plastic
is at the perfect temperature
for the pigments
to penetrate properly.
they carefully position the hot
decorative plastic on the model.
using a vacuum bag,
they remove the air and
press the plastic on tightly.
the plastic sets in about two
minutes, maintaining the form.
they cut the required shape,
line the inside,
and sand the edges smooth.
finally, they attach straps to
fasten the orthosis to the leg.
the orthotist checks the fit
on the patient,
then runs various tests
to make sure the orthosis
is doing exactly
what it's designed to do.
narrator: ever wonder
how ballerinas manage to dance
on the tips of their toes?
it takes years of training,
remarkable skill,
and special ballet slippers.
these toe shoes are handmade
in what's truly
a manufacturing pas de deux --
a graceful pairing
of traditional methods
and modern materials.
they sew the toe shoe's exterior
with three pieces of satin.
they cut those pieces using a
press equipped with a metal die.
it slices through
enough fabric at a time
to make four pairs of shoes.
they also cut a pure cotton
lining for each piece
to protect the dancer's feet
from irritation.
this v-shaped piece
is called the vamp.
it'll become the front half
of the shoe.
the seamstress extends the "v"
by attaching
the two other satin pieces,
called the quarter panels.
they'll form the back half
of the shoe.
she sews the ends of the "v"
together, making a heel seam,
which she reinforces
with a rayon ribbon.
then she feeds the same type of
ribbon through a special machine
that folds it in half
over a drawstring.
she stitches it to
the top perimeter of the shoe.
this encased drawstring
will enable the dancer
to pull the shoe
tightly around her foot.
now they put the satin upper
onto a wooden form
to check the sizing.
it's absolutely critical
that the height of the vamp
be correct
to within 1/8 of an inch.
if it's even slightly off,
the top of the shoe
will cut into the dancer's foot.
the shoemaker nails
the cotton lining to an insole
on the bottom of the form.
the insole is made
of rigid cardboard for support,
imbued with plastic
for flexibility.
after trimming off the excess,
he glues the lining
onto the insole,
making neat little pleats.
once the glue dries,
he removes the nail
and trims the excess pleating
to eliminate any bumps
that would irritate the foot.
now they sculpt the toe box,
the hard encasing
inside the tip of the shoe.
it's made of papier-mâché,
only instead of paper and paste,
they use fabric and paste.
then they soften up a piece
of resin-coated cotton in water
and apply it on top.
next they saturate two pieces
of burlap with paste
and apply them, one after
the other, over the cotton.
the paste is made of flour,
water, starches,
and a
rubber-and-plastic-based resin
that hardens
to a semi-flexible state.
that's key, because the toe box
has to be stiff enough
to bear the dancer's
full weight,
yet flexible enough so that
the ballerina can move fluidly.
now the final layer of fabric --
a piece of pure cotton.
they wrap the toe box in plastic
to keep the hammer clean
as they square off the front,
creating what's known
as the platform.
then they press the toe box
onto a piece of marble
to make it completely flat.
they verify that the platform
is perfectly square.
if not, the ballerina
will topple over.
after letting the toe box
dry for 24 hours,
they glue the lining over it
with contact cement.
they trim off the excess, then
glue the satin over the lining,
forming delicate pleats.
they use lighter glue this time,
because contact cement
would stain the fabric.
they apply a foam filler to
even out the shoe's underside,
then coat it
with high-strength vinyl glue.
they apply the same glue
to a sole,
then leave both to air dry.
24 hours later,
they put them on a heater
set to 200 degrees fahrenheit.
this reactivates the dried glue
in about half a minute.
they apply the sole
then put the shoe in a press for
15 seconds to solidify the bond.
now they can remove the shoe
from the form.
the sole is made of suede,
a material that has
just the right amount of grip.
it's nonslip,
yet still enables the dancer to
glide smoothly across the floor.
the last step is to glue in
a white suede sockliner.
it cushions the ballerina's foot
and keeps it
from slipping forward
when she's dancing on her toes.
narrator: a city's fleet
of public transit vehicles
might include standard buses,
low-floor buses, or both.
low-floor buses have
a special kneeling feature.
when they pull up
to the bus stop,
they can mechanically lower
themselves to curb height
to make boarding easier
for children, senior citizens,
and handicapped people.
this low-floor bus
is 40 feet long
and can carry
more than 80 passengers.
to build the bus's
internal structure,
workers put stainless-steel bars
into a press.
it applies between
90 and 110 tons of pressure,
bending them
to the required shape.
workers assemble the structural
pieces on a support frame
called an assembly jig.
they use
an electronic inspection arm
to verify their work.
once they've assembled
the roof structure
and the side structures, they
bring them together for welding.
everything goes
on a rotating jig.
it turns like
a giant rotisserie,
giving workers easy access
to whatever part of the bus
they need to weld.
when the welding is finished,
they turn the bus right side up.
they put the structure
on a dolly
and release it from the jig
so that they can move it
down the production line.
meanwhile,
the stainless-steel structure
for the floor of the bus
takes shape.
once that's complete, it's back
onto the rotating assembly jig
to weld it
to the rest of the structure.
this bus factory
uses stainless steel
because it stands up well
to corrosion.
transit systems need to keep
these buses running full-time
for up to 20 years.
less rusting means
fewer expensive
and time-consuming repairs.
workers now move
the completed structure
to another part of the factory
where they spray the underframe
and lower section
with a black,
anti-abrasion coating.
this protects against
the noise and damage
that stones
and other road debris cause
when they hit the bottom
of the bus.
next, workers apply
high-strength glue
to the floor structure
and lay down a subfloor.
then they drive in screws
for reinforcement.
now they turn
the bus upside down
to install four tanks of
compressed air under the roof.
three are for the brake systems,
the fourth for the doors
and other mechanisms.
melamine ceiling panels
hide everything
that's under the roof.
next, the engine's radiator
goes in at the rear of the bus.
then workers turn the bus
right side up again
and lay down a waterproof
vinyl floor covering
that's specially designed
to withstand
heavy-duty transit use.
they cover the sides and roof
with fiberglass panels.
to prevent corrosion,
workers use glue
rather than screws or rivets.
then they attach
the fiberglass front of the bus
to the rest.
the bus's low-emission
diesel engine
arrives at the factory
already assembled.
workers attach it
to the transmission
and drive shaft
in the engine compartment.
buses without air-conditioning
have sliding windows
that open widely.
on air-conditioned buses,
just a small top section opens.
the upholstery
on the molded fiberglass seats
is a velour-like fabric
woven onto a strong canvas,
then glued onto
a fiberglass insert.
this construction
makes it impossible
for vandals to slash the seat
with a knife.
workers install
the driver's seat,
the steering wheel,
and all the controls,
including the toggle switch that
activates the kneeling feature.
this bus also has a ramp
for wheelchairs.
a safety system
locks the accelerator pedal
and applies the brakes
to prevent the bus from moving
when the ramp or kneeling
feature are in operation.
the finished bus
undergoes a half-hour
water-infiltration test
with all of the systems running.
this ensures there are no leaks.
at every phase of production,
the factory does
a quality-control inspection,
checking everything from
mechanical safety to finishings,
right down
to the tiniest of details.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...