-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
kitchen knives...
...mannequins...
...socks...
...and hypodermic needles.
any good cook knows that you're
only as good as your tools,
so using the right kitchen knife
for the job is essential.
from chef's knives and cleavers
to boning knives, filleting knives,
and paring knives,
a serious cook buys only quality cutting utensils
and stores them in a block to keep their blades sharp.
today's blades are truly a cut above
the stone tools the cavemen used.
knife-making is now a science,
producing tools that really give
you that edge in the kitchen.
first, they roll out steel by the sheet from a big coil.
then this machine, called a press,
cuts out the blades with a punch.
and it really does pack a punch.
it presses down with 110 tons of pressure
in order to make these steel cutouts.
next, things get really hot.
they roll baskets full of the blade cutouts
into a high-temperature furnace.
the blades bake at almost 1,600 degrees fahrenheit
for 2 hours.
this hardens the steel.
out of the fire and into the freezer,
the blades chill out at subzero temperatures --
negative 56 degrees fahrenheit for two hours.
this freezer is cooled by liquid nitrogen.
now we have what they call "cold, hard steel."
next, they douse each blade with water
while a belt grinder smooths the back of the blade
and sparks fly.
continuous water keeps the steel cool and hard
while a sander smooths the back of the blade.
now a robot moves in.
this robotic arm has vacuum grippers like an octopus.
it picks up a blade by suctioning,
then it transports it to a grinding machine.
the machine grinds the blade to give it that cutting edge.
water flows continuously through the grinder,
again to keep the steel cool.
the robot keeps everything moving,
putting a paring blade through the grinder every 12 seconds.
the automated process for this
bigger blade is a bit different.
this robotic arm holds the blade in a grip,
rather than through fast-action suctioning.
that's because it takes more time to grind this big blade,
called a cook's knife.
so this arm holds onto this blade a few seconds longer.
but if this makes you nervous, relax.
the robot doesn't have a habit of dropping them.
some blades require a personal touch,
like this shiny chef's knife, used for chopping vegetables.
the worker runs the blade over the grinding stone
very carefully.
this gives it a very thin edge.
then a laser burns the brand
name onto the side of the blade.
next, a piece of wood goes into a clamp,
and a router shaves it into the shape of a handle.
the end of the blade now fits neatly into the handle.
a worker clamps the knife onto a riveting machine.
those things that look like bullets on an ammunition belt
are actually the rivets.
the machine forces the rivets
into the handle from both sides.
the rivets lock together inside the handle
so they can never be taken apart.
now they grind down
any protruding steel from the handle.
this makes the wood flush with the steel from the blade.
the piece of metal that extends
into the handle
is called the tang.
it gives the knife weight and balance.
finally, they hone the knife
between two stone grinding wheels.
with this kind of an edge, these knives will slice paper.
but these knives will do their best work on the cutting board,
where they'll make the cook's life easier and meals tastier,
no matter how you slice it.
narrator: they strike
alluring poses in store windows,
motionless models flaunting the latest fashions.
for clothing retailers,
mannequins are a vital sales tool.
they come in fixed or flexible versions,
the bodies realistic or abstract.
and they can be made out of a range of materials,
from wood to fiberglass.
meet lady swing and mr. x --
not flesh and bone, but polyurethane foam.
these fully flexible fashion figures
start out as humongous blocks of soft polyurethane foam.
using a band saw, workers
divide them into smaller blocks,
about the size of a large refrigerator.
a worker creates a pressed-wood mold
using both a grinder and a sander
to soften the inside.
she applies a layer of putty over rough or damaged areas.
this will harden and prevent the foam from clinging.
she'll make separate molds
for the arms, legs, head, and torso.
a 3-square-foot slab of foam goes on top of the mold,
then a slab of harder foam, called a pattern,
on top of that.
the foam layers and wood mold
now go through what's called a pressure cutting machine.
pressure forces the slabs together,
while a thin blade slices the excess foam away.
exactly how much pressure the machine applies
is a closely guarded trade secret.
the foam arms pop right out on the other side.
for the head and torso,
they use a foam slab measuring 58"x17"x5 1/2",
and a foam pattern
that includes shapes for breasts
and a belly button,
and grommets to shape the nipples.
this foam pattern is impressionistic.
this mannequins are not meant to be anatomically correct.
here's the pressure-cutting machine close up.
nine rollers compress the mold,
soft foam,
and pattern slabs together,
forcing them through a paper-thin opening,
and slicing away up to six inches of foam.
true to form, lady swing pops up
on the other side.
her flexibility is her best trait.
she and mr. x are often displayed on sports equipment,
like snowmobiles and bikes.
their manufacturer first named them in the 1970s,
and the monikers just stuck.
workers inspect the mannequin and trim the excess material.
they extract her easily
because they sprayed the empty mold cavity with lubricant.
next, a worker assembles
a quarter-inch-thick steel skeleton
to give the mannequin some structure.
workers will insert the skeleton
between the half-sections of the foam body.
a welder fuses together 16 joints
in the ankles, knees, thighs, hips, elbows, and shoulders.
another worker sprays slow-drying, water-based glue
on the skeleton and on the foam
body sections that'll cover it.
this will make them adhere together snugly.
the hand skeletons are thin and pliable, like coat hangers,
so they'll bend.
a worker places the skeleton between the torso halves,
positioning the foam so the edges meet evenly.
these dummies don't come cheap.
they sell for between $600 and $800 each,
depending on the market value
of the foam's main ingredient, oil.
still, that's a bargain
compared to their more realistic-looking,
but much less flexible, fiberglass cousins.
they cost up to $2,000 each.
after letting the parts dry and set overnight,
a worker tests the limbs for flexibility.
she joins together the lower leg portions.
the skeleton protrudes at the heel
so that it can be secured to the floor
when the dummy goes on display.
now, here's a scene worthy of a horror movie.
using an electric carving knife,
a worker slices of 2 1/2 inches
from the front of the head.
she glues on a hollow face mask
made of plastic,
using solvent-based glue for an extra-strong bond.
next, they spray the mannequin
with a flesh-colored water-based glue,
then sprinkle it with a fine powder
made of tiny cloth particles.
this is called flocking.
it takes 12 hours to dry and gives the mannequin
a protective fire-retardant skin.
this factory's flocking comes in 18 different colors,
from a variety of skin tones to several vibrant colors.
before lady swing makes her debut, a makeup session --
powder blush to color her lips and cheeks,
and water-based paint on her eyes, lashes, and brows.
they add a wig, and voilà --
she's ready for her date with mr. x.
narrator: socks are something we put on without thinking.
but consider this --
the very first socks were strips of cloth or hide
wrapped around the feet.
imagine walking around in those.
thankfully, that's ancient history,
and today's socks are much better for the sole.
with so many styles and fibers for sock these days,
it's no problem putting your best foot forward.
but you have to step into this room of knitting machines
to truly understand what a science sock-making has become.
here's a machine with the top open
so we can get a view of the knitting action.
an automated whirling cylinder
pulls yarn from spools through holes in metal spokes.
little hooks on the needles grab the yarn.
the hooks have latches.
the latches open as the hooks snare the yarn
and close as they knit so you don't lose a stitch.
as you can see,
this machine knits socks a lot faster than grandma,
sometimes making over 360 pairs a day.
as the layers are added,
a sock emerges from a tube at the bottom.
the knitting machine is fully computerized.
it automatically switches to a different color of yarn
to make a stripe or a company logo.
now the machine changes gears to make a heel.
it does a half rotation instead of a whole one
to knit the heel shape.
the needles go up and down as the latches open,
and the needles pick up the yarn, pulling it in.
knit one, purl two.
here it is in slow motion.
this is about the speed at which a human could knit at,
but this machine normally runs
at a speed of over 200 revolutions a minute.
a tension mechanism moves back and forth,
keeping the yarn from going slack and getting tangled.
now a sock shoots out of a vacuum tube,
and a worker turns it inside out.
she sews the toe closed and cuts off the extra fabric.
then she turns the sock right side out again,
and it's sucked up by the vacuum.
next, the vacuum tube deposits the sock into a bin.
the trapdoor on the end of the tube
ensures that vacuum pressure isn't lost.
but there's more than one way to close a sock toe --
a more automated way.
a worker slides the sock between two metal plates.
pressure holds them in place.
then a motorized conveyer system
transports the sock to a sewing head.
a blade cuts off excess fabric,
and a needle goes up and down like an oil rig,
stitching one row and then another as reinforcement.
this automated system produces a finer seam
than a sewing machine that's run manually.
now that the toe is closed, a robotic arm moves in
and feeds the sock to a set of rollers.
a blade pushes the sock down
while the rollers turn the sock
right side out.
a vacuum chute fires the sock into a bin.
then it's on to the rotary dying machine.
he loads 1,800 pairs or more,
depending on the size of the dying machine.
the socks toss around
in a bath of dyes, chemicals, and softeners.
for athletic socks,
they add antimicrobial treatment
to the mix.
it will help prevent fungus or bacteria that cause foot odor.
now they slide the sock onto a foot form
made of polished aluminum that won't cause snags.
the aluminum leg forms stretch the socks
to the prescribed size
as they travel down a conveyer belt into a boarding machine.
the boarding machine is like a gigantic iron,
and the heat seals the stretch in the nylon
so the sock stays that size.
once out, a robotic arm grips the sock
and pulls it off the aluminum form.
it's called a stripper.
then an automated rack with protruding pins
collects the socks.
the worker removes them a bunch at a time,
and the socks are ready for packaging.
and then, all you have to do is pull up your socks.
narrator: a hypodermic needle is the proper term
for a syringe and needle.
it's used to draw blood or inject medication.
this indispensable tool was invented back in 1853,
but it wasn't until 1954
that mass-produced disposable syringes came on the market,
developed for the vast immunization campaign
against polio.
a syringe may make you cringe,
but the treatment it delivers could be a lifesaver.
to make a hypodermic needle,
they start with a flat strip of stainless steel.
the milling machine rolls it into a tube shape.
a laser welds the seam together.
but what makes the steel stiff enough to use
is something called cold-work,
in which they press the tubing through a die several times.
this also slims the tube dramatically,
so now you have a thinner, tougher tube.
it takes about a couple of days
to turn this stainless-steel strip
into a tube with needle potential.
but it will have to be sharp to perform,
and the next steps will focus on getting the steel tube
to a point where it's more than just a blunt object.
an electrically powered blade scores the walls of the tubes
as rubber pads bear down and roll.
this rolling causes the tubes to
finally break at the score line.
the tubes are being cut down to size --
about two inches long.
the tubes fall into a bin, a tangled mess.
the bin, driven by air pressure,
agitates,
and this shaking motion straightens them out.
an operator bundles them together with a plastic band,
but removes a few to check the specs.
this micrometer uses laser light
to measure the outside diameter.
the tube is supposed to be 8/100 of an inch,
and it's right on.
next, a mechanically driven drum
rolls superadhesive tape onto the tubes.
the tape will hold the tubes in place
as more work is done on them.
they razor cut five-inch strips
of the tape tubes
so that there are about 100 tubes per strip.
then they spray aluminum oxide on the ends of the tubes.
this roughs them up
so that the surface will be easier to work with.
now they place the strips of
tubes into the grinding fixture,
and then they snap it shut.
coolant flushes over the tube tips
as the fixture moves across a grinding wheel.
the wheel grinds through the tops of the tubes,
shaping them into a rough point.
this is only the first grind, so it's not yet needle-sharp.
now the fixture rolls and rotates the tubes.
then it's back to the grind.
the angle of the wheel is changed
so that it sands the sides of the tubes.
these two secondary grinds
sharpen the tubes into a finer point.
this is how they look before grinding,
and this is after, with their sharp needle tips.
now it's time for the big inspection.
she pushes the ends of the needles
with the back of her tweezers to make sure they're even,
and then pulls out a needle for sampling.
she measures the length of the grind.
it should be a few hundredths of an inch long.
next, she sizes up the needle's outside diameter
with a micrometer.
holding the needle between posts,
it measures the space between them.
then she checks the inside diameter
by inserting a plug gage into the tube.
now she inspects a whole bundle of needles
for irregularities or burrs.
using tweezers, she removes one
for a closeup look under the microscope.
once they pass inspection, it's on to the big wheel,
or the automated assembly machine.
brass- and nickel-plated fittings, called hubs,
drop onto pins on the wheel.
then needles fall into the hubs.
metal fingers align them so they fit together precisely.
the hub is the piece
that will connect the needle to the syringe.
automated crimpers press the needle into the hub.
sheer friction bonds them.
now two metal pads on the same wheel
position the needle.
a plastic sleeve drops down, encasing the pointed tip.
finally, a robotic arm lifts the needle off the wheel
and drops it into a bin.
the needles are now ready for you,
but are you ready for them?
if you have any comments about the show
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...