-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
fiberglass boats...
clothes driers...
bubble gum...
and fireworks.
they're sleek, they're fast, and they're fun.
fiberglass boats can jump waves
and turn on a dime.
the fiberglass body is low-maintenance and durable,
so these watercraft don't deteriorate
the way wooden boats can.
a computerized saw cuts out the wood pieces
they'll use to build the mold for the fiberglass boat.
it takes a team of artisans about 15 months
to design and build the mold.
they first construct the frame.
then they construct the shape out of fiberglass.
the mold must be perfect
in order to cast a boat that's free of faults and defects,
so they painstakingly work on the mold's finish in particular,
coating it in a special high-resistance paint
that will withstand about eight years of castings.
once they finish the mold,
they can begin casting the fiberglass boat.
the equipment feeds just the right ratio
of fiberglass to plastic resin.
fiberglass is glass in the form
of very fine, flexible fibers.
they may look fragile,
but those fibers are stronger than steel,
and they won't burn, stretch, or rot,
so they make perfect boat-building material.
workers make sure they roll the fiberglass
into every nook and cranny.
this is critical
because if they don't apply the fiberglass thoroughly,
the boat will have structural defects.
as heat within the fiberglass builds up, it hardens.
next, they roll on a material called roving.
it reinforces the fiberglass and makes it more rigid.
they also install wood
in the areas where they'll later mount equipment.
they coat the wood with fiberglass
to protect it from moisture.
after about an hour,
it's time to extract the casting
from the mold.
they use a lever system to lift out the hull.
they cut out holes for the mechanics.
then they install the boat's deck.
they install the motor and the electrical wiring
for the mechanics and plumbing.
the boat truly takes shape in the final assembly.
they put together the upper part
of the boat, called the shell,
and the inside, called the liner.
they install the furniture...
certain components are installed by hand,
such as the dashboard.
last stop, quality control --
a series of tests to ensure that
all the mechanics function well
and that the boat is absolutely watertight.
finally, a wrapping is added
to protect the boat during shipping.
narrator: electric cars are cheaper to run
than gasoline-powered cars.
just plug them in to recharge. no fill-up required.
but they cost 40% more to buy, which offsets the savings.
battery technology will have to
improve and come down in price
before electric cars can truly take off.
clothes dryers were invented in europe in the early 1800s.
the lady of the house would put the clothes
in a metal barrel with holes in it,
then turn it by hand over the fire.
the first electric dryers were invented around 1915.
most of the parts are made from steel
just 3/100 of an inch thick.
the factory receives it from the supplier in giant rolls.
they go onto a machine that cuts
sheets about 3 feet long.
using those sheets,
industrial presses stamp out various dryer parts.
these are motor supports.
and this is the back panel of the drum,
the rotating compartment that holds the clothes.
note those small holes. we'll come back to them shortly.
to form the side of the drum,
the machine bends a sheet of prepainted steel
into a circular shape.
when a clothes dryer operates,
it sucks in outside air through a hole at the front.
the air passes through the heating element
and goes into the drum,
entering through those little holes you saw a few moments ago
located in the back panel.
once the automated machines have finished shaping the drum,
they form a groove on its outside surface.
this groove is for the motorized
belt that drives the drum.
next, they put the drum on another machine
that screws three baffles in place.
baffles are those thick plastic
wings located inside the drum.
they're what throw the clothes around as it rotates.
back on the automated line, the drum's front rim goes on.
they manually assemble the drum's back panel.
then a machine installs it.
next comes the exhaust duct.
hot, moist air exits the drum through a series of holes
and a large slot in the dryer door.
the air gets channeled downward
through the lint screen,
then goes through a duct at the
front of the dryer to the fan.
the fan blows the air out this exhaust duct
at the back of the dryer.
the dryer's heating element
works much like the element in a toaster,
except it consumes a lot more power --
up to 6,000 watts.
the factory receives the steel
and ceramic heating coils ready-made.
workers simply position them on a sheet of galvanized steel.
they also install a temperature
sensor that shuts off power
should something go wrong and cause the dryer to overheat.
in the finishing department,
they coat the dryer with powdered paint
that's heat- and shock-resistant.
then they assemble the bottom and back of the appliance.
they install the motor
that drives both the belt and the fan.
then the exhaust duct goes in.
automated machines prepare the electrical wiring.
they paint and cut the wires...
...then install a terminal on each end.
workers wire the dryers...
then install the drum.
they close up the sides...
...screw on the door, then wire up the control panel.
it's connected to a series of gears and switches
that control the dryer cycles.
the model and serial-number sticker
marks the last stop on the assembly line.
narrator: chewing gum dates back
to the ancient greeks,
who chewed resin from trees.
modern chewing gum was patented
in the u.s. in 1869
by -- believe it or not -- a dentist.
in 1928, another american invented bubble gum.
bubble gum comes in gumballs of all colors and sizes,
but for blowing bubbles,
nothing beats the chewy, gooey pink stuff in the twist wrap.
it all starts with a gum base, the stuff that makes gum chewy.
traditionally, the base came from tree resin.
today it's synthetic -- made of plastics and rubbers.
they pour the gum base into a mixer,
then add color and flavoring.
as it begins mixing, they pour in glucose syrup, a sweetener.
because it's liquid, it helps keep the gum base soft.
next, they add dextrose, a powdered sweetener.
they blend the ingredients for about 20 minutes.
the stirring action builds up heat,
which melts everything together.
the mixture is ready
when it reaches the consistency
of bread dough.
they transfer it by cart to a machine called the pre-extruder.
the machine squeezes the mixture
through a narrow opening,
like squeezing toothpaste from the tube.
this transforms the big, bulky wad into thin, manageable strips
that can then go through the extruders.
the extruders squeeze each strip
down to the actual width of a piece of bubble gum.
it comes out as one long, continuous stream,
to be cut into bite-size pieces
later on.
this extrusion process heats up
the gum.
if they were to cut and wrap it now,
it would stick to the wrapper,
so the next stop is a cooling chamber.
the gum goes in for 15 minutes
at temperatures between 37 and 45 degrees fahrenheit.
when the bubble gum comes out,
it's cooled down enough for what
they call the "cut and wrap."
one machine does both jobs
in a fraction of a second.
watch the action in slow motion.
as the continuous stream of gum
enters on one end,
the machine cuts it into bite-size pieces,
pushes each piece into a wax-paper wrapper,
then twists both ends of the wrapper closed.
here's the slow-motion replay from a different angle.
the machine processes 900 pieces
of bubble gum per minute.
last stop -- packaging.
the bubble gum moves onto a scale
that automatically weighs out the right amount per tub.
they seal the tub with plastic to make it airtight.
this keeps the bubble gum fresh.
ever wonder why bubble gum is pink?
it's because that's the only color walter diemer had on hand
when he invented this treat back in 1928.
since then, the color just stuck.
narrator: what's a 4th of july celebration without fireworks --
brilliant colors exploding in the air,
the oohs and ahhs they elicit on the ground?
fireworks are so high-tech these days,
it's easy to forget they're not a modern invention.
historians believe gunpowder,
the explosive ingredient in fireworks,
was invented in china around 1000 a.d.
it's said that in a famous battle,
the chinese emperor illuminated
the sky with it,
scaring away the enemy.
during the renaissance,
the europeans invented the type
of fireworks we know today.
modern pyrotechnicians
use computers to ignite fireworks from a safe distance
and to synchronize their bursts
with music.
assembling explosives into fireworks
is the job of the pyrotechnician.
even the tiniest spark of static
electricity could set them off,
so antistatic gloves are a must.
a firework is made up
of separate compartments within a shell.
the burning fuse explodes one compartment at a time,
creating those staggered bursts
in the sky.
the pyrotechnician first glues the main fuse
into the bottom of the shell.
the glue is naturally colorless.
it's dyed blue so he can tell exactly where he's applying it.
he puts the bottom aside to work
on the second compartment
of this 2-compartment firework.
he starts by spooning a powdered
explosive into the center.
then he caps it.
here he's working on two fireworks at a time.
next step -- a brown cardboard shock absorber
to shield this compartment from the first compartment explosion.
then a corrugated cardboard disk
and a plastic spacer.
it'll take the fuse 1 1/2 seconds
to burn through these two components,
creating a slight delay
between the first explosion and the second.
gluing the second compartment together is tricky.
if it's too tight, it'll stifle the explosion,
but it has to be tight enough to withstand the delay.
with the second compartment done,
it's time to prepare the first.
he glues a sleeve onto a case,
then fills it with hundreds of stars.
stars are what create the flashes of color.
they're carefully measured explosives
mixed with coloring agents
such as magnesium for white, copper salts for blue,
and charcoal for orange.
the pyrotechnician must handle them gingerly,
or they could detonate.
next, he adds comets, another type of exploding decoration.
he tops it off with gunpowder.
finally, he glues the two compartments together,
filling the remaining space
with the same combination of ingredients.
once the shell is full, he glues on the cover,
and the tighter, the better.
the more pressure that builds up,
the bigger and more spectacular
the explosion.
next, he wraps the fireworks in craft paper.
the label uses international color codes
to indicate the size of the shell.
the lift charge --
a gunpowder bag with a long, fast-action fuse --
goes at the base of the shell.
that's what'll send the firework
into the sky.
when they light the main fuse at the top,
it simultaneously lights two secondary fuses --
the time-delay fuse inside the shell,
running through the compartments
of explosives
and that long fuse running along the outside
down to the lift charge at the base.
once the lift charge ignites,
heat and gas build up inside the
launch tube until they explode,
propelling the firework close to 1,000 feet skyward.
let the light show begin.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...