-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made,"
carpets,
drinking water,
laser-eye surgery,
and acoustic guitars.
people use the words "rug" and "carpet" interchangeably,
but they're not the same thing.
a rug covers just part of the floor.
a carpet goes wall to wall.
today most carpets on the market
are made of synthetic materials.
the first step is to make the carpet yarn.
they start by feeding bales of nylon or polyester fiber
into the opening and blending machine.
the carding machine then untangles the individual fibers,
lining them up in neat rows,
then gathering them into wider bands.
the bands go into cans.
from the cans,
they go into a machine called a drawing frame...
which draws out five threads
to make one rough, loose thread.
that thread goes onto spools.
then they twist threads from two spools
to make a stronger and thicker thread.
next they twist two of those threads together
to form a two-ply yarn.
to ensure the two plies don't untwist,
the yarn goes through a heat-setting machine
at almost 270 degrees fahrenheit.
the continuous heat permanently sets it,
much the way a curling iron sets hair.
after 45 seconds of heat-setting,
the yarn is rewound on spools.
those spools then go to the tufting department,
where the carpet-making begins.
a standard 144-inch-wide carpet
is made from 1,440 spools of yarn.
each spool feeds into a plastic tube,
which feeds into the tufting machine,
where the 1,440 lines of yarn
feed 1,440 tufting needles.
the needles stitch the yarn
into a canvas backing made of polypropylene.
with slow motion,
you can see the yarn being hooked on the canvas
then cut underneath into carpet pile.
up to 12 needles work each inch of canvas.
the result is a pile carpet in the standard 12-foot width.
next they dye it.
for multicolored carpets,
they use a machine called a chromojet.
it works much the way a computer ink-jet printer does,
forcing streams of dye in different colors
into the carpet fibers.
the more complicated and colorful the design,
the more often the machine passes over the carpet.
for solid-color dyeing, there's
a mixer in each dye reservoir
to keep the color even.
they soak the carpet for four hours
in a hot bath of dye and water
heated to 212 degrees fahrenheit.
another method uses heat and air pressure in an autoclave.
what the bath method does in four hours,
this method does in just 30 minutes
and with more carpets at a time.
once the dyeing is finished,
they apply a water-based glue to a polypropylene backing
then put the backing over the original canvas backing,
locking the carpet fibers in place.
then it's on to what's called the marriage roll,
a roller press that marries the two backings together.
after a quick run through an oven
to make the water and the glue evaporate,
they cut the finished carpet into rolls.
a standard roll is 100 feet long.
narrator: researchers have invented a pollution-free car
that runs on hydrogen.
the research team modified the standard car engine
to burn hydrogen instead of gasoline.
now they have to figure out
how to prevent the hydrogen tank
from blowing up in a collision.
drinking water that's fresh, clean, and crystal-clear
is something many of us take for granted.
we might not give it a second thought,
but between the source and our tap,
a lot happens to make that water fit to drink.
our water may come from mother nature,
but it's far from pristine.
it starts its journey to the treatment plant
through a water-intake pipe.
on the wall of that pipe, about 6 1/2 feet down,
is a 6-inch hole.
covering that hole is a metal grill
designed to keep out large debris, such as tree branches.
the water flows to the pumping station,
where it goes through a preliminary screening.
a giant revolving screen removes
fish, garbage, and grass.
once they remove the debris,
a low-pressure pump moves the water into the treatment plant.
the untreated water, called raw water,
is dirty and smelly.
they first add a powerful form of the chemical element carbon
called activated carbon.
it absorbs contaminants such as solvents and pesticides.
that rids the water of bad taste
and odor.
from there,
the water then goes through a series of mixing tanks.
the first tank holds a chemical
called aluminum sulfate.
it acts as a coagulant,
a substance that thickens liquid into globs.
in the raw water,
the aluminum sulfate forms tiny,
sticky globs called flocks.
bacteria, mud, and other impurities
stick to those flocks.
then the flock-filled water
moves on to the second mixing tank.
the second tank holds a chemical called polymer,
which is essential to the next step of the process,
called sedimentation.
five pipes inject the water with
superfine particles of sand,
called microsand.
the polymer coats the sand, making it sticky.
the grains of sand then stick to the flocks in the raw water,
weighing them down even more.
the water then flows into a settling tank,
where the flocks, because they're heavier,
settle to the bottom.
you can see the result in this demonstration.
the water is finally clear, but it's far from drinkable
because it's still full of bacteria, viruses,
and other organic matter.
so, on to the next step -- filtration.
the water flows onto the top of the filter
then trickles downward,
passing through a layer of anthracite, a type of coal,
then through a layer of sand.
this filters out any remaining particles,
which then flow to the middle.
but the water is still teeming with bacteria and viruses,
so it has to be disinfected.
they add 1.9 milligrams of chlorine
for every 4 cups of water,
enough to kill off those germs and bugs.
then they add a mineral called silicate
to prevent calcium buildup from blocking our water pipes.
the treatment plant
sends water samples to a government inspector,
who continuously monitors the water supply
to ensure it meets safety standards.
the amount of chlorine remaining in our drinking water
is 20 millionths of an ounce per liter.
the chlorine gas the plant uses
is highly toxic.
should any leak out,
emergency teams would have to evacuate a 6-mile radius.
so the plant stores the drums of chlorine
in a high-security area.
it's taken about 45 minutes
to turn raw water into treated water.
now these electric motors
will pump it through underground
pipes, right to your tap.
narrator: short-sightedness, far-sightedness, and astigmatism
are all due to light not focusing precisely
onto the retina.
surgeons can correct this by using a laser
to reshape the curvature of the front surface of the eye,
called the cornea.
the surgeon operates on one eye at a time.
he cleans the eye, the lid, and
the lashes with antiseptic...
and administers anesthetic drops
to freeze the eye and lid.
he opens the lid wide with a speculum
then rinses the eye with a saline solution.
everything's frozen, so the patient doesn't feel a thing.
next -- antibiotic drops to prevent infection.
before every operation, the surgeon tests the equipment.
he fires the laser on a metal plate
to test its energy level.
the surgeon administers a few more anesthetic drops...
...then inspects the microkeratome,
the device he'll use to lift a very thin layer
from the outer surface of the eye.
he also measures the patient's cornea
using an ultrasonic instrument.
the cornea must be a minimum thickness
for it to be safely reshaped.
the surgeon uses the speculum again to prop the lid open.
then he begins the operation.
he marks the eye with sterile ink,
reference marks he'll use later.
next he positions a metal ring around the cornea.
the ring is attached to a suction pump
so it clings to the eye.
like holding a tomato steady while you slice it,
it holds the eye steady while the surgeon cuts the tissue.
the surgeon lubricates the eye with sterile water
then mops up the excess water with a small, absorbent sponge.
then he takes the microkeratome
and slips it into grooves in the metal suction ring.
in a matter of seconds, the device moves across the eye,
cutting open a flap of tissue,
the same way a carpenter's plane
shaves a layer of wood.
the surgeon uses a sterile sponge ring
to keep tears from contaminating the cornea.
he folds back the flap of tissue, exposing the cornea.
he mops up the excess liquid...
...then starts up the laser.
meanwhile, a tiny sponge keeps the flap moist.
the laser, an invisible light,
fires in pulses -- 50 pulses per second.
each pulse vaporizes an area of corneal tissue
100 thousandths of an inch thick.
the laser has been computer-programmed beforehand
so it knows exactly how to reshape the cornea
to give most patients 20/20 vision.
in less than a minute, it's done.
the surgeon removes the sponge
and then using those little ink marks he made earlier
as reference points,
folds the flap back to its original position.
if the flap isn't precisely where it was before,
the patient will have distorted vision.
using a syringe that flushes the area with sterile water,
the surgeon carefully smoothes the flap
the same way you'd smooth out a tablecloth.
then he removes the sponge ring.
within 45 seconds,
the negative pressure inside the
cornea sucks the flap back on.
the flap literally seals itself.
with a sponge, the surgeon dabs up any excess water.
he applies antibiotic drops as a preventive measure
then inspects the microkeratome again
before moving on to the other eye.
he takes the speculum off, tapes the eye closed,
then performs the same operation
on the other eye.
when that's done, the surgeon uses a high-powered microscope
to make sure the flaps are wrinkle-free.
the patient wears protection shields until the next morning
then overnight for a week.
narrator: the best guitars come
from trees about 800 years old,
trees with enough rings in their trucks
to provide wood with a tight and straight grain,
wood flexible enough to vibrate,
yet strong enough to withstand the pull of the guitar strings.
the guitar traveled from north africa to europe
with the moors, who invaded spain in the 8th century.
in time, the guitar became the signature instrument
of spanish flamenco music
and the trademark of the singing cowboy.
in the 1930s,
the acoustic guitar debuted as a jazz instrument.
by the 1960s, as the electric guitar took over rock 'n' roll,
the acoustic guitar remained a staple of the folk-music scene.
they use spruce or cedar
because those woods are lightweight and vibrate well.
using a 30-ton press that works like a cookie cutter,
they punch out the shape of the guitar.
the size of the sound hole
affects how the guitar will sound --
the larger the hole, the more treble,
the smaller the hole, the more bass.
then they glue on a wood inlay decoration called a rosette.
next they make the sides of the guitar.
they first immerse wood pieces in boiling water
for about 15 seconds...
...then place them in a heated press to make the curve.
the press applies heat from both the top and the bottom
for about a minute.
then they connect the two sides
with blocks of wood made of either mahogany or poplar.
one is glued and clamped at the
bottom, the other at the top.
then they glue on and clamp a wooden lining
which will connect the sides to the top and back.
those little cuts give it flexibility around the curves.
then with a hand router,
they carefully notch the lining
to receive four wooden braces
to support the back of the guitar.
strategically placed braces help the top of the guitar
withstand the tension of the strings.
they also equalize sound frequencies
by controlling vibration differently at different spots.
after a vacuum press makes the bracing adhere evenly,
they glue on the top and bottom.
the body of the guitar is now assembled.
it goes into a press, then a drying rack for several hours.
next they glue on a plastic binding
to protect the guitar's edges.
then comes a fine sanding.
next a machine with a special sensor
measures the precise angle
at which the body and neck of the guitar
will later be attached.
the angle is critical for sound quality.
it drills the holes and sands the pieces accordingly.
next they apply lacquer --
four to eight coats, depending on the finish.
the fingerboard is made of rosewood or ebony.
the metal frets separate the halftones on the musical scale.
an adjustable rod goes inside the neck.
this lets the neck adapt to the different tensions
that different types of strings
require.
they glue the fingerboard on the neck...
...then vacuum-press it to make sure it adheres evenly.
next they install the machine heads
on which the strings will be wound.
the rod in the neck slips into a groove on the body.
the neck is then bolted and clamped until the glue dries.
next they glue on the bridge,
securing it with temporary screws and a clamp.
then they glue on the headstock nut,
a hard, plastic piece that spaces the strings evenly.
next comes the saddle, then the bridge pins,
which lock the strings in the bridge.
finally they string the guitar using an electric winder.
because of all the glue-drying time,
it takes three weeks to make a guitar.
the wood will become suppler the more the guitar is played,
so as the guitar ages, the better it will sound.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...