-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made,"
gummies,
aluminum cans,
fish farming, and bronze sculptures.
there's nothing kids love more
than candies they can pull and stretch,
which probably explains why gummy candies and licorice
have always been stick-to-your-teeth favorites,
except with parents who don't have a family dental plan.
everyone calls this red licorice,
but there's actually no licorice root in it.
the ingredients are wheat, sugar, and corn syrup,
with red food dye
and both artificial and natural strawberry flavoring.
they cook the mixture for 2 hours at 216 degrees.
this slowly forms a thick paste.
they cool it down, then put it through extruders.
the extruders work like icing nozzles,
shaping the paste into a design
such as the twirls we see here.
a water-lubricated knife slices the continuous strips
into 7- and 8-inch lengths.
the water also rinses off any licorice buildup on the blade.
the cut licorice goes on aluminum trays.
the stacks of trays then go into an oven
to dry for 8 hours at 140 degrees.
as the excess moisture evaporates,
the licorice shrivels.
workers weigh the correct amount
of licorice for each package.
to make gummy candies,
they use what are called printing boards --
large sheets with raised shapes.
to make gummy worms, for example,
they mount the gummy-worm board
on a stamping machine.
the machine then stamps the worm shapes
onto trays of cornstarch.
this creates a series of cornstarch molds
for the gummy worms.
while that's going on,
another machine mixes gelatin, sugar, corn syrup,
color, and flavoring and cooks the mixture at 240 degrees.
a machine called the depositor
pours the mixture into the cornstarch worm molds.
the molds then go into a refrigerated room.
in 12 to 15 hours, the candies cool and solidify.
a machine then flips the candies
out of the trays.
the cornstarch molds disintegrate.
as they fall downward, the machine sifts out the lumps,
then recycles the used cornstarch
into new cornstarch trays for the next batch.
the candies go through a cleaner.
as they spin, air nozzles blast off the cornstarch.
the next drum coats the candies
with mineral oil
to make them shiny.
children love gummy worms
because they're gooey and slippery and wiggly,
but it's not just kids who are hooked on them.
many fishermen actually use them for bait.
before packaging the candies,
the workers weed out any that are stretched out
or stuck together.
wonder if they get to eat the rejects?
narrator: a prion is what causes
killer neurological diseases
such as mad cow in animals and creutzfeldt-jakob in humans.
it's a protein normally found in the membranes of cells.
scientists are trying to determine
what changes that protein to an abnormal form
to cause these fatal brain diseases.
the next time you buy a canned soft drink, consider this --
that aluminum can will always be recyclable.
unlike plastic, aluminum never deteriorates,
no matter how often it's melted down and used again.
aluminum cans are so lightweight
that it's hard to believe
they're made from a huge roll of aluminum sheeting
that weighs almost 10 tons.
the sheet is about 5 feet wide
and as thin as construction paper.
a roll like this is long enough
to make three-quarters of a million drink cans.
the sheet feeds into a press that punches out round pieces
that will be formed into cans.
the punch press actually performs two operations.
it punches out a disc 5 1/2 inches in diameter,
then bends it into a cup.
what's left of the sheet
gets compacted and sent back to the aluminum factory,
where it's recycled into new rolls.
the cup goes into a machine
called the draw-and-iron body maker.
a tool draws out the aluminum, forming the body of the can.
the tool is lubricated so it won't tear the aluminum
while stretching it.
the lubricant also acts as a coolant
because the aluminum heats up as it's being worked.
once the body is formed,
a trimmer cleans and straightens the edge.
now the cans move along upside down on the conveyer belt
over to the washer.
the washer performs a 6-stage cleaning.
the first two washes are in hydrofluoric acid
at 140 degrees.
the last four washes are in deionized water,
neutral water with no ph, also at 140 degrees.
the cans come out of the washer
and go under a hot-air dryer.
they're now shiny because the hydrofluoric-acid wash
removed a thin surface layer of aluminum.
next, a roller passes over the cans,
coating the bottom rims with varnish.
this varnish coating
allows the cans to slide easily
on the conveyer belts
and into vending machines.
it shows up as a blue ring under an ultraviolet light.
the cans are now ready to be printed.
this rotation printing system can apply up to five colors,
one at a time.
the machine then applies a layer
of varnish to protect the ink.
this is what the print and varnish process
looks like in slow motion,
and here's the actual speed -- 1,800 cans per minute.
next, the cans fly through an oven
that instantly hardens the ink
and dries the protective varnish.
the next machine
sprays a water-based varnish on the inside of the cans.
this creates a barrier between the drink and the aluminum,
so the drink won't end up tasting like metal.
it also prevents the aluminum
from being eaten away from the inside
by the acid in carbonated drinks.
next, the cans go through a machine called the necker
which forms a 2-inch neck on the can.
this is done gradually in 11 steps,
so as not to puncture the paper-thin aluminum.
the next machine, called the flanger,
forms a curved-over edge at the top of the can,
which will later attach to the pull-tab cover.
the cans pass through a sophisticated vision system
that photographs the inside of each can.
any can that doesn't meet standards,
that has a bump or ink inside, for example,
is automatically removed from the production line.
they strap the finished cans onto a pallet.
from here, they're shipped to the drink company,
which fills them and then attaches the pull-tab cover.
narrator: fish farming generates about 20%
of the world's fish production.
some fish farms are very high tech,
while others use more traditional methods.
fish farming began in 2000 b.c.
if these rainbow trout
are going to have the energy to make baby trout,
they'll have to be well fed.
on today's menu -- brown shrimp.
the fish farmer gives the mating process a hand.
he takes the female fish
and presses on her belly to squeeze out her eggs.
a 1-pound fish has about 1,000 eggs.
it takes about a minute to get them out.
next, he takes the male fish and squeezes out his sperm.
this also takes about a minute.
the fertilization process is pretty low tech --
no microscopes, no test tubes.
the farmer mixes the eggs and sperm by hand.
he then rinses the eggs with clean water.
he repeats this step seven or eight times
until the water runs clear.
the eggs that stay at the surface are duds,
so they're discarded.
the farmer transfers the good eggs to bottles,
then fills the bottles to the top with water.
the eggs incubate for about a month.
by the 25-day mark, if an egg is alive,
two little black dots appear --
fish eyes.
after the incubation period,
the farmer empties the bottles
and spreads the eggs on a surface with slats.
the eggs lie here underwater...
...until they hatch 10 to 15 days later.
the newly hatched trout
swim down through the slats into the basin below.
the baby trout feed off their placenta for the first 18 days.
after that, they eat special trout food made of fish meal.
the trout grow to about 8 inches long
by the age of 8 months.
at that point, the smaller trout
swimming around them
start looking pretty appetizing.
so the farmer has to classify the fish by size
and move them into separate basins.
trout reach adulthood at the age
of a year and a half.
now the farmer transfers them into his man-made lake.
from here, the fish will go to market.
but before they leave, the farmer mates them,
starting the cycle all over again.
narrator: bronze is the oldest metal alloy known to man.
it is ideal for casting works of art because, when molten,
it flows into even the tiniest crevices of a mold.
this allows sculptors to achieve
incredible detail in their work.
man first discovered how to cast metal around 3500 b.c.,
during the period known as the bronze age.
many civilizations honored their royalty and gods
with bronze statues.
when it comes to art,
the late 19th-century french sculptor auguste rodin
was the master.
they say his bronzes
were more lifelike than the subjects themselves.
bronze is also a popular medium
for modern art.
sculptors first carve a replica
of their sculpture from wood
or shape it out of a plaster or clay.
they coat it with a lubricant...
then with silicone rubber.
when the rubber hardens about six hours later,
the lubricated replica slips out easily,
leaving a detailed rubber mold.
next, they pour hot wax into the mold.
the wax cools in about 15 minutes,
leaving an exact wax replica of the sculpture.
next, they attach what's called a sprew --
a wax channel that will funnel the molten bronze into the mold.
they dip the wax replica into a ceramic material.
then coat it with powdered silicone,
a common mineral, to strengthen the ceramic.
next stop -- an autoclave.
in about 10 minutes, under the machine's hot steam pressure,
the wax inside the ceramic shell
melts away,
leaving a hardened and hollow ceramic mold.
that mold goes into a kiln at 1,560 degrees.
after two hours, it's fired.
this is the finished mold into which the bronze will be cast.
at the foundry, they heat the bronze to 2,084 degrees...
then carefully pour it into the mold.
the molten metal takes just a few minutes to solidify.
then they chisel off the ceramic casing
to reveal the bronze statue inside.
they sandblast the statue to remove the ceramic residue.
then, they saw off the sprew.
they weld shut any holes or other imperfections...
then polish the statue using various abrasive heads.
they heat the statue, then spray on an acid coating.
this coating, called patina,
gives the bronze its shimmer and richness of color.
finally, a coat of wax makes the statue shine.