-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
individual transporters...
...cedar canoes...
...and electric guitars.
it's the world's first self-balancing,
electrically powered personal transportation device.
built-in sensors and an onboard computer
keep this $6,000 vehicle upright
as it zooms around,
up to three times faster than walking speed.
perfect for large warehouses, delivery routes,
or anyone who just wants a lift.
tough, lightweight construction materials
enable the transporter
to safely take you almost anywhere
you'd otherwise walk or run.
this aluminum chassis will house
the vehicle's electronics.
it can withstand an impact force
equivalent to the weight of three large cars.
using a press, a worker attaches
couplings to two motors.
these couplings will connect the
motors to gearboxes later on.
for safety reasons,
many of the transporter's components are doubled.
normally, they'll share tasks equally,
but any of the twin parts can do
all the work if the other fails.
it's what the industry calls redundancy.
using three screws on each side,
she installs the motors into the chassis.
the worker then installs two controller boards
in the top side of the chassis.
microprocessors in these boards
control the motors.
then she adds what's called the balance-sensor assembly.
this includes five gyroscopes
and two components called fluid-tilt sensors.
these instruments gauge the vehicle's position
relative to the ground.
the controller boards check these instruments
100 times per second
and adjust the vehicle
by rolling the wheels forward or backward
when the rider leans either way.
next come wire clusters called harnesses.
they connect the vehicle's batteries to the control shaft.
the chassis cover doubles as a floor plate
for the rider to stand on.
when you step on, your weight pushes four rubber buttons.
these disrupt an optical beam on the controller board,
telling the transporter it has a rider.
the harnesses fit through holes
in the cover,
which attaches with eight screws.
next, she connects the harnesses
to a power converter
in the base of the control shaft.
the power converter uses household electricity
to recharge the batteries.
inside the gearbox,
four gears transfer power from the motor and turn the wheels.
the gears' teeth are cut on an angle
so they engage gradually and more smoothly.
this keeps the vehicle's noise to a relatively low hum.
the worker tightly secures the gearboxes
to the chassis with a mallet.
then she opens a waterproof rubber seal
and plugs in the machine's power cord.
she tests the electrical system
to ensure that it's grounded
and that there's no short circuit.
next, she uses five screws
to attach one of two plastic fenders.
a tapered metal hub connects each wheel to its gearbox.
the wheels are about the height
of a small bicycle tire
but three times wider.
a molded rubber and metal mat covers the floor plate
and snaps into place on both fenders.
after flipping the chassis,
a worker connects two batteries
to the controller boards.
when you plug the batteries into a wall socket,
they recharge in about eight hours.
the transporter runs as far as 23 miles on a single charge,
depending on the terrain.
this machine tests the rider-detect buttons
by applying pressure in a random pattern.
the rider and cargo must weigh at least 99 pounds
but no more than 260 pounds.
the machine also tests the wheels and motors.
next, the handlebar on the control shaft.
to steer, you turn the handgrip
left or right.
the motor responds by spinning
one wheel faster than the other.
you could also spin the wheels on opposite directions
to make the vehicle pivot.
ignition keys with computer chips in them
restrict traveling speeds
to either 5 1/2, 10, or 12 1/2 miles per hour.
the keys also instruct the vehicle to make slow,
medium, or sharp turns.
now the fun part -- taking each
transporter for a test-drive.
the tester listens for unusual sounds
and checks for vibrations coming from the gearboxes.
he feels how quickly and reliably the controls respond.
he runs the transporter up small inclines.
it's designed to conquer slopes
of up to 20 degrees,
depending on traction with the ground and the weight on board.
it goes down over a sidewalk curb just as easily.
only after this thorough test-drive
is the transporter ready for its first real trip.
narrator: canoes are truly vessels of history,
dating back as far as 10,000 years.
native north americans made them
with frames of wooden ribs
covered with bark.
they used these boats to fish, travel, and trade.
today's canoes blend traditional construction
with some high-tech materials
for even greater durability.
most of this boat's made of white cedar,
which is lightweight and weatherproof.
but for reinforcement,
the rim and leading edges
are made of ash, a heavier wood.
construction starts
with an upside-down template of the canoe
that's 15 1/2 feet long.
a worker clamps two long strips
of ash, called gunwales,
to create the canoe's inner rim,
then adds similar strips curbing
along the two extremities.
he'll attach the rest of the skeleton to this rim.
workers soften what will be the boat's cedar ribs
in nearly boiling water for 45 minutes.
the ribs are 2 inches wide and almost a half-inch thick.
the hot water makes them relatively pliable.
using a hammer for leverage,
they simply bend the ribs over the template.
steel guiding strips ensure the
ribs are 1 3/4 of an inch apart.
with a pneumatic staple gun,
workers fire two stainless-steel staples
through each end of the ribs and into the gunwales.
cement blocks weigh down some of the 43 ribs
that workers secure over the entire canoe.
at this point, the ribs measure
between 3 and 5 feet long,
depending on the area they're covering.
the workers will later trim the ends to align them.
next, workers mark the center line
along the bottom of the boat with a chalk line.
this is where they'll put the first cedar plank
to create the skin of the boat.
they lay 18 rows of planks on the boat
and use a box cutter to shape the ends into a curve.
they secure the planks with brass tacks.
brass because it's rust-resistant
and its color blends well with the blond wood.
since the planks are straight-angled,
this process leaves some wedge-like spaces
they'll cover separately.
they cut thin wedges of wood to cover the remaining spaces.
it takes 8 hours and 2,500 tacks
to fit all the planks on the boat.
in total, it takes one person 30 hours to make one canoe.
using a circular saw,
a worker trims the excess from the ends of the ribs.
then two workers lift the boat off the template,
flip it right-side up,
and set it down to rest on two sawhorses.
here, a worker feels inside the boat
for any protruding tacks.
he uses a hammer and metal block
to flatten them.
most were deflected earlier
when they hit the metal guide strips on the template.
a worker tightens a nylon string
between the gunwales,
bringing the boats extremities together in points.
he joins the tips of the gunwales with a screw
at both ends of the boat.
then he installs triangular pieces of mahogany.
this hardwood stands out visually when stained
and also reinforces the ends of the boat.
workers then trim and close off the ends.
next, they attach two more gunwales with 44 screws
to create the outer rim of the boat.
to protect the wood
and make its surface watertight,
workers cover the bottom of
the canoe with fiberglass cloth.
then they seal it with three coats of clear epoxy resin,
which will need up to two hours
of drying time between coats.
workers reinforce the front and back of the boat
with more fiberglass and more resin.
they do this because these areas
will hit rocks in the shore
more often than other parts.
a worker fills holes he drilled
through the bottom of the boat
with silicone.
this helps attach the keel, the spine of the boat,
as well as two long brass components on top of the keel.
workers complete this step by flipping the canoe
and attaching 37 screws through the silicone
and into the keel.
after thawing frozen strips of rawhide leather in water,
a worker cuts holes in them.
these holes enable her to weave the strips together
to cover the canoe's two ash-wood seats.
it takes her about an hour
to weave the required 65 feet of rawhide.
the pattern is similar to what you see
on traditional snowshoes.
it takes two days
for the leather strips to dry out and tighten.
workers then protect and strengthen them
with marine varnish.
then they install the seats inside the boat
with four brass bolts.
next comes the yoke,
a bar running across the width of the boat.
it's designed to fit on your shoulders
when you carry the boat upside down.
the other bar is for securing gear safely
while you're out paddling on the water.
bon voyage.
narrator: the electric guitar dates back to the 1920s.
the original idea was to amplify
the sound of the acoustic guitar.
the first commercially successful model
came out in 1932.
by the 1950s, though,
the instrument underwent a radical change,
its body evolving from the traditional hollow shape
to a thin, solid block of wood.
guitar bodies are usually made of mahogany, poplar,
or certain maple species --
lightweight woods that are flexible enough
to produce the right balance of treble, midrange,
and bass vibrations.
workers first saw a plank of wood into specific widths.
they plane the pieces to a specific thickness,
usually in the range of 2 to 4 inches.
then they mark them with the same number
so they'll end up in the same guitar.
mixing pieces from different planks
would combine different wood densities
and make the body vibrate unevenly.
damp wood tends to warp,
so the pieces have to go into a heated room
until their moisture content drops to less than 6%.
this takes about two months.
once the wood dries out,
workers glue and clamp the pieces together,
setting them in a vise for three
hours until the glue dries.
the water-based glue re-wets part of the wood,
so the block has to go back into the drying room
for another two months.
when it comes out, it goes onto a holding device.
then a computer-guided cutting machine
uses eight different heads, one after another,
to gradually carve the body shape.
this is a semi-acoustic model,
so the body has some hollowed-out areas.
after a fine sanding to smooth the surface,
they trim the contour at a 45-degree angle
using a small stainless-steel blade.
then they sand again.
by this point, they've also inserted round metal fixtures
to hold the bolts that will attach the body and neck.
to construct the neck,
they slice a piece of mahogany or hard-rock maple in two
using a diamond-edged saw for a perfect cut.
then they glue a .05-inch-thick
sheet of maple veneer
onto one piece.
this will be the front surface of the neck.
now they flip the piece over and glue it to the other one.
flipping inverts the wood grain.
this strengthens the neck,
enabling it to withstand the tension of the guitar strings.
the maple veneer hides and reinforces the joint.
they clamp the components in a vise for three hours
until the glue sets.
a computer-guided cutting machine contours the neck shape
and cuts a groove down the middle
for a steel bar called the truss rod.
when the neck bows from tension
created by heavy-gauge strings,
you straighten it
by adjusting the protruding end
of the truss rod.
next, the fingerboard --
the surface against which you press the strings
to produce different notes and chords.
it's made of maple, ebony, or rosewood.
after gluing the fingerboard over the truss rod,
they place the neck into a vacuum press.
the press sucks out all the air,
compressing the components into one solid unit.
once the glue dries,
the neck goes onto a
computer-guided carving machine.
its 12 different cutting heads finalize the shape.
next, a 22-blade saw
simultaneously cuts very precise
slots for 22 fret wires,
the metal lines on the fingerboard.
a worker rounds off and smoothes
the back of the neck
against a belt sander...
...then installs the fret wires.
the wires are made of nickel and lead.
they have teeth on the bottom that grab the wood.
that's why it's essential
that the slots be a very precise
width and depth.
finally, they run the sides of the neck
against the sanding belt.
this trims off the excess fret wire
and rounds off the edges of the fingerboard.
back to the body now.
a worker puts it in a silk-screen printer
to apply the company name.
the ink dries in just seconds under ultraviolet light.
after applying a sealant to block the wood's pores,
they spray on up to 22 coats of wood stain and lacquer.
this protects the wood
and gives it a semi- or high-gloss finish.
narrator: now onto the mechanics.
an electric guitar works like this.
a magnet-and-coil assembly called a pickup
works like a mini-microphone.
it picks up the sound vibrations
of the strings
and sends them to an amplifier
which sends them to a speaker
which emits that trademark electric-guitar sound.
before installing the electronic
components, though,
a few final steps.
after a 6-week curing period,
they wet-sand the painted and lacquered wood,
then buff until the surface is so glossy
it produces a mirror finish.
then they polish it with wax.
if the frets aren't level, the guitar will buzz,
so workers color the top of each fret with a marker,
then run a sheet of fine sandpaper
down the fingerboard.
the ink rubs off on any frets that are higher than the rest
and have to be filed down.
the filings flatten the fret's edges,
so workers round them off using a special curved file.
then, with very fine sandpaper,
they buff away the filing marks.
they clean the fingerboard with mineral oil.
this also nourishes the rosewood
so it won't dry out and crack.
now they turn an allen key in the truss rod
to straighten out the neck.
this gauge measures the curve.
when the needle hits zero,
the neck is perfectly straight.
now the six tuning keys --
one for each string.
depending on the model,
these steel keys are plated with either gold or nickel
or painted black.
you turn the black acrylic peg
to tighten or loosen the string
for tuning.
workers use a digital gauge
to measure the height of the nut --
a thin piece of either bone or very hard plastic
with six slots to space the strings.
if it isn't in precisely the right position,
tuning will be off and the strings will buzz.
now the neck is ready to join the body,
courtesy of four bolts driven
from the back of the instrument.
they fit into those round metal fixtures
we saw in the previous segment.
and now the electronic components.
workers begin by soldering control knobs
for the volume and tone
to the pickup selector switch --
the switch that activates any of the pickups --
sets of magnets with wire coiled around them.
like miniature microphones,
they pick up the sound vibrations
entering their magnetic field,
transform them into electronic signals,
which then go out to the amplifier and speaker.
one pickup will be just above the bridge --
a brass piece that anchors the other end of the strings.
the pickup has one magnet and wire coil for each string.
standard electric guitars don't
have a pickup at the bridge,
but this model has one
to enable the instrument to also
sound like an acoustic guitar.
you can even use the electric and acoustic sounds together.
workers drill holes in the body
for installing the bridge,
using a template as a guide.
they attach the bridge with screws...
...then install the bridge pickup just above it
and the body and neck pickups above that.
then they flip it over
and hook up what's called the tremolo,
a lever-activated set of steel springs
that temporarily loosen the guitar strings.
the musician uses the tremolo on select notes and chords
to create a quivering effect --
that distinctive electric-guitar sound.
the volume and tone knobs come next,
tucked into a cavity in the back,
then secured to the front with a nut.
now the pickup selector switch.
it also comes through the back to the front of the instrument.
then they add the last electronic component --
a jack for the cable going to the amplifier.
they plug in the cable,
and flicking the selector switch,
do a tap test on each pick up.
now it's time to string the guitar.
they pull the steel strings from the back
through the bridge in the front,
then wind them onto the tuning keys
using a drill with a special adaptor.
then it's into a soundproof booth
to tune the guitar with the help
of a digital tuner.
and then it's played for the first time.
[ playing scales ]
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...