narrator: today on "how it's made"...
air filters...
...billiard cues...
...ice sculptures...
...and suits.
pollutants in the air
can make it tough for you to breathe and function.
but pollutants can also affect your car's performance.
it's the reason an air filter is standard equipment
on internal combustion engines.
the filter keeps dirt and particles out of the engine
so it runs smoothly and gives good mileage.
trapping dust and grime is a dirty job,
and it takes its toll.
air filters get clogged and have to be replaced regularly.
so we need a steady supply.
to make an air filter,
an automated spool unwinds thick paper
and feeds it between two rollers.
bumps on the rollers press indentations into the paper.
the short, vertical ones are spacers
to help air flow through the filter.
the long, horizontal lines are the pre-fold creases.
the rollers fold the paper along those lines
as they push it out the other side.
an automated counter keeps track of the folds,
because each filter needs
to have approximately 75 pleats.
now a conveyor belt moves the paper to a circular blade.
a steel bar holds the paper pack down
while the blade slides on a motorized rail,
slicing the paper at the correct number of folds.
the paper pack rolls down the conveyor belt,
heading to the next station.
in the meantime,
a robotic arm sprays liquid wax
onto the aluminum molds
that will be used to shape the
tops and bottoms of the filters.
the carousel turns, positioning
another set for spraying.
the wax will ensure
that nothing sticks to the molds
during the next steps.
now chrome-plated steel screens
fall into a positioning tray.
a robot picks them up with magnets two at a time.
it places them on the bottom mold for the filter.
a platen, or plate, bearing two top molds
flips forward on the carousel.
the carousel turns, and remember the paper packs?
a worker places one in each of those two top molds.
now a robot dispenses a liquid polyurethane mixture
around the screen in the bottom mold.
then the automated platen flips back
so that the top molds with the paper packs face down.
an air cylinder pushes a platen
holding the bottom molds up
to meet the top ones,
and heat triggers this chemical reaction.
the polyurethane swells
and covers the screen and the paper pack,
forming a solid, flexible plastic layer.
a robot with grippers peels the
new air filter out of the mold
and sets it on a cooling rack.
because of the wax sprayed onto the molds,
the robots don't have to work hard
to pull the air filters out.
like well-greased cookie sheets,
nothing gets stuck to the bottom.
after they're cool, the rack tips up,
and the air filters tumble down a slide
to a worker who collects each one.
with a band saw, she trims the excess polyurethane,
or flash, from the rim.
now all that's left is the packaging.
on another assembly line,
a robot prepares to make a radial seal type of filter.
it sprays the no-stick wax
onto the brims of molds that look like inverted top hats.
a small wheel turns
and delivers the molds to a larger assembly wheel.
another robot picks up plastic caps
and places them inside the molds.
then a pneumatic pusher raises the caps,
and nozzles dispense a hot glue bead onto their edges.
another pneumatic pusher tool
forces round packs of pleated
paper out of cylindrical holders
and into the molds.
the big wheel keeps on turning,
positioning the molds
to receive more packs, or tubes,
of filter paper.
the wheel pushes the paper-filled molds
onto a conveyor belt.
and down the line,
a robot pumps a polyurethane mix
into the bottom mold for the filter.
a worker presses the paper-filled top mold onto it.
heat triggers the chemical reaction
that expands the polyurethane,
encasing the bottom of the filter paper
and forming a gasket
that will fit snugly near an engine intake.
the radial air filter is now completely assembled,
and it's taken just 20 minutes.
the filters are ready to work
under the hood of today's automobiles.
narrator: the game of billiards
has been popular
for several hundred years,
dating back as early as the 15th century.
then players used a mace to strike the ball.
when the mace's large head
made it tough to shoot along the rail,
players started using its slimmer tail end.
this led to the invention of the cue stick
so players didn't have to worry
about switching back and forth.
pick a cue, but be selective,
because choosing a stick that feels right for you
pays off when you're behind the eight ball.
to make the butt, or bottom section, of a cue,
they start with a block of expensive bird's-eye maple.
the wood spins on a lathe.
a doughnut-shaped blade moves on rails
and cuts around the circumference,
turning the block into a cylinder.
as it cuts, the shavings are vacuumed away.
now a square-tipped steel cutter
carves into one end of the wood.
it makes a groove that will be used
to attach the butt's forearm to its lower part.
he slides a black plastic ring around the rim
and glues it down.
it's decorative,
but it will also give the cue some stability.
next, he brushes glue on top of it to attach another ring,
this one made of a nickel/silver alloy.
he screws the forearm into the lower part of the butt.
glue oozes out of the joint as the screws tighten.
the forearm is now bonded to the lower part of the cue,
making one butt piece.
then they employ a vertical cnc lathe.
computerized cutters move up on rails,
precisely tapering each butt piece to the desired diameter.
after that, another computerized
tool called a cnc inlay cutter
chisels geometric designs into the cue's forearm.
the same type of cutter
carves matching designs from ebony wood.
a worker removes the ebony cutouts and inspects them.
he handles them cautiously
because the thin strips of wood
are fragile and break easily.
with a stick, he slathers a thick epoxy mixture
into the cue stick's carved-out design.
the ingredients of this high-strength glue
are a trade secret.
next, he presses one of the ebony cutouts
into the glue-filled cavity.
he fits a synthetic ivory cutout
inside of the ebony one,
pressing it down into the glue with big tweezers.
he continues to build the design
with another piece of ebony.
these intricate inlays give the cue some attitude.
a cue stick's good looks can affect a player's mind-set
and give him or her a competitive edge.
this glue may look a bit messy now, but when it dries,
the ample amounts will keep the inlay tight,
preventing air and moisture from
getting in and doing damage.
he inserts little pieces of synthetic stone
as a final touch...
and then presses all the pieces
down with a wood dowel.
next, a computerized drill bores a hole
in the exact center of the joint section.
a second drilling makes a thread inside the hole.
he screws a steel joint pin dappled with glue
into the thread created by the drill,
twisting it tightly with a special tool.
when the joint is fully entrenched,
he unscrews the tool.
and now the butt can be screwed
to the shaft for the game
and then taken apart for transport.
an automated paint gun
sprays clear varnish onto the cue sticks.
a motorized stamping machine
inks the logo onto the cue's butt piece.
and a worker applies glue as the cue stick turns on a lathe.
this is in preparation for the wrap.
then the turning cue pulls linen
thread from a spool,
wrapping itself with the lower section with glue on it.
this linen wrap will make the cue easier to grip
and will absorb moisture.
they roll the cue stick up against
a high-speed cloth buffing wheel
to give it a shine.
now these cue sticks are ready for some serious competition
in the pool hall.
narrator: ice sculptures can make quite an impression
at a party or social engagement.
before they melt, their beauty can be seen and admired.
mass production of ice sculptures is now possible
with new machines and tools.
and the market for ice sculptures is expanding.
it's a curtain of ice,
and it's in demand for big events.
they string beads of ice on plastic-coated aircraft cable.
as it melts, it creates a waterfall effect.
it's guaranteed to make an impression.
but just how do they get this ice to be crystal clear?
they start by tucking
a plastic liner into a big tank.
they pipe filtered water into it.
then a worker places a measuring bar with a dipstick
across the tank.
the dipstick is set at 10 inches.
that's how thick the block of ice needs to be.
he clamps electric submersible pumps on each end of the tank
and positions them underwater at a 45-degree angle.
these pumps are key.
they keep the water moving,
forcing bubbles and impurities to the top
while clear water below freezes.
he shuts the lid to allow the water to freeze.
24 hours into it, he'll remove one of the pumps.
three days later,
he probes the ice under the watery surface with a pick.
it needs to be level,
so he checks the entire ice surface with a measuring bar.
next, he siphons off the excess water with a wet vacuum.
he'll take off a couple of buckets full.
then he attaches a lifting bar
to brackets on each end of the tank
and lifts the 300-pound ice block with a chain hoist.
now he peels away the plastic liner and inspects.
the ice has to be absolutely perfect --
no clouds, cracks, or impurities.
because water expands when it freezes,
the block is a bit too thick,
so they slice off the excess ice
with an electric band saw,
trimming it back to the desired 10-inch mark.
the steel blade cuts cleanly and evenly.
he slides the extra pieces of ice into a heated pit,
where they'll melt and be recycled back into the system.
before the ice is carved, they put the design on paper.
the artist is sketching a liquor luge --
two vodka bottles made of ice, through which drinks will flow.
now its time to cut the ice.
the block turns on a special lathe.
then they propel an electric router
across the spinning block.
the sharp edges of the router cut into the ice.
a guide wheel above the router
follows a plastic outline of a bottle
so it cuts precisely to the design.
all this is done in the freezer.
the temperature in here is
just over 17 degrees fahrenheit.
now the vodka bottle is starting to take shape.
it takes about four minutes for this machine to carve it.
this task couldn't be performed
as quickly or precisely by hand.
after the carving, the worker brushes off the ice shavings.
then its time for the blowtorch.
it melts the frost so the ice looks like glass,
through which you can clearly
see the label and plastic tubing
that have been frozen inside.
now we have the finished vodka luge,
which will be used to serve drinks at parties.
the barman pours the drinks through a funnel at the top,
and the drink chills all the way
down to the martini glass.
if a fish fountain is more your style,
this is how it's done, the old-fashioned way.
the sculptor, armed with a chainsaw,
shapes the ice following a cardboard template.
she smoothes the ice
with an electrically powered disk grinder,
then cuts in detail
by using a die grinder with a triangular bit.
she dusts off the snow...
and then polishes the ice
with a blast from the blowtorch.
now, that's a work of art.
narrator: in today's world, suits are common,
allowing both men and women to dress the part
for any situation --
everyday work or a special occasion.
while men and women may wear different parts of a suit,
the basics of the suit have been
unaltered for over a century --
a jacket and trousers or skirt.
it's a look that's never out of style.
every suit begins with a design on paper.
the style is precisely sketched.
it's a creative process but also highly technical.
he plans the entire outfit, right down to the last stitch.
no detail is left to chance here.
they feed the design data
to this computerized cutting machine.
the blade slices through fabric
placed under paper.
and because it's computerized, it's very precise,
producing pieces that will fit together like a puzzle.
this is how they used to cut the fabric -- by hand.
it was more time-consuming,
and the margin for error was much greater.
now it's time to reinforce the fabric.
she places fusing tape made of fabric onto a sleeve piece
and then sends it to a heat chamber with rollers
that will bond the tape to the material, giving it strength.
next, it's over to the sewing machine.
a worker lines up two sleeve layers,
and it's hands-free from here.
a rail powered by compressed air
descends
and guides the fabric under the needle.
a computer controls the sewing.
this frees up the operator
to continuously feed the machine.
this is an automatic pocket welt machine.
she places the front of a jacket
under a clamp
and puts the welt fabric in the clamp
and a pocket flap at the side.
the clamp automatically slides the fabrics to needles
that sew the welt and flap onto the jacket.
then two tiny knives emerge and cut the pocket open.
the result -- a precisely made
pocket completely by automation.
the only human involvement is to feed the machine
and then collect the finished product.
now over at another station,
an operator irons fusible tape onto the open seams.
this stabilizes them and gives them a crisp finish.
a worker places the front of the jacket
on a headless mannequin called a buck.
a hot metal press moves in,
and the pressing reshapes the jacket
to the contours of the buck.
now she puts a sleeveless jacket
on another buck
and tucks a shoulder pad underneath.
she presses a pedal to activate the machine,
and the hot presses lower,
melting the glue on the shoulder pad,
which fuses it to the jacket.
now to steam the fabric.
another jacket is on another mannequin.
and a worker clamps down the sleeves.
a big steam bag made of porous vinyl swings in,
wafting steam onto the front of the jacket.
at the same time,
hoses pipe steam into the porous mannequin cavity,
so this jacket gets a steam press from both sides.
this machine is a collar master.
she folds the collar into the correct position
and lowers a big fabric-covered
metal press onto the collar
to iron down the fold.
it's time for the auto-jig machine.
it's making an extension piece to the second button
for a pant waistband.
this is the piece
that goes over the second button
on the waistband of dress pants.
it sews and cuts two layers
of fabric that are held in a jig
and then feeds the excess fabric
to a vacuum tube for disposal.
now it's time to define a crease
in a pair of trousers.
an operator slides a pair of pants, inside out,
onto a double rail.
then using a device similar to a caulking gun,
she pipes a silicone-based liquid along the crease line.
the liquid is a perma-crease mixture,
which will give the crease some staying power.
there's also a nib on the end of this gun
which sharpens the crease.
all that stitching and steaming
seems to have gone without a hitch.
but the designer still needs to inspect the work
to see if it measures up to his original concept.
if adjustments have to be made,
he marks the spots.
that's because how it fits
can be just as important as how it looks.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...