-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc.
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
traditional bows...
...coffee machines...
...mascots...
...and hammocks.
when some innovative caveman
invented the bow and arrow,
it was a huge breakthrough.
the discovery turned
the homo sapien
into an efficient
hunter-gatherer.
these days,
archery has made a comeback
in the hunting community,
and it's even been reclassified
as an olympic sport.
today's bows are definitely not
primitive devices.
crafted
with calculated precision,
they make it easier
for you to take your best shot
and hit your intended target.
to make a longbow, a craftsman
cuts six strips of cherry wood
just under a quarter of an inch
using a band saw.
then, with a belt sander,
he repeatedly thins
the wood strips on both sides,
tapering the ends a little
each time.
the tapering gives the wood
some flexibility,
which the bow will need
to launch arrows into the air.
with this band saw,
he now carves a handle
from a piece of wood.
next he brushes superadhesive
glue onto fiberglass strips
and the tapered strips
of cherry wood.
he works swiftly
because the glue will start
to dry in less than an hour.
now he layers the strips.
the fiberglass strips buttress
the six glued wood strips
on either end.
this process
is called lamination.
next he glues the wood handle
to the fiberglass
and wood lamination.
and he tops it
with a piece of masking tape
to protect it
from scratches and glue smudges
during the next steps.
now the laminates
are squeezed together.
he places them on a carved
plywood shape called a bow form.
he positions a steel heat strip,
a rubber hose,
and another plywood form
on top of the laminates.
he clamps it all together,
then inflates the rubber hose
with an air compressor.
the pressure from the hose
combined with the heat
from the metal strip
mold the wood to the bow shape
as the glue sets.
one hour later,
he removes the laminates,
nicely pressed and glued
into more bow-like curves.
now he draws the bow form onto
the newly curved lamination,
following a template
made of fiberglass.
with his band saw,
he cuts the wood
along the lines he's just drawn.
he cuts an arrow shelf.
that's the notch for the arrow
to rest as the archer aims.
then he trims the handle,
making it a little wider
at the center for comfort.
next,
using a coarse-toothed file,
he hollows out little grooves
in the upper and lower limbs
of the bow.
they're called string nocks
and the string
will loop around them.
to strengthen the tips,
he glues little pieces
of fiberglass and moose horn
over them
and the freshly filed nocks.
he clamps it in a vise grip
to set.
when it's dry, he files
through the horn and fiberglass
to bring back the nock groove.
he smoothes it with sandpaper.
now he glues another
piece of wood over the handle
to improve
the look and feel of it.
he clamps it together
while the glue dries,
and three hours later,
he sands it.
next he wraps the handle
in a piece of leather
and stitches it together
with nylon thread
called artificial sinew.
many years ago, they used the
tendons of an animal for thread.
the leather will make
the bow easier to grip.
with a gel pen,
he writes a serial number
on the back of the bow,
along with the draw weight.
this bow will hold about
44 pounds of pressure in check
when it's drawn.
this is a flemish string jig --
a wood fixture with posts on it.
he loops nylon string
around the posts.
this is how he measures
the string.
it's always four inches shorter
than the bow.
he cuts it with a utility knife,
then rolls wax onto it
to make it easier to work with.
he measures some string.
then he twists
16 strands of nylon --
8 black and 8 white -- into
a braid with loops on the ends.
he hooks the string on the nocks
and it's time
for target practice.
as he bends the bow,
energy is stored.
he releases it, and the energy
propels the pointed projectile
right on target.
narrator: coin-operated
coffee machines are a staple
in offices and public places.
years ago,
these machines just weren't able
to produce consistent brews.
and there also wasn't much
choice in brewing style.
but today, even finicky java
junkies drink machine coffee
because the latest machines
have mastered the art
of making delicious coffee
one cup at a time.
this office coffee machine
actually makes several different
types of hot beverages.
and if your employer prepays,
you don't have to insert
any coins.
production begins
with a sheet of steel
about 6 1/2 feet long
by about 1 1/2 feet wide.
this flat, as it's called,
will become the top
and side sections
of the machine's casing.
a computer-guided punch press
makes dozens of perforations
for ventilation
and for the various fittings
the machine will need
in order to function.
a worker puts another sheet
of steel into a press.
this press bends the metal
into 90-degree angles.
this piece will become
the bottom of the casing.
a worker uses
a spot-welding machine
to assemble what's called
the base panel.
this will later house
a waste chute,
overflow sensors, and wires.
another worker coats the casing
with an epoxy-based
paint powder.
this process
statically charges the powder
and draws it to the metal
like a magnet.
excess powder
falls into a barrel below.
here a worker installs a fan
that will vent
the steam and heat
generated inside the machine.
another worker assembles
one of the two
coffee-delivery mechanisms,
called augers.
when the machine's on, they move
the ground coffee to the brewer.
he installs the augers into
what's called the dual hopper.
the hopper's two sections
will hold up to six pounds
of different coffee blends,
such as dark and light roasts.
next he installs what's called
an agitation wheel.
this plastic wheel helps move
the ground coffee along
and prevents it
from getting stuck.
the worker then aligns plastic
couplings on the augers
to mate
with the ingredient dispenser.
the dual hopper attaches
to the ingredient dispenser
with one screw
in a pivoting bracket.
workers also connect power wires
to the dispenser's motor
and to a water-inlet valve.
next they install
a heater and temperature sensor
inside a plastic water tank
that's nearly two gallons large.
this 1,100-watt heater keeps the
water at 200 degrees fahrenheit,
just below boiling.
that's the optimal temperature
for extracting flavor
from ground coffee beans.
after applying stickers
warning service technicians
to turn off the machine
before draining it,
a worker installs
three outlet valves --
one to dispense
hot water for tea,
one for coffee,
and another for hot chocolate.
next come stainless-steel rods
to monitor
the water level inside the tank.
they trigger
an automatic refill mechanism.
the worker connects power wires
to the brewer motor.
then she mounts what's called
the whipper mixing bowl.
this aligns with
the chocolate-syrup dispenser
to prepare the hot chocolate.
next she installs
the brewer-motor assembly
into the machine's casing.
this is the coffee machine's
15-button selection panel.
it lets you select
what type of hot drink to brew,
in what cup size,
and when to start.
the panel
also displays the prices
when the coffee's
not on the house.
once that's hooked up,
workers test the chocolate-syrup
delivery system.
they run water through it
to ensure it doesn't leak.
they also test to see
if the system dispenses
the correct dose of syrup.
one dose is a half ounce --
a tablespoon.
a small cup of hot chocolate
requires two doses.
a large cup requires four.
now they install the brewer.
it works much like
a french press coffee maker,
brewing a separate batch
for each cup.
to test it,
they run water through it
and make sure the selection
panel works properly.
by testing the panel
with the coffee machine closed,
they ensure the circuits
are properly aligned
behind the selection buttons.
depending on how strong
you select your coffee,
a dispenser releases
between .2 and .6 ounces
of ground coffee
into a re-usable nylon filter.
a piston then forces hot water
through the filter
for 10 to 20 seconds, depending
on the size of the cup.
this process extracts
the flavor of the ground beans.
the machine then scrapes away
the coffee grinds
and throws them down
the built-in waste chute.
then it prepares
for the next customer,
and the next delicious cup.
narrator: mascots
are supposed to bring luck,
but the people
who wear mascot costumes
have had a few lucky breaks
themselves in recent years.
the outfits
are much lighter now,
and there's even
an exhaust system
complete with a tiny fan
inside the head
so it's not so hot in there.
that helps the mascot keep his
energy up for the entire game.
this dinosaur mascot
for the lung association
is part of a new breed.
it's really evolved
into something
that's relatively easy
to work in.
to make this dinosaur,
they sketch him out.
then the artist modifies the
figure to human proportions,
targeting a height of 5'10",
which means the costume would
fit performers 5'8" to 6' tall.
the artist designs huge eyes
and a very extravagant mouth,
and not just
for creative reasons.
the large openings will give
the mascot performer room
to see and to breathe
through screens.
now a sculptor carves big pieces
of lightweight,
uncrushable foam.
with a utility knife,
he shapes the dinosaur's head,
based on the design pattern.
traditionally, fiberglass
has been used for mascot heads
but foam is half the weight.
he attaches a battery pack
to the inside of the head,
at the back of the neck,
using velcro.
he tests it to make sure
it has enough juice
to power this tiny,
square exhaust fan,
which is to be placed
inside the head at the top.
then he sprays glue on the foam,
sticking the sculpted layers
of foam together.
now the dinosaur head
is starting to shape up.
he cuts out
those enormous eye holes.
then he tries on the head
for size.
he checks visibility
and ease of movement.
next the sculptor slices
into a very dense piece of foam.
it's dense because it will need
to hold up to heavy traffic.
this is the dinosaur's foot.
he scoops out foam
in the center of the foot,
hollowing out an area.
then he carves out more,
following a pattern
of a size-12 shoe
so that a human foot could fit
inside this big mascot claw.
he rounds the outside of the
foam foot with a belt sander.
now the foot is fully sculpted
and ready
for the fabric department.
there, a worker sprays
heavy-duty glue
onto the outside of the foot,
and stretches
a nylon fleece fabric over it.
the fabric has a lot of give
so that it can be tightly pulled
into the grooves of the foam.
now she sprays adhesive
onto the bottom of it
and cuts off the excess fabric.
she sews the seams
with a very tough thread.
then a worker glues
a rugged rubber sole
onto the bottom
of the dinosaur foot.
this is a toenail made
of nylon stuffed with polyfill.
it takes three hours
to make a foot.
now it's back to the other end.
he glues an eye
onto the mascot head.
the eye is made
of breathable nylon
stretched over a plastic frame.
another worker sews on a horn,
which is made
of fabric-covered foam.
then she stitches on
the nostrils.
and now the mascot
has some expression.
but there's one more step.
he glues a white nylon screen
over the mouth
and sticks
black fabric strips over it
to give the mascot its smile.
now a worker drafts a pattern
for the outer body.
it will go over
an inner-body suit
that will give the mascot
its rotund shape.
she cuts the liner fabric
for the outer body,
following the pattern...
and then follows the same
pattern for the outside fleece.
she sews three layers -- fleece,
foam, and liner -- all together.
this serger machine
cuts off excess fabric,
and it sews and binds the edges.
she hand-stitches the scales
onto the back
of the dinosaur mascot.
and now it's time to give
this mascot suit a test run.
it fits like a glove.
but what's the view like
from the inside of that head?
hmm. not too bad.
this dinosaur mascot suit
is ready to help its user
excite the crowd.
narrator:
when christopher columbus
discovered the new world
back in the 15th century,
he also discovered the hammock.
it was in the west indies
that columbus found natives
lounging in what he later
described as sleeping nets.
and when hammocks were
introduced to the europeans,
they really caught on.
hammocks are still used
centuries later.
hammocks
were once called hamacks
because they were woven with
fibers from the hamack tree.
today they're made
of braided polyester.
to make a hammock, a worker
measures and marks the spots
for holes to be drilled
in a hardwood spreader bar.
he spaces the 22 holes
almost 3 inches apart.
he rounds the edges
of the wooden bar
with a shaped cutter
called a router,
smoothing out any sharp edges
that could jab you
when you climb into the hammock.
using an electric drill,
he makes holes a half inch
in size in the spreader bar.
then, with a countersink,
he scoops out the wood
around the edges of the holes,
to make a gentler slope
for the polyester rope.
he adheres the company's
prepasted label onto the bar.
next, 16 bobbins turn at a speed
that could make you dizzy
just watching.
they're spinning
the polyester cord.
the bobbins
twist the 16 polyester strands,
braiding the strands
into a herringbone pattern
while electrical pulleys
draw them up.
the pulleys drop the cord
in a drum.
now it's all
in the wrist action.
a weaver deftly intertwines
the thick cord
into a triangular shape.
she's making
the hammock's harness.
it's called a clew.
she tugs each row tightly
to a ring at the top
to ensure that the weave
is steadfast.
as she weaves, she drapes
the long pieces of cord
over a wood frame,
to keep them from tangling.
after the triangle is formed,
she checks for errors
in the weave.
now she threads the clew cords
through the holes
in the spreader bar.
she snares a cord
with a large crochet hook.
using the hook,
she threads a cord
through the hole at the furthest
end of the spreader bar
and then knots it.
and she does the same
on the other end of the bar.
while the bar hangs
by the two cords,
she pulls
the rest of the clew cords
through all 22 holes in the bar.
next she positions the spreader
bar under a guide bar
to ensure everything's level.
and she knots
the rest of the cords tightly
onto the underside
of the spreader bar.
it's a critical step.
if there's any slack
in the clew,
the yarn will stretch and
the hammock will be misshapen.
this hammock harness
is now strong enough
to support a 450-pound person.
next she uses
a 10-foot-long cord
to make a chain of small links
by pulling each link
through the previous one.
the top of the chain rope hangs
from a hook, stabilizing it,
and allowing the weaver
to quickly turn the simple cord
into an intricate-looking chain.
now she hooks each end of
the chain onto pins on a loom.
she weaves another cord
into the chain,
threading it
with a crochet hook.
she makes one loop
in about every sixth link
in the chain rope,
and she hooks that cord
onto the same pin as the chain.
there's no rest
for the hammock weaver.
she takes a shuttle,
which is a piece of wood
with 656 feet of cord
wrapped around it.
she pulls it from below up
through the available loops
and then back down,
expertly weaving the web
that is the hammock bed.
she hooks a second chain rope
on the loom,
and threads the edge
of the woven bed to this chain.
now she places the spreader bar
of a finished harness
on one end of the loom.
she lines up the pins of the
loom with the holes of the bar.
she knots the cord on each pin
to a cord from the spreader bar.
she repeats the process
at the other end of the loom,
binding the second harness
to the hammock bed.
she makes one last knot
in the chain...
...and then removes the excess
cord with the heat gun.
the heat gun makes a clean cut
with no ragged edges to unravel.
with high-quality construction,
this hammock will surely provide
years of relaxation.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...