>> narrator: today on "how it's
made"...
magnets...
cooked ham.
silver-plated teapots.
and crash-test dummies.
you can't see or feel the force
causing this globe to levitate,
but it's not magic, it's
magnetic.
an essential part of our daily
lives, magnets are used for a
lot more than just sticking
stuff to the fridge.
they help run motors and
generators and are also found in
computers, televisions, and
microphones.
magnets occur in nature.
but only two centuries ago,
scientists figured out how to
make them using metal and
electricity.
production at the magnet
foundry begins with a creation
of a mold.
a tray containing four magnet
shapes is loaded into a machine
that fills it with sand.
a worker removes the pattern
and smoothes the surface dimpled
by the machine's lid.
then it's back inside.
this time the machine pumps in
gases that chemically alter the
sand, hardening it in a matter
of seconds.
the sand slab is now a
durable mold.
and these molds are made in a
wide variety of shapes and
sizes.
now it's time to mix together
the ingredients for the magnets
themselves.
they include copper, cobalt,
sulfur, nickel, pure iron,
aluminum, and titanium.
all of these metals are
loaded into an electrical
induction furnace.
it generates a pulsating
electromagnetic field that heats
the metal to almost 3,000
degrees fahrenheit, melting
everything into a molten soup.
the metal is poured into the
molds.
because the gases that harden
the sand are highly flammable,
the molds burst into flames.
still ablaze, they slide to
another part of the foundry
where workers knock them to the
floor and bust them open with
sledgehammers.
this lets the air in, cooling
the molds and allowing the
gases to burn off.
all of the pieces are
shoveled into a bin, and
workers separate the metal from
the sand chunks using what
else?
a magnet.
but these metal pieces aren't
yet magnetized themselves.
that will come later.
a set of rings designed for
use in electric motors is
threaded onto a copper pipe.
the ring-covered pipe is placed
in a tube.
then, silica sand is packed in
to hold the rings in position.
both ends of the tube are
sealed with concrete.
then, it's into an electrical
furnace.
it heats the tube until it's
red-hot.
this superheating primes the
rings inside to accept an
electromagnetic field which will
be delivered by this metal rod.
the rod slides down the center
of the copper pipe and is
clamped into place.
water keeps the pipe from
melting as a low-voltage,
high-current charge is delivered
to the rings inside.
workers break open the seal.
the process has left the rings
mildly magnetized.
any rough edges are smoothed
away.
at this point, the magnets
are pretty useless.
but this machine empowers
them with a strong
electromagnetic charge.
the establishment of that
weak magnetic field earlier
ensures that the magnetization
is now properly oriented.
now, that's some serious
magnetic muscle.
the wide array of magnets
manufactured today are critical
to our daily lives because their
invisible power helps keep so
many things running.
up next -- turning raw pork
into a succulent smoked ham.
>> narrator: ham comes from the
hind leg of a pig.
you can buy it raw and cook it
yourself, or you can buy it
already cured and smoked.
you can buy your ham boneless or
with the bone still intact.
bone-in ham has more natural
flavor.
>> narrator: the process
starts with raw hams fresh from
the slaughterhouse.
the factory's automated
sorting system weighs each one,
then knocks it into the
appropriate vat.
by grouping hams of similar size
together, the factory can
better control the quality of
the curing and cooking
processes.
each vat empties into a tumbler
which spins the hams for about
five minutes.
this loosens the skins so that
workers can quickly remove them.
they use an automatic trimming
machine to skin the back
portion, called the butt.
in keeping with traditional
style, the machine leaves just
a small amount of skin on
the thin part of the leg,
called the shank.
now the circular wizard
knife does its magic, removing
all but a thin layer of fat.
finally, the base of the shank,
called the hock, is chopped off.
now a curing solution is
prepared, made of water, sugar,
salt, and a few secret
ingredients.
this mixture gives the ham its
trademark flavor and pink color.
without it, the meat would end
up looking and tasting like a
pork roast.
pipes feed the curing solution
to an injection machine armed
with 138 needles.
as the hams pass below, they're
thoroughly and evenly injected
with solution.
and all that piercing tenderizes
the meat.
next, workers load a machine
called the stuffing horn, which
fires each ham into a
heat-resistant cotton net.
workers seal each one with an
aluminum clip, then cut off the
excess netting.
cooking hams on trays would
flatten the underside.
but hanging them by nets keeps
them nice and round.
the cooking racks are
transferred to a food-processing
oven, the industrial equivalent
of a traditional smokehouse.
hickory wood chips go into the
oven smoker.
then a worker starts her up.
for the next 12 hours, the
hams slow cook at temperatures
ranging between 150 and 180
degrees fahrenheit.
this tenderizes the meat and
gives the smoke ample time to
seep in.
after cooking, the hams get a
cold ten-minute shower.
this rinses away the drippings
that fall from the higher hams
onto the lower ones.
then it's on to the chill
area, where over the next 36
hours, the hams cool to around
30 degrees fahrenheit.
next, the nets come off and
packaging begins.
the factory sells hams whole,
or, using a band saw, slices
them into halves or smaller
sizes such as single-portion ham
steaks.
workers bag the ham in
plastic, then position a
soft, plastic pad over the bone
to prevent any sharp edges from
ripping through the airtight
seal.
each bag is positioned for
sealing.
then, an automated vacuum
chamber descends over each bag,
sucking out the air and sealing
the plastic.
a robotic arm transfers the
hams to a conveyor belt leading
to a hot-water bath.
just five seconds in hot water
is enough to shrink the plastic
tightly around the ham.
this airtight seal will keep
the ham fresh in your
refrigerator for three months,
and up to nine months in
your freezer.
coming up -- the artistry behind
some of the world's finest
teapots.
>> narrator: the mayans
started using pots like these
2,600 years ago, probably for
hot chocolate.
they've evolved since then.
and today, aficionados consider
them essential for that perfect
cup of tea.
silver-plated teapots come in
many different styles, and
making them requires the talent
and skill of an old-world
master.
a century-old hand-circling
machine cuts a perfect circle
out of a brass sheet that's
6/100 of an inch thick.
then the disk heads to the
press.
after lubricating the press
surface with vegetable oil, the
disk is positioned and covered
with a polyurethane stopper.
as the press applies its three
tons of pressure, the die
moves upward, shaping the disk
from underneath.
the stopper, meanwhile,
provides a counterpressure to
keep the die from breaking the
brass as it thins and stretches.
they call this the draft shape.
it then goes into another die
that produces the final shape of
the teapot's base.
next, they solder on the teapot
rim, which was made the same
way.
a craftsman then hammers the
metal to remove any
imperfections left by the
pressings and punches in the
maker's mark.
spinning is another technique
used to form metal teapot parts.
here, a craftsman shapes a
copper teapot mounted on a
lathe.
the metal is decorated using a
technique called hand chasing.
with a paper stencil, he applies
the design in white powder.
he pencil traces the pattern,
then hammers in the design with
a variety of tools.
this intricate process
requires the talented hands of
an expert artisan.
for the teapot spout, workers
press brass plates into left-
and right-side dies.
a quarter-ton press produces
the final spout shape.
soldering paste is brushed onto
the halves.
they're wired together, then
fired to 600 degrees fahrenheit.
the spout gets an acid bath to
remove all of the impurities
left behind from the soldering
process.
workers polish the teapot with
three progressively finer grades
of pumice, which is crushed
volcanic rock.
one final buffing ensures the
surface is perfectly smooth.
with diamond-tipped hand
tools, engravers can etch
anything onto the teapot from
custom designs to company
logos.
workers now screw on the lid,
wire up the teapot, and immerse
it in cleaning chemicals
followed by a silver-plating
bath.
just before shipping, they
attach hardware and perform a
final cleaning.
finally, the teapots are
wrapped in acid-free cellulose
to prevent the silver from
tarnishing.
it takes a highly skilled
team of craftspeople to create
these unique teapot designs
in styles ranging from
elizabethan to ultra modern,
beautiful and functional.
when we return -- bringing
crash-test dummies to life.
>> narrator: crash-test dummies
may look human, but they're
actually high-tech guinea pigs
for a wide range of impact
tests.
so, how do they make dummies
whose form and structure mimic
the human body?
you're about to find out.
crash-test dummies are
designed to take some serious
hits.
automakers use the data they
provide to build safer cars,
vans, and trucks.
a dummy's anatomy is pretty
simple.
beneath its vinyl skin, there's
a metal skeleton made of steel
and aluminum bones.
those bones contain load cells,
electronic devices that measure
crash force.
production of the load cells
begins with a machine that
shapes steel bars using a solid
carbide end mill.
lubricant cools the intense heat
and washes away the metal
particles.
using a precision tool called
the dial indicator, workers
verify the load cell's
dimensions to within 2/1,000
of an inch.
next comes the strain gauge --
the component within the
load cell that measured crash
force.
the hair-width wires that
connect the strain gauges are so
delicate that soldering them
requires a microscope.
the vertebra in the dummy's neck
also contains a load cell.
the strain gage soldered inside
it measures not just lateral and
vertical forces, but also twist,
or torsional force.
the completed bones and
corresponding load cells are
laid out, but they can't be
connected until the dummy's rib
cage is complete.
to make the rib cage, steel
bands are bonded to a flexible
damping material.
this material was originally
designed to deaden sound in
nuclear submarines.
it allows the dummy's rib cage
to compress just like the real
thing.
a technician bolts the
entire rib assembly to the
spinal column and covers it with
a plastic chest plate called a
bib.
the long bones and load-cell
forms are inserted into aluminum
molds.
workers then bolt the molds shut
and pour in liquid vinyl.
the molds bake at around 350
degrees fahrenheit for 10 to 20
minutes.
when they come out, workers cut
away any flash -- the excess
vinyl that oozes out during the
baking process.
then, a technician inspects the
components to ensure an accurate
fit.
this is no ordinary vinyl.
it's specially designed to
resemble human flesh in
consistency and density.
this gives researchers realistic
crash data.
now, it's time to install the
bones into their respective
vinyl compartments, starting
with this tibia or shin bone.
zippers allow the engineers to
easily remove the components
after performing a crash test.
a technician bolts all the
dummy's joints in place and
ensures they have a human-like
range of motion.
using a neck-compression tool,
a technician lines up a load
sensor with the neck
vertebrae and fashions the
completed neck assembly to the
dummy's head.
next, the upper body is
completed.
the thorax is bolted onto the
pelvis, the head and neck
assembly onto the thorax.
then, the vinyl jacket is
fitted over the chest.
finally, the technician bolts
on the limbs.
crash-test dummies range in
size from newborns all the way
up to 225-pound adults
so that auto manufacturers
can be sure their seat belts
and air bags protect everyone
equally well.
it took a full 12 weeks to
make this dummy, and now he's
ready for a life of hard knocks
to make traveling safer for all
of us.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at
sciencechannel.com/howitsmade.