>> today on "how it's made,"
ice-cream treats...
wooden golf clubs...
aircraft wings...
and car-battery recycling.
before refrigeration, ice cream
was a handmade luxury.
ingredients went into a mixing
bowl inside a tub filled with
ice and saltwater.
the salt helped the ice absorb
heat, cooling the mixture to
below freezing.
in the 1920s, commercial
freezers made mass production
possible, and the ice cream
industry was born.
to make ice-cream treats, you
first have to make the ice
cream.
it all begins with fresh cream.
the factory stores it in
refrigerated silos set just a
few degrees above freezing.
the silos feed a high-speed
mixer that blends the cream with
other ingredients.
the main dry ingredients are
powdered skim milk and
plant-based stabilizers and
emulsifiers.
stabilizers prevent the ice
cream from crystallizing, and
emulsifiers allow the mix to
bond with air during the
whipping process.
the other ingredients are sugar
and corn syrup.
after about three minutes of
mixing, a pumping system moves
the mixture into pasteurization
tanks and heats it to 162
degrees for half an hour,
killing any bacteria and
activating the stabilizers.
then the factory homogenizes
the mixture, a process that
breaks up the fat globules,
giving the ice cream a smooth
texture.
the mixture is cooled, and
concentrated vanilla flavoring
is added.
then the concoction is chilled
and whipped for about 15
seconds.
whipping blends the mix with
air, transforming it from a
liquid to a soft solid.
without air, the finished
product would come out looking
like frozen milk rather than ice
cream.
the ice-cream sandwich wafers
are made of chocolate-cake
ingredients.
a filling machine feeds two
lines of wafers toward an
injection pipe.
just as two wafers come
together, the machine injects a
third of a cup of vanilla ice
cream in between.
the pipe's head fits the ice
cream into a rectangular slab
that fits perfectly between the
wafers.
all this happens at a rate of
140 ice-cream sandwiches per
minute.
as the sandwiches move on to
packaging, the filling is still
ice cold from the freezing
phase, so there is no threat of
a meltdown.
the packaging system raises each
sandwich into a wrapper, then
folds and tucks the ends.
the next machine counts the
sandwiches and inserts them into
boxes.
once sealed, the boxes go
directly into a storage freezer
at minus 22 degrees.
on another line, ice-cream
cone production is under way.
a feeder drops prewrapped
sugar cones into holders on a
conveyor belt.
sprayers coat the insides with a
chocolaty layer, which adds
flavor and creates a barrier
between the cones and ice cream,
so the cone remains crispy until
you eat it.
next, nozzles squirt in the
ice-cream filling.
one production line, two
flavors.
one row of cones gets vanilla
ice cream, the other row
chocolate.
now for a tasty surprise in
the cone's core, an injection of
liquid caramel.
this factory also makes
ice-cream cones with chocolate
and strawberry sauce inside.
next, a chocolate-flavored
liquid topping.
then the crunchy finishing
touch, a layer of chocolaty
coated puffed rice.
finally, the cones move under
a lid dispenser that applies a
wax-coated paper lid to each
one.
a heating element instantly
melts the wax, sealing the lids
to the cone's paper sleeve.
from here, the ice-cream cones
go into boxes, then straight
into the freezer, ready to take
a licking.
up next, the forgotten art of
wooden golf clubs.
>> high-tech metal clubs rule
today's golf courses.
but don't count wooden clubs out
of the game yet.
wooden golf clubs are all about
tradition.
golfers have played with them
for centuries.
and some players still prefer
the look and feel of these
finely crafted clubs.
go with the grain, and your golf
game could be on the upswing.
each club head starts with a
log of persimmon wood, which is
a type of ebony.
it's sliced into quarters, and
the lower quality center section
is discarded.
each quarter is cut down into a
workable shape and size.
then it's locked into this
duplicating machine.
a more sculpted piece of wood,
called a "master model," is
placed overhead.
a wheel traces the contours of
the master model and guides a
blade below so that it carves
the rough chunk of wood into a
duplicate of the master model.
the first master model is
swapped out for a more refined
version, and, again, the blade
below copies the shape.
the duplicate stub is cut off,
and it gets a light sanding.
next, using a spinning cutter, a
generous slot is carved into the
face of the club head.
heavy-duty glue is spread in the
slot, and then it's plugged with
an insert made of rigid plastic.
this reinforcement will protect
the club head from the force of
the golf ball.
the overlap is trimmed off, and
the head is sanded until the
plastic insert blends seamlessly
with the wood.
next, a router is used to carve
an hourglass shape into the
bottom of the golf-club head.
this slot will hold the sole
plate, which will add weight and
protect the bottom of club.
the club head can't be more than
three grams off the target
weight.
after factoring the weight of
the sole plate that's still to
be installed, this club head
gets a lead pellet to make it a
little heavier.
an extra hole is drilled in case
more lead needs to be added
later.
then the lead pellet is
press-fit to the club head.
adhesive is slathered into the
slot.
then the stainless-steel sole
plate is installed.
again, sanding smoothes away any
bumps or grooves.
a drill bores a hole in the neck
of the golf-club head, and a
glue-coated metal sleeve slides
into that hole.
then the neck is tapered with a
sanding belt.
a jeweler saw is used to score
the face of the golf-club head.
these lines are critical,
because they help give the ball
spin.
the club head gets a dip in
water-based stain that soaks
into the wood but doesn't
penetrate the metal sole plate.
then, things get messy, as a
pasty substance is rubbed all
over the golf-club head,
plugging the open pores of the
persimmon wood.
it's a crucial step that will
insure a mirror finish down the
line.
the head is numbered to identify
it as a fairway club.
and then the sole plate gets a
good scrubbing with steel wool
to get rid of any fingerprints.
five coats of polyurethane are
sprayed on.
next, the glue-covered end of
the shaft is pushed into the
sleeve and the club head.
the club's weight is fine-tuned
with the addition of some
pulverized lead into the extra
hole drilled earlier.
for a player to hit balls
accurately, each club in the set
has to feel as if it's the same
weight.
so, there's one more weigh-in
before this wooden golf club is
up to par.
finally, it's time to hit the
links with a club that lives up
to tradition.
coming up, crafting the wings
that give us flight.
>> aircraft wings provide the
lift that takes us to the skies.
they're designed to be very
strong and very light.
producing them requires a
strategic balance of old-school
production methods and high-tech
computer-assisted design.
the wing's frame is made up of
three main components, the rear
spar, the main spar, and the
ribs.
the ribs are crafted from
aircraft-grade aluminum.
it's corrosion resistant and has
great strength, allowing it to
resist extreme wind pressure.
a computer-guided stamping
machine punches small holes for
rivets and control cables.
it also stamps larger holes to
reduce overall weight.
workers break attachments called
microjoints and extract the
ribs.
each rib now goes onto a
metal-and-rubber forming die.
a hydraulic press applies 150
tons of pressure, stamping the
rib to the die shape.
using a grinder, workers smooth
out the sharp edges left behind
by the stamping process.
then they peel off the plastic
film that protected the ribs
from scratches.
the factory uses the same
process to construct the main
spar.
the spars run the entire length
of the wing.
it takes even more pressure this
time -- 222 tons -- to bend the
spars into shape.
that's because this aluminum is
three times thicker than that
used for the ribs.
to ensure they've aligned the
ribs perfectly for riveting,
workers push spring clamps into
the spar.
these hold the ribs in position.
they hand drill holes for larger
rivets and smooth out the sharp
edges with a deburring drill.
then, using a pneumatic riveting
gun and bucking bar, they rivet
the ribs to the main spar.
a tiny bucking bar is required
for some of the tighter spaces.
the completed airframe now goes
onto a positioning rack, where
it will get an aluminum covering
they call the wing skin.
workers use spring clamps to
position the top skin onto the
airframe.
they use the same procedure for
the leading-edge wing nose.
once everything's clamped
together, workers permanently
rivet the assembly.
meanwhile, welders fuse the
wing's fuel tank using an argon
gas torch, which contains fewer
contaminants than the typical
acetylene torch.
they fit the tank into the
wing chamber, then secure it by
bolting steel belts on to the
spars.
now they position the tank's
covering plate and screw it
onto the wing.
these holes are for fuel lines
and control cables, which run
the entire length of the wing.
finally, the wingtip is fitted
and bolted on to the wing.
it's made of a lightweight
fiberglass-and-plastic
composite.
the completed wing is now ready
to be bolted on to the aircraft
body.
this wing weighs in at a mere
175 pounds.
but it's certainly no
lightweight when it comes to
strength.
it can withstand nearly 5,500
pounds of wind pressure.
when we return, turning trash
into treasury at a car-battery
recycling plant.
>> car batteries may die, but
that doesn't mean it's the end
of the road for their
components.
these lead-acid batteries are
routinely recycled.
this keeps toxic materials out
of landfills and gives those old
car batteries a lot more
mileage.
this battery may be toast, but
it's not trash, because dead car
batteries are jump-starting a
major recycling industry.
pallets of old batteries are
tipped on to a conveyor belt.
it takes them up into an
enclosed machine that has over
30 rotating hammers.
they smash the old batteries
to bits, and then a screen
filters out the lead-acid paste.
the broken bits of lead and
plastic tumble into a vat of
water.
the lead and other metals sink,
while the lighter plastic pieces
float to the surface -- a
convenient way to sort and
separate the battery components.
once the plastic pieces have
been cleaned, a machine blows
them into the back of a truck.
they'll be taken to a
plastic-recycling plant and
turned into pellets that will
eventually be used in the
production of new car batteries.
a worm screw now moves the lead
and other metals to another part
of the plant for further
processing.
remember that lead-acid paste
screened out of the smashed-up
batteries earlier?
the acid has been neutralized
and turned into water.
this press squeezes the water
out so all that remains is a
lead paste.
it's removed and added to the
pile of lead and other metals.
the water from the
deacidification process contains
some metallic residues, so it's
treated with chemicals that
cause the contaminants to
precipitate, then settle into a
sludge on the bottom of the
tanks.
workers sample the water to make
sure the particles are settling
properly.
they pump out the sludge, then
filter the water, which now
meets regulatory standards and
can be poured down the drain.
the sludge goes into that big
pile of lead and other metals.
a few shovels full of refined
coal are added to the pile as a
processing aid.
then the battery solids head
up a conveyor into a revolving
drier.
the metals spend 20 minutes in
here to remove any excess
moisture.
then it's into a furnace for
10 hours.
the lead melts into a liquid,
and the other metals float to
the surface, allowing them to be
skimmed off.
the molten lead goes into a
steel kettle, where it's mixed
with caustic soda.
this cause some remaining
contaminants to float to the
surface for easy removal.
the liquid lead is now fairly
pure, so it's time to pour.
the lead is pumped into
bar-shaped molds, and any
lingering impurities are skimmed
off.
below, a constant spray of
ice-cold water chills the molds,
and the lead hardens into bars
in just four minutes.
the conveyor winds downward,
and the bars are tapped free of
their molds.
there's enough lead in one of
these bars to make three car
batteries.
they'll be remelted and molded
into battery components.
and the final product is as good
as new...
proving that recycling can give
old car batteries new life while
keeping dangerous substances out
of our landfills.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...