>> narrator: today on "how it's
made"...
pocketknives...
soapstone products...
electric pole transformers...
and traditional snowshoes.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
pocketknives can be used to cut
rope or slice an orange.
just unfold the blade,
and you're good to go.
folding knives actually date
back to ancient rome.
many centuries later, the
smaller pocket-sized versions
came along so people could carry
their knives without shredding
their pockets.
pocketknives can pack a lot of
punch.
they often contain several
blades and tools, all of which
can be retracted into the
handle.
to make pocketknives, rollers
first feed a strip of stainless
steel to a series of dyes.
then dyes punch out blade
shapes.
they cut holes in the handle for
installation, stamp on the
company logo, and create grooves
so the user can get a grip.
a trip into a fiery furnace
hardens the metal.
it's the first step in
heat-treating the blades.
once they're cool, the blade
shapes are placed on the
magnetized rim of a rotating
carousel.
it moves the base of the blades
under an induction-heating coil.
the heat anneals that end,
making it pliable enough to bend
and easier to fit in the
pocketknife handle.
a robot now transfers a blade
shape into a computerized
grinder that bevels the edge but
leaves it blunt.
it won't get its cutting edge
until later.
here you can see the difference
the grinding makes.
vibrating ceramic pellets polish
the blades with paste for 32
hours to achieve a mirror
finish.
a magnetic belt collects them
and transfers them to the next
station.
meanwhile, a rocking cutting
tool carves ridges into a piece
of cow shinbone, which will
adorn the pocketknife handle.
a bag of those ridged shinbones
are dipped in dye, tinting them
a vibrant green.
cow shinbone is just one of the
many materials used to adorn the
knives.
some are synthetic, and some are
natural, like this material --
mammoth ivory.
using epoxy adhesive, workers
decorate these pieces of bone
with embellished metal inlay.
then they trim the excess bone
so that it's flush to the metal
liner.
next, they place a spring on the
underside of the bone and brass
part followed by a rocker arm
and a spacer.
this sandwich is finished off
with another bone-covered brass
liner.
workers insert blades in one
end, first dipping them in oil
for lubrication.
a pin holds it all together.
a separate set of blades goes in
the other end of the
pocketknife, and another pin is
inserted.
a pneumatic tool flattens the
ends of the pins, riveting all
the parts together.
sometimes a shim is pounded
between the layers so the knives
can move more freely.
it's a little fine-tuning.
the pinheads are grinded down to
blend them to the rest of the
pocketknife.
sparks fly as workers hone the
beveled edges against a belt
sander until they're sharp
enough to cut.
next, all the blades are
retracted, and the knife is
buffed until it shines.
here a laser edges an insignia
into the bone handle.
the engraving is enhanced with
paint.
and now you have a pocketknife
that's sharp and sharp-looking.
coming up, soapstone products --
a real rock-'n'-roll story.
>> narrator: dig deep into the
history of civilization, and
you'll find plenty of soapstone.
over the centuries, it's been
used to make everything from
cookware to countertops to the
kitchen sink.
soapstone doesn't stain or burn,
and that's why it continues to
be a rock-solid material.
but before you can make
something out of soapstone, you
need raw materials.
several deep holes are bored
into a soapstone hillside.
the horizontal and vertical
holes form an intersecting
lattice.
miners loop one end of
a long diamond-encrusted cable
and attach it to a rod.
this makes it easy to maneuver
as they snake the cable through
one of the vertical holes.
a coiled snare is attached to
the cable's other end and
inserted in one of the
horizontal holes, jiggling it
around it until the snare snags
the loop.
next, the cable is threaded
through the rock.
two ends of the cable are
crimped together to create one
big circle over 200 feet in
circumference.
a section of the diamond cable
is wound around mechanical
wheels.
the machine moves backward as
the wheels turn the cable
through the rock, and slowly but
surely the tiny diamonds saw
through the soapstone.
the process kicks up a lot of
talc, the mineral that gives
this stone its soapy texture.
so water is sprayed into the cut
to minimize the dusty fallout.
as the cable exits the rock, it
snaps off the wheels, so
everyone has to steer clear.
it has taken about 20 minutes to
slice through this soapstone
hillside.
now it's time for the excavator.
as it pulls the soapstone away
from the hillside, the slab
breaks into chunks, each one
about two or three square yards.
the chunks are washed.
then they're lifted up by a
front-end loader and delivered
to a band saw.
like the cable, the saw has a
diamond edge that easily cuts
through the stone.
they get several one-inch thick
slabs from each block, perfect
for a countertop.
the smaller-end slabs are used
to build apron sinks.
this type of sink was first
popular a century and a half
ago.
but these days, computerized
blades and lasers make the job
of building one a whole lot
easier.
the laser lines serve as guides
while the blades cut the
soapstone to precise dimensions.
this piece will be the bottom of
the sink.
a precision grinder tapers the
sink bottom from the center out
so that liquid will flow down
into a drain in the middle.
next, a drain hole is punched
out.
a constant flow of water keeps
the cutter cool and the dust
down.
epoxy resin is mixed with
hardener for a high-strength
waterproof adhesive.
it's quickly applied along the
edge of the sink bottom so it
doesn't dry.
then a sink wall is pressed onto
the glued surface.
they piece together the rest of
the sink, and it's ready to
blend in with the soapstone
countertop.
from the shower floor to the
stove surround soapstone can
perform many functions with
style.
when we return, the shocking
truth behind electric pole
transformers.
>> narrator: electric
transformers -- we see them
everywhere but often take for
granted the big part they play
in our everyday lives.
their job is to transform the
high voltage from electrical
power lines to the lower voltage
that's suitable for home use.
without them, raw electrical
power would be virtually useless
to the average person.
transformers are a critical part
of modern life, but did you ever
stop to wonder what's inside
those canisters?
to build a transformer, workers
start by taking paper that's
coated with epoxy glue and tape
it to a wooden block.
next component -- an
1/8-of-an-inch-thick aluminum
strip.
it's a metal that can withstand
the heat that a high-voltage
current produces.
as the block is rotated, the
paper and the aluminum strip are
wrapped around it.
an aluminum bus bar, called the
low-voltage lead, sends low
voltage current out from the
transformer.
workers fold the lead and move
the unit to another rotating
block for more wrapping.
the insulating paper has epoxy
glue on both sides.
this glue will later melt and
bond several components in
place.
on the next block, a worker
tapes on more epoxy paper along
with epoxy-coated copper wire.
he covers the paper...
then repeats the same process,
forming a second layer of copper
wire.
he solders a high-voltage lead
wire to the copper wire then
rolls yet another layer of
copper wire.
next, he welds on what's called
the lead wire out, the wire that
will protrude from the
transformer cylinder and
attaches vinyl-coated wires that
will connect to different
voltages out of the transformer.
this completed unit is called
the coil.
now using electrical steel,
workers build the transformer's
other main component, called the
core.
the coil and core are tightly
secured together with metal
strapping, which will help to
fix the assembly in the tank.
then it's into an oven where
they bake for 8 hours at 275
degrees.
the heat improves insulation by
removing any traces of humidity.
it also melts the epoxy glue,
fusing together the paper, the
aluminum strip, and the copper
wires.
the assembly now goes into a
steel tank.
a rubber gasket is hammered
around the perimeter, and a
grounding wire is bolted on.
then three thermoplastics
bushings are inserted.
workers connect the low-voltage
lead to the thermplastic
bushings then bolt the bushings
to the tank.
they adhere an oil-filling guide
to the side of the tank then
position an automated filling
machine.
a machine fills the tank with
mineral oil, drawing a vacuum to
make sure the oil disburses
throughout the coil and core.
the oil is used for its thermal
and insulating properties.
an internal fault detector will
alert maintenance crews if
there is a short circuit.
a worker runs lead wire through
the thermoplastic bushing and
secures it in place.
next comes the high-voltage
connector.
finally, the tank cover is
bolted shut.
the transformation, so to speak,
is finished.
before transformers go into
service, they have to undergo
some truly electrifying tests.
this equipment simulates a
145,000 volt lightning strike.
then it's into a water tank to
test the transformer for leaks.
if it passes muster, it could
soon be appearing at a pole near
you.
up next, how they make snowshoes
step by step.
>> narrator: historians believe
the ancestors of north american
native peoples brought snowshoes
with them when they migrated
from central asia some 4,000
years ago.
today, the tradition of snowshoe
making lives on thanks to
skilled artisans who combine an
age-old craft with a few modern
improvements.
every snowshoe frame comes from
a single piece of hardwood,
usually white ash.
craftsmen start with a two-yard
strip about 3/4 of an inch
thick.
using a planer, they thin the
middle down to about half an
inch.
then it's on to a table saw,
where each end is tapered to a
fine point.
they take the trim pieces known
as bows and hammer steel braces
onto each one.
these support the wood where
it's thinnest so it won't break
later on during the bending
process.
the bows go into a steam chamber
to soften the wood.
30 minutes later, they're damp
enough to bend without breaking.
the craftsmen start working from
the middle, the area called the
toe, where the wood is thinnest
and easiest to bend.
they wrap it around a steel form
on a bending jig...
then lay one tapered end over
the other and tack them
together.
now back to the steamer for a
second bow to complete the pair.
a temporary crossbar helps hold
the shape.
different steel forms are used
to shake different snowshoe
models.
the frame is set on a bending
machine called a press break.
then a wooden bar is positioned
on the frame to act as a
fulcrum.
as the press comes down, it
curves the tip of the frame
about 2 3/4 inches upward.
a crossbar is inserted
lengthwise to hold the bend in
place.
still damp from the steam
chamber, the frames will need to
dry out for several days.
only then can the temporary
crossbars safely come out.
the craftsmen then sand the wood
to a smooth finish.
they drill slots on the inside
for the two permanent crossbars
while another machine stamps
those bars with the company
logo.
it takes just a quick stretch to
insert the bars -- one near the
toe, the other near the heel.
now the frames go for a dip in a
vat of oil-based varnish to seal
and waterproof the wood.
once the varnish dries, the
frames are ready for lacing.
in keeping with tradition, the
laces are made of animal hide.
wetting it makes it easier to
cut into the long strips.
a skilled weaver threads her
needle then begins by hooking
the rawhide lace through a nylon
thread that runs along the
shoe's inside perimeter.
she nimbly builds up a pattern
of webbing that always begins
and ends with a series of
triangular shapes.
this intricate weaving technique
is a traditional skill passed
down through generations of
native canadian women.
she finishes by wrapping up the
heel end of the frame with
rawhide then pulls it tight.
now that the toe piece is
finished, she starts weaving the
middle piece.
using a large width of rawhide,
she builds up another web of
triangles, this time knotting
the strips directly onto the
frame.
finally, she weaves an opening
to leave room for the bindings
that hold the snowshoe to your
boot.
once the rawhide dries, the
webbing will lie taut across the
frame.
the last step -- another coat of
varnish to seal and protect both
the wood and webbing.
and now these traditional
snowshoes are ready to make
some tracks.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...