-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, llc
>> narrator: today on "how it's
made," stainless steel...
football helmets...
resin figurines...
and laboratory glassware.
stainless steel was invented in
the early part of the 20th
century.
the key ingredient is chrome,
which forms a protective oxide
film on the surface.
originally called nonrusting
steel, it amazed consumers
because it didn't need to be
because it didn't need to be polished and today, the concept
hasn't lost its luster.
polished and today, the concept
hasn't lost its luster. stainless steel is made to look
shiny and new even though it
stainless steel is made to look
starts from scrap.
shiny and new even though it
starts from scrap. old stainless steel is recycled
to make new, giving trashed
old stainless steel is recycled
sinks, pots, and other refuse
to make new, giving trashed
a new lease on life.
sinks, pots, and other refuse
tons of scrap steel are fed into
a new lease on life.
a roaring furnace along with
tons of scrap steel are fed into
chrome and nickel alloys for
a roaring furnace along with
added strength and
chrome and nickel alloys for
rust-proofing.
added strength and
enormous electrodes heat the mix
rust-proofing.
to the melting point, creating a
enormous electrodes heat the mix
dramatic fireworks display in
to the melting point, creating a
the process.
dramatic fireworks display in
the process. after several hours, the molten
mix goes into a refining
after several hours, the molten
furnace.
mix goes into a refining
pipes blast in argon gas and
furnace.
oxygen, converting some
pipes blast in argon gas and
impurities to gas and causing
oxygen, converting some
others to float to the surface
impurities to gas and causing
for easy removal.
others to float to the surface
a technician regularly checks
for easy removal.
the temperature and takes
a technician regularly checks
samples to make sure the
the temperature and takes
chemistry is right.
samples to make sure the
a bit more scrap is added to
chemistry is right.
bulk up the mixture as it melts.
a bit more scrap is added to
the scrap also causes a chemical
bulk up the mixture as it melts.
reaction that helps to fuel the
the scrap also causes a chemical
refiner.
reaction that helps to fuel the
the bubbling steel soup now
refiner.
flows out of the refining
the bubbling steel soup now
furnace.
flows out of the refining
rollers guide it as it's cast
furnace.
into a long mold.
rollers guide it as it's cast
the result is a 75-yard-long
into a long mold.
ribbon of steel.
the result is a 75-yard-long
torches cut it into shorter
ribbon of steel.
chunks called slabs.
>> narrator: a worker writes
identification information on
each one using chalk designed
for hot surfaces.
then, the slabs are hoisted over
to another station to await
further processing.
further processing. after this break in production,
the slabs are reheated to soften
after this break in production,
them up for more processing.
the slabs are reheated to soften
by now, a rusty scale has
them up for more processing.
accumulated on the steel
by now, a rusty scale has
surface.
accumulated on the steel
workers pressure wash it away
surface.
without cooling the hot metal.
workers pressure wash it away
the slab shoots back and forth
without cooling the hot metal.
the slab shoots back and forth through a machine with rollers.
a constant spray cools the
through a machine with rollers.
rollers as they stretch the
a constant spray cools the
steel longer and thinner.
rollers as they stretch the
it's now over 650 yards long,
steel longer and thinner.
the length of a couple of city
it's now over 650 yards long,
blocks.
the length of a couple of city
a spray of water cools the
blocks.
stretched steel a little, but
a spray of water cools the
not too much because it needs to
stretched steel a little, but
be soft and flexible enough for
not too much because it needs to
coiling.
this spool coils the strip
tightly like a roll of toilet
paper.
then, the roll is transferred to
another station.
another station. here, the steel goes into a hot
acid wash that removes the scale
here, the steel goes into a hot
that's built up since the last
acid wash that removes the scale
cleaning.
that's built up since the last
burners in this machine also
cleaning.
heat the steel, then slowly cool
burners in this machine also
it.
heat the steel, then slowly cool
this relieves stress in the
it.
this relieves stress in the metal, softening it for further
processing.
metal, softening it for further
processing. the steel is now unwound into a
machine that rolls it to the
the steel is now unwound into a
machine that rolls it to the customer's specified thickness.
rolling the metal when it's cold
customer's specified thickness.
also hardens it and closes its
rolling the metal when it's cold
also hardens it and closes its surface pores, making it shine.
after one last cleaning, the
surface pores, making it shine.
stainless steel strips are
after one last cleaning, the
gleaming and the chrome in the
stainless steel strips are
steel combines with oxygen in
gleaming and the chrome in the
the atmosphere to form that
steel combines with oxygen in
rust-preventing oxide film.
the atmosphere to form that
finally, rotating knives trim
rust-preventing oxide film.
finally, rotating knives trim the edges and slit the steel to
various widths, again, to meet
the edges and slit the steel to
customer's specifications.
various widths, again, to meet
this job is now done, and it's a
customer's specifications.
brilliant finish indeed.
this job is now done, and it's a
up next, meet the starting
brilliant finish indeed.
lineup at a football helmet
up next, meet the starting
factory.
>> narrator: football helmets
cushion the cranium, helping
players score touchdowns without
sustaining head injuries.
helmets have been part of the
sport for over a century.
first made of leather, then
padded plastic, they keep the
padded plastic, they keep the end zone from becoming a danger
zone.
end zone from becoming a danger
in a game of tackles and
zone.
tumbles, a helmet is essential
in a game of tackles and
equipment.
tumbles, a helmet is essential
to make one, plastic pellets are
equipment.
suctioned into a machine that
to make one, plastic pellets are
melts and molds them into a dome
suctioned into a machine that
shape.
melts and molds them into a dome
this fist-like device shapes the
shape.
inside of the shell, which
this fist-like device shapes the
hardens in just a matter of
inside of the shell, which
seconds.
hardens in just a matter of
a robot then collects it and
seconds.
transfers it to a conveyor.
a robot then collects it and
it's quite a lineup.
transfers it to a conveyor.
the shells move into position
it's quite a lineup.
for a trimming, and the extra
the shells move into position
plastic from the molding is
for a trimming, and the extra
clipped off.
plastic from the molding is
clipped off. next, a robot drills up to nine
holes in the shell.
next, a robot drills up to nine
the holes will be used to attach
holes in the shell.
a liner, face guard, and various
the holes will be used to attach
pieces of hardware.
a liner, face guard, and various
this robot works far more
pieces of hardware.
quickly than a human can,
this robot works far more
performing all the drilling in
quickly than a human can,
just 30 seconds.
performing all the drilling in
this is the ultimate in
just 30 seconds.
computerized precision.
a worker collects the drilled
shell and moves a new one into
position for the robot.
position for the robot. the outside of the helmet shell
is roughed up with an orbital
the outside of the helmet shell
sander.
is roughed up with an orbital
this preps it for priming and
sander.
painting.
this preps it for priming and
this factory uses a high-grade
painting.
brand of automotive paint, and
this factory uses a high-grade
it takes three coats to make
brand of automotive paint, and
sure this paint job is rugged
it takes three coats to make
enough to survive a go on the
sure this paint job is rugged
gridiron.
enough to survive a go on the
the helmets cure in the open air
gridiron.
for up to 18 hours.
the helmets cure in the open air
during this time, a chemical
for up to 18 hours.
during this time, a chemical reaction hardens the paint to a
glossy finish.
reaction hardens the paint to a
not every helmet is painted.
glossy finish.
some teams prefer tinted
not every helmet is painted.
plastic.
some teams prefer tinted
it all depends on the look the
plastic.
team is going for.
it all depends on the look the
labels are attached, including
team is going for.
safety information, trademark
labels are attached, including
logos and the date of
safety information, trademark
production.
logos and the date of
this padding is made of vinyl
production.
and foam.
this padding is made of vinyl
and foam. workers snap it in place in the
crown of the helmet.
workers snap it in place in the
the padding for the side and
crown of the helmet.
back is made of the same
the padding for the side and
material.
back is made of the same
the back is reinforced with a
material.
plastic bumper.
the back is reinforced with a
a helmet from each production
plastic bumper.
run undergoes an impact test.
a helmet from each production
it's fitted on a head-shaped
run undergoes an impact test.
form equipped with sensors which
it's fitted on a head-shaped
are carefully calibrated.
form equipped with sensors which
are carefully calibrated. the technician presses a button
and the helmeted head falls.
the technician presses a button
this mimics the effect of a
and the helmeted head falls.
player's head hitting the ground
this mimics the effect of a
during a tackle.
player's head hitting the ground
the computer then measures the
during a tackle.
force of the impact on the head.
the computer then measures the
once the production run gets the
force of the impact on the head.
okay, the face guard is
once the production run gets the
attached.
okay, the face guard is
it's made of plastic-coated
attached.
steel and has been custom
it's made of plastic-coated
produced at a different factory.
steel and has been custom
there are dozens of face guard
produced at a different factory.
there are dozens of face guard styles for the player to choose
from.
styles for the player to choose
this helmet is now looking
from.
pretty fierce.
this helmet is now looking
but it's not ready for action
pretty fierce.
yet.
but it's not ready for action
it needs a chin strap and cup.
yet.
this machine uses heat to
it needs a chin strap and cup.
transfer a foil logo onto the
this machine uses heat to
polyester chin straps.
transfer a foil logo onto the
it also cuts them to the correct
polyester chin straps.
length.
it also cuts them to the correct
once a chin cup has been sewn to
length.
the strap, the assembly is
once a chin cup has been sewn to
the strap, the assembly is loosely fastened to the helmet.
later, it will be precisely
loosely fastened to the helmet.
fitted to the player's head.
later, it will be precisely
fitted to the player's head. this helmet is now almost ready
for kickoff.
this helmet is now almost ready
there's a final inspection and
for kickoff.
then they wrap it up, complete
there's a final inspection and
with the manual and fitting
then they wrap it up, complete
instructions.
with the manual and fitting
it's taken less than a day to
instructions.
manufacture a football helmet
it's taken less than a day to
manufacture a football helmet that can withstand thousands of
blows.
that can withstand thousands of
because in the game of football,
blows.
protection against head injury
because in the game of football,
is a victory in itself.
protection against head injury
when we return, bringing resin
is a victory in itself.
figurines to life.
>> narrator: figurines are made
of many materials, from
porcelain to plaster to resin --
not the kind that comes from
not the kind that comes from trees, but a synthetic resin, a
kind of plastic.
trees, but a synthetic resin, a
it's affordable, lightweight,
kind of plastic.
and easy to use, making it the
it's affordable, lightweight,
material of choice for many
and easy to use, making it the
artists and craftsmen.
material of choice for many
each figurine in this collection
artists and craftsmen.
is cast from a mold of the
each figurine in this collection
original sculpture, then hand
is cast from a mold of the
painted.
original sculpture, then hand
this character is a 19th-century
painted.
federal marshal.
this character is a 19th-century
federal marshal. working from period photographs
of her subject, the artist makes
working from period photographs
a sketch she'll use as a model.
of her subject, the artist makes
she needs plastic-based clay so
a sketch she'll use as a model.
it's easier to sculpt.
she needs plastic-based clay so
she works on the facial
it's easier to sculpt.
features, constantly referring
she works on the facial
to the photographs.
features, constantly referring
she usually starts with the
to the photographs.
figure's head and then adds it
she usually starts with the
to the body.
figure's head and then adds it
to the body. she works from more photographs
to create his rifle.
she works from more photographs
it's a delicate piece, so she
to create his rifle.
sculpts it separately before
it's a delicate piece, so she
setting it onto the figure.
sculpts it separately before
setting it onto the figure. bearing the artist's signature,
it's now ready for casting.
bearing the artist's signature,
first, the sculpture bakes for
it's now ready for casting.
30 minutes at 275 degrees to
first, the sculpture bakes for
harden.
30 minutes at 275 degrees to
then, workers cover it with a
harden.
thin layer of releasing agent so
then, workers cover it with a
it won't stick to the production
thin layer of releasing agent so
mold they're about to make.
it won't stick to the production
they place a wall around the
mold they're about to make.
they place a wall around the piece, tightly seal the base to
prevent leaks, then pour in the
piece, tightly seal the base to
silicone rubber mix.
prevent leaks, then pour in the
silicone rubber mix. in two days, the rubber hardens
enough to hold the shape of the
in two days, the rubber hardens
sculpture, but is still flexible
enough to hold the shape of the
enough that workers can remove
sculpture, but is still flexible
the original artwork without
enough that workers can remove
damage.
the original artwork without
after removing the retaining
damage.
after removing the retaining wall, suction is used to gently
pull the piece from the mold
wall, suction is used to gently
which retains the sculpture's
pull the piece from the mold
shape down to every last detail.
which retains the sculpture's
now, figurine production can
shape down to every last detail.
begin.
now, figurine production can
workers fill the mold with a
begin.
workers fill the mold with a mixture of resin and flour made
from ground pecan shells.
mixture of resin and flour made
from ground pecan shells. this colors the resin and makes
it stronger.
this colors the resin and makes
the mixture sets in less than an
it stronger.
hour and out comes the first of
the mixture sets in less than an
many figurines, an exact replica
hour and out comes the first of
of the original artwork.
many figurines, an exact replica
of the original artwork. the base is sanded to level it.
then, it's stamped with the
the base is sanded to level it.
figurine's name, i.d. number,
then, it's stamped with the
and copyright information.
figurine's name, i.d. number,
resin is an ideal material for
and copyright information.
resin is an ideal material for casting because it captures all
the details of the original
casting because it captures all
artwork.
the details of the original
artwork. it creates lightweight, durable
reproductions that can be
it creates lightweight, durable
finished in a variety of ways.
reproductions that can be
finished in a variety of ways. here the first artist coats the
figurine's broad areas with
here the first artist coats the
acrylic paint.
figurine's broad areas with
working color by color, she uses
acrylic paint.
various brushes depending on the
working color by color, she uses
area she's painting.
various brushes depending on the
she finishes up with the smaller
area she's painting.
details.
she finishes up with the smaller
then, she passes the figurine
details.
on to the next artist.
then, she passes the figurine
on to the next artist. this second artist fills in the
facial features and other fine
this second artist fills in the
details.
facial features and other fine
she starts with the whites of
details.
the eyes, then views the
she starts with the whites of
figurines from all angles to
the eyes, then views the
figurines from all angles to make sure she hasn't overlooked
any tiny details.
make sure she hasn't overlooked
her fine brushwork on the facial
any tiny details.
features is what truly bring
her fine brushwork on the facial
this figurine to life.
features is what truly bring
bass reeves, u.s. marshal, is
this figurine to life.
just one figurine in this series
bass reeves, u.s. marshal, is
that proudly honors the
just one figurine in this series
contribution of
that proudly honors the
african-americans in shaping the
contribution of
history of the united states.
once marshal reeves passes inspection, workers wrap him up
in protective bubble plastic.
inspection, workers wrap him up
each piece in the series comes
in protective bubble plastic.
with a certificate of
each piece in the series comes
authenticity bearing the
with a certificate of
artist's signature as well as
authenticity bearing the
the name and life story of the
artist's signature as well as
person the figurine portrays.
the name and life story of the
collecting this set of resin
person the figurine portrays.
figurines isn't just for the
collecting this set of resin
knickknack lover.
figurines isn't just for the
this is indeed affordable art
knickknack lover.
for the history buff,
this is indeed affordable art
small-scale figures that pay a
for the history buff,
large-scale tribute to
small-scale figures that pay a
african-americans pioneers.
large-scale tribute to
african-americans pioneers. coming up, behind the scenes of
a real test-tube birth.
>> narrator: their size, shape
and function run the gamut,
ranging from beakers and test
tubes to petri dishes and vials.
mixing, measuring, storing, or
mixing, measuring, storing, or sampling is all in a day's work
for a piece of laboratory
sampling is all in a day's work
glassware, built to withstand
for a piece of laboratory
even the most potent of
glassware, built to withstand
chemical concoctions.
even the most potent of
many scientific breakthroughs
chemical concoctions.
are born inside laboratory
many scientific breakthroughs
glassware, the containers
are born inside laboratory
scientists use to hold samples
glassware, the containers
for chemical experiments.
scientists use to hold samples
the glassware starts off as thin
for chemical experiments.
glass tubing stacked by size,
the glassware starts off as thin
weight, length, and diameter.
glass tubing stacked by size,
weight, length, and diameter. workers select the correct size
for the culture tubes they're
workers select the correct size
for the culture tubes they're about to make and place them in
a magazine.
about to make and place them in
as it spins, it drops a tube
a magazine.
into each slot on a cutting bed.
as it spins, it drops a tube
then comes the flame.
into each slot on a cutting bed.
then comes the flame. when the heated tubing contacts
the wet steel blade, the thermal
when the heated tubing contacts
shock results in a clean
the wet steel blade, the thermal
separation of the glass.
shock results in a clean
the tubes get a second thermal
separation of the glass.
the tubes get a second thermal shock treatment which cuts them
to length.
shock treatment which cuts them
then it's on to the glazing bed.
to length.
a glazing burner shoots out
then it's on to the glazing bed.
1,200-degree flames.
a glazing burner shoots out
1,200-degree flames. the heat melts each tube at one
end, forming a lip called the
the heat melts each tube at one
glass bead.
end, forming a lip called the
glass bead. just two seconds of heat splits
the tubes in half and forces the
just two seconds of heat splits
glass bottom of each tube to
the tubes in half and forces the
close in on itself.
glass bottom of each tube to
the finishing fire smooths out
close in on itself.
the closure.
the finishing fire smooths out
then, a small amount of air is
the closure.
shot into the open end of the
then, a small amount of air is
tube to form its round bottom.
shot into the open end of the
now, the tubes head into an
tube to form its round bottom.
annealing oven side by side.
now, the tubes head into an
they bake for about 15 minutes
annealing oven side by side.
at 1,200 degrees.
they bake for about 15 minutes
this strengthens the glass so it
at 1,200 degrees.
will better resist cracking.
this strengthens the glass so it
the heat also sterilizes the
will better resist cracking.
tubes.
the heat also sterilizes the
once the tubes cool, workers
tubes.
collect and pack them.
once the tubes cool, workers
here they're making pipettes,
collect and pack them.
long tubes that labs use to
here they're making pipettes,
transfer fluids.
long tubes that labs use to
transfer fluids. a flame heats the glass to form
an indentation which determines
a flame heats the glass to form
the flow rate through the
an indentation which determines
pipette.
the flow rate through the
a wider flame then heats the
pipette.
glass, making it soft and
a wider flame then heats the
malleable.
glass, making it soft and
malleable. large rollers tug at the sides,
drawing the soft glass to form
large rollers tug at the sides,
the pipette's tip.
drawing the soft glass to form
now, for the other end of the
the pipette's tip.
pipette.
now, for the other end of the
pipette. thermal shock is used to cut it
to length and again, a glazing
thermal shock is used to cut it
to length and again, a glazing burner forms a glass bead along
the rim.
burner forms a glass bead along
a cutting wheel slices through
the rim.
a cutting wheel slices through the tip end, creating two tubes
of identical length.
this production line makes
vials.
these gizmos, called top
these gizmos, called top turrets, feed large glass tubes
into a machine.
turrets, feed large glass tubes
into a machine. first, a punch-out burner heats
the end of the tube to create an
first, a punch-out burner heats
opening.
the end of the tube to create an
then, a steel pin widens the
opening.
hole on the upper part of the
then, a steel pin widens the
vial.
hole on the upper part of the
a forming dye squeezes the
vial.
heated glass to sculpt the
a forming dye squeezes the
shoulder while a steel plug
heated glass to sculpt the
rises from the bottom to open
shoulder while a steel plug
the vial even wider.
rises from the bottom to open
then, a second forming dye
the vial even wider.
shapes the neck.
then, a second forming dye
next, a parting burner splits
shapes the neck.
the vial into two.
next, a parting burner splits
a bottom turret plucks the
the vial into two.
newly created half and draws out
a bottom turret plucks the
the soft glass to lengthen it.
newly created half and draws out
fingers inside the turret
the soft glass to lengthen it.
prevent the glass from breaking.
fingers inside the turret
all that's left now is shaping
prevent the glass from breaking.
the bottom of the vial.
all that's left now is shaping
a burner forms a concave base in
the bottom of the vial.
less than a second.
a burner forms a concave base in
the vials now slide down to
less than a second.
what's called an after-former
the vials now slide down to
machine.
what's called an after-former
here, suction cups lift and
machine.
place each vial into metal
here, suction cups lift and
grooves on a printer bed.
it's a basic silk-screening
process with a squeegee pushing
paint through the screen's holes
onto the vial.
grippers place the vials on a
rack headed for the oven where
they'll bake for about 20
minutes.
finally, a robotic arm whisks
the finished vials to packaging.
from there, it's off to a blood
bank, a hospital, or chemistry
class.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...