-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
>> narrator: today on
"how it's made"...
wooden barrels...
fire hydrants...
automotive seats...
and cathode-ray tubes.
in the old days, wooden barrels
stored all kinds of goods,
simply because they were easy to
move.
if you couldn't lift them, you
could roll them.
today modern machinery has made
barrels obsolete, except for
storing fine wine and spirits.
and so the time-honored
tradition of barrel making lives
on.
these wooden barrels are for
storing whiskey.
they're made from american white
oak cut into pieces called
staves.
the staves go into a planer that
shaves them to about an inch
thick.
next, a machine punches two
quarter-inch holes on either
side of each stave.
dowel pins made of hickory, a
very strong wood, go into these
holes to hold the staves
together.
workers take the staves, place
them on a guide, and press them
together.
a smaller piece completes the
shape.
now it's onto the rounder, a
machine that cuts it into a
circular shape.
this creates the barrel's lid,
or head, as it's called.
and each barrel requires two,
one for the top and one for the
bottom.
the barrel head now goes onto a
contraption called the char
tunnel.
its gas burners scorch the wood.
this charring not only changes
the wood's appearance, it also
gives color, flavor, and aroma
to the whiskey this barrel will
hold.
the workers coat the head's edge
with liquid beeswax, which helps
them set it snugly into the
barrel body.
they run the staves against this
machine to narrow their ends.
this gives the barrel its
characteristic shape, with a
smaller radius at the ends than
in the middle.
at the barrel-raising station, a
worker positions an iron hoop
and starts to assemble the
barrel inside it.
he selects staves that vary in
width in order to use as few as
possible.
this reduces the numbers of
joints and potential leak
points.
he has to be gentle as he lassos
the barrel together.
if he pulls that dry wood too
tight, it will break into
pieces.
a loose hoop gives the wood room
to expand.
next, the barrels pass through a
steam tunnel for about 15
minutes.
this adds moisture to the wood
so it can flex without snapping.
workers pull out the barrel and
remove the top and bottom hoops.
sturdier hoops replace them and
are hammered into place.
without them, the barrel would
spring apart.
next, two more hoops around the
body.
the wood groans from the intense
pressure that forces the staves
together, but there can't be any
gaps between the staves or else
the barrel will leak.
the barrels pass over a gas
burner that blasts a flame
inside each one to char its
interior.
seconds later, water shoots into
the barrel to put out the
flames.
an automated saw cuts a v-shaped
notch into the top and bottom of
each barrel.
this is where the barrel head
will slide in.
a fan blows away the sawdust.
now a machine removes the iron
hoop on each end.
a worker pours in a gallon of
water to cool the barrel, still
hot from the charring process.
then he puts on a barrel head
and stronger, permanent iron
hoops on both ends.
now machines remove the two iron
body hoops and replace them with
stronger ones.
these barrels hold their shape
by sheer pressure.
there's not a drop of glue
holding them together.
that gallon of water is still
inside the barrel.
workers drill a hole in the
side, then plug it by hammering
in a rubber stopper with a
spout.
an inspector checks the barrel
for leaks, stamps it approved,
and labels it with a bar code
for inventory.
then they remove the stopper and
out comes the water, turned to
steam because of the heat.
the barrels are now ready to go
onto the distillery, where
they'll get their fill of some
fine kentucky whiskey.
when we return, you see them on
every street corner, but how are
they made?
>> narrator: fire hydrants have
been in use for more than 200
years.
in the old days, their main
purpose was to supply water to
fight fires, but they also
provided the public with a handy
water supply.
today fire crews rely on the
nearest hydrant to help them
douse flames whenever and
wherever they break out.
fire hydrants are essential to
every community.
they need to be instantly
recognizable, easily accessible,
and simple to operate.
the ones in residential areas
are designed to deliver an
impressive 1,500 gallons a
minute.
the hydrant-making process
starts with recycled scrap iron,
along with steel and raw iron.
using a magnetic crane, workers
load the metals into a furnace
and melt them at 2,800 degrees
fahrenheit.
this turns the scrap metal into
molten iron.
this superhot mixture is
transferred into a
remote-controlled ladle...
and emptied into an automated
pouring system.
to cast the hydrants, workers
first make two-part molds by
compressing a mixture of sand
and bonding materials.
one part, called the mold,
forms the hydrant's exterior
shape, while the other part,
called the core, forms the
interior shape.
an automatic core setter
positions a core in each mold.
then a conveyer advances the
mold under the pouring box,
which fills the cavity between
the mold and core with molten
iron.
after the iron cools and
solidifies, the molds enter a
tumbling barrel.
as they revolve, the sand
gradually disintegrates, freeing
the iron casting inside.
workers drill and thread the
hydrant castings to prepare them
for assembly.
then they pre-assemble and paint
them.
the fire hydrant's internal
workings, called the valve
assembly, allow water to flow
through when the hydrant's open.
a series of rubber "o" rings on
the main valve will prevent
leaks when the hydrant is
closed.
now the hydrant is ready for
final assembly.
workers attach the nozzle
section to the top of the
hydrant barrel and fasten nozzle
cap chains with a crimping tool.
using a torque wrench, they
attach cast-iron safety rings.
these rings are designed to
disengage the top from the
bottom of the hydrant so it
doesn't get damaged if a vehicle
hits it.
workers clamp the water-main
connector into place and
pressurize the hydrant to normal
city pressure to check for
leaks.
using a hoist, they lower the
pre-assembled nozzle section
over the stem...
and fasten it to the water-main
connector with stainless steel
bolts.
they lower the bonnet into
place...
bolt it to the nozzle section...
then open the hydrant for a
high-pressure test.
they turn the operating nut to
allow water to flow through.
but first, they have to force
out the air inside the hydrant
with water.
workers transfer the finished
hydrant to a pallet and apply
final paint touch-ups.
some fire hydrants that were
installed more than 100 years
ago are still in use today.
coming up, it's a cushy job, but
somebody's got to do it.
>> narrator: most people don't
pay too much attention to car
seating, but this feature has
come a long way since the car
was invented in the 19th
century.
back then, seats had no springs
and not much padding.
so you could feel every bump on
the road.
in today's car seats, we have
a much easier ride.
padded and belted, modern
automotive seats are designed to
be safe and comfortable.
the components are manufactured
separately and shipped to this
factory for assembly.
they arrive as needed on the
production line so there's not a
lot of stockpiling.
it means the flow of parts into
this plant has to be highly
organized because they make over
400 seat variations here.
the parts are carted to the
assembly line in the order
they're needed.
on this assembly line, there are
60 workers, each with specific
tasks to perform.
they receive a build ticket for
each part and scan it.
this allows a central computer
to track production and verify
that the right parts are being
used to build the right seat.
an operator tucks the
seat-warmer pad and cables into
the cushioning for the bottom
half of the seat.
she loosely places the fabric
cover over the assembly and
attaches it with wire.
then it's over to the next
station, where the operator
completes the upholstery job.
each worker has just 88 seconds
to perform his or her tasks, so
there's no sitting down on this
job.
they install a seat-warmer
system on the backrest section
of the seat and cover it.
then they slide an air bag into
a special sleeve.
these seats come with springs
that clip on to their metal
framework to provide lumbar
support.
workers fit the cushion assembly
onto the spring framework and
pull it tight.
they smooth out any wrinkles,
a process called finessing.
then they install the headrest.
next they tackle the lower
framework.
they equip it with a mechanism
that adjusts the height of the
seat.
electrical connectors go in
next.
then they bolt the lower
framework to the cushioned
backrest.
they attach the pretensioner
apparatus, which locks the seat
belt into position, then wire
the connector box.
they fit the lower cushioning on
the framework and add the
recliner spring.
a plastic valance makes it all
look neater.
now it's time to take this
driver's seat for a test run.
inspectors hook it up to a power
source and make sure the air bag
and seat warmer are operational.
they iron out all the wrinkles
because the automaker will
reject any seat that's less than
perfect.
then they slide and tilt the
seat to make sure the adjustment
mechanisms are working properly.
workers assemble the rear seats
using the same techniques.
again, each operator gets
exactly 88 seconds to complete
his or her job.
when you add it all up, an
entire seat set takes just 62
minutes to assemble.
before they ship the seat set to
the car factory, they snap a
photo as a production record.
it proves each set was in
perfect condition when it left
the factory.
now these seats are ready to hit
the road.
workers strap them onto delivery
pallets and load them into a big
truck, 60 sets at a time.
they'll arrive at the car plant
just as the vehicles they were
made for are rolling off the
assembly line.
once they're installed, all you
need to do is sit back and enjoy
the ride.
next, making the tubes that
bring tvs to life.
>> narrator: the crt, short for
cathode-ray tube, produces the
image that we see on our tvs and
computer monitors -- the ones
that aren't lcd are plasma, that
is.
believe it or not, the
cathode-ray tube was invented
back in 1879.
a crt is made up of two main
components, a large glass bulb
and an electric gun.
crts start with a molded glass
bulb.
workers remove microscopic
debris with a high-pressure
water rinse.
then they spray hydrofluoric
acid to clean the glass at an
atomic level.
phosphor solution is poured into
the bulb.
phosphor is an organic compound
that emits light when struck by
electrons.
the phosphor particles settle
and form a chemical bond with
the bulb face.
workers pour off the excess
solution...
and clamp the bulb over a nozzle
that sprays clear lacquer over
the phosphor.
the centrifugal force guarantees
an even coat.
this worker paints a conductive
coating over the anode button
which will provide a flow path
for the electrons that will
light up the phosphor particles.
meanwhile, another worker drops
an aluminum pellet into a
tungsten coil.
he places the bulb over a vacuum
device and draws out the air.
then he applies an electrical
current to the coil.
it evaporates the aluminum
pellet, which spreads a
mirror-like coating on the
inside of the bulb.
now they heat the bulb to 425
degrees fahrenheit for one hour.
this bakes out the lacquer and
any trace of moisture.
using a high-temperature flame,
a worker aligns and fuses a
glass neck to the bulb.
then he paints it with the same
conductive coating.
this assembly is part of the
electron gun that goes inside
the bulb.
it shoots electrons at the
bulb's phosphor particles that
lights them up, creating the
image we see on screen.
workers stack the grip cups that
focus the electrons on the
screen.
then using beading glass, they
align and fuse them into
position.
robots heat and affix the
beading glass to assemble the
electron-gun components.
then the gun is cooled with
pressurized air.
once cooled, a worker builds up
the gun and inserts the
completed gun assembly into the
bulb.
next he positions the bulb on a
glass-blowing lathe and cuts
excess glass from the neck.
using a graphite paddle and a
high-temperature torch, he mates
the glass neck to the
electron-gun stem.
this ceramic heating coil melts
that green glass pellet to keep
the bulb under vacuum.
the tube is heated to 750
degrees fahrenheit for two
hours, and once again, a vacuum
is drawn.
to minimize image flicker over
the tube's life-span, workers
condition the bulb using a
high-voltage coil.
it smoothes any rough surfaces
that might remain on the
electron gun.
finally, workers apply
electrical connections to the
electron gun to bring the
cathode-ray tube to life.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...