-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, llc
>> narrator: today, on
"how it's made"...
steel shipping drums...
police whistles...
miniature-train cars...
and glass blocks.
the steel shipping drum was
invented in the late
19th century for the oil
industry, which needed an
alternative to leaky wooden
barrels.
but those first steel drums also
leaked from their soldered
seams.
welding them proved to be the
solution, giving this container
an airtight reputation.
it's a product that really
delivers the goods.
a punch press first cuts and
forms the drum's bottoms in one
swoop.
a conveyer shuttles the bottoms
down the line to a turntable.
as a drum bottom rotates on the
turntable, a nozzle sprays
sealant onto it, coating it
completely.
then the drum bottoms are
stacked up.
meanwhile, another punch press
shapes steel discs into tops for
the drums.
rollers turn up the outer edge
to a precise measurement.
next, steel fittings tumble down
a vibratory conveyer to a
machine that simultaneously
punches threaded openings in the
tops and inserts the fittings.
one hole is for opening and
closing the drum.
the other is a vent.
at this station, workers check
the thickness of sheet steel
that will be used for the body
of the drum.
the thickness varies depending
on what the container is to
hold.
a machine called a shear slices
the the coiled steel into
sheets.
the steel sheets then move on to
a forming machine, where rollers
curl them into the drum's shell.
automated pushers then move each
shell through an
electric-resistance welder.
it generates heat to weld the
side seam, bonding it from both
the inside and the outside so
it won't leak.
the shells roll down to a
machine called a flanger.
the flanger stretches and
presses on the outer rims at
both ends, creating a lip.
then it's over to the beater.
its rollers bear down on the
shells to make grooves called
rolling hoops.
these rolling hoops add rigidity
to the shells.
the shells now travel down
another conveyer and merge with
the drum tops.
automated pushers deliver a top
to the base of a shell.
the shell rotates in a spinning
clamp as rollers curl the edges
of the top and shell together.
this creates an interlocked
seam called a chime, which is
then flattened by another
roller.
mechanized arms flip the shells
so the bottoms can now be
installed.
to join the bottoms to the
shells, rollers form another
chime.
these interlocking seams are
comprised of seven layers of
steel, making them leakproof.
that's critical, since the steel
drums may be used to transport
hazardous goods.
the steel drums now move forward
to a testing station.
here, inspectors inject air into
each drum and check the seams
for leaks.
the seams have been soaked up,
so if bubbles materialize, it
signifies a problem.
the steel drums then go for a
whirl under the paint gun.
it sprays them with enamel paint
for a protective sheen.
black is the most common color
for these shipping containers.
but custom colors can be
ordered, too.
the steel drums then journey
through an oven that bakes the
paint to a hard finish.
the thickness of the paint is
gauged with a special tool that
makes sure it's thick enough to
withstand rusting.
workers plug both openings and
put a temporary seal on the vent
to prevent tampering.
after that, these steel shipping
drums are ready for the long
haul.
next, get the blow-by-blow at a
police-whistle factory.
>> narrator: it was in the late
19th century that london police
started using a special whistle
to get attention.
it was lightweight and had a
piercing sound, a real
improvement over the hand
rattles they had been using
before.
that same design is still used
today.
they may be a blast from the
past, but there's nothing better
for blowing the whistle on
lawbreakers.
the average traffic cop blows
his whistle thousands of times a
day, so the whistles have to
resist a lot of spit.
the whistle's body is made of
high-grade brass tubing, in
which two slots are punched.
these are sound holes that
will allow the noise to escape.
using hydraulic pressure, the
brand name is stamped onto the
tube.
next comes the mouthpiece.
rollers sculpt a piece of
spinning brass into a shape
that's a bit like an hourglass.
with the mouthpiece complete, a
hydraulic punch is used to bend
a piece of brass into a part
called the slab.
the slab will be used to create
two sound chambers inside the
whistle.
a loop is fitted on to an endcap
to make the whistle easier to
hang on to.
a rotating press bends the
loop's tab against the inside of
the cap to fasten them together
permanently.
next, an endcap is attached to
the slab, and then the slab is
forced into the cavity of the
whistle, splitting it into two
chambers.
a police whistle actually
produces two notes at once,
giving it that distinctive
tambour.
these two separate sound
chambers will produce two
different pitches.
now the ends of the whistle are
dipped in solder paste and then
the looped cap and mouthpiece
are hammered onto the pasted
ends.
the solder paste is a special
lead-free compound so the
whistle-blower won't be exposed
to toxins.
solder wires are also inserted
in the whistle chambers before
capping the ends.
these solder wires will act in
conjunction with the solder
paste to seal the whistle in a
process that happens next.
the whistles move through an
electromagnetic conduction coil,
which heats them to a smoking
425 degrees.
this causes the solder paste and
wires inside to melt and flow
into the whistle's seams.
each whistle is then dipped in
an acid bath, which hardens the
solder, sealing the whistle's
seams.
next, the whistles are lowered
into a nickel bath, where
positively charged nickel ions
migrate to the negatively
charged whistles.
now it's time to make some
noise.
each whistle is tested with
compressed air.
the tiniest pinhole will cause a
whistle to fail, and that
happens in 3% of them.
failure is a crushing
experience.
the rejects get flattened and
sent to a company that reclaims
the metal.
on both land and sea, whistles
are the sound of authority.
here, workers assemble a
boatswain's pipe, used by naval
officers to issue commands and
salute dignitaries.
there's a tiny hole in the ball
at the end of this pipe.
the player opens and closes that
hole with his hands to change
the whistle's pitch.
and with that, production at
this whistle factory comes to a
screeching halt.
up next, all aboard.
you're about to see how raw
plastic is transformed into a
miniature train car.
>> narrator: making miniature
train cars is all about the
details.
every feature is scaled-down to
a fraction of the real thing,
and nothing is too small to
replicate.
the miniature train car is more
than just a toy.
it's a work of art and a
collectible.
on a miniature train track, the
past comes full circle with
replicas of trains from days
gone by.
craftsmen start with historical
photos and drawings of actual
train cars and scale them down
to 1/48th size.
they feed polystyrene pellets
like these into an
injection-molding machine.
it melts the pellets into a
thick paste.
the four sections of the mold
close and nozzles pump in the
plastic.
it oozes into all the grooves
and hardens almost instantly
into the shape of a train car.
then the excess plastic gets
clipped off.
here's a view of how the four
parts of the mold come together
to shape melted plastic into a
boxcar.
they even create holes in the
boxcar to attach accessories
and they impress details like
ridging that mimics the steel
ribs of the life-size train car.
more molds are used to replicate
door rails, brake wheels, and
other accessories.
the assembler clips the parts
off the framework and files
down the rough sections.
that is the brake wheel she's
snapping onto the end of the
model.
using a hobby knife, she trims
excess plastic from the train
car's step.
she then glues a steel weight to
the bottom of the train car to
make it 1/48th the weight of the
real thing.
making something to scale is a
bit of a balancing act.
finally, she attaches air-brake
tanks to the underframe of the
car, and it's time to
spray-paint the model train car
vivid orange.
it's a color that would have
been used on an actual boxcar,
combined with white.
for that two-toned look, the
model is held in a paint shield,
which protects the orange
sections as they spray on the
white.
this technique ensures the
paint job has clean lines.
the car is left to dry
overnight.
not all paint jobs are so
flashy.
this car is basic black, the
perfect canvas for white
lettering.
a pad picks up the ink from
letter engravings on a printed
plate and transfers the image to
the car.
metal wheels now roll off a
revolving conveyer.
they funnel into mechanisms that
press-fit them onto each end of
metal axles.
the wheel-and-axle assemblies
drop into a bin below.
two sets of wheels are now
installed on a plastic
framework.
the framework is then attached
to a coupler, the device that
links train cars.
the wheels-and-coupler assembly
are screwed on to one end of the
car.
then the process is repeated on
the other end.
the couplers are snapped
together to connect two train
cars.
in the world of train models, a
little grime is just fine.
a misting of paint makes the
cars look dusty and aged on
purpose.
the painter layers colors to get
just the right effect.
this technique adds the element
of realism to the model train
car.
it's all a matter of preference.
some hobbyists prefer this
weathered look, while others
like their model trains shiny
and new.
the model train cars have now
rolled off the assembly line
and, they're ready to hit the
tracks for a whistle-stop tour
of another era.
coming up, the hot scoop on one
of the world's favorite building
blocks.
>> narrator: when it comes to
building materials, glass blocks
are clearly a classic.
in the 1920s and '30s, they were
a cornerstone of the art-deco
style of architecture.
today, glass blocks are still
popular for creating walls,
windows, and stunning design
features, a stylish way to build
a privacy barrier that still
lets in light.
glass blocks aren't just
decorative.
they insulate from heat, cold,
and noise.
production begins with just four
ingredients -- recycled glass
pieces called cullet, sand,
soda ash, and limestone.
a computerized system portions
out each one and feeds them into
a melter.
this giant furnace heats the
batch of ingredients to a fiery
2,700 degrees, transforming them
into molten glass.
the melter pumps out enough
molten glass to make one half
block at a time.
automated shears slice just the
right amount.
the gob of glass then slides
into a waiting mold.
a plunger pushes the gob down,
spreading glass throughout the
mold cavity.
its waffled surface imprints
that pattern into the glass.
a blast of ambient air cools
down the molten glass
drastically, from 1,800 degrees
to 1,100 in just a few seconds.
this way they don't lose their
shape when a retractable arm
extracts them from the mold and
lays them on a conveyer belt,
leading into a sealing machine.
this is where two half blocks
join together to form a full
block.
entering the machine, each piece
passes over a series of burners
that keep the glass temperature
constant.
sudden cooling could crack or
shatter the glass.
the machine then slowly reheats
the half blocks until their
edges start melting.
next, they enter the part of the
machine called the squeeze
station.
here, an automated press forces
a top half and bottom half
together.
their melted edges fuse, forming
a single block.
the blocks now travel into a
leer, an oven that cools the
glass at regulated temperatures
over several hours.
this annealing process prevents
cracking and allows the glass
time to set properly.
the glass goes in at about
1,800 degrees.
coming out, it's down to 175.
the blocks are now ready for
inspection.
workers use digital-alignment
gauges to make sure both halves
are flush.
then they run a straight piece
of steel along the block's
surface to check for any
distortion.
every block must meet precise
standards for both size and
shape -- a 7½-inch square that's
4 inches thick.
building with glass blocks is
similar to building with
bricks -- you use mortar to
stick them together.
to prep the blocks for
mortaring, workers now place
each one onto a separate
station.
as it spins, nozzles spray the
edges with liquid vinyl.
this coating will help the
mortar stick to the glass
surface.
just one last step.
an ink-jet printer applies the
product code along with the
manufacturing date and time.
the quality-control department
runs samples through an impact
test.
a worker drops a weight through
a tube onto the side of the
block.
this verifies the strength of
the sidewall and the seal
between the two halves.
finally, the glass blocks are
ready for shipping.
workers pack them into cardboard
boxes that have block-sized
sections to keep them safe
during transport.
glass blocks come in so many
shapes, sizes, and patterns that
the design possibilities are
endless.
both practical and beautiful,
it's no wonder they're so
popular with builders and
decorators alike.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...