--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, llc
>> narrator: today on
"how it's made" -- automotive
cricket bats...
change machines... and d
when you start your car, it
activates a pump that's
usually  located i
this electrical system pushes
the gas out of the tank and
into
injectors, which aerate the
and deliver it to the engine
cylinders. without a
flowing, your car would be
going
nowhere fast.
you might think that   su
an electric pump in gasoline
would be a risky thing, but
it's actually a very safe
place
to be.   productio
pumping mechanism.
a gear and several rollers are
plates.
the rollers will rotate to
pull    fuel into
pushing it out of the tank.
each roller assembly is tested
by spinning it from the
a robot then pops it out and
moves it to the next station.
attached to the roller pumping
mechanism. then it g
and a plastic cap.
all the parts that make up the
pumping mechanism have now
assembled.
next comes an end cap with a
a metal sleeve slides over the
pump unit, and the whole thing
inside this chamber, large
magnets generate a very strong
this causes the metal sleeve
to
collapse, crimping at one end
so    that it ho
together.
next, retainer rings go into
a metal bracket goes over the
pump.  it steadies
serves as a guide as workers
install the brushes and coils
which will supply electricity
the fuel-pump motor.
a brass terminal slides onto
the   end of eac
assembly to facilitate the
electrical connection.
then the terminals are
to the assembly.
when the job is done, a robot
they built this fuel pump from
the inside out, and now the
inspectors hook each pump up
to
a power source and run fluid
through them to test the
action.
then they check for proper
flow  and pressur
if the pump passes
inspection, a
robot sends it down the
assembly line...
where a tubing system is being
assembled to carry the
gasoline to the eng
the joints are sealed with a
brazing paste.
then it's into a gas oven, w
the paste hardens and fuses to
the tubing. workers r
the oven and brush off any
unwanted bits of metal and h
the ends of the apparatus are
capped to keep them from
during shipping.
rubber tubing is attached to
the   pump and s
clamps.
then the rubber tubing is
system.
workers wire the fuel pump,
then hook up a co
attach to the engine's wiring.
this is the sending unit.  i
that's attached to an
electronic
sensor.  the sensor
about fuel levels to the fuel
gauge on the dashboard.
a computerized system checks
sending unit's accuracy as the
sensor is moved up and down.
once everything checks out,
time to fill the tank and hit
the road.   up next
we'll go behind the scenes at
a
bat factory.
>> narrator: references to the
game of cricket date back to
the 1300s.
historians believe it started
as
a children's game. in th
up the pastime, and before
long,
it caught on with the upper
by the 18th century, cricket
was
one of england's favorite
cricket bats are made of a
particular species of white w
it has stringy wood fibers
that
are usually long.
these give the wood  ela
the key to its performance.
bat makers use as much sapwood
as possible because it's
and more flexible than the
heartwood at the tree's core.
pieces about 2 1/2 feet long.
the first machine trims them
a few sprays of water limber
up
the wood fibers. then e
pressing machine three to four
times.  a curved r
three tons of pressure,
rounding
the bat's face and compressing
the wood by almost half an i
this pressing is essential to
the bat's performance and
the bat maker draws a "v" on
the
end where the handle will at
then he removes the bulk of
wood
behind the "v" on a table saw.
work he'll have to do by hand
later.    now he c
this creates a joint in which
to
insert the handle.   the
dried vine stems, glued
together
in sections, and coated with
the grip end has been shaped
on
a lathe.
the other end will attach to
blade.
the bat maker cuts the  bl
that will fit into the "v"
cut,
then glues the two pieces
a few taps with a hammer
ensures
a tight fit. he sprea
over the joint to seal it.
now he shapes the bat's
profile
using a classic woodworking
called a drawknife.
this takes only a few minutes
but requires years of   e
and an expert eye.
then he completes the shaping
the bottom third of the bat.
international cricket rules
regulate the length and width
bats, but there's no
restriction
on curve.   getting
though.
too much curve, and he'll
limit   the blade
performance.
the bat maker finishes off the
then he uses a metal hand
plane
to flatten the blade's edges.
spring by hitting it with a
dense wooden mallet.  he
the strike.
the softer the sound, the
softer
the wood, and the better the
will play.
he smooths the bat against an
molds to the bat so it doesn't
wear away the shape he worked
so    hard to ac
then a worker smooths out the
rest of the surface with a
belt
sander designed specifically
cricket bats.
the entire bat is sanded
twice,  first with
then with a fine one.
next, the bat is mounted on a
handle gets a coat of glue.
a wrapping of twine binds  t
that make up the handle.
extra glue prevents the twine
from unraveling.   next
using a cotton wheel.
once the wood is shiny enough,
brand-name decals go on.
finally, a rubber grip goes
the binding to prevent the
player's hands from slipping.
complement each other when
striking the ball.  the
enough to deliver a good hit,
and the cane handle absorbs
that
energy, protecting the
hands.
when you return -- making the
>> narrator: change machines
were invented in the mid-1950s
vending-machine boom.
they began as simple
mechanical   coin ch
quarter into nickels and
dimes.
today's modern machines can
even   convert $2
times sure have changed.
it's like magic.  in go
out comes the exact change.
but behind the scenes, there's
innovative design and some
pretty high-tech equipment.
machine's cabinet.
a computer-guided laser cuts
the  cabinet par
steel measuring 1 by 1/2
yards.
workers shake the parts free
and  push out th
panel that will become the
cabinet's front door. the
machine called the press
break.
this is one of the door
panels.  the machi
a die, bending the edge.
these bent edges will
strengthen
the door and help it fit sn
into the frame.
the laser cutter also makes a
cabinet part.
then workers press threaded
a vibrating feeder
automatically
dispenses the studs into the
now they bend the sheet, again
using a press break, and make
the three-sided panel that
become the cabinet sides and
back. they attach
panels.
then they position the cabinet
station and rotate the table.
a robot makes precision welds
shields workers from heat and
harmful rays.  now the
machine's coin dispenser.
it has two counter-rotating
discs fitted to the diameter
thickness of a coin.
they work together to seize
and
align the coins, then drop
into the coin chute.
workers set in these metal
discs, along with a plastic
mechanism that rotates them.
then they secure the parts on
a   fixture...
and drill holes into the gear
mechanism.
roll pins are inserted to hold
the parts together.
then workers make sure the
discs spin freely.
the next task is to assemble
the
coin-dispenser discs and ge
this is precision work.
first, they set the parts in a
plastic rings go around the
discs to guide and support the
then they attach the
gear-train
motor which powers the
a plastic guide on the casing
helps the coins drop in
next comes the coin chute that
guides the change out of the
dispenser and into the   m
coin cup.
the dispenser holds up to
$800,   which can
pounds, so it needs a strong
handle.
it's locked into place with
tool, called a ring fastener.
now it's time to put the whole
first, an electric power
supply
is installed on the inside
back  wall.
next comes the bill validator.
and the coin cup.   then
electronic control board, the
brains of the machine that c
finally, on go the instruction
decals.
so, how do bills transform
coins?
let's open the door and see.
the bill's paper and ink, then
stacks it in a box.  the
transaction, then cha-ching,
exact change.  coming
steel into the pipes that keep
our cities running.
>> narrator: chances are you
use
ductile-iron pipe every day
and   don't even
the underground pipes that
transport a city's drinking
iron.
so are the sewer pipes that
take  away househ
ductile iron is more flexible
than ordinary gray iron.  u
before it breaks.
ductile-iron pipes are made of
life-span of hundreds of
years.
production begins in the pipe
these old cars are on their
way
to a shredder that chews them
up    into littl
the factory sorts the bits by
material. it discard
the aluminum and copper, but
keeps the steel and iron.
steel from demolished
buildings
and other sources. the s
by its chemical composition
and
sorted accordingly.    a
industrial magnet to gather
precise amounts of steel and
the shredded metals then go
into
a blast furnace fueled by
coke, a form of c
at 2,500 degrees fahrenheit,
the
iron and steel liquefy, while
workers then add magnesium.
this turns the metal from or
stronger, more flexible
ductile
iron. the molten i
trough into a casting machine.
it enters a spinning mold,
where  centrifuga
iron against the mold walls.
a cooling system chills the
walls, and the iron solidifies
then an extractor pulls out a
20-foot-long cast-iron pipe,
the    standard
before each casting, workers
insert a round form, called a
mold.
the molten iron fills the void
forming a flared edge,
called a bell.
the core also seals off that
of the mold, preventing molten
iron from flying out during
when it's time to connect the
pipes, installers will fit the
straight end of another.
a rubber gasket seals the link
the casting machine can make
pipes of different diameters
by  changing the
inside.
after the pipe is extracted,
inspectors weigh it and
the wall thickness to be sure
everything meets
specifications.   then
remove the core.
since it's made of sand and
disintegrates.
this factory makes pipes in
several diameters, but
regardless of size, the
process is always the same.
it just takes less time with
harden faster.
a freshly cast pipe is around
1,500 degrees fahrenheit, but
cools quickly after leaving
the
mold.  such rapid
iron brittle, so the pipe goes
directly into a gas-fired an
it to 1,700 degrees
fahrenheit.
this alters the internal
structure of the iron, making
strong and flexible.
the pipe then runs through a
cooling chamber that showers
in cold water.
to prevent the iron from
sprayed with cement, building
up
a lining an eighth of an inch
then the pipe is spun for a
few
seconds to smooth out the
cement.
the entire pipe is painted
inside and out.
this seals the surface,
enabling
the cement to cure over the
next 24 hours.
it also provides some extra
rust
protection.
finally, a robot paints a
stripe
around the straight end of
each
pipe.
this is a depth guideline so
installation crews know when
they've inserted the straight
end of one pipe as far as it
can
go into the bell end of
another.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future
shows,
drop us at line at...