-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc.
>> narrator: today, on
"how it's made"...
prepared mustard...
violins...
nuts and bolts...
and toilet paper.
we eat it on hot dogs and
hamburgers, on sausages and
sandwiches.
no condiment cuts the mustard
quite like mustard.
the ancient romans took the
mustard seed to what is now
france, and by the 9th century,
big-time mustard production was
under way.
yellow mustard and dijon mustard
have a few ingredients in
common, but that's where the
similarity ends.
not only are they prepared quite
differently -- they're derived
from different varieties of
mustard seed.
yellow mustard is made from the
seeds of the white mustard
plant.
turmeric and paprika provide the
yellow color and sharp flavor.
the other ingredients are salt,
water, and white vinegar.
the powdered ingredients go down
a shaft to a mixing tank
containing the water and
vinegar.
yellow mustard's proportions are
roughly 60% water, 20% vinegar,
15% seeds, and 5% salt and
spices.
the last ingredient to go in is
the mustard seed -- hull, bran,
and all.
the tank's rotating mixers
blends the ingredients for about
an hour at seed-crushing speeds
reaching 165 miles per hour.
the tank's contents empty into
several stainless-steel mills.
inside each one, a pair of
synthetic stones grinds the
seeds, a process known as stone
milling.
that grinding action heats the
mixture to about 140 degrees
fahrenheit.
the liquid thickens into creamy,
bright yellow mustard.
before bottling, they perform
what is called a finesse test.
this ensures the mustard is
smooth enough.
if its particles are larger than
9/1000 of an inch, the factory
adjusts the milling stones
closer together to produce a
finer grind.
they make dijon mustard from
brown mustard seeds, sometimes
mixed with other varieties, and
they usually use two types of
vinegar -- cider and white.
the ingredients ferment in a
tank for 12 hours before mixing.
that's what gives dijon mustard
its strong flavor.
after mixing, it's the same
stone-milling process we saw
before.
here's what the inside of those
mills look like -- a rotating
stone rubbing seeds against a
stationary stone -- the same
principle as an old-fashioned
mortar and pestle.
dijon is made with twice as many
seeds as yellow mustard and 20%
less water, which is why it
comes out thicker and denser and
needs the occasional stir.
filters screen out any particles
larger than 9/100 of an inch.
the factory saves these coarse
pieces to put into specialty
mustards.
now the creamy, smooth dijon
mustard goes into a
stainless-steel tank.
a slow-speed revolving mixer
removes the air, which would
otherwise turn it brown and dull
its flavor.
the yellow mustard tanks also
have mixers to remove air and to
keep the condiment well-blended.
both dijon and yellow mustard
have to cool overnight before
bottling.
from start to finish, it takes
about 20 hours to produce yellow
mustard, and about 32 hours for
dijon because of its
fermentation period.
yellow mustard has a 15-month
shelf life, while dijon stays
fresh for a year.
both should be refrigerated
after opening to preserve their
flavor.
mustard is a condiment that even
health-conscious eaters can
enjoy.
it packs a lot of flavor in just
a few calories.
mustard contains a small amount
of fat, somewhat more if the
manufacturer uses oil in the
recipe, but it's still a
cholesterol-free food.
>> narrator: the violin was
developed in the 1500s, evolving
from a series of guitar-like
instruments that musicians
played with a bow.
while the violin is best known
for classical and gypsy music,
today you hear it in pop,
country, bluegrass, even jazz.
first they cut a piece of maple,
then split it in half to expose
the grain in mirror image.
they melt down glue flakes made
from animal hide, then bond the
pieces together.
violin makers only use glue,
never nails or screws.
these pieces of wood will form
the back of the violin.
after four hours, the glue
is dry, and they can remove the
clamps.
using a small plane, they even
out the surface.
then they trace the violin's
shape and cut it out.
they shave the surface sculpting
a downward slope from the middle
using an even smaller plane.
then they carve a groove along
the circumference.
after dabbing it with glue, they
insert what's known as purfling,
a reinforcement made from a thin
strip of hardwood, usually
maple.
finally, they carve the reverse
side to the right form and
thickness.
next they make the sides
of the violin, known as the
ribs.
first they soak thin strips
of maple or sycamore and press
them against a heated bending
iron to curve them.
then they glue the strips around
a form, connecting them at the
top and bottom, and at the
corners with small blocks of
wood.
they clamp everything together
and let the glue dry for four
hours.
next they glue thin strips of
wood called counter-ribs onto
the edge of the ribs.
this enlarges the surface so
that it's easier to glue the
ribs and the back together.
they make the violin's front, or
belly, from a solid piece of
spruce.
to the underside, they glue a
spruce support bar called the
base bar.
sound escapes through the two
curved slots called f-holes.
they cut out and carve the
violin's neck and scrolled head
from a piece of maple.
then they glue it to the body.
they sculpt the fingerboard from
ebony, a hardwood durable enough
to withstand centuries of
a violinist's fingering.
using a tool called a peghole
reamer, they make the holes for
the ebony or rosewood pegs
around which the strings are
wound.
they coat the wood with four or
five coats of varnish, depending
on the color, then polish
it with several coats of oil
over several days until the
finish is shiny and
silky-smooth.
next they insert the sound post.
this little cylinder conducts
sounds and supports the belly
against bowing pressure, so it's
critical to position it in
precisely the right spot between
the belly and the back.
it's not glued, but rather
wedged into place.
the bridge isn't glued either.
it's held in place by the
pressure of the four strings,
which they feed through the
ebony tailpiece and wind onto
the pegs.
the bridge has little notches
in which the strings sit.
the violin is finished.
they make the bow from horsehair
and a high-quality brazilian
wood called pernambuco.
they bind the hairs at one end
with strong sewing thread, then
burn them and seal them with wax
to prevent fraying.
this end goes into the frog, the
wooden box at the bottom, or
heel, of the bow.
they cover the frog with the
mother-of-pearl lining, then
slip on a ring made of nickel,
silver, or gold to prevent the
hairs from tangling.
next comes the screw that
controls the tension of the
hairs.
they comb the hairs to make them
parallel, then insert them into
the tip of the bow, known as the
head.
they tighten the screw until the
hairs are taut.
finally they rub on rosin, a
sticky pine-tree resin that
keeps the bow from slipping off
the strings.
>> narrator: at "how it's made,"
we pride ourselves in showing
you the nuts and bolts of how
everyday items are made, so it's
about time we visited a real
nuts-and-bolts operation.
we sure couldn't do without
these tiny but essential pieces
of hardware.
if only they weren't so darn
easy to lose.
nuts and bolts are made from
what's called steel wire rod.
after spending up to 30 hours in
a furnace to make it pliable,
the wire rod goes into a bath of
sulfuric acid to remove any rust
particles.
it's rinsed in water then
coated with phosphate, a
chemical compound.
this prevents the steel from
rusting before the bolt forming
begins and lubricates the steel
to make forming easier.
they form the bolts by cold
forging, shaping the steel at
room temperature by forcing it
through various dies at high
pressure.
the forming machine first
straightens the wire rod, then
cuts it into pieces slightly
longer than the bolt length.
the extra will become the bolt
head.
each piece goes through a die
that makes it perfectly round,
then through a series of dies
that progressively shape the
head of the bolt on one end.
the machine heads up to 300
bolts per minute.
here's what the heading stages
look like in slow motion.
this die creates a slight
collar.
the next one turns it into a
round head.
then the last one transforms
that into a hexagonal head --
the most common shape.
next the machine forms the
opposite end of the bolt.
a tool called the pointer shapes
the bottom of each bolt,
creating what's called the
chamfer, the part the nut
catches on to.
here's the bullet before and
after the chamfer.
the bolt needs threads to enable
the nut to screw onto it.
once again, they use the cold
forging method.
high-pressure rollers press in
the thread pattern...as we see
here in slow motion.
this is the actual speed, up to
300 bolts per minute.
during each production run, they
take several samples to verify
dimensions.
they use various measuring
devices -- a micrometer to check
the bolt's length, calipers to
measure the width of the head,
and a ring gauge to check the
threads.
to make the nuts, they use a
process called hot forging.
they cut steel bars into small
pieces known as slugs, then heat
them to 2,200 degrees fahrenheit
to make them malleable.
as we see here in slow motion,
hydraulic cameras punch the
slugs into hexagons, while a
die pierces the hole.
then a tool called a tapper
drives into the hole to cut the
threads.
that black liquid is a lubricant
oil to minimize wear and tear on
the tappers.
the nuts and bolts now go into
an oven at 1,600 degrees
fahrenheit for about an hour.
this gives them the required
strength.
then a rapid cooling in oil for
five minutes to solidify the
steel's internal structure.
by now the steel is hard, but
brittle, so they heat the nuts
and bolts for another hour.
this removes their brittleness
yet maintains their strength.
the quality-control team pulls
samples off the line, measuring
how much force it takes to break
them.
if a bolt meets its minimum
strength requirement, it passes
inspection, provided the break
occurred in the threading -- the
weakest part.
finally packaging -- labeled,
among other things, by size and
grade.
>> narrator: toilet paper is
probably the most indispensable
item in your home.
after all, it's not something
you want to run out of at the
wrong time.
most of us probably take our
rolls of toilet paper for
granted.
so you may be surprised to learn
that bathroom tissue, as it's
properly called, is a relatively
new invention.
the vikings used wool.
the ancient romans employed
sponges, and french royalty
wiped with lace.
then in 1857, an american
entrepreneur figured that people
had had enough of using leaves,
corncobs, newspapers, and
mail-order catalogs, so he
invented therapeutic paper, as
he so tastefully named it.
toilet paper only came in piles
of pre-cut sheets until 1890.
that's when one company
introduced bathroom tissue on a
roll.
ever wonder where all that
recycled paper goes?
well, look no further than your
bathroom.
many brands of toilet paper
begin as recycled paper.
the bales of paper drop down
into the pulper, a giant tank
with an agitator, similar to a
washing machine.
it mixes the paper in lukewarm
water for about 10 minutes,
transforming it into what's
known as pulp and screening out
all the bits of metal and
plastic.
now they have to take out the
ink.
the ink-removal system injects
the pulp with air.
ink particles attach to the air
bubbles, which rise to the top.
the system then skims off the
foam, leaving the pulp ink-free.
next the pulp passes through a
series of rollers, which squeeze
out the water.
this dries out the soggy pulp,
enabling it to absorb the
chemicals they'll use to bleach
it.
revolving knives now chop up the
pulp to prepare it for the
bleaching process, the details
of which are a closely guarded
trade secret.
the bleach turns the gray pulp a
pure white.
the company says it does this
without using chlorine or other
toxic chemicals.
they spread the wet pulp onto a
flat screen that runs through a
hot dryer.
in less than a second, the pulp
dries into a delicate paper
4/1000 of an inch thick.
each spool holds close to 47
miles of paper.
that spool now feeds a machine
with rollers that emboss a
pattern, in this case a waffle
print.
the pattern isn't just
aesthetic.
it also makes the paper thicker
and therefore more absorbent.
elsewhere in the factory,
production is rolling, so to
speak, with two strips of
cardboard, each 3 inches wide.
the machine coats the underside
of the top strip with glue, then
winds the two strips diagonally
to create a continuous cardboard
tube.
the machine then cuts the tube
in 65-inch lengths.
the tubes ride an elevator to
the toilet paper zone.
there, two giant spools of paper
feed what's called the winding
machine.
the two sheets come together to
form a two-ply toilet paper.
the paper then winds onto a
cardboard tube, creating a
super-wide roll of toilet paper.
when the roll is full, a blade
automatically cuts the paper,
and winding resumes on the next
tube.
the machine automatically seals
the end of the roll with glue
to prevent unraveling.
a circular saw slices the
super-wide toilet paper roll
into 16 standard rolls,
4 inches wide.
the toilet paper is finished and
ready for packaging.
this batch is for commercial
use.
each roll is individually
wrapped in paper.
check out this slow-motion
wrapping action.
toilet paper destined for
residential use gets wrapped in
transparent plastic, 4 to 30
rolls per package.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...