-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc
>> narrator: today on
"how it's made"...
fresh cut flowers...
adhesive tape...
tofu...
and lottery tickets.
to wish condolences,
congratulations, or for romance,
there's no shortage of
occasions for sending flowers.
whether made up in a splendid
arrangement or simply placed in
a vase, fresh cut flowers rarely
go unappreciated.
roses are a perennial favorite.
florists buy them from
commercial greenhouses.
those greenhouses have
sophisticated sprinkler systems
positioned to irrigate the soil
rather than the plants because
watering directly on the rose
bushes would grow harmful
fungus.
the hotter the weather, the more
watering is required -- up to
seven times daily for about
five minutes each time.
the greenhouse climate is
computer-controlled.
if it gets too humid, the
computer automatically triggers
the roof to open, bringing down
the temperature.
the ideal greenhouse temperature
for most flowers is about
70 degrees fahrenheit during the
daytime and 60 degrees at night.
with every watering, the roses
get a low-level dose of
fertilizer, the botanical
version of taking a daily
vitamin supplement.
it's a mix of nitrogen,
phosphate, and potassium.
the proportions are determined
by ongoing soil analysis.
if the pest specialist detects a
bug problem, he applies an
insecticide treatment to target
the particular pest, but first,
they close the roof so as not to
pollute the outside environment.
workers handling the chemicals
wear masks and protective
clothing.
the roses grow through the
openings of horizontal trellises
positioned one above the other.
this ensures the stems grow tall
and straight.
crooked roses, after all, are
worthless.
cutting the roses is tricky and
prickly.
workers have to wear thick
gloves to protect them against
the thorns.
they cut the stem at a
30-to-45 degree angle just above
the second set of 5 leaves.
the cut must be precisely at
that spot for a second rose to
bloom about 40 to 55 days later,
depending on the season.
growth is slower in winter
because there's less sun.
the growth period also varies
somewhat according to the
variety of rose.
the fresh cut roses go into a
bucket of lukewarm water with a
few drops of bleach to kill off
any harmful bacteria.
workers then check each and
every rose to make sure the
blooms and foliage are free of
defects.
then they classify the roses by
length.
the longer the stem, the more
the rose is worth.
they make a bundle of each
length...
then trim the bottom of the
stems to equalize the height.
they wrap the roses in newsprint
so they won't dry out during
shipping.
the transport trucks are
refrigerated in summer and
heated in winter to keep the
roses at a safe temperature,
about 40 degrees fahrenheit.
to make a bouquet of dried roses
they select open blooms for a
nicer look, then hang them
upside down in a room cooled by
fans.
they leave lots of space between
bouquets so the air will better
circulate.
the roses take a week to dry
out.
fresh cut flowers are striking,
whether part of an arrangement
or in a vase.
they can last in water for about
a week, provided you trim half
an inch of the stems to open up
the water channels.
fill the vase with lukewarm
water, never cold water.
pour in a bit of bleach to ward
off stem-clogging bacteria.
change the water every three
days, and be sure to keep the
flowers away from the heat of a
sunny window.
>> narrator: adhesive tape was
invented in 1925 as a painter's
masking tape for auto-body
shops.
that led to transparent tape,
designed to seal the cellophane
wrap used by the food industry.
then tape was introduced as a
household item, and the idea
just stuck.
these rolls of plastic film
called polypropylene are on
their way to becoming shipping
tape.
the rolls go on a machine called
the unwinder.
workers then position a strip of
adhesive splicing tape along the
end of each roll.
this will enable them to connect
one roll after another, creating
an uninterrupted feed to the
production line.
now watch closely.
once a roll unwinds completely,
its end sticks onto the splicing
tape at the beginning of the
next roll.
once that roll's unwound, its
end will stick to the beginning
of the next, and so on.
an automatic tension adjuster
ensures that the machine pulls
the film evenly to prevent
ripping.
the unwinder also applies a
solvent to the film's surface.
this prevents the film from
sticking while unrolling.
to transform this film into
tape, they coat one side with a
hot adhesive known as hotmelt,
made from several ingredients.
synthetic rubber gives it
flexibility.
a u.v. protector keeps it from
drying and discoloring, while an
antioxidant prevents aging.
synthetic resin makes it sticky,
while pigmentation oil provides
a choice of color -- in this
case, tan.
they load the hotmelt into a
preheated holding tank, which
keeps the melt at a piping
390 degrees fahrenheit to
prevent it from hardening.
the tank pumps the adhesive to a
machine called the gluer.
they wipe away the excess, then
roll the film.
and there goes the adhesive.
a cooling roller -- that black
one on top -- immediately
hardens it.
a computerized sensor ensures
there's an even coat of
adhesive.
if not, it automatically signals
to the pump to adjust the
output.
now a machine called the
rewinder rolls the tape onto
spools.
remember the unwinder that
spliced the rolls together?
well, the rewinder unsplices
them.
when a spool fills, a knife
separates the tape at the splice
point so that winding can begin
on the next spool.
the tape on just one of these
spools would run the length of
85 football fields.
the spools feed a row of sharp
razor blades called the slitters
which divide the 5-foot-wide
tape into several strips.
shipping tape is almost
2 inches wide, so they get
31 strips per spool.
each strip winds onto a
cardboard core, and its end is
sealed with a tab.
the length of tape per roll
varies according to the
customer's specifications.
as the machine ejects the
finished tape rolls, in comes
the next batch of cardboard
cores.
then it's off to the packaging
department.
nothing's shipped out, however,
before a quality-control check.
they test a sample roll from
each spool.
in one test, they unroll the
tape sticky side up, then
release a tiny, stainless-steel
ball down an incline, measuring
how far the ball rolls before it
sticks and comes to a stop.
to pass the test, the ball has
to adhere within a certain
distance.
the stopping distance varies
depending on the type of
adhesive tape.
>> narrator: some people just
can't get past that rubbery
texture, but tofu enthusiasts
say it's all in how you prepare
it.
tofu is a great source of
protein, low in saturated fat,
and cholesterol-free.
and it's versatile, absorbing
whatever flavors surround it.
tofu is made from soybeans, the
seeds that grow in the pods of
the soybean plant.
they contain 40% protein, more
than double the protein in beef
or fish.
they start by soaking the
soybeans in cold water for
18 to 24 hours, depending on the
season.
in winter, beans are stored in
outdoor silos and take time to
warm to room temperature.
here's what the beans look like
before and after soaking.
as they absorb the water, they
double in size and soften up a
bit.
the bloated soybeans go on to a
conveyor belt where a rotating
device transports them to a
crushing machine.
the machine crushes them into a
thick and grainy soup of soybean
milk and pulp.
it does this by forcing the
beans through an internal
filtering screen.
next, they transform the soup
into a paste by heating it in a
steam cooker for 3 to 4 minutes.
then it's into a centrifuge
machine.
as the chamber spins, the
centrifugal force separates the
milk and pulp.
the milk passes through a
cone-shaped filter, while the
pulp, called soy meal, sticks to
the sides of the chamber.
the soy meal goes off to be sold
for cattle and pet food.
the milk stays behind to be
transformed into tofu.
still piping hot, it goes into a
coagulation tank to be thickened
into curd, but first, they add
different herbs and spices,
because this batch will be sold
as flavored tofu.
then they add the coagulant,
magnesium chloride...
along with water to activate it.
then more stirring.
it takes about 15 minutes for
the soybean milk to congeal into
soybean curd, otherwise known as
tofu.
when it's ready, it's still
steaming but pretty soggy, so
they run it through a perforated
cylinder to drain as much liquid
as possible.
by the time the tofu comes out
the other end of the cylinder,
it's relatively dry and roughly
the consistency of scrambled
eggs.
now it can be processed into
those familiar blocks you buy at
the supermarket.
they transfer the tofu into
large rectangular molds lined
with cheesecloth.
then it's into a press that
applies 130 pounds of pressure.
this squeezes out most of the
remaining liquid and molds the
lumpy, loose tofu into a firm
rectangular block measuring
15 by 29 inches.
they cut the block lengthwise
and widthwise into 54 blocks of
10 1/2 ounces each.
tofu is pretty tasteless, but
like a sponge, it absorbs the
flavor of whatever it comes into
contact with.
they drench this batch in a
spicy marinade to make
jalapeÑo-flavored tofu.
after verifying the weight of
each block, they package the
tofu with a sprinkle of spices
for garnish.
then, to kill off any bacteria,
the blocks go into a pasteurizer
at 230 degrees fahrenheit for an
hour.
when they come out, they drop
into a cooling basin filled with
water just above freezing
temperature.
they stay submerged for about an
hour.
tofu comes either preflavored or
plain.
it also comes in different
textures.
firm tofu maintains its shape in
soups and stir-fries, while soft
tofu and silken tofu are ideal
for blended dishes and desserts.
>> narrator: the odds of winning
big in a lottery are slim to say
the least.
still, we keep hoping that
lottery ticket will become our
one-way ticket to extreme
wealth.
experts say your odds of picking
the winning numbers never change
no matter how many people buy
tickets.
lotteries are by no means a
modern invention.
the emperors of ancient rome
held them for entertainment.
european monarchs used state
lotteries to help fund their
extravagant lifestyles, and the
american colonies held lotteries
to finance roadwork and
construction projects.
pressure from the church and
widespread fraud led many
countries to ban lotteries
during the 1800s, but
governments eventually
reconsidered.
they just couldn't resist
milking that cash cow.
eye-catching lottery tickets are
designed by graphic artists.
a technician takes the design,
separates it by color, then
sends the information to a
machine called an image setter,
which generates one negative per
color.
next, they place the appropriate
colored film under each negative
and expose it to ultraviolet
light.
this hardens the color not
shielded by the dark portions of
the negative.
when they wash away the
unhardened color, they're left
with a color image.
they layer the films to make the
client a mockup of the finished
lottery ticket, in this case a
scratch-and-win type.
now they make the printing
plates -- one for each color of
the design -- first for the
non-playing area, everything
outside the scratch zone.
each negative goes onto a
paper-thin aluminum plate coated
with a u.v.-sensitive emulsion.
they expose the plate to
u.v. light for about 20 seconds.
this hardens the unshielded
emulsion.
the rest is washed away in a
chemical bath, leaving the
design in relief on the plate.
for the ticket's playing area, a
similar process is used, but
instead of an aluminum plate
coated in emulsion, they use one
made of photo polymer, a
light-sensitive plastic.
the finished plates are now
ready to go on to the printing
press.
their raised service will work
just like a rubber ink stamp.
the non-playing area goes on
first.
this method is called offset
printing.
the press applies up to nine
different colors, one after
another, from lightest to
darkest.
high-intensity u.v. lights dry
the ink in the mere half-second
between color applications.
next comes the playing area.
a high-speed ink-jet printer
first applies the game numbers,
chosen randomly by computer.
infrared lamps dry the ink in a
split second.
a strobe light enables the press
operator to do spot checks as
the tickets whiz by at a rate of
16 feet per second.
then the printer gives each
ticket a unique bar code.
this enables ticket vendors to
scan your ticket to see if
you've won.
it also shows whether a winning
ticket is genuine or a forgery.
the next machine seals the game
numbers with layers of varnish
and applies six coats of
scratchable ink.
an electronic scanner checks the
positioning of the scratchable
ink, making sure it hides the
numbers.
the first three scratchable-ink
coats are black.
the next three are white.
all those layers are used to
keep cheaters from holding the
card up to the light to see the
numbers.
now they can finally print the
playing area design onto that
white background -- in this
case, a crossword design.
a machine now perforates
the rolls of tickets so they can
be folded.
it processes almost 10 feet of
tickets per second.
here's what that looks like in
slow motion.
the next machine folds the
tickets along the perforation
lines into piles called fan
folders.
goodbye, slow motion.
here's the actual speed.
before the lottery tickets are
shipped out, several samples
undergo a quality-control
inspection.
the company checks that the
tickets are properly printed.
it also performs a series of
scratch tests and chemical tests
to make sure they're absolutely
cheatproof.