>> narrator: today, on "how it's made"... wheel loaders...
"how it's made"... wheel loaders... vegetable oil...
wheel loaders... vegetable oil... hand tools...
vegetable oil... hand tools... and cotton swabs.
they're big, they're bulky, and boy, can they move stuff. wheel loaders are drivable heavy
boy, can they move stuff. wheel loaders are drivable heavy
machines.
wheel loaders are drivable heavy
machines. you see them on construction
machines. you see them on construction sites moving dirt, at landfill
you see them on construction sites moving dirt, at landfill sites moving garbage, and in the
sites moving dirt, at landfill sites moving garbage, and in the
winter, you see them all over,
sites moving garbage, and in the
winter, you see them all over, clearing large quantities of
winter, you see them all over, clearing large quantities of snow.
clearing large quantities of snow. they start by assembling the
snow. they start by assembling the 100-odd steel components that
they start by assembling the 100-odd steel components that make up the front frame.
100-odd steel components that make up the front frame. these parts are so heavy that
make up the front frame. these parts are so heavy that workers have to use
these parts are so heavy that workers have to use industrial-strength magnets to
workers have to use industrial-strength magnets to move them.
industrial-strength magnets to move them. take note of those pieces with
move them. take note of those pieces with the holes in them.
take note of those pieces with the holes in them. we'll come back to them later.
the holes in them. we'll come back to them later. workers measure and mark exactly
we'll come back to them later. workers measure and mark exactly
where they'll weld the front
workers measure and mark exactly
where they'll weld the front frame parts together.
where they'll weld the front frame parts together. you might not think precision is
frame parts together. you might not think precision is
all that important when it comes
you might not think precision is
to building a 20-ton hunk of
all that important when it comes
to building a 20-ton hunk of machinery, but it is.
to building a 20-ton hunk of machinery, but it is. being just a few hundredths of
machinery, but it is. being just a few hundredths of an inch off can cause major
being just a few hundredths of an inch off can cause major problems.
an inch off can cause major problems. the preliminary welding is done
problems. the preliminary welding is done by hand.
the preliminary welding is done by hand. workers tack the parts together.
by hand. workers tack the parts together.
they do the same with the
workers tack the parts together.
they do the same with the 100-plus steel parts that make
they do the same with the 100-plus steel parts that make up the loader's three other
100-plus steel parts that make up the loader's three other sections -- the rear frame, the
up the loader's three other sections -- the rear frame, the driver's cab, and the moving arm
sections -- the rear frame, the driver's cab, and the moving arm
at the front called the boom
driver's cab, and the moving arm
at the front called the boom arm.
at the front called the boom arm. once the manual welding is
arm. once the manual welding is completed, robots take over to
once the manual welding is completed, robots take over to do the major welding.
completed, robots take over to do the major welding. they weld about 90% of the wheel
do the major welding. they weld about 90% of the wheel
loader.
now that the front frame is solidly fused, it undergoes a final machining.
solidly fused, it undergoes a final machining. remember those parts with the
final machining. remember those parts with the holes in them?
remember those parts with the holes in them? they're what enable the boom arm
holes in them? they're what enable the boom arm
to move.
they're what enable the boom arm
to move. a computerized sensor now
to move. a computerized sensor now measures those holes and
a computerized sensor now measures those holes and calculates how to cut them to
measures those holes and calculates how to cut them to the exact specifications of the
calculates how to cut them to the exact specifications of the engineering design.
the exact specifications of the engineering design. the computer then guides the
engineering design. the computer then guides the machining tool to tailor the
the computer then guides the machining tool to tailor the holes to spec.
machining tool to tailor the holes to spec. first, a preliminary cut.
holes to spec. first, a preliminary cut. then, after some oil
first, a preliminary cut. then, after some oil lubrication, the final cut.
when this operation's complete, the front frame will join the other sections at the paint
the front frame will join the other sections at the paint shop.
other sections at the paint shop. after painting, workers begin
shop. after painting, workers begin the final assembly.
after painting, workers begin the final assembly. they position an axle under the
the final assembly. they position an axle under the front frame and another under
they position an axle under the front frame and another under the rear.
front frame and another under the rear. then, they affix the frames to
the rear. then, they affix the frames to the axles with heavy-duty bolts.
then, they affix the frames to the axles with heavy-duty bolts.
they mount the diesel engine and
the axles with heavy-duty bolts.
transmission in the rear frame.
after assembling the cab, they install it onto the rear frame...
...then connect the wiring for the controls.
now comes the boom arm. remember those front frame parts
with the holes?
remember those front frame parts
with the holes? workers line them up with the
with the holes? workers line them up with the holes on the boom arm, then
workers line them up with the holes on the boom arm, then insert giant steel pins.
holes on the boom arm, then insert giant steel pins. this creates a pivot mechanism,
insert giant steel pins. this creates a pivot mechanism, enabling the arm to move up and
this creates a pivot mechanism, enabling the arm to move up and down.
enabling the arm to move up and down. the moving parts must fit
down. the moving parts must fit together snugly, but not so
the moving parts must fit together snugly, but not so tightly as to restrict movement,
together snugly, but not so tightly as to restrict movement,
which explains why welding and
tightly as to restrict movement,
which explains why welding and machining precision was so
which explains why welding and machining precision was so crucial.
machining precision was so crucial. once they've tested the boom
crucial. once they've tested the boom arm's hydraulic lift system...
once they've tested the boom arm's hydraulic lift system... workers install the tires, which
arm's hydraulic lift system... workers install the tires, which
are almost 6 1/2 feet tall.
workers install the tires, which
are almost 6 1/2 feet tall. using a specially calibrated
are almost 6 1/2 feet tall. using a specially calibrated torque gun, they bolt the tires
using a specially calibrated torque gun, they bolt the tires to the rim...
torque gun, they bolt the tires to the rim... 32 bolts in all.
to the rim... 32 bolts in all. the wheel loader is fully
32 bolts in all. the wheel loader is fully assembled.
the wheel loader is fully assembled. now the boom arm can be equipped
assembled. now the boom arm can be equipped
with a forklift, a broom, or a
now the boom arm can be equipped
with a forklift, a broom, or a big shovel called a bucket.
>> narrator: vegetable oil is a fat extracted from the fruit or seeds of certain plants, such as
fat extracted from the fruit or seeds of certain plants, such as
corn, canola, cottonseed,
seeds of certain plants, such as
corn, canola, cottonseed, safflower, sunflower, or
corn, canola, cottonseed, safflower, sunflower, or soybean.
safflower, sunflower, or soybean. there are various ways to
soybean. there are various ways to extract the oil.
there are various ways to extract the oil. the method we're about to see is
extract the oil. the method we're about to see is
called cold pressing.
the method we're about to see is
called cold pressing. it all starts with seeds -- in
called cold pressing. it all starts with seeds -- in this case, a dark variety of
it all starts with seeds -- in this case, a dark variety of sunflower seeds.
this case, a dark variety of sunflower seeds. cold pressing yields less oil
sunflower seeds. cold pressing yields less oil than other methods, so it's
cold pressing yields less oil than other methods, so it's usually just smaller specialty
than other methods, so it's usually just smaller specialty companies that use the process.
usually just smaller specialty companies that use the process. the big vegetable-oil makers
companies that use the process. the big vegetable-oil makers tend to use solvents and
the big vegetable-oil makers tend to use solvents and high-pressure, high-speed
tend to use solvents and high-pressure, high-speed presses.
high-pressure, high-speed presses. that is much more productive.
presses. that is much more productive. but it also generates heat,
that is much more productive. but it also generates heat, which darkens the oil and
but it also generates heat, which darkens the oil and diminishes its flavor and
which darkens the oil and diminishes its flavor and nutritional value.
diminishes its flavor and nutritional value. these seeds, shells and all,
nutritional value. these seeds, shells and all, will go through this
these seeds, shells and all, will go through this low-pressure press.
will go through this low-pressure press. the temperature inside is kept
low-pressure press. the temperature inside is kept below 104 degrees fahrenheit --
the temperature inside is kept below 104 degrees fahrenheit -- hence the term "cold pressed."
below 104 degrees fahrenheit -- hence the term "cold pressed." the press operator has to
hence the term "cold pressed." the press operator has to carefully monitor and adjust the
the press operator has to carefully monitor and adjust the
speed, pressure, and
carefully monitor and adjust the
speed, pressure, and temperature...
speed, pressure, and temperature... because keeping a press cool is
temperature... because keeping a press cool is no easy task, given the heat
because keeping a press cool is no easy task, given the heat that mashing seeds naturally
no easy task, given the heat that mashing seeds naturally generates.
that mashing seeds naturally generates. the pressing mechanism, the
generates. the pressing mechanism, the screw press, is made up of
the pressing mechanism, the screw press, is made up of several sections.
screw press, is made up of several sections. they can shorten or lengthen it
several sections. they can shorten or lengthen it according to the type of seeds
they can shorten or lengthen it according to the type of seeds they're pressing to allow for
according to the type of seeds they're pressing to allow for more or less room for the seeds
they're pressing to allow for more or less room for the seeds within the chamber.
220 pounds of seeds go through the press every hour, producing about 10 gallons of oil...
the press every hour, producing about 10 gallons of oil... low volume, but high quality.
about 10 gallons of oil... low volume, but high quality. the seed residue, called seed
low volume, but high quality. the seed residue, called seed cakes, is later sold for animal
the seed residue, called seed cakes, is later sold for animal feed.
cakes, is later sold for animal feed. now, though, they're the key to
feed. now, though, they're the key to monitoring temperature.
now, though, they're the key to monitoring temperature. if the seed cakes are too warm,
monitoring temperature. if the seed cakes are too warm, that means heat is building up
if the seed cakes are too warm, that means heat is building up and they have to open the exit
that means heat is building up and they have to open the exit wider to reduce the inside
and they have to open the exit wider to reduce the inside pressure and bring the
wider to reduce the inside pressure and bring the temperature down.
pressure and bring the temperature down. once the oil is extracted, they
temperature down. once the oil is extracted, they pump it through a filtration
once the oil is extracted, they pump it through a filtration system.
these cloth filters allow the oil to pass through, but any remaining seed residue gets
oil to pass through, but any remaining seed residue gets caught in the fibers.
the oil runs through the filters
repeatedly until it becomes clear.
mastering the art of cold pressing takes a lot of know-how
and experience, but it results
pressing takes a lot of know-how
and experience, but it results in oil that's healthier and
and experience, but it results in oil that's healthier and tastier.
in oil that's healthier and tastier. cold-pressed oils made from
tastier. cold-pressed oils made from other seeds pose different
cold-pressed oils made from other seeds pose different production challenges.
other seeds pose different production challenges. flaxseed and hempseed are
production challenges. flaxseed and hempseed are extremely sensitive to heat, so
flaxseed and hempseed are extremely sensitive to heat, so workers have to cool the press
extremely sensitive to heat, so workers have to cool the press during the process to offset the
workers have to cool the press during the process to offset the
heat that pressing generates.
during the process to offset the
heat that pressing generates. canola, on the other hand, isn't
particularly sensitive to heat,
canola, on the other hand, isn't
particularly sensitive to heat, nor is sesame.
particularly sensitive to heat, nor is sesame. all-natural, no-preservative
nor is sesame. all-natural, no-preservative vegetable oils like these have
all-natural, no-preservative vegetable oils like these have to be babied because exposure to
vegetable oils like these have to be babied because exposure to
air makes them prematurely
to be babied because exposure to
air makes them prematurely spoil.
air makes them prematurely spoil. plastic isn't airtight, so they
spoil. plastic isn't airtight, so they bottle these oils in glass --
plastic isn't airtight, so they bottle these oils in glass -- dark glass to block the oil's
bottle these oils in glass -- dark glass to block the oil's other enemy, light.
they seal the bottles with a flow-control cap. without preservatives,
flow-control cap. without preservatives, sunflower, canola, and sesame
without preservatives, sunflower, canola, and sesame oils have an 18-month shelf
sunflower, canola, and sesame oils have an 18-month shelf life.
oils have an 18-month shelf life. flaxseed and hempseed oils have
life. flaxseed and hempseed oils have to be refrigerated.
flaxseed and hempseed oils have to be refrigerated. even then, they go bad after
to be refrigerated. even then, they go bad after just a few months.
>> narrator: you don't have to be a do-it-yourselfer to own a few basic hand tools.
be a do-it-yourselfer to own a few basic hand tools. even the renovationally
few basic hand tools. even the renovationally challenged are likely to posses
even the renovationally challenged are likely to posses a hammer, a screwdriver, maybe
challenged are likely to posses a hammer, a screwdriver, maybe even a pair of pliers -- if not
a hammer, a screwdriver, maybe even a pair of pliers -- if not in a toolbox, then at least
even a pair of pliers -- if not in a toolbox, then at least crammed into a messy drawer
in a toolbox, then at least crammed into a messy drawer somewhere.
crammed into a messy drawer somewhere. here's a look at how some hand
somewhere. here's a look at how some hand tools are made.
here's a look at how some hand tools are made. every screwdriver and chisel has
tools are made. every screwdriver and chisel has
to have a handle.
every screwdriver and chisel has
to have a handle. this factory makes handles from
to have a handle. this factory makes handles from acetate, a synthetic resin.
this factory makes handles from acetate, a synthetic resin. these acetate bars are 6 feet
acetate, a synthetic resin. these acetate bars are 6 feet long and come in many colors and
these acetate bars are 6 feet long and come in many colors and
contours.
long and come in many colors and
contours. they arrive here ready-made.
contours. they arrive here ready-made. workers load the bars onto a
they arrive here ready-made. workers load the bars onto a machine that feeds them into a
workers load the bars onto a machine that feeds them into a lathe.
machine that feeds them into a lathe. as the lathe spins, an automated
lathe. as the lathe spins, an automated
knife cuts one handle after
as the lathe spins, an automated
knife cuts one handle after another, rounding off what will
knife cuts one handle after another, rounding off what will be the top of the handle.
another, rounding off what will be the top of the handle. then, it sculpts the other end.
be the top of the handle. then, it sculpts the other end. then, a drill makes the hole
then, it sculpts the other end. then, a drill makes the hole into which they'll later insert
then, a drill makes the hole into which they'll later insert the blade.
into which they'll later insert the blade. all this takes just a few
the blade. all this takes just a few seconds.
all this takes just a few seconds. now the handles travel to their
seconds. now the handles travel to their next stop, the dipping machine.
now the handles travel to their next stop, the dipping machine. acetate becomes dull and opaque
next stop, the dipping machine. acetate becomes dull and opaque when it's cut, so the machine
acetate becomes dull and opaque when it's cut, so the machine dips them in acetone, a chemical
when it's cut, so the machine dips them in acetone, a chemical
solvent.
dips them in acetone, a chemical
solvent. this brings back their
solvent. this brings back their translucence and shine.
this brings back their translucence and shine. it also removes any acetate
translucence and shine. it also removes any acetate shavings stuck to the ends.
it also removes any acetate shavings stuck to the ends. here's what the handles look
shavings stuck to the ends. here's what the handles look like before the acetone bath.
here's what the handles look like before the acetone bath. and here's what they look like
like before the acetone bath. and here's what they look like after.
the handles air-dry on their way
to the next stop on the production line -- printing.
to the next stop on the production line -- printing. the hot-stamp printer works in
production line -- printing. the hot-stamp printer works in conjunction with an ink ribbon.
the hot-stamp printer works in conjunction with an ink ribbon. it applies about 55 pounds of
conjunction with an ink ribbon. it applies about 55 pounds of pressure, engraving the product
it applies about 55 pounds of pressure, engraving the product code and brand name, while the
pressure, engraving the product code and brand name, while the heat, about 160 degrees
code and brand name, while the heat, about 160 degrees fahrenheit, transfers the ink
heat, about 160 degrees fahrenheit, transfers the ink from the ribbon into the
fahrenheit, transfers the ink from the ribbon into the engraved lettering.
from the ribbon into the engraved lettering. the handles are finished, and
engraved lettering. the handles are finished, and it's finally time to insert the
the handles are finished, and it's finally time to insert the blades -- in this case, phillips
it's finally time to insert the blades -- in this case, phillips
head screwdriver blades.
blades -- in this case, phillips
head screwdriver blades. blades are made of carbon steel,
an automated machine forces them
blades are made of carbon steel,
into the handle with about 80
an automated machine forces them
into the handle with about 80 pounds of pressure.
workers insert chisel blades manually in order to protect their sharp edge.
manually in order to protect their sharp edge. at the same time, they top the
their sharp edge. at the same time, they top the handle with a steel cap to give
at the same time, they top the handle with a steel cap to give the chisel extra striking power.
another common hand tool is the drywall square, also known as a t-square.
drywall square, also known as a t-square. they cut two strips of aluminum,
t-square. they cut two strips of aluminum,
the first 4 1/2 feet long, the
they cut two strips of aluminum,
the first 4 1/2 feet long, the second 22 inches long.
the first 4 1/2 feet long, the second 22 inches long. then, they apply the markings by
second 22 inches long. then, they apply the markings by
silk-screen printing.
then, they apply the markings by
silk-screen printing. next, they use a bending machine
to hold over the top edge of the
next, they use a bending machine
piece that will form the
to hold over the top edge of the
piece that will form the horizontal part of the "t."
piece that will form the horizontal part of the "t." this will allow the tool to hook
horizontal part of the "t." this will allow the tool to hook
onto the edge of a drywall
this will allow the tool to hook
onto the edge of a drywall panel.
onto the edge of a drywall panel. finally, they rivet the two
panel. finally, they rivet the two pieces together.
the drywall square is finished. factories can alter the size of the tools they produce to meet
factories can alter the size of the tools they produce to meet their clients' specifications.
the tools they produce to meet their clients' specifications. standard screwdrivers have
their clients' specifications. standard screwdrivers have handles measuring 3 1/2 to just
standard screwdrivers have handles measuring 3 1/2 to just over 4 inches long with blades
handles measuring 3 1/2 to just over 4 inches long with blades that are 1 1/2 to almost 8
over 4 inches long with blades that are 1 1/2 to almost 8 inches in length.
that are 1 1/2 to almost 8 inches in length. some screwdrivers, on the other
inches in length. some screwdrivers, on the other hand, have extra-long blades,
some screwdrivers, on the other hand, have extra-long blades, while stubby screwdrivers have
hand, have extra-long blades, while stubby screwdrivers have short handles for getting into
while stubby screwdrivers have short handles for getting into tight places.
short handles for getting into tight places. then, there are those skinny
tight places. then, there are those skinny pocket screwdrivers and
then, there are those skinny pocket screwdrivers and precision screwdrivers for
pocket screwdrivers and precision screwdrivers for jewelers and electronic
precision screwdrivers for jewelers and electronic technicians...
jewelers and electronic technicians... all of which proves there's a
technicians... all of which proves there's a tool that's the right size for
all of which proves there's a tool that's the right size for every job.
>> narrator: we use them to apply and blend our makeup, we use them in a pinch to pry
apply and blend our makeup, we use them in a pinch to pry dirt out of tight crevices, and
we use them in a pinch to pry dirt out of tight crevices, and of course, we use them to clean
dirt out of tight crevices, and of course, we use them to clean our ears, though doctors say
of course, we use them to clean our ears, though doctors say never to insert them into the
our ears, though doctors say never to insert them into the ear canal.
never to insert them into the ear canal. cotton swabs are just one of
ear canal. cotton swabs are just one of those little things that are
cotton swabs are just one of those little things that are really handy to have around the
those little things that are really handy to have around the house.
really handy to have around the house. cotton swabs were invented in
house. cotton swabs were invented in 1926 by leo gerstenzang, a
cotton swabs were invented in 1926 by leo gerstenzang, a polish-born american.
1926 by leo gerstenzang, a polish-born american. he got the idea from watching
polish-born american. he got the idea from watching his wife clean out their baby's
he got the idea from watching his wife clean out their baby's ears using a flimsy toothpick
his wife clean out their baby's ears using a flimsy toothpick stuck into a piece of cotton.
ears using a flimsy toothpick stuck into a piece of cotton. leo set out to design a safer
stuck into a piece of cotton. leo set out to design a safer device.
leo set out to design a safer device. he took a thicker wooden stick
device. he took a thicker wooden stick and wrapped the ends with cotton
he took a thicker wooden stick and wrapped the ends with cotton
in such a way that it wouldn't
and wrapped the ends with cotton
in such a way that it wouldn't come off and get stuck in the
in such a way that it wouldn't come off and get stuck in the ear.
come off and get stuck in the ear. the leo gerstenzang infant
ear. the leo gerstenzang infant novelty company marketed this
the leo gerstenzang infant novelty company marketed this invention under the trade name
novelty company marketed this invention under the trade name baby gays.
many cotton-swab makers also produce cosmetic pads. both start with bleached cotton.
produce cosmetic pads. both start with bleached cotton.
it arrives at the factory
both start with bleached cotton.
it arrives at the factory compressed in large bales.
it arrives at the factory compressed in large bales. the cotton first goes into a
compressed in large bales. the cotton first goes into a machine called the feeder...
the cotton first goes into a machine called the feeder... from there, into a machine
machine called the feeder... from there, into a machine called the opener, which shreds
from there, into a machine called the opener, which shreds the bales, pulling the cotton
called the opener, which shreds the bales, pulling the cotton fibers apart.
the bales, pulling the cotton fibers apart. next stop, the carding machine.
fibers apart. next stop, the carding machine. its large rollers comb the
next stop, the carding machine. its large rollers comb the cotton fibers out.
its large rollers comb the cotton fibers out. then, guided by weight-detecting
cotton fibers out. then, guided by weight-detecting
sensors, it produces a uniformly
then, guided by weight-detecting
thick ribbon of cotton called a
sensors, it produces a uniformly
thick ribbon of cotton called a web.
thick ribbon of cotton called a web. this web is now ready to be
web. this web is now ready to be processed into either cotton
this web is now ready to be processed into either cotton swabs or cosmetic pads.
to make pads, they layer several
webs -- just how many, though, is a closely guarded company
webs -- just how many, though, is a closely guarded company secret.
is a closely guarded company secret. and so is how much pressure they
secret. and so is how much pressure they
apply to those layers to
and so is how much pressure they
apply to those layers to compress them.
apply to those layers to compress them. this secret recipe of layers and
compress them. this secret recipe of layers and
pressure is what ultimately
this secret recipe of layers and
pressure is what ultimately determines the weight of the
pressure is what ultimately determines the weight of the pad.
determines the weight of the pad. the heavier it is, the higher
pad. the heavier it is, the higher the quality because it's
the heavier it is, the higher the quality because it's thicker.
the quality because it's thicker. the now-compressed layers of web
thicker. the now-compressed layers of web
go through a machine called the
the now-compressed layers of web
go through a machine called the slitter.
go through a machine called the slitter. it cuts the wide roll into
slitter. it cuts the wide roll into several narrower rolls called
it cuts the wide roll into several narrower rolls called header rolls.
each header roll then goes through a machine that stamps on
a quilt-like pattern, purely for
through a machine that stamps on
aesthetics.
finally, using a punching die, they cut the pads. on this production run, each pad
they cut the pads. on this production run, each pad
weighs about 2/100 of an ounce,
on this production run, each pad
weighs about 2/100 of an ounce, but the factory can produce
weighs about 2/100 of an ounce, but the factory can produce whatever weight the client
but the factory can produce whatever weight the client requests.
whatever weight the client requests. the cosmetic pads are ready to
requests. the cosmetic pads are ready to be packaged.
the cosmetic pads are ready to be packaged. this client wants them in bags
be packaged. this client wants them in bags of 100.
this client wants them in bags of 100. the blue light shows the workers
of 100. the blue light shows the workers
the 100-pad cutoff point.
the blue light shows the workers
the 100-pad cutoff point. to make cotton swabs, the
the 100-pad cutoff point. to make cotton swabs, the initial web is divided into four
to make cotton swabs, the initial web is divided into four
narrower webs, each weighing
initial web is divided into four
narrower webs, each weighing about 5/100 of an ounce per
narrower webs, each weighing about 5/100 of an ounce per yard.
about 5/100 of an ounce per yard. each narrow web travels through
yard. each narrow web travels through a funnel, which transforms its
each narrow web travels through a funnel, which transforms its shape from flat to round.
a funnel, which transforms its shape from flat to round. then, it coils into a barrel.
shape from flat to round. then, it coils into a barrel. the swab-making machine then
then, it coils into a barrel. the swab-making machine then takes cotton strands from two
the swab-making machine then takes cotton strands from two barrels at a time, feeding a
takes cotton strands from two barrels at a time, feeding a line of cotton to each end of
barrels at a time, feeding a line of cotton to each end of the stick.
line of cotton to each end of the stick. like the cosmetic pads, the
the stick. like the cosmetic pads, the amount of cotton per stick
like the cosmetic pads, the amount of cotton per stick varies according to the client's
amount of cotton per stick varies according to the client's
specifications.
varies according to the client's
specifications. the stick feeder prepares the
specifications. the stick feeder prepares the sticks.
the stick feeder prepares the sticks. then, as we see here in slow
sticks. then, as we see here in slow motion, the machine cuts the
then, as we see here in slow motion, the machine cuts the cotton strand and rolls a piece
motion, the machine cuts the cotton strand and rolls a piece onto both ends of the stick
cotton strand and rolls a piece onto both ends of the stick simultaneously.
onto both ends of the stick simultaneously. just prior, a heating device
simultaneously. just prior, a heating device melted the tips of the plastic
just prior, a heating device melted the tips of the plastic sticks so the cotton would
melted the tips of the plastic sticks so the cotton would adhere.
sticks so the cotton would adhere. with wood or cardboard sticks,
adhere. with wood or cardboard sticks, they glue the cotton on.
with wood or cardboard sticks, they glue the cotton on. the finished swabs are sprayed
they glue the cotton on. the finished swabs are sprayed with an antibacterial solution.
the finished swabs are sprayed with an antibacterial solution. here's that action in slow
with an antibacterial solution. here's that action in slow motion.
here's that action in slow motion. now in real time -- 2,000 swabs
motion. now in real time -- 2,000 swabs per minute.
sensors detect any defective
swabs and automatically toss
them off the production line.
if you look closely, every so
often, you'll see one missing.
finally, a robotic arm grabs the
exact number of swabs per box,
again determined by the
customer's specs, and packages
them.
the company's lab does spot
checks on its swabs to ensure
that the antibacterial solution
is working...
and that the products are
germfree.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
if you have any comments
about the show, or if you'd like
to suggest topics for future
shows, drop us a line at...