--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
>> narrator: poorly fitted shoes can ruin a runner's day. they can compromise the
gait and lead to injuries. it's why custom-made running
tailored for one specific pair of feet, they give the runner the necessary support to go
distance. thanks to the use of synthetic
more lightweight and flexible than ever before.  custo
the concept one step further.
they start by taking a precise 3-d laser scan of each foot.
device called a pressure plate. rubber tipped pins sprout up
this technique creates an exact outline of the sole, including
next, a high-pressure water jet cuts through synthetic fabric
a computer guides the cuts, following the measurements from   the scans.
the cutouts will be used to make the upper -- that's the part of the shoe that
top of the foot. a seamstress sews together the
shell of the running shoe's upper.   uppers co
colors, and when a shoe is custom ordered, the athlete can choose.
after holes for the laces have been punched into the upper part    of the ru
seamstress stitches on stripes -- a trademark look for  the company
she sews the tongue and a fabric innersole to the upper, using
prevent fraying. the innersole joins the two
custom running shoe is starting to come together.  but t
structure before it's ready to pound pavement.  so, th
plastic replica of the athlete's foot, called a last, into the
she glues fabric to the heel of each shoe, and then pounds and presses it to ensure the fa
adheres.
left to sit for five hours, the shoes conform to the shape of
but if the measurements are even slightly off, they'll scrap the  shoe and st
it's time for the foam midsoles. the workers cut the foam with
feet. the foam is dual density for
he sands each midsole, beveling the tips.  this will
landing when the foot hits the ground. the outsole
the worker sculpts these treaded rubber soles along the same
they'll fit together perfectly. he glues the mid and outer soles    together
to make sure this job really sticks, they squeeze the two soles together using a   h
press. in a custom shoe, the athlete
a deeper tread is more appropriate for trail running,
pavement better.
the worker now glues the bottom of the shoe to the top. the sole is made a little l
than the fabric upper, which allows her to fold it around the    upper for
a machine they call the claw applies pressure to enhance the bonding of the sole to the s
then they insert a memory foam insole which melds to the shape  of the foo
this insole is also breathable and has been treated with an
the athlete's name on the heel is the final personal touch for   these cust
they've taken about five days to make, but they're ready for a
>> narrator: ever since primitive times, humans have
the first axes were simple, sharpened stones, but when a
years ago, it increased the force that could be applied with each strike,
ax much greater impact. today, the ax hasn't lost its
despite the proliferation of mechanized tools, it offers a
the job done. a modern ax starts as a cylinder of high-qu
a ram nudges it into an induction furnace. the intense heat makes the s
white hot and pliable, allowing it to be stretched and shaped. a powerful press then pounds
steel into a series of dies to further define the ax profile.
operators now transfer the ax to another ram, which presses it
level it. then it's on to a revolving rack for a half-hour to cool down
harden, just enough so they can be handled.  a worker
axes into a tumbler. they are tossed about with tiny steel pellets, and the   r
friction rubs scale from the surface of the steel and also
then this worker presses the back of the ax head against a sanding belt to bevel the e
he sands the sides of the ax head for a smooth finish.  i
both sides of the cutting edge. it takes well-honed skill to do this with such quick
he then polishes the neck of the ax against a narrower,
and it's time for a dip in a special solution, heated to
they then quench the red-hot steel in warm oil.  the
hardens the metal so it's tough enough for any wood-chopping
at the next station, a worker assembles prepunched leather and  plastic rin
grip. she places the black-and-white plastic rings at each end of
leather pad, to give the grip a customized look.   the
smaller as she tapers the grip to fit the throat ax handle. it takes about 36 of the
rings and 6 plastic ones to make one grip. she transf
an assembly press...and inserts the lower part of the ax, which  has been l
wax, into the grip's center holes.    a hydrau
through. the lubrication ensures this job doesn't hit
she now flattens metal prongs at the base of the handle to secure    the grip
the axes rotate as a long, abrasive belt rocks against the    leather.
it sands the grip to make the layers flush.
a worker finishes off the job with a particularly aggressive
his handiwork makes this grip look really smooth.  a di
out the grain of the various pieces of leather, and they
once the lacquer dries, another worker polishes the exposed steel against a belt with a
fine grit. the result is a glossy sheen
definitely look good on the job.
it takes about two days to make one of these axes, but they're
>> narrator: kart racing is an international motor sport that has a huge following,   e
in europe. the karts look a bit like mi
but have no suspension system. kart racing can be even more
[ engine revving ] of their small size and increased maneuverability.
this italian-made racing kart -- with its one-cylinder, 125cc engine -- reaches speeds of
miles per hour. an aluminum case houses all the   engine com
a computer-guided drill bores various holes for installing
first in -- the engine's six steel gears. each gear is actually   c
of several gears. they thread them onto a shaft.
gear box.
behind the gears goes the gear shifter, which the driver op
next comes the drive shaft. it turns a chain that rotates
rear wheels are mounted. on the other side of the engine case, they
drive-shaft gears. these ensure the shaft rotates at a stable and controlled r
the red markings help the technicians align the gears.
gear box. the clutch's main housing,
clutch disks. these disks transmit crankshaft  motion t
turns the drive shaft, which moves the chain that rotates the  rear wheels
thick steel springs grip and release the clutch disks. this flap component, called
lameli pack, controls how much fuel enters the engine.  st
pedal creates a vacuum that opens the flaps and sucks in
the cylinder houses the piston that rotates the crank shaft.
cylinder in which the combustion cycle occurs.  the ign
side of the engine. the engine is now finished and
technicians use special instruments to monitor and
the racing kart's chassis is made of steel tubing. at the back, they mount
to hold the rear axle. then they mount the axle itself    and on i
they attach brake calipers to the chassis. under breaking, they squeeze
disks to stop the wheels from turning. after measuring again, to e
the rear axle is perfectly centered, they lock it into p
it to rotate, of course. now for the steering system.
technicians mount a spindle on each side.  the spin
front wheels.
once technicians fasten the steering column up top, they
spindles.
tie rods transmit the rotation of the steering column, via the spindles, to
next, technicians mount two spring-loaded pedals in front of  the chassis.
the brake system is hydraulic, meaning that pressurized fluid
or release the brake disks. next come the wheel humps on
then the engine... followed by the tires... and a fiberglass driver's s
which, due to the lack of suspension, lets the driver feel    every inc
finally -- the steering wheel and a data recording device that tracks everything from speed
lap time to tire and exhaust temperatures.
>> narrator: animatronics is the construction of robotic puppets  that move
you often see animatronic characters in science fiction
and carnivals. please be advised that this
may not be suitable for younger viewers.   when it
genre, the more gruesome the animatronic character, the b
meet crazy kristen. she starts out as a hunk of
her creator sculpts her form on a vertical table. once h
switches to finer tools to craft her gory features.
he uses water and a sponge to give her skin realistic texture. once the clay is hardened,
lay crazy kristen on her back and drown here in gypsum
in an hour or so, the plaster sets, and they remove the sculpture, creating a mold
which they'll produce multiple crazy kristens. the mold is quite heavy, so
easier handling, they sever the body in two.   then t
cavity with liquid latex rubber. a three-millimeter skin soon hardens against the mold ca
wall. they suction out the remaining
meanwhile, they weld together a steel skeleton, a grate for her rib cage, a strip for her
chains for her arm bones, ball bearings for her joints, and steel reinforced rubber for
neck. so far, crazy kristen has skin
now she needs flesh. they fill each mold cavity with  expanding p
to control the expansion, they cover the top with a plastic
their hands. the lower body doesn't require
because it's immobile -- just steel chains to hold them in
once the foam hardens, it's safe to extract crazy kristen's body from the mol
they trim off excess latex along the perimeter...then sit her upper body on a large   s
ball bearing mounted on a vertical metal base.   th
through holes in the base. each rod is bolted to a plate
joints in her skeleton. the other end gets welded to the  base.
these cylinder are pneumatic, meaning air pressure opens and
crazy kristen thrash about. it's all controlled by this d
guitar amplifier. it sends electric pulses that control the pneumatic   c
an actress records the accompanying shrieks and moans.    >> [ scr
>> narrator: they transfer the soundtrack to the digital  c
the box triggers the sound effects, along with the
it's time to apply crazy kristen's makeup. for her skin colors, they use
half-and-half mixture of house paint and liquid latex rubber.
off-white opaque ink.
then they airbrush the iris...
and paint in the pupil with the
stick end of a small brush...
a few veins with a red pen...
airbrushed ink on her
mouthguard...and finally clear
epoxy over her eyeballs, to make
them glassy.
they top her off with a wig,
mount her lower body to the
base, then complete her look
with a straight jacket, because
crazy kristen's home is
the insane asylum.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop