narrator: in the american wild west, the gun ruled,
and that gun was usually a six-shooter revolver.
today, replicas of those revolvers
can take you back to dodge city,
and they do
at cowboy shooting competitions.
it's a chance to engage
in a little old-fashioned
gunslinging for old times' sake.
with its six-shot cylinder
and innovative cocking mechanism,
the 1873 colt was carried by the likes of jesse james.
they start these automatic replicas
by shaping and machining the gun's frame.
a computerized blade carves the cylinder.
it cuts slots for the ammunition
and notches for rotating the cylinder after a shot is fired.
a technician files down rough edges
so the parts will fit together perfectly.
he then screws the curved grip and the trigger guard
to the frame.
he assembles the wooden grip casing to the metal back strap
and attaches them to the grip.
once he confirms it's a good fit,
he removes the casing the writes
the gun's serial number inside.
he stamps a matching number onto the grip
and polishes it and the gun's frame to a glossy finish.
he now rolls the model number
and other identifying information
onto the gun's barrel.
to add a bit of flourish, an artist engraves designs
copying the artwork on an original colt.
another worker now dips the parts in hot salts,
then in cold water.
a reaction occurs
that both hardens the parts a bit and tints them.
in this case, they turn a bronze color.
this is called color case hardening.
the grip and trigger guard
have been removed from the gun frame for color casing.
this makes it easier for the technician
to install the cartridge loading gate on the frame.
he files down the mechanism for rotating the cylinder
to make the dimensions perfect.
he then inserts a bushing and a pin
in the cylinder's center.
he uses that pin to install the cylinder in the gun frame.
the pin will also serve as the axis
for the cylinder to revolve on.
he slides a couple of test slugs
into the chambers
to confirm the gap between the cylinder and gun frame
is spot on.
he then fits the gun barrel to the frame.
and, using a special measuring rod,
he checks the alignment of the cylinder and barrel.
he tightens the barrel to the gun frame,
using a stick as a lever.
the technician aims the assembled gun
and eyeballs the alignment of the barrel to the frame.
once he's certain
the configuration is right on target,
he installs the gun's hammer and trigger.
he pops the cylinder back into the gun frame
and inserts the rod for ejecting spent ammunition.
he screws a spring into the side of the hammer
and cocks it
in its three different positions
to verify that it's in working order.
he then reattaches the grip and trigger guard.
he assembles a flat spring to the curved grip.
this is the main spring.
it transfers energy from the trigger to the hammer
to cause the revolver to fire.
then it's over
to a government testing facility
called the proof house.
behind bulletproof glass,
special equipment fires ammunition
at three times the usual operating pressure.
if the gun can handle this, it's deemed safe to operate.
after a few more parts have been color cased,
this revolver replica is ready for its target market.
and that would be history buffs
who are interested in a real blast from the past.
narrator: arc trainers can give you a full-body workout.
they provide a number of exercise programs
to choose from,
like strength training, weight loss, and cardio.
they monitor such things
as heart rate and calories burned.
like any piece of exercise equipment,
using one properly is the key to a safe and healthy workout.
arc trainers are made to give you
a wide range of incline and resistance levels
to let you train as easy or as hard as you like.
to start, a tube laser
machine-cuts and profiles the steel tubing
that will make the arc trainer's side frame.
a worker cleans the steel tubes,
then runs them
through a computer-controlled roll-forming machine.
this machine shapes all the steel
used to build the arc trainer's frame.
they use a robot to weld all the parts together
because robotic welding is more consistent and accurate
than hand-welding.
the completed frames then get a surface preparation,
giving the steel a uniform finish
that is now ready for powder painting.
workers then paint the frames
using an electrostatic paint process.
these guns spray electrically charged paint particles
that are drawn to the grounded frames
in a smooth and even coat.
the frames then bake in an oven
for 40 minutes
to cure the paint.
next come the handlebars.
a worker then makes them by lubricating a rubber tube
and sliding it onto an assembly frame.
he then locks a preformed metal tube in place
and lubricates it as well.
he turns a handwheel,
which brings the two tubes together,
forming the handgrip.
he completes the assembly by screwing on an end cap.
meanwhile, a worker assembles the control panel
by putting on the overlays for the user interface.
she then hooks up the printed circuit board
that controls the unit.
she closes the housing
but leaves the connectors exposed
for connection to the mainframe later.
a worker then attaches a steel support fixture onto the frame.
next comes this drive-wheel assembly,
which he bolts onto the support fixture.
he puts a drive belt around a pulley
that provides various resistance levels for the user
and rolls the belt onto the drive wheel.
he then uses a pneumatic tool to tighten down the pulley,
which stretches the drive belt
and sets it to the appropriate tension.
next he attaches the computer board
that controls the various fitness programs.
a worker then installs the leg bars
onto the arc trainer's frame
and attaches a foot pedal onto each leg bar.
he installs linkage bars onto the drive-wheel assembly.
then he aligns the drive wheel
and puts on the molded front housing...
followed by the protective side covers.
he connects a linkage bar
that extends from each leg bar to the drive wheel,
then connects one linkage bar to each arm handle.
he makes sure all the linkage bars are working properly.
finally, he tests
the free-floating foot pedals and the dual-action arms,
as well as all the other functions and features.
these arc trainers are high-tech exercise machines.
some models even come with a tv.
narrator: used-oil furnaces generate heat
by burning used oil without having to refine it.
these furnaces are found in automobile shops,
maintenance facilities, and construction sites.
transport fleets and trucking companies also use them
to turn the used oil they produce
into heat for their facilities.
it takes a special furnace to burn used oil.
used oil is thick and dirty
compared to residential fuel oil
and must be turned into a fine mist
to burn properly.
it all starts with a computer-controlled laser
making what's called the front and rear flue plates
out of steel.
the plates for this hot-air furnace
are made of stainless or hot-rolled steel
depending on the size of the unit.
a worker then makes what's known as the heat exchanger
by joining the flue plates together
with steel tubes called flue tubes.
this device is called a swagger machine.
it expands just the ends of the flue tubes,
binding them in place with the flue plate.
next, he assembles the section in which hot gases collect
after passing through the flue tubes
on their way out of the furnace.
he then sets a combustion chamber
on the top of the heat exchanger
and welds them together.
he completes the heat-exchanger assembly
by welding on a base equipped with two air-deflector plates.
these square plates help direct the ambient air
as it enters the furnace
and circulates around the combustion chamber.
meanwhile, an electrostatic powder-coating machine
paints the outside covers for the furnace.
next they put on inner air deflectors,
then assemble the cabinet.
they bolt everything in place, then put on an insulated door.
now he hooks up a blower control box.
this electrical box regulates
when hot air is sent into a room.
a worker then connects a tester box
to the temperature controls
that measure the temperature inside the furnace.
he runs a number of tests
to confirm that both the blower
and the burner
will turn on or off when they're supposed to.
he verifies the operation of the door
that allows for cleaning out ash residue.
a technician installs a 100-watt pencil heater
inside a brass nozzle adaptor,
then threads a thermostat into it.
this nozzle adaptor heats the oil
and turns it into a fine mist so it burns properly.
she then attaches assembly fittings to the adaptor
so she can later mount it inside a burner housing.
she checks these fittings with a leveling tool
to ensure the adaptor will go on straight inside the housing.
she also installs an assembly that controls oil flow,
temperature, and air pressure.
then she mounts the nozzle adaptor
and covers it with a retention head
that shapes the flame for optimal heat,
completing the burner assembly.
a worker then hooks up
the used-oil and compressed-air lines
to begin testing the burner.
he turns on the oil, ignites the burner,
and looks through an observation port
to verify the burner is working properly.
a closer look shows the flame is at the right intensity
for optimal heat with minimal emissions.
the furnace is now ready to turn
used oil into useful heat.
narrator: top-of-the-line pizza
cutters and vegetable peelers
can be a pleasure to use.
they make preparing and serving
your favorite foods
quicker and easier
and are ergonomically designed for style and comfort.
they are also easy to clean and guaranteed for life.
vegetable peelers and pizza cutters work like a charm,
making straight cuts
without damaging your pans or your fingers.
quality pizza cutters start
with cutlery-grade, high-carbon stainless steel
from which a stamping press punches the cutter blades.
the blades go
through a three-step heat-treating process.
first, they enter a high-temperature furnace.
then it's into a deep freezer
to maximize hardness and corrosion resistance.
finally, they go into a tempering oven,
which increases the durability of the metal.
a polishing machine with two buffing heads
then polishes both sides of the blade,
giving it a protective and cosmetic finish.
a worker than loads the blade onto a bevel-grinding machine
that thins out the edge of the blade.
it grinds a beveled edge
that is thin enough to cut pizza
but not sharp enough to cut your finger
or damage a cutting surface.
a worker puts a steel-bar insert
into an injection molding machine
that makes the soft-polymer handle.
he then cools it down in water.
he puts the handles on an extraction fixture
which removes the inserts,
making the handles ready for assembly
along with all the other molded parts.
he then attaches what's called
a swing arm to the blade holder,
and he secures it in place with a screw.
he dips the tip of the blade holder into lubricant
and uses a pneumatic-assembly fixture
to insert the blade holder into the handle permanently.
using the swing arm,
he snap-fits the blade onto the blade holder
and hides the swing-arm screw with a cover cap.
finally, he ensures the blade rolls properly and safely
so it will cut through pizza with ease.
the finest vegetable peelers
also do their job quickly and effectively.
they also start
with cutlery-grade stainless-steel blades
that undergo tempering
to ensure the metal is durable and corrosion-resistant.
after cleaning and polishing,
the blades are dried in a vibrating medium
of ground corncob,
then removed from the tub by a magnet.
the blades are now ready for sharpening.
a worker mounts the peeler blades
on a computer-controlled edge-grinding machine.
the grinder sharpens one edge of each blade at a time.
once both sides of the peeler blades are fully sharpened,
they're ready for assembly.
meanwhile, an injection molding machine
makes the blade holders.
a worker dips each blade holder
into lubricant
and inserts it into the molded soft-polymer handle,
joining them together permanently.
finally, he attaches the blade
by deflecting the holder just enough
to insert the tip of the blade into a tiny hole.
these top-quality vegetable peelers
are sold individually or in combination
with other kitchen utensils like pizza cutters,
and they sure are handy in the kitchen --
even if you're not.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about the show
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...