narrator: an airboat is a flat-bottomed vessel
with a huge propeller at the back.
all of the boat's mechanics are above the water line,
and just a bit of the hull rests below.
this makes the airboat the preferred mode of transport
through shallow water,
particularly marshes and swamps.
[ engine turns over ]
to steer an airboat,
large vertical rudders direct the propellers' airflow.
at full speed, an airboat can hit 62 miles per hour.
the boat's hull is made of aluminum
that's about 2/10 of an inch thick.
workers stiffen the hull's bottom plate
with aluminum "t" bars positioned 7 inches apart.
after they clamp the "t" bars,
a jig descends to hold everything steady
as workers weld on the strips.
next, they weld on aluminum sheets
to form the sides of the hull.
at the front, they push the bottom up for welding,
giving the boat a curved bow.
they complete the hull
by welding on a sheet across the back to form the transom.
to that, they weld a splash plate
that prevents water from coming over the edge
into the back of the boat.
next, they weld various parts to the front of the boat
to reinforce it structurally
and to create a covered storage area.
once that's done,
they screw a thick sheet of high-resistance polymer
to the bottom of the hull.
should the boat scrape against a rock,
this layer will shield the hull
from damage.
once that's secured,
they paint the inside of the boat
with a blend of epoxy and paint.
this forms a layer of what they call "webbing."
on the outside of the boat,
they apply a coat of primer
followed by two coats of durable marine paint.
meanwhile, others have constructed
and painted the boat's above-water structure
out of steel or aluminum tubes.
the rigging, as the structure's called,
supports the mechanics, two fiberglass seats,
and the instrument panel.
they mount a belt-driven reduction unit
to the boat's gasoline engine.
this unit reduces the propeller speed
in conjunction with a preassembled set of gears.
without it, the propeller would turn
at the same rate as the engine.
this would exceed
the propeller's operating limits
and destroy it.
the engine is now ready
to take its place at the rear of the rigging.
heavy-duty bolts secure it.
under the engine goes a 50-gallon fuel tank --
at the very back, an aluminum radiator.
then they bolt the rigging to the hull's "t" bars.
next comes a floor panel and a 3-passenger bench seat
with a storage compartment underneath.
the boat's exhaust system
consists of stainless-steel pipe,
which attaches with band clamps
to a header coming off the engine.
the other end leads to a stainless-steel muffler.
from that, an exhaust pipe runs out the rear of the boat.
next, they mount the propeller guard,
a stainless-steel safety cage
that surrounds the engine and propeller.
the three propeller blades are made of carbon fiber.
aluminum rudders steer the boat
by directing the propellers' airflow.
cables or rods connect the rudders to a control stick.
smaller airboats, like this one,
are ideal for hunting and fishing.
there are also much larger pleasure models
that can carry 18 or more passengers on excursions.
narrator: historians believe
consumption of this common vegetable
dates back to prehistoric times,
when it grew in the wild.
man eventually learned to cultivate onions,
and this strong-tasting plant bulb
became a food staple of many ancient civilizations
throughout the world.
in ancient egypt, the onion was an object of worship,
the inner structure of concentric rings
symbolizing the eternal circle of life.
today mechanical harvesters
pull the bulbs out of the ground
and lay them out in rows.
after drying for a day or two,
a tractor collects them into large baskets for storage.
to prevent spoilage,
the onions are stored at between
34 and 36 degrees fahrenheit.
when they arrive from the field,
their first stop is a cooling tunnel
from which powerful fans remove the heat.
the vegetables take about five hours
to cool down to the storage temperature.
the grower separates the onions
according to variety and size,
then either bags them for sale whole
or sells them to a processing plant.
at the processing plant,
workers load the onions on a conveyer
that leads to the peeling and cutting stations.
a cutter chops off each bulb's top and tail simultaneously.
it also scores the skin to prep it for peeling.
the onions then move into a
custom-designed peeling machine.
it uses a combination of air and water pressure
to blow off the skin.
the onions then roll off the peeler
and pass before quality-control
workers
who swiftly cut away bruises and any other imperfections,
as well as anything the cutter and peeler might have missed.
the next machine rinses the onions
with cold, ozonated water that kills bacteria.
then the onions pass through a metal detector,
just as a precautionary measure.
at this point, there's a fork in the processing road.
one direction leads to slicing,
the other to dicing.
on the slicing line,
workers load the onions into tubes
that feed slicing blades.
these blades are adjustable to output slices
anywhere from 1 1/2 to 25 millimeters thick.
workers gather up the complete slices
and fill 5-pound plastic trays.
a conveyer moves the trays through a machine
that seals them with plastic film.
the film has microperforations
designed to allow in just the right amount of oxygen
to keep the onions fresh.
on the dicing line, meanwhile,
the onions collide head-on with a rotary blade
that chops them to bits
ranging from 3 to 25 millimeters
in diameter.
the diced onions then go for a bath in cold water.
chopping an onion releases juice from its tissue,
paving the way for bacteria to grow.
this cold-water treatment reverses the damage,
restoring shelf life.
next, an escalator transports them
from a spin dryer to the packaging department.
there, an automatic scale
portions out the specific weight
they're packaging
in this production run.
when the target weight is reached,
a trapdoor swings open,
dropping the portion into the waiting package.
restaurants buy their diced onions in jumbo-sized bags.
the filling machine
automatically forms plastic into a bag,
adds a zipper closure, then seals the bag.
for grocery stores,
the factory packages smaller quantities
of both diced and sliced onions
in plastic containers.
kept in the fridge, they remain fresh
for at least a couple of weeks.
for busy cooks, it's a
convenient, no-tears time-saver.
narrator: building complex shapes out of metal
typically requires weeks of manufacturing,
using tailor-made casts
or precise machining techniques.
but 3-d metal printers are faster and cheaper.
they build objects
from successive layers of metal powder,
which are then fused together at high temperatures.
3-d metal printing makes it easy
to manufacture complex metal shapes
using a fully automated process.
every item starts with a computer model of the object.
this is the build box in which the object will be created.
a technician plugs in electric heaters
and pours super fine stainless-steel powder
into the box.
the heat will keep the metal powder from clumping.
he pushes the box into the machine,
then fills the feed box with more stainless-steel powder,
which will be needed later in the process.
the machine spreads the first layer
of stainless-steel powder in the build box.
tubes carry a binding substance
to the machine's printhead.
this binder acts like a weak glue
and is injected in very narrow jets by the printhead.
as the printhead moves back and forth
over the stainless-steel powder bed,
it deposits binder at the exact locations
specified by the computer.
as soon as the printhead
has finished printing a full slice of the object,
powerful overhead heaters ensure
the layer is completely dry.
a roller applies a new layer of powder
a fraction of a millimeter thick.
then the printhead adds a new layer of binder.
this builds the object from the bottom up.
the printing process takes several hours.
once the layering is done,
they put the build box in a curing oven
heated to 350 degrees fahrenheit
for 24 hours.
this will evaporate all the moisture and harden the binder.
they vacuum out the loose powder,
and the piece emerges,
its stainless-steel particles
lightly held together by the binder.
they gently blow air to dislodge any excess powder.
at this point, the object is very porous
and contains about 40% air.
it is so fragile
that it can easily be crushed with bare hands.
using more stainless-steel powder,
they prepare another box
in which the piece will be infused with bronze.
they're making a support structure
on which to rest the pieces
during the next phase of the process.
they carefully fill the box with alumina oxide grit,
which will support the pieces during the infusion process.
this dam prevents the grit from leaking out.
now they pour in bronze powder.
the piece is then heated in a furnace
at more than 2,000 degrees fahrenheit for 24 hours.
this melts the bronze,
which then gets sucked up into the piece
like water by a sponge.
infused with bronze, the piece is now solid metal.
they knock off the base with a hammer.
it's taken just a few days
to build this intricately designed piece of hardware.
it can now be polished, gold-plated,
or painted to match any decor.
whether they build sophisticated door handles
or fancy sculptures,
3-d metal printers work faster than conventional methods
at just a fraction of the cost.
narrator: to create classic, elegant style
in a kitchen or bathroom,
decorators typically use traditional materials
such as wood and marble.
curved cabinets can heighten that effect,
but their unique style comes at a higher price
because for the most part, these elegant doors
must be custom-ordered and handmade.
most cabinet doors produced
by this factory are custom-made.
they typically start out as a sketch,
which the factory transforms into a technical drawing.
they then use that drawing
to program the automated woodworking machines.
after cutting all the pieces of wood they'll need,
they run each one through a planer.
it simultaneously smoothes both
the top and bottom surfaces.
a cabinet door consists of a center panel
surrounded by a frame.
this machine, called a molder,
carves the frame's two vertical pieces
and cuts a groove on one edge
into which the center panel will fit.
to construct that center panel,
a worker feeds planks through a wood shaper
that bevels their edges.
the angle of the bevel is such
that when the pieces line up side by side,
they'll form a curve.
after trimming the pieces to the length of the center panel,
another worker runs them through a glue applicator,
which coats the beveled edges in adhesive.
then she lines up the pieces in an assembly fixture
that's been adjusted to the
center panel's width and radius.
once everything's positioned,
she applies clamps which force the pieces tightly together.
the glue sets in 20 minutes.
once the glue cures to full strength,
the piece goes onto a computer-guided router.
it rounds both sides of the panel
for a smooth, seamless look.
this particular door has a concave curve.
others can have a convex curve or a crossbow curve,
which is "s"-shaped.
the same router now automatically switches
to a different type of tool and profiles the panel's edges.
it also carves a tongue
that fits into the groove in the frame pieces.
the same machine can then load another tool
to engrave a custom motif
or monogram if the customer desires.
next, a computer-guided sander smoothes out the panel,
preparing the wood for stain or paint later on.
making the frame's horizontal pieces
is more complex than making the vertical ones
because the top and bottom
have to curve just like the center panel.
workers coat thin slices of wood
with heat-activated glue,
then stack them over a curved form in a press.
the press squeezes the slices tightly together.
then a high-frequency electrical
current generates intense heat,
triggering the adhesive.
the bonded slices exit the press
looking like a solid, curved piece of wood.
once the glue has set,
a computer-guided router carves
it to the same decorative style
as the vertical pieces.
it also miters the corners
so the horizontal and vertical frame pieces
will fit together seamlessly.
all that's left to do is glue the frame to the panel.
the tongue running along the panel's perimeter
fits neatly into the groove of each frame piece.
workers now clamp everything together
and let the glue set for a half-hour.
then the cabinet door goes off for painting or staining.
this factory produces curved cabinets
in 10 different types of wood
and dozens of colors and finishes,
opening the door to endless design possibilities.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...