>> narrator: several millennia
before it ever adorned a
martini, the olive and its oil
were central to many ancient
economies.
today, olives remain as popular
as ever.
not only are they tasty, they're
also healthy, low in calories
and cholesterol and high in
dietary fiber and iron.
olives are inedible unless
they're pickled.
these gourmet olives are stuffed
by hand with all kinds of
fillings, from almonds to garlic
cloves, even blue cheese.
straight from the field, they go
into barrels of brine.
for nine months, they ferment,
their hard and bitter flesh
becoming softer and sweeter.
then it's on to a conveyor that
takes them to the cleaning area,
where workers remove leaves and
other debris.
next, they drop on to a belted
conveyor.
the openings between the belts
gradually widen.
as an olive reaches an opening
exceeding its width, it falls
through into a barrel below.
by the time the olives reach the
end of the conveyor, they're all
sorted by size, from small to
extra large.
the next stop is the pitting
room.
the first phase of the pitting
operation is a spinning drum
with olive-sized pockets lining
its perimeter.
as the drum rotates, an olive
settles into each pocket.
this lines them up so that they
exit the drum in a line onto
the conveyor that transports
them to the pitting machine.
the machine pits 900 olives per
minute.
let's slow it down to show you
what happens.
a coring knife enters one end of
the olive, pushing the pit out
the other end.
as the pit exits, it creates a
hole that's just the perfect
size for the stuffing.
next, a quality inspection.
workers weed out any olives that
aren't perfect.
then it's off to the stuffing
department.
these beauties are being stuffed
with pickled garlic gloves.
the stuffer cuts the cloves into
hole-sized pieces, then inserts
one piece into each olive.
it's the same procedure with
other stuffings, such as
jalapeÑo peppers, sun-dried
tomatoes, habanero peppers,
onions, almonds, and more.
workers empty the baskets of
stuffed olives onto a table of
empty jars, spreading them
around until every jar is full.
on their way to the capping
machine, the open jars pass
under nozzles that fill them
with fresh brine.
an air jet blows off just a bit
to help the cap go on easily.
from there, it's into the
capping machine, which twists a
lid on each jar, heat-sealing it
for an airtight fit...
then stamping on a lot number
for tracking purposes.
finally, the jars head into a
machine that rolls on an
adhesive label.
the brine serves as a natural
preservative, giving these
delectable gourmet olives a
two-year shelf life.
>> narrator: in the middle ages,
navigators looked to the stars
and planets to find their way,
and for that, they relied on a
scientific instrument called the
astrolabe.
using this instrument, they
could measure the angular
distances between celestial
objects to calculate latitude.
it was the medieval equivalent
of gps.
today, craftsmen still make
astrolabes to celebrate their
place in history.
without it, columbus may not
have discovered the americas in
1492.
back then, astrolabes were
hand-forged and hand-engraved.
today, these instruments take
shape in two-part rubber molds
and closed in a metal drum.
the operator ladles molten
pewter into the mold through an
opening in the drum's lid.
inside, the mold spins, forcing
pewter into every part of this
astrolabe plate, complete with
geometric engravings on both
sides.
he molds the dial and pointers
the same way.
he slices off excess pewter.
it will be remelted and reused.
he then sands the ragged edges
of the plate for a smoother
circumference.
next, he pours an acidic liquid
onto the astrolabe plate, which
blackens the pewter.
he swishing the blackening agent
around to ensure it covers every
surface completely.
he places the blackened plate in
a barrel full of gritty, plastic
cones, soap, and water.
as it revolves, everything
tosses about inside to scrub the
surface of the astrolabe plate
but leave the engraved designs
black.
this process adds definition to
the markings.
in columbus' time, they would
have used a pumice stone and a
lot of elbow grease to achieve
this effect.
next, the astrolabe plate goes
for a tumble with bits of
ceramic to buff the pewter to a
glossy shine.
against the shiny pewter
backdrop, the geometric markings
now stand out.
clearly visible on the front is
a map of the sky and the zodiac
calendar.
and on the back, the
mathematical scales are now
clearly defined.
the elaborate dial undergoes the
same processing to enhance its
celestial engravings.
he now inserts a brass bushing
in the center hole of the
astrolabe plate and twists it
into position.
this bushing will act as a pivot
for the dial and pointers.
once the dial is in position, he
installs a pointer on each side
of the plate.
these pointers can be turned
like the hands of a clock, and
the user measures the angle of
the stars and planets in
relation to the horizon to
calculate his location.
he caps the bushing with a screw
on one side and a nut on the
other.
he secures the assembly with a
specific amount of torque to
allow the dial and pointers to
move freely.
he slips a metal ring through
the top hole of the astrolabe so
this instrument can be linked to
a chain if the owner wishes.
he spins the dial and pointers
to confirm that they don't snag
on the outer lip of the
instrument.
centuries after its heyday,
this incredible instrument still
fascinates.
the amount of information that
can be gleaned from holding it
to the sky is astounding.
more than latitude, the
astrolabe can be used to tell
time, determine seasons, and
predict the future with
horoscopes.
of course, it takes a basic
understanding of geometry and
astronomy to use it.
to the trained eye, this
astrolabe now reads 1:00 p.m.,
proving that this instrument
from another era can still
provide up-to-the-moment
information.
>> narrator: in the american
wild west, cowboys spent long
days in the saddle, which could
leave them too sore to ride off
into the sunset.
and that led to the development
of the western saddle.
large and sturdy, this saddle
was modeled on the type used
by spanish conquistadors, and it
made chasing cows a less painful
experience.
today, riders still saddle up
western-style, which is more
relaxed than english-stile, with
the reins held in one hand
instead of two.
the contours of the saddle
seat are more pronounced for
added comfort.
a western saddle also has a horn
for looping rope, called the
lariat in cowboy lingo.
it starts with the saddletree,
made from laminated wood
covered in sections of rawhide.
an artisan cuts out the
saddle skirt and other
components using a hydraulic
press.
he cuts the saddle seat by hand
with this tool, called a head
knife.
the seat gets special attention
because it's being custom-made
for a particular horse.
he shaves the edges of each cut
out so it can be tucked neatly
onto the saddletree.
the technique is called skiving.
he brushes glue on the
leather section that fits around
the stem of the saddle horn.
then he works it into position,
creating a lip around the horn's
top.
he presses the horn cap onto
the leather-rimmed top, then
crimps the edges together.
he collects tacks with a
magnetic tip of a hammer, then
pounds them through the leather
cap, securing it to the wood.
a thick leather cutout hides
the nail heads.
he carves a groove around the
top of the horn and punches
holes through the leather.
this will make it easier to sew
the layers together.
he uses two needles to interlock
the stitches.
this secures the cap and gives
the saddle horn a tailored
look.
to complete the horn, the
saddlemaker trims away excess
leather with a special forked
blade.
now the artisan builds up
sections of the saddletree with
strategically placed strips of
leather.
he skives away some leather to
improve the form.
then he places a leather-backed
piece of tin over the built-up
areas and nails it down.
this part will add strength to
the seat.
he continues shaping the seat,
then shaves the edges to blend
it to the saddletree.
the seat area gets one last
leather buildup and some
intensive skiving and sanding.
next, he glues the nail's
leather around the base of the
horn -- an area called the
swells.
he then applies leather to the
back of the seat, called the
cantle.
after cutting away surplus
leather, the artisan uses this
edging tool to trim the skirt.
this makes it smooth so it won't
chafe the horse or the rider.
another worker immerses the
saddle seat in warm water.
this makes the leather soft and
pliable, allowing it to be
shaped.
he drapes the seat around the
built-up saddletree and straps
it down.
as it dries, it hardens into the
shape of the tree.
he shapes the back section of
the seat separately and pins the
wet leather to dry to the form.
then he glues the whole seat to
the saddletree.
but there is much more to be
done before it's ready for ranch
duty, so stay tuned.
>> narrator: a western saddle
serves an important function,
but it also sports elaborate
artwork engraved in the leather.
this custom goes back to the
wild west, when a saddle was a
status symbol and ornate art and
decorative silver signified
that a cowboy was riding high.
the saddlemaker now shapes the
seat right up to the back of the
cantle.
he crimps the edge to build up a
part called the cheyenne roll.
he maps out its precise
dimensions with a compass...
then trims the part following
his scratch line.
with a wooden dowel, he
again presses the leather seat
to the saddle's contours for a
final shaping.
he sews through four layers of
leather to finish off the
cheyenne roll.
the thread is an artificial
sinew -- a superstrong nylon
that makes the seam virtually
indestructible.
the focus now moves to the
leather saddle skirts, as an
artist engraves a floral design.
the artist uses a wide range of
tools with expertise, like this
one, called a back rounder,
which he uses to carve recesses
around the design.
a spray of water softens the
leather, making it easier to
engrave.
next, he installs metal plates
on either side of each skirt.
they're part of the saddle
rigging, which will be used to
secure the saddle to the horse,
so it's crucial that these
plates be firmly entrenched in
the leather.
he secures each plate to the
skirt with several rivets, then
rounds them off, getting rid of
any sharp edges that would
irritate the horse.
the saddlemaker then brushes
glue on the back of the skirt to
attach a leather part with a
rear cinch ring riveted to it.
here, he glues and rivets the
top part to this skirt to
the main section.
he arranges a piece of
sheepskin facedown...
then glues the back of the
saddle skirt to it so the woolly
side will rest against the
horse.
this part is all about the
horse's creature comfort.
the saddlemaker sews the skirt
onto the sheepskin using a
machine with a heavy-duty
needle.
he then trims the excess
sheepskin following the line of
the leather skirt.
to remove some of the bulk, he
shears the wool, tapering it
around the edges.
next, he braids leather lace
into a tight weave called
latigo lace.
it ties both halves of the
skirt together and will later be
used to fasten the skirt to the
saddle.
he pulls the lace under the
weave to secure it.
next, he applies a generous
amount of glue to a leather
stirrup cover.
the stirrup is meat of oak,
steamed into a "u" shape and
then reinforced with galvanized
tin.
he presses leather into the
crook of the stirrup.
then he bolts a metal spacer
into the top.
now it's time to attach the
saddle skirts to the tree.
he threads cinch strings through
the cinch keeper and nails it to
the saddle.
another worker now rubs special
oil into this western saddle to
add color to the leather and
preserve it.
the oiling also exposes the
grain of the leather and
highlights the engraved designs.
from start to finish, this
western saddle has taken
40 hours to make, but the modern
cowboy should get plenty of
mileage out of it.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...