♪♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: artificial intelligence
is an area of computer science
focused on creating intelligent machines
that work and react to humans.
the term "robot" first appeared in 1920.
it comes from the czech word "robota,"
meaning "forced labor."
this facility makes a type of educational robot
equipped with a series of interconnected servomotors.
this type of equipment allows the robot
to move with an extraordinary degree of dexterity.
construction starts from scratch.
tiny bushings are created from a steel rod
placed inside this high-tech automated machining device.
a technician monitors the operation
as the machine shapes the parts
with digitized precision
to the design specifications.
the high-speed steel bits
carve the metal at an incredible speed.
this machine can manufacture 1,309 parts
per every eight-hour shift.
the parts fall into a vibrating mechanism
that feeds them into the next phase of production.
a specialized device called a gear-hobbing machine
quickly and accurately cuts a series of cogs
to create tiny sprocket wheels.
♪♪
a technician uses state-of-the-art measuring devices
to gauge the profile, tooth alignment, and pitch
of sample parts
to ensure they are up to standards specified
in the manufacturer's control plan.
another operator mounts a gear plate on a device,
fastening it to a smaller part called the sun gear.
♪♪
once all the required parts are tested and prepped,
technicians begin putting them all together
to create d.c. motors.
since the robots are specialty items
with small production quantities,
this facility is able to assemble each motor by hand.
the gears used in the motors are made of a variety of metals
to account for different requirements
of torque and loading force within the device.
moving with speed and precision,
specialists are able to assemble each motor
in less than 10 minutes.
♪♪
next, the tiny control unit is installed.
that will allow the user to manipulate the robot.
the technician carefully attaches
the bottom portion of the unit inside the motor container
with a small cordless drill.
once the unit is firmly secured,
he expertly positions the wire leads
to prepare them for the next step.
a technician quickly solders the wires in place.
now that the installation of the control panel is complete,
a technician finalizes the d.c. motor assembly
by attaching the cover
and securing it down with four screws
using a cordless drill.
♪♪
next, the individual motors
are installed into the framework of the robot.
one motor becomes the robot's head,
while the remaining motors are attached to hinged joints
that correspond to a major body part.
then the robot's wiring is plugged in,
ensuring the motors are connected to each other.
they now form parts of an integrated device
which can act together.
technicians use a 3-d printer
to create a suit of armor for the robot,
which they mount on its exterior
to give it a more finished look.
♪♪
a specialist plugs the robots into a computer
and programs their different movements.
the robot tech communicates with the robot's control panel
to make it do remarkable things.
but first, an old-fashioned rock 'em sock 'em
before they take over the world.
♪♪
narrator: when professional boxers win a title,
they're crowned the champ
and rewarded with a belt to be worn around the waist.
each international organization
commissions a belt
that's custom-designed to its specifications
and prominently features the organization's logo
in the belt's central medallion.
these boxing championship belts
are entirely handcrafted.
the laterals, the side pieces
flanking the ornate centerplate,
are sometimes engraved with a fighter's portrait.
when a boxing association commissions a new design,
the company's artisans prepare a sketch for each piece.
following the sketch, they sculpt a clay model.
from that, they cast a plaster model,
then a metal model,
refining the sculpture at each step.
artisans use the final metal model
to produce a rubber mold,
which is used to cast the piece
in white metal.
the extracted castings are quite rough,
so the workshop's craftsmen
use files, chisels, and automated tools
to refine the shape.
some of the devices and techniques
are routinely used by jewelers,
while others were designed specifically for this purpose.
♪♪
once the intricate details are completed,
the team files down rough spots
along the perimeter.
♪♪
the belts feature
a three-dimensional sculpture of an eagle
fused to the centerplate.
an artisan heats the wings with an open flame
to make them pliable.
then he bends them to render the eagle more lifelike.
♪♪
every piece must be meticulously hand-polished
on a buffing wheel.
this prepares the metal to be plated with gold or rhodium.
♪♪
the piece is electroplated with copper,
then nickel, then 18-karat gold.
the nickel carries the shine through to the surface.
after a thorough buffing on the surface,
the pieces are embellished with
crystals into molded cavities.
♪♪
sometimes the championship winner
may order precious stones such as diamonds and rubies
to replace the crystals, depending on their preference.
a team of enamelers paints the finished pieces
with jewelry-grade enamel.
this requires a steady hand and close attention to detail.
once the piece is painted,
it's put into an oven to bake the enamel.
♪♪
the belt strap is made of high-grade bonded leather.
a craftsman traces a belt template in the leather,
then cuts it out with a knife.
then they adhere the strap to leather or high-grade vinyl.
the designer sews the strap's lining separately,
stitching black spandex over a faux-fur backing
and attaching the authenticity label
which bears the belt's serial number.
this distinguishes it from cheaply made copies.
the craftsman attaches leather/high-grade vinyl piping
to the strap perimeter.
he places a brand sticker on the back
next to an inscribed tribute
to the originator of the modern boxing belt.
they adhere the lining.
then, after smoothing out the layers of the belt
with a hammer,
the designer stitches the lining to the strap.
some belts have buckles, others hook-and-loop fasteners,
which are stitched to the strap
at the same time as the lining.
once the belt is finished,
the centerplate and laterals are attached.
it's essential to wear gloves while doing this
to protect the pristine surface.
the final step is to place an engravable brass plate
into each lateral.
then the championship belt is delivered
in a hand-crafted protective case
for a knockout presentation.
♪♪
narrator: radar helps sailors navigate
through inclement weather while on the water,
ensuring they aren't operating blind.
these specialized pedestal mounts
elevate the radar systems,
which maximize the antenna's range.
the mounts also provide equipment stability
while traveling over rough waters.
boat-radar mounts are one of the most critical pieces
of navigation equipment to have on deck.
radar-mount construction
begins with a computer-generated drawing
that specifies the height and angle of the tower.
the parts are made from extruded marine-grade aluminum.
a machinist clamps the first top plate in a jig
and sets the tower upside down on the top plate.
the jig holds the tower in position
as he tack-welds the assembly in place.
♪♪
after clamping side gussets to the tower,
the technician turns it right-side up
and inserts the bottom tabs in a baseplate
to position it for assembly.
using an angle ruler,
he confirms that the tower stands at 90 degrees.
then he welds the radar-equipment tower
to the base.
he sets the tower on its side
to measure locations for tack welds,
marking each with a pen.
next, he makes larger stitch welds intermittently.
this will secure the gussets to the tower.
♪♪
the machinist installs a gusset arm or bracket
in the middle of the radar tower.
♪♪
using a metal puck as a guide,
he centers another top plate on the gusset arm.
he clamps it and measures its placement
to verify that it's properly centered,
and welds it to the arm.
♪♪
he removes the puck
and installs another mounting arm at the base.
a computerized drill cuts bolt holes
in a radar-mounting plate.
radar-bolting patterns vary, so it configures them
to match up with a specific radar system.
once the bolt holes are placed,
the drill carves around the border of the plate,
reshaping it from square to round.
the circular profile will match the base
of the satellite-radar system.
in a process known as countersinking,
he bevels the rims of the bolt holes
to a graduated profile.
this method will provide a stronger connection
between the mounting platform and the radar system.
with a special deburring tool,
the technician removes
sharp edges left by the countersinking process.
he smooths the outer edges of the mounting plate
using a hand sander.
the mounting plate is placed in a tub
of vibrating ceramic stones mixed with water.
the friction removes any lingering imperfections
and sharp edges.
another technician cuts aluminum wings
for an accessory extension.
the extension could hold a number of accessories,
including a radio, gps antenna,
or deck lights.
the parts are hollow in order to house wiring.
the wings will be assembled to a center trunk.
but first, they cap one end of each wing.
this wing will contain wiring
snaked through from holes in the sides of the trunk.
♪♪
the technician welds a wing to each side of the trunk.
this step completes the accessory-extension structure.
♪♪
next, it's time to build an arm
for a navigation light.
a hydraulic press bends the arm
to the desired curvature.
a measuring tool indicates the angle of the bend.
the technician drills a hole for
the installation of the light.
after a powder-coat finish has been applied to all the parts,
the mount is ready for assembly on the boat.
♪♪
by using critical navigational equipment,
this boat-radar mount will ensure
that any boater will be able to find their bearings.
♪♪
narrator: european radiators exude both warmth and style.
the heating-tube technology
can be modified for electric or hot-water heating systems
and can be made in a range of designs.
these radiators can blend into a background
or stand out to make a statement
on the wall.
♪♪
this european-style radiator is typically mounted to a wall
so it doesn't take up floor space,
allowing more room for furniture and people.
making panel radiators starts with steel flat tubes.
using a circular saw,
the machine cuts a stack of the tubes to length.
these flat tubes will be held together
by struts known as headers.
an automated drill punches holes
for bushings into the ends.
at the next station,
a machine inserts bushings into the holes
and welds them together.
♪♪
another welding device
seals the ends of the flat heating tubes.
the tubes are stacked.
♪♪
meanwhile, technicians prepare the headers,
which are made of square steel tubes.
an automated machine punches holes in the headers.
these holes will allow hot water
to flow throughout the radiator.
a circular saw cuts the header to its specified length.
most radiators are custom-made,
and sizes are determined
by the heating requirements of the space.
the headers are equipped with endcaps and fittings
to supply water and vent air.
a technician inserts the caps
into the ends of the header tube
and hammers them down.
♪♪
he clamps several of the capped headers
in a fixture.
♪♪
the fixture holds them in position
as an automated welder joins the caps to the headers.
♪♪
here is the header tubing
before and after the holes were punched
and the endcaps were welded.
with the header clamped into another fixture,
a drill carves a threaded connector into the side.
this connector will be used to plumb the radiator
to the hot-water system.
♪♪
it's now time to build the grid of heating tubes.
first, a machine moves the header into position.
an automated arm slides the flat heating tube
into place on the header,
and a welding device joins them together.
the automated welder
installs flat tubes on each side of the headers
and applies the company logo.
strips of steel will be used
to make fins that direct heat upward.
♪♪
a machine punches a series of notches in the steel
to mount the fins to the back of the radiator.
a hydraulic press bends the notched steel,
creating an accordion-like profile.
these ridges create pockets
that will capture hot air and allow it to rise.
the fins coil up at the end of the line
for easy transfer to the next station.
at this point, all the flat tubes
have been fully assembled to the headers.
an operator places the fins,
which have been cut to a specified length,
on the back of the flat-tube grid.
a machine welds the fins to the heating tubes
between the folds.
this step produces a heating panel
that will radiate heat up and out.
another team member installs metal trim
on the top of the radiator.
he places mounts on the back corners
and welds them together.
these mounts will house threaded bolts,
which will be used to level the radiator to the wall.
the radiator is now fully assembled.
the radiator undergoes a quality-control test.
technicians pump in air and submerge it in water.
if bubbles appear, it indicates a leak.
if not, the radiator is removed
from the water.
electrostatically charged epoxy particles
are sprayed onto the device,
which provide a protective layer.
this european-style radiator is now ready
to release some major heat.