-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: the first computers
used to be the size of an entire room.
then they were built to fit on your desk.
the newest design is a portable
device that sits on your lap,
and today's laptops are made
even smaller and more powerful than ever.
with its lightning-fast processor
and impressive graphics,
this laptop is designed for high-performance gaming.
the computer's brain, called the motherboard,
begins as a printed circuit board.
its pattern of lines and pads and copper
is the wiring for the electronic components
that will be soldered to the board.
this machine places a stencil of the component layout
onto the board
and applies solder paste through the openings.
a quality-inspection camera photographs the solder paste
and sends the images to a computer.
the computer analyzes them, looking for any missing paste,
misalignment, or other mistakes.
if the board passes inspection,
it passes through 15 robotic machines,
each of which places up to 150 components
on the correct locations
on the board in just 30 seconds.
then the board runs through an oven
that melts the solder paste,
connecting the components to the board.
another camera inspection ensures
that the internal processor is correctly soldered,
and that no component is missing
or shifted out of position.
after function testing and a visual inspection,
the motherboard moves to the assembly line
and is set aside for the time being.
next, technicians manually assemble the top half
of the laptop called the panel kit.
they place protection film on the 15-inch lcd screen.
then they plug in the cable
that will connect the lcd to the motherboard.
they insert the lcd screen into a frame with a web camera
and microphone already embedded.
then they attach this antenna
bottom cover to the screen cover
and position
the motherboard cable inside it.
next, they install the module for the webcam and microphone.
they attach two hinges,
which connect this panel kit to the rest of the laptop.
then they install the wi-fi antenna
in the antenna bottom cover.
♪♪
all components are concealed in the antenna bottom cover
behind this antenna top cover.
they complete the panel kit
by pressing in a thin metal frame around the screen.
♪♪
next, they assemble the bottom half of the laptop.
first, technicians attach the top cover
to the panel-kit hinges and the touchpad.
♪♪
then they install the right and
left speakers in the top cover.
now the motherboard comes back into play.
after inspection, a computer-guided router
cuts out openings to accommodate
the computer's fans,
which prevent the electronics from overheating.
a gaming laptop generates a lot
more heat than a regular laptop
and therefore requires two powerful fans rather than one.
after checking that the fan screws
are sufficiently tightened,
they place the motherboard into the top cover.
contaminants such as dust or oil
can impede proper contact,
so as a precaution, they clean the connectors
for the memory modules with solvent,
then dry them with compressed air.
then they install the memory module,
the wi-fi and bluetooth module,
and the solid-state disc, which stores data.
they connect a high-capacity battery to the motherboard.
batteries for gaming laptops are typically larger
because the faster processor and
dual fans consume more power.
the last component is the keyboard,
which fits into a rectangular opening
in the top cover of the bottom half.
a laser-etching machine
marks the required information underneath.
an automated machine tests numerous functions,
and a quality-control team tests
several others,
including the virtual-reality feature...
...the lcd and keyboard color displays...
and the keys.
not only must the keys function
properly,
they need to be durable,
so enthusiastic gamers won't break them while playing.
♪♪
narrator: panettone is a traditional italian sweetbread
most commonly prepared for dessert on christmas
and new years.
baking authentic panettone
can take up to two days or more to make.
a certain expertise is needed to turn these ingredients
into its domed-like shape while
maintaining its fluffy center.
the baker pours high-protein flour to a mixing bowl.
then he adds the flour
into an industrial-sized dough mixer
that has hooked mixing arms.
he adds fresh yeast, milk powder,
and enough water to bind the ingredients together.
he places the safety cage over the dough mixer.
as the hook agitators blend the ingredients, gluten forms.
glutens will give the panettone structure.
sugar will feed the growth of the yeast.
the agitators evenly distribute it in the dough.
meanwhile the baker cracks eggs
and separates the yolks from the whites.
he weighs the yolks and adds them to the mix.
this panettone recipe calls for egg yolks only.
yolks provide fat to help emulsify the dough
and give it flavor.
to further enrich the flavor of the panettone,
he adds a generous amount of butter.
the mixer folds it into the dough.
he transfers the dough to a container
and leaves it to rise for 11 hours.
this process is called proofing the dough.
the dough undergoes multiple proofings.
in between each proofing period,
the baker deflates the dough
and returns it to the mixer.
during this process, the yeast consumes sugar,
so he adds more to feed the process.
next, he adds more of the other ingredients,
and the mixer kneads them into the dough for one hour.
the mixer works the dough, creating bands of elasticity,
so that the dough will stretch during rising.
in the final mixing stage,
the baker adds vanilla extract for another flavor dimension.
while the dough mixer distributes it,
he measures fruit by weight.
the panettone recipe calls for two parts raisins,
one part candied orange pieces,
and one part candied lemon pieces.
the mixer folds them into the dough.
after another proofing,
the baker slices the fruited dough into chunks.
some of the water in the dough will evaporate during baking
and the panettone should end up about two pounds.
he shapes each chunk into a uniform mold
and leaves the dough chunks
to rise for an hour in a warm chamber.
instead of metal pans, panettone
is baked in these paper molds.
the molds will also be used as retail packaging.
after about an hour in the warming chamber,
the dough chunks have doubled in size.
the baker works them into a rounder form
and transfers them to paper molds.
then it's back into the warming
chamber for another proofing.
as the dough rises,
the round shape is contained by the paper molds.
after six hours, he takes out the molds and carves
crosses into the risen dough.
he adds small pieces of butter to the middle of each cross.
after 24 hours of preparation,
the panettones are ready to be cooked.
they bake for 45 minutes at 320 degrees fahrenheit.
once complete, he quickly spears each panettone
with a metal rod near the base and hangs it upside down.
the panettones cool for up to 24 hours
in this upside-down suspended state.
this stretches the warm breads to give them their dome shape
and stops them from caving inward.
once cooled, the panettones are
ready to be wrapped for retail.
all that proofing has allowed the flavors to mature
and the fluffy texture to develop.
the yeast will act as the preservative,
keeping this italian christmas bread fresh for up to 30 days.
♪♪
narrator: the saxophone was invented in the mid-1800s
by adolphe sax,
the son of belgium's chief instrument maker.
with the saxophone, sax blended
the power of a brass horn
with the nuances of a woodwind instrument.
this instrument has the ability
to sound
bright and edgy or dark and moody.
even though it's made of brass or high-copper alloys,
the saxophone is technically a woodwind instrument.
that's because it produces sound
by vibrating a reed attached to the mouthpiece.
the process of making a saxophone
starts with a long brass or copper sheath.
a hydraulic punch cuts the metal
into rectangles.
after tracing a flared pattern onto one piece of metal,
a craftsman aligns the pattern with the punch
to cut out the part.
this part will now be formed into the saxophone's bell.
the worker folds it around the metal rod
and pounds it with a wooden stick
to do some initial shaping.
this takes the part from flat to three dimensional.
after the seam has been welded,
more hammering rounds the shape
substantially
and improves on the flare at the end.
next, the craftsman repeatedly pounds the flare
to form it into a bell.
hand-hammering shapes the metal
and also alters the physical properties
to make the sound more resonant.
throughout the forming of the instrument,
it is heated with a torch.
this makes the metal flexible enough to be shaped.
next, he slides the bell onto a form.
he brushes lubricant onto the metal...
and lowers a roller.
the form spins the curved bell against the roller,
which smoothes out dents and forces the bell
to conform
to the dimensions of the roller.
the rolled saxophone bell is the one on the right.
it's dramatically different.
now we can see the saxophone's body take shape.
it starts with this piece of metal that's wider at one end.
the operator places it under a cone-shaped form.
using hydraulics, it descends to fold the part
and imprint the cone shape on the metal.
after more forming,
another worker welds the seams to complete the cone.
this part of the instrument is also called the tube.
meanwhile, the forming work on the saxophone bell
has been completed.
a worker locks the upper part of the bell into a machine
and turns the punch device to cut the tone holes.
sound waves will be emitted
through both the open tone holes
and the bell's flare.
later, another worker aims a torch
at the saxophone body to soften the metal,
so that the rims of the tone holes can now be formed.
he slides the body onto a steel
mandrel with round inserts.
he aligns the tone holes with holes on the mandrel.
he sets a guide rack on top, aligning the holes in the rack
with the holes in the instrument.
he inserts tools through the holes
and threads them into the round
inserts in the mandrel.
a support bracket props up the tools.
using the tools, he pulls the inserts through the holes.
this forms a rim around each hole.
the raised edging will allow key cups
to close the tone holes effectively.
the craftsman drills the rims to smooth and level them.
this will prevent gaps that could affect the sound
of the instrument when the key cups close.
the next part is the bow,
which will link the saxophone bell and body.
the craftsman brushes a cleaning agent
known as flux onto one end.
he connects the two parts
and applies more flux to
the bell where it meets the bow.
he then melts solder where the two parts come together,
completing this critical connection.
the solder makes the joint airtight.
he turns over the bell and bow assembly to complete the job,
ensuring that the solder encompasses the entire joint.
he dabs water onto the soldered
joint to cool it down.
but before this saxophone is ready to make music,
a few more steps must be taken for good measure.
♪♪
narrator: the saxophone has tonal qualities
similar to those of the human voice.
its sound can range from sultry,
dark tones
to high-pitched exuberance.
it's no wonder the saxophone has found a place
in many music styles from jazz to pop to the classics.
the standard saxophone has 23 different tone holes
and an equal number of key cups to close them.
at this factory, each key cup is assembled by hand.
a craftsman arranges the parts of a key cup in a fixture
to position them for soldering.
he inserts a rod that will act as an alignment
and positioning tool.
he applies flux to clean the part
and melts silver solder into the connecting points.
to prevent the parts from sliding,
the craftsman uses pincers to adjust their position.
other keys are grouped together
on a brass plate known as a rib.
he spaces the key posts evenly on a rod
that serves as an alignment tool.
several overhead clamps hold the posts in place on the rib.
he applies the chemical cleaner
to the base of the post
and the plate around them.
silver solder is melted around the post,
and as it solidifies, it fuses them to the plate.
next, the craftsman removes the overhead clamp system.
after sliding keys onto the ends
of the alignment rod,
he positions the assembly on the saxophone body.
he closes the keys onto the corresponding tone holes
and solders the base plate
to the lower part of the saxophone body.
he brushes water onto the solder
to accelerate the cooling and solidification.
he then removes the alignment rod
and uncaps the tone holes for now.
a cleaning agent is brushed onto
the back of a rib
that supports a second grouping of key posts.
he solders the rib to the upper
part of the saxophone body
and takes the alignment rod off.
the posts have been installed in a specific sequence
to support extending keys on a hinge rod.
later, another worker polishes the bow and bell assembly
against a buffing wheel, which polishes the instrument
to remove smudges or fingerprints
and give the brass parts a mirror finish.
they dip the brass saxophone parts in a bath
where sound waves help
remove residual dirt and grease.
there's also a chemical primer in the bath
that will help a lacquer bond to the brass.
a technician sprays the lacquer
onto the brass
to protect it from corrosion and tarnish.
floral artwork will add visual flair
to this copper saxophone bell.
the copper has been painted
black to make the art stand out.
the artist follows the stencil with an etching tool,
rotating it using a twirling motion technique,
etching in fluid movements.
he doesn't stop until he's completed a line
to prevent any inconsistencies in the engraving.
after he completes the pattern,
he does detail work.
this exposes the copper metal and makes the art pop.
returning to the brass saxophone now,
a technician screws long hinge rods to the posts.
he attaches the keys,
which have been equipped with pads in the cups.
a tiny screw secures this grouping of keys.
he turns the saxophone over, inserts a light,
and looks for escaping rays, making adjustments if needed.
he installs needle springs under
the key rods and main hinge rod.
they'll enable the keys to spring back
after they're pressed.
he tests the spring action and,
again, checks for light leaks.
he now fits the bell bow to the main body.
there's a connecting ring that holds them together,
but he'll also lock them in place with a screw.
from start to finish,
it takes about a month to craft this saxophone.
whether it's made out of basic brass
or something a little showier, the look of the instrument
can reflect
the saxophonist's playing style,
but the tone of the instrument defines it.
[ saxophone music plays ]
♪♪