-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: people have been steaming food for thousands of years.
once upon a time, steamers were
made out of clay pots
with perforated floors.
today, we've come up with all sorts of metal
and plastic innovations.
the traditional bamboo steamer is a perfect balance
between the old and the new.
perfected by generations of craftsmen,
traditional bamboo steamers are lightweight, strong,
and durable.
they look like simple cooking tools,
but building them requires enormous artisanal skill.
the craftsman buys lengths of bamboo from local farmers.
he uses a traditional planer he crafted himself
to smooth the bamboo joints.
a customized chopper tool helps
him split the bamboo lengthwise.
he inserts a bamboo stick to hold the split open.
after removing the chopper, he pulls on the stick
to split
the entire length of the bamboo.
the craftsman splits the sections again.
to assemble the steamer base,
the craftsman will split the bamboo into 32 pieces.
the cover will require 128 pieces.
a custom-made knife knocks down
the intersections of the bamboo.
for the steamer's cover,
the craftsman splits the bamboo horizontally.
next, the craftsman uses this slicing tool to cut the wood.
he sets the desired width
and slices a thin sheet of wood lengthwise.
he uses this section of wood to form the base of the steamer
and slides a bamboo ring over it to hold it in place.
then he punches small holes with a drill...
...and reinforces the joint with stainless steel wire.
the installation process begins.
first by installing a series of inner rings
which will serve to reinforce the structure of the steamer
and to support multiple levels of steamers inside it.
the craftsman uses special techniques to ensure
that each joint is perfectly aligned for maximum strength.
working almost entirely by hand
with skills acquired over time,
he meticulously creates a strong,
yet lightweight piece of kitchen equipment.
the basket still needs a bottom
to rest dumplings in.
the craftsman begins building the basket floor
by custom fitting
a series of rugged cross pieces.
he ensures that each piece fits
perfectly before proceeding.
then he inserts thin, more pliable pieces of bamboo
to hold the cross pieces in place.
next, he lays the final layer on top,
placing the pieces with their outer sides
facing up to form a smooth surface for food
to sit on while steaming.
with the floor of the steamer in place,
it's time to secure the upper pieces
by binding them to the support pieces.
to do this, he threads a stainless steel wire
through the cracks,
twisting the ends tightly to the base.
then he gives the inner support
rings under
the steamer floor a few taps, securing them in place.
the basket's base is now complete.
next, the craftsman begins weaving the bamboo pieces
together that will form the cover.
he uses a traditional pattern called a twill weave.
then he inserts paper before
adding a second layer of bamboo.
the paper will help prevent steam from escaping
the basket too quickly.
he then snaps in a series of carefully sized reinforcements
to keep the layers in place.
finally, he custom fits another
interior ring
under the reinforcements to hold everything together,
tapping it carefully into position.
the steamer cover is now complete.
♪♪
narrator: a three-wheel motorized scooter
provides the rider
with more stability than a two-wheeled scooter.
by utilizing three points of contact with the ground,
this scooter is less likely to skid or fall over
when making a sharp turn,
or while driving on an unpaved surface.
this high-end, three-wheeled scooter
has the look and comfort of a motorcycle
without the high price tag.
it can reach speeds of up to 85 miles per hour
and travel about 186 miles on a full tank of gas.
at the factory, mechanics begin
assembling the engine
by pressing two ball bearings
into the left side of an aluminum crankcase.
they insert a third ball bearing that's assembled
to the gear shaft.
♪♪
then the crankshaft is installed
on the opposite end.
in between the two cases,
a gasket is mounted to prevent oil from leaking out.
mechanics fit the right side of
the crankcase to the left side
and bolt them together.
they place one end of the drive
chain around the crankshaft,
and then another.
this gear is installed for the oil pump.
as the crankshaft rotates,
the interior of the engine is greased with oil.
this gear rotates the crankshaft,
which starts the engine.
and this gear, assembled to a generator,
goes on the crankshaft.
when the generator rotates, it provides electric current
to run the scooter's lights
and other electrical components.
technicians close up the right side
of the crankcase with a cover...
...install the water pump...
...and cap the generator.
next, mechanics install reduction gears
onto the ball bearings
that were placed in the left side of the crankcase.
reduction gears lower the
rotation speed of the crankshaft
to make it more manageable for the drive shaft
which turns the wheels.
a pulley-based automatic transmission system
called a cvt is assembled.
it's powerful, fuel-efficient, and runs smoother
than a standard, gear-based, automatic transmission.
technicians attach the piston to the piston rod
and place it into the engine's single cylinder.
the bottom of the piston rod is linked to the crankshaft.
they place an aluminum cover over the transmission
and install the cylinder head,
which is equipped with several sensors
for fuel injection and other functions.
next, mechanics mount the
rear wheel onto the drive shaft.
this aluminum swing arm supports the wheel and engine.
the steel frame is pained black
and is engraved with the scooter's vehicle
identification number.
♪♪
technicians bolt the frame to the front of the engine
and to a pair of shock absorbers at the back.
♪♪
they install part of the front suspension system,
one on each side of the frame.
♪♪
then they mount the three wheel hubs
and install each integrated
brake disc with a brake caliper.
back to the front suspension system,
mechanics connect a shock
absorber to each triangular arm.
they install the handlebars,
brake levers with hydraulic cables,
and switches for the lights, signals, and horn.
once the ignition switch and vinyl seat is built in,
mechanics install the rear lights
and turn signals, the l.e.d. headlights...
and mount the three wheels and tires.
♪♪
the last step is to run the scooter
through a series of tests.
the test evaluates
the functionality of the lights,
turn signals, front and rear brakes, acceleration,
and the accuracy of the speedometer.
there is no question this scooter provides
a ton of stability.
with a front suspension system
designed to keep both front wheels on the ground,
the rider is guaranteed a smooth
and enjoyable ride.
♪♪
narrator: a conservatory is designed to let in sunlight.
it's often referred to as an extension of the home,
allowing people to enjoy the warmth of the sun
without ever having to step outside.
a prefabricated conservatory can be assembled in three days,
so you can quickly have an indoor place in the sun.
producing a prefab conservatory
starts with a customized computer-generated design.
first, a designer selects the parts for the framework.
this piece of vinyl cladding will be part
of a decorative ridge.
then all the materials are placed on racks.
there can be 50 to 500 pieces,
depending on the size of the conservatory.
using a circular blade,
the metal cutter trims aluminum components
to various lengths and angles, according to his measurements.
another designer welds aluminum
parts to build a gutter system.
he makes tight welds for waterproof joints.
next, a team assembles the frame
to confirm
that the parts connect together.
if successful, the framework will be taken apart
for reassembly on site.
after the roof's ridge beam is set on stands
in the center of the frame,
technicians bolt one end of a load beam to the eaves
and the other to the elevated ridge.
more beams are added to create a truss system
to support the roof.
the stands supporting the ridge
beam are removed.
a designer measures and maps out
roof panels on polycarbonate.
the polycarbonate has a hollow,
waffle structure
that gives it insulating properties.
he cuts out the panels according to his measurements.
after sealing the edges with felt,
the panels are mounted to the roof.
vinyl cladding on the exposed structural bar
secures the panels.
the designer tapes the vinyl with a hammer
to flare it against the polycarbonate.
then he installs the vinyl ridge gap.
the elaborate, molded finials make a statement
while stopping water from dripping
into the top of the roof.
he peels off the protective liner
to reveal the translucent polycarbonate panels.
on another production line,
an automatic saw cuts vinyl components
for the walls at the specified length.
routers carve holes for hardware.
saws cut notches in specific locations,
enabling them to join the rest of the building framework.
a technician arranges the vinyl
posts and beams
in a thermal welder.
the machine melts the parts where they intersect
and fuses them together.
each part of the wall frame is welded separately,
and then joined together.
the welding leaves the seams a bit rough,
so a machine trims off any excess vinyl.
a circular saw moves in and cleans up the exterior corners.
to customize the color,
designers spray the wall frame with an acrylic paint
that chemically bonds to the vinyl to prevent chipping.
back to the white frame.
a team inserts a glass panel in the ridged rim.
strips of vinyl around the edges
hold the glass in
and keep water out.
♪♪
the team assembles a factory display model.
the wall panels are installed into grooves on the frame
and connected by aluminum posts.
next, the doors are installed.
a technician tightly pulls the wall
frames to the aluminum posts using nylon composite devices.
vinyl casings cover the posts and any nylon locks.
using a crane, the team lowers the roof onto the structure
and bolts it in place.
the conservatory is complete.
now it's time to relax while sitting indoors.
♪♪
narrator: people have used copper pots
and pans for thousands of years.
copper is an ideal heat conductor,
allowing food to be cooked quickly and evenly.
copper pots allow for more precise temperature control,
which means dinner is less likely to be served burnt.
in the culinary world, copper is a precious metal.
besides being a great conductor
of heat,
copper pots look good on the cooktop.
to cut out a round blank,
a craftsman places a centering disk on a copper sheet.
he links it to a plasma torch using a metal spindle.
the spindle holds the torch at a specific distance
so that, as the torch cuts out
the circle, the radius is exact.
the coppersmith ensures that the cutout is as close
to the edge of the copper sheet
as possible to minimize waste.
next, he examines the circular blank.
the plasma cutting has left the edges frayed,
so he smoothes them by clamping
the copper blank in a lathe.
he taps the blank with a rubber mallet
and centers it between the clamping chucks.
the coppersmith uses a tool to check
that the blank is positioned correctly.
then he adds oil to the cutting tool
and moves it against the spinning blank.
it trims the circumference, creating a cleaner edge
and removes any flaws.
he files the rim of the copper blank to make it smooth
and even.
using sandpaper, he finishes the edge.
with the imperfections removed,
the copper blank is formed into
a sauce pan with sloping sides.
two craftsmen press a roller against the copper blank
so that it conforms to the shape of a mold.
that's part of one of the clamping chucks.
this process is called metal spinning.
while one craftsman moves the roller across the copper blank,
the other applies pressure.
this shaping method takes eight
to ten rounds.
finally, the pan has taken shape,
but the forming process has left
fine lines on the surface.
so as it continues to spin,
the coppersmith smoothes it down.
he applies lubricant to a cutting tool
and trims the rim of the saucepan.
this gives the pan the desired height.
the cutting leaves the edges very sharp,
so he files them down again.
the copper saucepan is ready for the cast-iron handle.
cast iron has less thermal conductivity than copper,
so the heat from the pan
will travel more slowly up the handle.
the craftsperson clamps the handle to the saucepan.
this holds it tightly in place as he drills rivet holes
through both the iron handle and the copper pan.
the craftsman removes the clamp
and bolts the handle to the pan temporarily.
this stabilizes it
for the drilling of the second rivet hole.
a rivet is inserted in the second hole
from the inside of the pan.
the coppersmith heats the tail of the rivet to soften it.
then the pan is transferred to an anvil.
using a pneumatic hammer,
the coppersmith flattens the first rivet,
removes the temporary bolt, and installs the second rivet.
he heats the pan over a flame
and melts a tin bar to the bottom.
he spreads the molten tin up the sides of the pan
using a rag that's been soaked with a flux chemical.
the flux cleans the copper
and allows the tin to flow more smoothly.
the tin lining will prevent acidic foods
from leeching raw copper into the food.
the heat from the tinning flame
has caused some discoloration.
the coppersmith removes the stains by using
a cotton buffing wheel and polishing compound.
as he continues,
the polishing takes the copper to a high sheen.
this copper saucepan is now ready for the stovetop.
but first, the craftsman pounds
a steel stamp
into the bottom of the pan,
imprinting it with the company logo.
for cookware that only takes a couple hours to make,
a copper pan can last for decades.
and if it's well cared for, it won't even show its age.