♪♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: glass faucets elevate
indoor plumbing to an art form.
the glass is hand-crafted in a range of shapes and patterns
for visual effect.
metal components are fused into the glass
to deliver one of the necessities of modern life,
running water.
glass faucets are about both form and function.
glass faucets have a delicate beauty,
but they're stronger than they look.
the glass is very thick,
allowing the faucets to hold up to heavy use.
making a glass faucet starts with chunks of clear glass.
a glass worker loads the glass
into an oven at 2,190 degrees fahrenheit.
another worker selects black and white billets of glass
to add stripes and patterns to the clear glass.
he preheats them so the glass won't shock and fracture
when exposed to higher temperatures.
with a metal rod,
he gathers a clump of the clear glass
from the main oven.
with the chunk of glass,
he picks up the preheated white cylinder,
simultaneously exposing both to the flames.
this process makes the glass flexible.
using a curved wood tool,
the glass worker gathers the clear glass at the base
and wraps it around the white billet,
encapsulating it.
he attaches the other end of
the glass to a second metal rod.
this allows the glass to stretch
as he pulls it across the room.
the glass is now over 35 feet long
and pencil-thin.
it starts to cool and solidify immediately
as it's set down.
the glass workers tap the glass
against a piece of metal
to break it into 8-inch pieces called canes.
they shape another piece of clear glass
by rolling it on a metal table called a marver.
the glass worker blows through the metal rod,
causing the glass on the end to bubble.
it will eventually become the faucet and two handles.
he adds a layer of black molten glass to the bubble.
another glass technician
arranges the striped canes on a grooved iron plate
and heats them with a torch.
meanwhile, a glass worker rolls
the hot glass bubble
onto the canes, which stick together.
then it's back into the furnace,
and the white-striped canes melt into the black bubble.
next, the craftsman rolls the glass
across the marver repeatedly.
he pinches the canes at the top,
closing them around the bubble.
the glass is reheated to keep it pliable
as the craftsman continues to form it.
the craftsman transforms the bubble
into a hollow glass tube
then elongating the tube to its desired length.
using a pincer-leg tool,
he forms the end into a round handle shape
while another glass worker
applies heat to the glass with a torch.
this keeps the glass pliable.
he then creates a hole for a piece of metal hardware.
then he applies molten glass to the metal hardware
and inserts the hardware into the round faucet handle.
this cuts the handle free from the rest of the glass.
using a forming tool,
the craftsman refines the shape of the glass.
next, he preheats a metal mold.
this stops the hot glass tube from fracturing
as he bends it around the mold to shape it into the faucet.
once the faucet has taken shape,
it's ready to go into the annealing oven.
the glass is placed in the oven
at a low temperature
and then cooled.
this process removes stresses and strengthens the glass.
meanwhile, using high-pressure water
that contains fragments of garnet,
a craftsman cuts steel trim rings
and a display plate for the showroom.
next, the craftsman installs the glass faucet
on the display plate
by threading a nut to the faucet valve.
he installs the trim rings at the base of the handles
and assembles them to the display plate
using the hardware that's been fused
to the inside of the glass.
the craftsman uses a rag
to clean the faucet
of any fingerprints and smudges.
finally, construction is complete.
this unique glass faucet is ready to make a statement.
♪♪
narrator: short fire trucks can easily access tight spaces
around the scene of a fire.
that's because they're lighter
and can carry more water and equipment.
however, it's difficult for smaller fire trucks
to support the weight of long ladders.
to compensate, manufacturers have built
longer ladders on shorter trucks.
this 108-foot-long ladder can be mounted
on a single rear-axle fire truck.
typically, a ladder longer than 75 feet
requires a tandem-axle truck to support its weight.
the secret to the design of this ladder
is that it's lighter, stronger, and durable.
the components are cut
from sheets and tubes of high-strength steel.
using a press brake, the machinist bends the parts,
verifying the accuracy of each bend.
once all the components are prepped,
the parts are welded together, then smoothed.
this welded part is the turntable base.
it rotates the ladder 360 degrees
and provides a platform for
the firefighter at the controls.
this is the torque box.
it supports the aerial pedestal
to which both the ladder and turntable are bolted.
to construct the ladder, technicians weld tubular rungs
to vertical side rails called base beams.
they reinforce the rungs
with diagonal tubes called k-braces,
which provide lateral structural strength.
welders fuse steel tubes between
the base beam and the handrail
to provide structural support.
next, an inspector from an independent testing company
examines the integrity of the welding.
once the ladder passes inspection,
it's put through a shot-blasting chamber,
which pummels the surface with steel pellets.
this process removes metal impurities
and preps the surface for painting.
craftsmen apply two coats of primer,
one top coat of color, then two clear coats of paint,
sanding by hand between each application.
next, a three-part anti-skid treatment
is applied to the turntable surface --
first, a coat of glue, then an abrasive material,
then a coat of sealant, which is
baked in an oven for 90 minutes.
the ladder rungs are covered with snap-on non-slip covers
made of fiberglass-reinforced plastic.
the ladders are stacked
in four or five compact sections.
technicians install a cable
that enables the sections to extend and retract.
the cable is attached to a hydraulic cylinder.
three telescopic sections of the aerial waterway
are attached.
this tube transfers water up to the top of the ladder
so when the ladder extends, so does the waterway.
this valve at the top of the waterway
allows firefighters to hook up a hose
to bring inside the building.
the water monitor, driven by an electric motor,
directs the water flow in all directions
when the aerial waterway is being used without a hose.
next, the machinists install the turntable controls,
which run the electrical power
and the hydraulics that move the ladder.
then they attach the ladder to the aerial pedestal
with a huge pin.
a large bolt is inserted,
which prevents the pin from sliding out of place.
this is what's referred to as a rear-mount ladder,
meaning it's installed on the back of the fire truck.
when a ladder is installed behind the cab,
it's called a mid-mount ladder.
assembly of the ladder is almost complete.
technicians bolt the turntable to the truck,
then hook up the hydraulic line
that operates the ladder.
♪♪
they install a swivel mechanism
which enables the aerial waterway
to move with the ladder and turntable.
♪♪
before it leaves the factory,
the ladder is put through a test run
to ensure it meets the highest standards.
♪♪
narrator: an antique clock can only be repaired by an expert.
this person would have either apprenticed under a clockmaker
or studied timekeeping at a horology school.
in today's digital landscape,
horologists are becoming a vanishing breed.
when your grandfather clock is struggling through old age,
it's time for a visit to the master clockmaker.
first step -- the dial and the mechanism
are placed on a stand for observation.
♪♪
two horologists inspect the clock for worn-down parts.
the mechanism contains two gear trains --
one for keeping time,
and another to regulate the hammer
that strikes a bell on the hour.
after the paperwork is completed,
the clockmaker gets to work.
he detaches the hands and dial
to gain access to the gear trains
and their linked components.
he removes tiny screws to release the hands.
then he removes pins that release the dial's four feet,
located within holes in the front plate.
an artist restores the dial.
the clockmaker unscrews the cast-iron bell
and begins disassembling the assortment of parts,
starting with the pallets.
the pallets receive power from the clock's suspended weights
and connect with the timekeeping gear train,
which moves the pendulum.
the shafts of the hour, minute, and second wheels
converge at the center of the largest wheel
on the front plate of the mechanism.
the clockmaker disassembles these and other components.
he lifts off the front plate to strip down the inner parts.
the cables suspending the weights
are made of woven brass.
the craftsman cleans all the metal parts
in an ultrasonic machine.
its high-frequency sound waves
force the chemical solution
into all the nooks and crannies.
he rinses the parts and dries them in jeweler's sawdust.
each part is inspected under a magnifying glass
to assess their condition.
if a part is worn,
the craftsman tries to restore it
to its original shape.
if it's too badly worn, he has to make a replacement
with a computer-guided milling machine.
the pin at the end of a gear is called a pivot.
after measuring its diameter with a digital caliper,
the clockmaker sets the disk of a filing machine
to its corresponding measurement.
he places the pivot between the disk
and a fine-grinding disk, filing away any rough surfaces.
♪♪
next, the craftsman works on the rear plate,
hammering in brass sleeves called bushings
into multiple gear holes.
he widens the bushing just enough to insert the pivot
and smooths out the hole.
he inserts one end of the pivot
in the rear-plate bushing,
the other end in the front-plate bushing,
and checks that the gear rotates smoothly.
he does the same for each pivot hole.
then, all the parts are cleaned,
and the mechanism is reassembled.
this gear on the front plate is the hour wheel.
♪♪
the clockmaker attaches the hour rack,
which connects to the gear train.
this system regulates
the striking of the bell on the hour.
once the mechanism is reassembled,
the horologist attaches the dial
to the front plate.
the dial of this clock required no restoration.
even the original steel hands are still in good condition.
when hands are in bad shape,
the clockmaker creates replicas.
when hands are missing,
he makes new ones in the style of the period.
during the entire reassembly,
the clockmaker wears gloves
to protect the steel and brass components
from the natural oils in his hands.
restoring an antique clock
can take several weeks of meticulous work.
when it's done,
the clockmaker mounts the clock
back on the stand,
connecting the weights and pendulum, and runs a test.
[ bell dinging ]
the job is complete when the clock keeps time
and the hammer strikes the bell
to announce the hour.
[ dinging continues ]
♪♪
narrator: cooking over an open flame
calls for a serious set of tools.
barbecue utensils are durable
and designed to withstand the heat.
built longer than regular kitchen utensils,
these tools enable the chef
to keep an arm's distance from the flame,
making barbecuing a safe and gratifying experience.
when barbecuing, it's important
to go big on tools.
these substantial utensils
will hold up to the intensity of the flame
while also offering precision and control.
making barbecue utensils
starts with a sheet of high-carbon stainless steel.
a laser cuts out several parts,
creating turner blades.
turner blades are broad,
enabling the user to flip burgers and fillets
without breaking them.
they also have slots for draining grease and juices.
a technician extracts the blades from the matrix
and punches out the pre-cut drainage slots.
the turner blades are placed on a rack
which lowers the blades between two coarse rollers.
an operator applies polishing compound to the rollers.
as the rollers turn,
the friction rubs off stamped information from the steel mill
and other blemishes.
technicians buff the blades to a smooth, matte texture.
this gives the blades a consistent polished finish.
♪♪
next, the blade is clamped to a special carriage
moving the blade back and forth
as a grinding wheel carves a thin beveled edge.
the beveled edge will make it easier
to lift meat off the grill.
an operator clamps the turner blade in a fixture.
a hydraulic press bends the neck of the blade.
high-grade walnut is the material used
to make the utensil handles.
it's a hard, durable wood
with a grain that adds visual interest.
using a bandsaw,
the operator carves the walnut block
into smaller chunks.
each one will become a handle blank.
he places the blanks on a conveyer
that takes them through a spinning cutting head.
the cutting head carves a taper
into the end of the handle
that will hold the blade tang.
to refine the shape,
a craftsman locks two handle blanks on a revolving table.
moving the handles against a router
can make the handles smoother for gripping.
it's quite a transformation.
multiple drill heads carve rivet holes on one side.
the holes have a graduated profile
to allow the rivets to sit flush to the wood.
the craftsman drills corresponding holes
on the other side.
using a circular saw, he cuts a slot
for the tang -- or stem -- of the barbecue utensil
to be inserted
and drills one last hole
for a piece of rawhide that will hang up the tool.
♪♪
next, the craftsman inserts the tang
into the slot in the handle
and slides a post through one of the holes.
this positions it
for a female rivet to be installed from the front.
male rivets are installed on the other side.
this completes the riveting steps
and secures the handle to the turner blade.
♪♪
using a coarse sanding belt,
the craftsman smooths the rivets to the wood
and sands off the metal tang at the protruding sides.
another technician rubs mineral
oil into the wooden handle
to give it luster and enhance the grain.
a mixture of ground corn and mineral spirits
serves as a gentle abrasive cleaner.
the technician dries off the blade
by plunging it into just the ground corn.
with a compressed air gun,
she blasts off the corn-cob remnants,
examines the tool for defects,
and props up the utensil under an engraving laser.
the laser etches the company name into the metal.
this barbecue turner will become part of a set
which will act as an extension of the chef's hands,
making it possible to cook over an open flame
without getting burned.