♪♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: mountain bike tires
are true trailblazers,
specifically designed
for off-road riding.
wider than regular road tires,
mountain bike tires
have raised knobs or lugs
that add stability
on uneven terrain.
built to withstand the trail,
these tires can handle it all.
when the rubber hits the dirt,
it's all about control.
mountain bike tires are designed
to grip the ground
and provide traction off-road.
first, designers use
a computer model of a tire
to simulate the effects
of different rubber compounds.
construction begins with
rubber compounds
being mixed together
to create parts of the tire.
ingredients include synthetic
and natural rubbers,
sulfur,
and other chemicals.
rotating spiral blades
break down the materials.
friction from the mixing
heats and softens them.
this transforms the ingredients
into a dough-like
rubber compound.
powerful rollers squeeze the
compound into thick long sheets
and blades cut the rolled rubber
into narrow strips.
then the rubber travels
through more rollers
that squeeze it down
to the desired thickness.
the rubber sheets land
on a cart, ready for use.
♪♪
technicians incase
steel bead wire
with one of these compounds.
the bead wire is the part
of the tire
that connects
to the wheel's rim.
as steel wire travels
through an aperture,
the rubber is extruded
to form the casing.
the machine delivers
the bead wire
to a spinning disk.
the disk winds the bead wire,
shaping it into rings
which fit to a wheel rim.
♪♪
to maintain the diameter
of the wire,
the technician tapes
the ends together,
holding the shape until
the next stage of production.
next, rubber sheets with
varying characteristics
enter an extruder.
using heat and pressure,
the extruder forces
the rubber through dies.
this process merges
their characteristics
into a single sheet.
the sheet will be used
to make the bicycle's tread.
the tread rubber travels
through a channel of cool water.
meanwhile, rollers coat fabric
with rubber
to make plies
for the tire casing.
a moving blade cuts it
into strips.
this rubber is naturally tacky,
so the pieces
can be easily spliced.
the system feeds the strips
to tire-building machine.
a skilled assembler wraps
the strips to the machine drum
to form the tire casing
and splices
the rubber where the ends meet.
next, robots slide two
wire beads around the casing.
the ends of the drum fold
the sides of the casing
over the bead wires.
the technician applies
rubber-coated fabric
to the bead wires,
strengthening the area.
the tread rubber is placed
in the center.
a roller applies pressure
as the drum spins
to wind the tread
around the casing.
then the ends are
pressed together manually.
and one more turn of the drum
secures the tread rubber
to the casing.
once vent holes have been
cut in the rubber,
it's over to an expanding mold,
where the tire takes shape.
the technician inserts a rubber
curing bladder
to maintain
the shape of the tire.
then he places the mountain bike
tires in curing molds.
these individual molds
will steam-cook the tires
under pressure
to further shape them.
this process forms knobs
and other protrusions
on the tire surface
that are designed to grip
a rugged terrain.
like a big waffle iron,
this mold has cooked
and formed
the mountain bike tire.
the tire is then placed
on a rack to cool.
next, the bike tire undergoes
a durability test
while a computer measures
rolling resistance.
that's the energy lost
when the tire rotates
and an indication of
how easily the tire will roll.
this mountain bike tire
is now cleared
to travel off the beaten path.
♪♪
narrator:
a leaf and debris vacuum
automatically collects
all types of fallen debris.
instead of spending hours
raking,
this device quickly
does it all,
making yard work
easier than ever.
a leaf and debris vacuum
is powered by
a gas or diesel engine.
the engine spins an impeller,
which creates the suction
and also shreds the leaves.
the machine is comprised
of about 100 different parts,
all cut from 0.11-inch-thick
sheets of steel
using this computer-guided
punch press.
this part is the rear flange
for the impeller housing.
to make the side wall
of the housing, called the wrap,
a technician bends
this steel strip
with a pinch roller.
another technician positions
the wrap on the rear flange
and tack welds them together.
♪♪
the craftsman places
the housing's front flange
on top of the wrap,
aligns its notches
with the wrap's tabs,
and tack welds
the parts together.
♪♪
he completes the housing
with this rectangular piece.
the shredded leaves
exit the housing
through this opening.
♪♪
next, the parts are placed
on a rotary welding table,
and the tacked joints
are welded together.
the fused seams ensure
the housing is airtight.
a computer guides
this fiber-optic laser cutter,
slicing out the impeller blades
from a sheet
of abrasion-resistance steel.
this steel is four times thicker
than the steel used
for the body parts.
each impeller has four blades
with sharp edges
that help shred the leaves.
the welder mounts the impeller
components onto a fixture.
each blade has alignment tabs
which fit into notches
on a backing plate.
after clamping each blade
in position,
he fuses them
to the backing plate.
♪♪
next, he welds steel
reinforcement straps
between each
of the four blades.
the straps add strength
and stability,
thereby increasing
the life-span of the impeller.
the technician
completes the assembly
by bolting a compression hub
to the center.
the hub holds the engine
crankshaft together,
which rotates the impeller.
then he inserts
a simulated crankshaft
and tightens
the compression hub.
he places the impeller
on this machine to balance it.
since the impeller
can spin at a speed
of more than 3,000 revolutions
per minute,
this step is critical
for the machine to run smoothly.
to maintain stability,
the welder adds beads of weld
to the lighter side
until the impeller balances.
then he removes the simulated
crankshaft.
meanwhile an assembler mounts
the 29-horsepower gas engine
to the engine deck
of the trailer frame.
the crankshaft pokes through
a hole in the frame's faceplate.
he bolts the impeller housing,
which has been painted,
to the faceplate.
♪♪
the technician installs
the impeller on the crankshaft
with a shear key.
then he bolts
a protective steel cover plate
and attaches everything
with a central bolt.
next, he applies a brand decal
on the housing's front cover...
♪♪
...and bolts the cover
to the housing.
when ready for use,
the debris chute, the hose,
and the intake hose
are attached to the front end.
as this demonstration shows,
the impeller can shred leaves
into particles small enough
to be used as compost.
♪♪
narrator:
with so much on their plates,
busy people rely on shortcuts
to help prepare meals.
nowadays,
you can stock your pantry
with cans of precooked meat
so there's always something
on hand to use in sandwiches,
stews, stir-fries,
and other tasty dishes.
this canned meat is
meticulously hand produced
by a craft cannery
and made in small batches.
it contains no artificial
ingredients or preservatives,
just meat and sea salt.
when a shipment of meat
arrives at the cannery,
the quality control manager
records its lot code
for tracking purposes.
as a food-safety precaution,
he confirms the temperature
of the meat,
which must come in between
0 to 39 degrees fahrenheit.
a skilled butcher
then inspects the meat
and trims off the excess fat.
♪♪
if it's a large piece,
the butcher slices
it into smaller pieces
so that it can pass through
the dicing machine.
the dicer cuts the meat
into one-inch cubes.
♪♪
at the filling station,
aluminum cans circulate
around a rotating table.
as one worker shovels cubed meat
onto the center of the table,
others manually fill cans
while simultaneously performing
a quality inspection.
workers will discard any cubes
that are discolored
or too fatty.
next, technicians place
a single cube of sea salt
in each can filled with meat.
this is the only
added ingredient.
♪♪
at the next station, workers
weigh each can individually
and either add or remove meat
to reach the required weight.
the filled cans
now travel on a conveyer belt
to the cook room.
there, they enter
the pre-heater,
which blasts them with steam
for 20 seconds.
this expels air that's trapped
between the cubes of meat.
next, the cans move
into the closing machine.
the machine compresses the meat
to provide sufficient clearance
at the top of the can.
this head space
creates a vacuum on the can
to draw out
the remaining air.
then a device attaches the lid
by a process
known as double seaming.
the process rolls the edges
of the lid and can together,
forming a rim
that provides an airtight seal.
it's time to get cooking.
a worker lowers the cans
into a commercial-sized
pressure cooker.
cooking under steam pressure
produces the tenderizing effects
of slow cooking
in a fraction of the time.
the meat cooks
in its own juices.
the cooking temperature varies
depending on the type of meat
and the can size.
when the meat is ready,
the technician removes the cans
and sets them aside
for about an hour
to cool and dry.
the cans are then moved
to the packaging area.
as a worker loads
the labeling machine,
he inspects each can
for dents or damaged seals.
one by one, the cans roll over
a glue applicator,
then a stack of labels,
wrapping themselves
and the top seal.
at the same time, the machine
counts the number of cans.
after rolling off
the labeling machine,
the cans pass through
an ink-jet printer
which applies
the best-used-by date.
♪♪
that date is next
to the lot code,
which the closing machine
printed while attaching the lid.
this can of meat
has a five-year shelf life
due to two crucial factors --
it is cooked properly,
and the can's seal is airtight.
♪♪
narrator:
have fish to fry?
if it's fresh and whole,
a fillet knife
will come in handy.
this is no ordinary
kitchen knife,
equipped with a thin,
flexible blade and a sharp tip.
this design allows the user to
move easily along the backbone
and under the skin of the meat.
a fillet knife
is a precision cutting tool.
it makes the work
of removing bones and skin
from fish possible.
making a fillet knife
starts with a sheet of thin
and pliable stainless steel.
a computer-guided laser cuts
the steel into blade blanks.
a craftsman clamps the blank
in a fixture.
the fixture moves the blank
across a grinding wheel,
beveling it from the spine to
the cutting edge on both sides.
then sanding belts are used
to shape the blade blank.
a craftsman rounds
the spine of the blank
using a rough-grit sanding belt,
eventually graduating
to a finer one.
with a rounder spine, the blade
will be safer to handle.
at the next station,
a craftsman drills a hole
into a solid block
of composite material
that contains resin.
the material is cut
into smaller chunks.
each one will be formed
into a handle end cap or pommel.
the center hole will house
the tang.
he slices other pieces of
the material almost wafer thin.
they'll become spacers
for the handle's other end.
these compound parts will
support the center material
for the cork handle.
the craftsman stacks the parts
of the handle on a stand.
he brushes waterproof glue
onto the spacer
and slides eight pieces of cork
onto the prong.
he applies glue
between each one.
he places the pommel
piece on the end.
since cork is buoyant,
if the knife
is dropped in water,
it will float
and can be easily retrieved.
once the glue dries, the handles
are transferred,
two at a time, to a fixture.
the fixture moves back and forth
as a rotor rounds the spacer,
carving the cork and the pommel.
at the next station,
a worker places
one of the fillet
knife blades in a rubber holder.
he clamps the holder
in a fixture,
stabilizing the blade for
the installation of the bolster.
the bolster is the steel ring
that acts as a transition piece
between the blade and handle.
then the craftsman applies glue
to the composite spacer
on the handle.
he slides the handle
onto the tang of the knife.
he inserts a hexagonal nut
into the hole and the pommel
as well as some epoxy.
he screws the nut onto the tang,
securing the blade
to the handle.
the epoxy provides
reinforcement.
the craftsman unclamps the knife
and works on shaping the handle.
he sculpts it with rough-grit
sandpaper.
he angles the outside
of the pommel,
making it smoother
and more attractive.
switching to a finer abrasive,
he sands the cork
to blend the layers together
so they appear to be
one uniform piece.
next, a worker drills
into the pommel
to widen and slope the opening.
he pipes more epoxy
into the recess.
he inserts a snap
that will be used
to retain the knife in a sheath
and drives it further
into the recess using a press.
once the epoxy cures,
he submerges
the knives into water.
this step is a test to confirm
the knives can float.
after the handle dries,
the knife undergoes
a final sanding
for the user's gripping comfort.
you can see the difference
the sanding makes
in the knife on the right.
next, the craftsman works on
the fillet knife's cutting edge,
sharpening it against
a sanding belt.
the blade slices a sheet of
paper cleanly without snagging,
proving that it's been
well-honed.
finally, another worker cleans
and lubricates the fillet knife.
she slides it
into a leather sheath
and snaps the tab of the sheath
to the end of the pommel.
with all the work that's gone
into this fillet knife,
the customer will be in
for one tasty, well-cut meal.
♪♪