♪♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: preparing rice in an electric cooker
is easier than cooking rice on the stove.
you throw in the rice and water,
press a button,
and walk away until it's ready.
this machine is designed to steam rice to perfection.
rice cookers use indirect heat
to circulate steam around rice and water,
from the outer pot to an inner pot.
this process cooks the rice evenly in half an hour.
to cast the outer cooking pot,
aluminum ingots are melted in a furnace.
a robotic arm scoops up
the required amount of molten aluminum
with a ladle...
...then pours it into the top of the mold.
it takes the metal four minutes
to cool and solidify.
then technicians extract the pot from the mold.
to refine its form,
the pot is mounted on a computer-guided lathe.
as it spins,
several machines contour the pot's outside surface
to its final shape.
♪♪
next, the pot is loaded onto an automated drilling machine.
the machine punctures 18 holes through the bottom.
the rice cooker's heating components
and its painted steel shell
are attached to the outer pot through these holes.
then the pot is returned to the computer-guided lathe.
a tool polishes the interior
until the aluminum is smooth and bright.
a disk of stainless steel is placed in a press.
the press molds the steel into the inner cooking pot.
the next press trims off
any excess metal around the top,
leaving a clean and even edge.
another machine curls that edge
to form a rounded lip.
the lip strengthens the pot and provides a place to grip
when the inner pot is placed into the outer pot.
once polished, the pot is placed in another press.
this press stamps water-level lines on the side
and a trench on the bottom.
the trench helps the water evaporate quickly.
next, an automated booth paints
the rice cooker's steel shells.
the shells are baked in an oven
for 15 minutes at 390 degrees fahrenheit
so that the paint can set.
with a pad printer, the company logo
is applied to the shell.
technicians install part of the switch mechanism
to the shell.
another technician places the heating element in a slot
on the bottom of the outer pot,
securing it with three clips.
they install two connection plates
used to attach the steel shell --
a porcelain plate and a magnetic core.
the core controls the on/off switch
based on the temperature inside the cooker.
♪♪
the technician connects the power cord
and attaches the thermal-insulation sheet,
which allows the cooked rice
to maintain a temperature of 158 degrees fahrenheit.
this part of the switch mechanism
hovers over the magnetic core.
when the cooking temperature hits 158 degrees fahrenheit,
the core activates the switch to turn off the heating element
and start up the thermal-insulation sheet.
after more switch wiring, technicians install the fuse,
which prevents the cooker from overheating.
one end is connected to the heating element,
the other end to the power cord
by the porcelain plate.
the painted steel shell
is attached to the base of the outer pot.
once attached, each connection plate
is secured with screws,
then handles are installed.
finally, every rice cooker undergoes a temperature test.
after starting the machine,
the cooking temperature is measured with a thermometer.
once approved, the cooker is packaged with a cover
and perforated insert for steaming other foods.
to use the cooker, you put rice
and water in the inner pot
and water in the outer pot.
in under an hour, the heating element turns off,
and the insulation sheet
kicks in to keep your rice warm.
♪♪
narrator: one way to keep personal valuables secure
and safely out of sight
is by storing them in concealment furniture.
this custom-designed home decor
allows you or your family
an understated place to store and lock a number of items.
this seemingly ordinary bookcase
has a few surprises.
behind it's decorative medallion
is a hidden release
for side pullout compartments.
and inside the lower section is a wireless keypad
which unlocks a drawer.
this company handcrafts various items,
from dressers to mirrors to wall art.
each piece of furniture is customized
based on the customer's wood,
finish, and storage configuration.
to create a valance at the top of a bookcase,
a planer levels a piece of wood
to its required thickness.
a computer-guided router carves
designs into the wood
and cuts out the shape of the medallion.
next, the medallion
is attached to the valance and release device
through three slots at the center of the valance.
♪♪
this is one of the side pullouts
after assembly is complete.
like the valance components,
the router carved the design on the front panel.
a craftsman uses an electric sander
on the pullout's side panel which has no carving.
all the decorative details are sanded by hand.
♪♪
the craftsman assembles the second side pullout.
a laser engraves the company's name and logo
on the inside of the side panel.
the craftsman measures and marks
where the pullout's bottom and top panels will be placed.
glue is applied into a groove
running the length of the fluted front panel.
then the side panel is inserted
into the groove
and the parts are clamped together.
the bottom and top panels are glued
at the pre-marked points and secured.
all the wooden components of the bookcase
are glued to each other.
three temporary boards
in between the top and bottom panels
keep the structure square while the glue dries.
next, a craftsman assembles the top of the bookcase,
attaching the base and sides, back, top, the valance,
and crown molding.
the customer selects the color of the finish.
painted on by hand,
the stain takes up to an hour to dry.
a craftsman sprays on a coat of vinyl sealer.
once the sealer dries, the surfaces are sanded
and two coats of fast-drying lacquer are applied.
the craftsman sands the wood between applications.
next, the hardware is installed.
a technician attaches the drawer slides
for each side pullout...
bolts in the lock for the hidden release device,
and secures a triangular latch to the pullout.
then a long rod is inserted.
this connects the locks to the release
so when you slide the center medallion right or left,
it pushes the rod against the pullout lock,
popping the latch.
the corresponding drawer slides
are attached to the pullout.
♪♪
the triangular latch, which releases the pullout,
goes in the top front corner
so that it aligns with the lock.
♪♪
once the pullouts are installed,
they form the sides of the upper
section of the bookcase.
these sections are now useable,
sturdy storage compartments.
♪♪
the next step is to connect
the rod to the center medallion.
the craftsman bolts a rectangular piece of metal
to the medallion through the valance's top slot,
connecting the medallion to the valance
through the other two slots.
a large opening on the top of the bookcase
provides access to the device should it ever need repair.
once joined with the lower section,
the bookcase, like this china cabinet,
is ready for double duty.
♪♪
narrator: often associated with japanese culture,
traditional origami is best known
as the art of paper folding.
it dates back to at least the 17th century.
today, marketing companies are engineering origami
for promotional use,
creating materials with more impact
than your standard brochure.
open this invitation, and an interesting scene unfolds.
based on strategic marketing research,
nontraditional invitations
and three-dimensional paper structures
can attract more interest.
a specialist known as a paper engineer
replicates an ultrasound machine
in origami.
the paper engineer breaks down the design
into flat parts to be printed and folded into modular pieces.
guided by a digital design,
a machine cuts and scores a thick sheet of paper
in the shape of the engineered origami parts.
later, the scored shapes will be
punched out and assessed.
the design will need tweaking
before the pieces of paper ultrasound
are ready for mass production.
next, the designer folds the cutouts
and glues them together,
creating the base of the ultrasound.
this particular module is a test build
to confirm that it folds correctly
and will fit to the other parts
of the mini paper replica.
the designer makes more prototypes
and adjusts some of the parameters.
he builds the undercarriage and wheels
out of chipboard.
these elements support the paper modular structure.
each part is labeled accordingly.
the designer constructs the final prototype,
checking that the seams are tight
and that all the parts are in perfect alignment.
once structurally sound,
the designer starts building the graphic details.
♪♪
he refers to photos of the prototype
and compares them to the flat screen image.
when complete, the artwork is printed, producing a proof.
the proof is a test copy of the artwork.
the areas to be glued or cut out
are printed in green.
this is done to indicate that no ink or coatings
are needed during the final printing.
♪♪
the technician does an initial check
to confirm the quality of the print
and that all the art has been properly placed.
♪♪
then, the designer and the production supervisor
evaluate the proof.
they confirm that the lines
correspond with those of the cutting die
by comparing folded modules to the flat proof.
this step ensures that when the artwork is printed
for mass production, the cutouts will fit.
adjustments are made to any problematic areas of the proof.
once the artwork is complete,
the revised artwork is printed and scored by a digital cutter.
this computerized cutter is only used for test purposes.
a cutting die will be used for mass production
of the origami parts.
technicians insert the cutouts
in the corresponding parts of the die.
this step confirms that the lines are correct
and are ready to go to print.
machines may mass produce
thousands of printed and die-cut sheets,
but it's up to the assemblers
to fold and glue the modules together.
the assembler starts with a base,
followed by the articulating arm
for the ultrasound screen.
the arm fits into a slot in the base,
which can be lifted and lowered.
the assembler attaches the control panel
to the lower part of the arm.
he installs the folded ultrasound screen on the top
and inspects his work.
weeks of design and planning have gone into this moment.
now assembled, this piece of promotional origami
can be packaged and mailed to targeted recipients.
♪♪
narrator: hedge shears have long steel blades
that hold a sharp edge.
they're essentially a serious pair of scissors.
used by a skilled gardener,
they can cut a large area of vegetation with one stroke.
needless to say, hedge shears can truly change the landscape.
taming an unruly hedge or garden
often calls for sheer strength.
that's why, for many gardeners,
hedge shears are a go-to tool.
to make hedge shears, technicians cut out the blades
from carbon steel using a die cutter.
the steel uncoils and travels over a roller conveyor,
sending it to the cutter.
the die cutter stamps out multiple blade blanks.
once the steel advances, the die
cuts the next batch of blanks,
cutting a hole in the center
for the assembly of the shear blades.
♪♪
a technician arranges the blade blanks
on a conveyor heading to the oven.
the blanks bake at 1,470 degrees fahrenheit.
this heat treatment is the first
stage of the hardening process.
another technician exposes the cutting edge to the heat.
this makes the edge a little stronger
than the rest of the blade.
the technician submerges the blade in oil
to bring down the temperature,
which completes the hardening process.
a grinding stone removes the dull, gray layer
on both sides of the blade.
this gets rid of scorch marks, and it brightens the finish.
then the grinder cleans and sharpens the blades.
♪♪
before the grinding, the hedge-shear blade
looked lackluster,
and its performance would have been dull.
the grinding has given the blade
a sheen and a cutting edge.
next, technicians install a rubber bumper device
on the blade's stem.
the rubber will cushion the force of the impact created
as the shear blades come together.
another technician joins the blades
with a pivot bolt and nut.
this connection allows the shears
to swing toward each other.
♪♪
a team examines the blades
to confirm they're engaged properly
and operate smoothly.
if needed, they adjust the interface
by bending back the blades.
this tweaking can be critical
to the functioning of the hedge shears.
then the shears are placed in a fixture,
and the device press-fits telescoping handles
onto the tangs.
an inspector tests the telescoping action
to confirm that the handles extend and retract effectively.
other technicians slide plastic gripper sleeves
onto the ends of the handles.
it's an initial installation.
the gripper sleeves
will need to be pushed further up the handles.
a mechanical pusher shoves the grippers
into their final position.
it's a press fit -- no glue or screws required.
the tips of the hedge shears
are dipped in an anti-rust solution
and placed on a rack to dry.
then a worker rubs the solution residue
into the steel.
♪♪
the shears undergo another inspection,
which checks the interface of the blades one last time.
the technician tweaks the angle
of the blades
and tightens the pivot bolt.
a label is pressed on the shears,
providing product information and safety precautions.
the hedge shears undergo a final inspection.
once cleared, they are packed for shipping.
these hedge shears should hold up
to years of trimming, cutting, and pruning.
without them, gardens might look
a lot wilder.