♪♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
♪♪
the delorean sports car was
manufactured in northern ireland
in the early 1980s.
with gull-wing doors and brushed
stainless steel panels,
the delorean was known for its flashy style.
today, many of these cars are in rough shape,
but a restoration can make a delorean look like new.
♪♪
this delorean is a rare relic from the '80s.
only 9,080 of these iconic cars
were manufactured.
no longer operational, this delorean
might have been destined for the junk yard.
but with professional restoration,
this company has the spare parts
to get it up and running.
the process starts with the diagnostics.
the technician examines the suspension,
the steering rack, and brakes.
he finds significant deterioration
and documents his findings.
he scrutinizes every part of the old delorean
and produces an 11-page report on its condition.
once all the problems have been identified,
the mechanic gets to work,
removing plugs to drain some of the coolant.
he disassembles many pipes and hoses
that run coolant from the radiator to the rear engine.
many of the coolant pipes will need to be cleaned
in order to be re-used.
the rubber hoses can't be salvaged
and will need replacement.
the mechanic disassembles the brakes.
the calipers are in bad shape but can be rebuilt.
the rusty rotors are still thick enough
that they can be resurfaced.
after mounting new tires
and refinishing the cast alloy wheels,
another technician bolts them to the hubs.
he lowers the hoist and sets the car on the floor.
he tightens the lug nuts to the final torque setting.
a technician begins disassembling
the rear drive engine.
in order to know what needs to be replaced,
the technician must take the engine apart.
he removes the air filter box
in order to access the intake manifold.
then he unbolts the "w"-shaped manifold pipe
that splits the air flow to the engine.
once it's off, he removes the air-mixture control unit,
which needs restored to work.
with the unit out of the way,
he can easily get to other parts
that need replacing or fixing.
those include spark plugs, wires, vacuum lines,
the distributor cap, and rotor.
under the front hood, the mechanic
pulls the fuel pump out of the gas tank
to check for deterioration.
it's beyond repair.
he drains any fuel the remains in the tank.
after the gas tank has been emptied and cleaned,
he inserts a new, modern-style pump module.
another technician holds the top of the pump down
as the module is clamped into place.
next, the technician removes the interior door panels
and uses a central tester to operate the power windows.
he confirms the power windows are functional.
he also checks the power locks and mirrors
to verify that they're working properly.
he pulls off exterior rubber trim.
he shaves off any remaining rubber bits.
this allows room to repair a dent
in the stainless steel body.
he files the area around the dent to remove some scratches.
he places a special tool over the dent.
it has a rod with a fine steel tip that welds to the body,
providing a solid grip, as he manually pulls out the dent.
meanwhile, another mechanic
applies tape to various sections of the car
to establish borders
for the refinishing of the steel body panels.
he sands out any imperfections or tool marks from the repairs
and restores the brushed finish
bumper to bumper.
since no paint can be used
to cover up repairs on bare stainless steel,
the body work must be done perfectly.
inside, technicians reupholster the seats
and treat any discoloration in the vinyl panels and dashboard.
finally, the entire car gets an extensive exterior cleaning.
it's taken months to restore this delorean,
but the question remains, will it run like a new car?
once tested in various driving conditions,
mechanics confirm that this 1980s throwback
is ready for its comeback.
♪♪
narrator: the bison is blessed with the perfect winter coat,
and now bison fibers are helping
people to endure the cold, too.
processed with polyester strands,
the fibers are made into insulation for winter coats,
allowing people to hunker down in frigid winter temperatures.
♪♪
these winter coats have been
insulated with bison fiber fill.
it's a by-product of bison ranching
and a garment insulation that's
no longer going to waste.
bison fiber fill is a combination
of the animal's coarse guard hairs, bison down,
recycled and low-melt polyester.
technicians load the four fibers separately
into spiked conveyors.
the fibers were compressed for shipping.
so as they're loaded, the fibers
are loosened by hand.
once loading is complete, an
operator turns on the conveyors.
the conveyors' protruding pins
snag the bison-and-polyester strands
and transport them upward.
the strands travel under rotating spiked cylinders.
the cylinders comb the fibers to
open them up and detangle them.
the four different fibers flow into scales,
which weigh equal portions and are released.
the fibers drop onto a conveyor
and move into a blender for mixing.
another vertical conveyor with pins picks up the fibers
and takes them upward,
past revolving bars that knock off the excess.
this ensures an even mass, as the bison-and-polyester fibers
move between a series of different wire-covered rollers.
this process arranges the fibers
in a parallel orientation and gets rid of any clumps.
a comb further aligns the bison-and-polyester fibers.
the fibers cling together in a web.
the web transfers to a wooden slat conveyor.
a vacuum suctions up loose fibers
to be recycled back into production.
an oscillating conveyor layers the fibers
in a zigzag pattern called "cross lapping."
♪♪
cross lapping produces a substantial mat,
and it also mixes the fibers.
next, the web lands on another conveyor,
passing between a series of rollers that compress it.
this process gives the mixed fibers
the appropriate mass and height
to produce a uniform batt.
a sprayer applies an adhesive
to the bison-and-polyester insulation.
the adhesive doesn't take right away.
it will need to be heat-activated.
the insulation moves into a 300-degree oven,
which triggers the activation.
the heat also activates the low-melt polyester strands
in the insulation.
this bonds the interlaced fibers
to prevent them
from migrating through fabric when used as fill.
next, the insulation heads downward into a shearing.
like a pizza cutter, circular blades
cut through the center of the insulation mat
and trim along the edges.
♪♪
rollers wind the strips
of bison fiber and polyester insulation together.
using a paper cutter,
an inspector cuts a sample to a specific size.
he weighs the sample
and confirms that it's adequate for the size,
verifying the density of the fiber mass.
next, he measures the sample's thickness.
at about .13 inches, the fiber fill
will provide warmth without a lot of bulk.
the team slices the bison fiber fabric fill
to its specified length using a hot wire.
once the roll is complete, they
start rolling the next one.
the bison fiber rolls are put in plastic bags for protection
during transport to outside clothing factories.
technicians weigh each bag separately.
after several hours, bison fibers and polyester strands
have been transformed into moisture wicking insulation.
stuffed inside a jacket liner,
this bison fiber insulation won't be seen.
but on a winter day,
its presence will definitely be felt.
♪♪
narrator: shuffleboard originated in british taverns
in the 15th century.
players would slide coins, called groats, down the bar,
aiming for them to stop as close
to the edge as possible
without falling off.
it was so popular that
king henry viii banned the game,
saying it was too much of a distraction from work.
centuries after shuffleboard was invented,
this easy and entertaining game
is making a comeback.
to make a shuffleboard table,
a technician trims maple strips.
the strips vary in length,
but they all have the same width
and thickness.
using a rolling wheel fused with glue,
the technician applies adhesive
to the strips.
these strips have grooves on one side
and protrusions on the other so that they can interlock.
the glue will ensure
the interlocked strips stay together.
after he assembles the strips, he counts them to confirm
that he has the correct number for the playfield size.
he lowers a curing press, then clamps the strips together.
the press applies applies high-temperature heat
to rapidly cure the glue joints.
the slabs are stored in racks for 30 days
so that they acclimate to each other.
once the process is complete, the slabs go into a planer.
the planer removes dried glue, smooths and levels the surface.
on the left is a slab before it went through the planer,
and on the right is the one that's had the work done.
a technician applies adhesive-backed strips
to mark the score zones
and tapes the ends to prevent peeling.
he smooths down the number decals
that will designate the scoring zones.
the company logo goes in the center.
next, a coat of polymer varnish
is applied to the board.
the varnish encases the decals,
making them resistant to wear.
the parts of the cradle base are built with plywood.
a router cuts slots in the base
for the playfield adjustment parts.
♪♪
a technician joins two sections of the base
and builds the cradle skirting.
♪♪
he adds a piece in the center for extra support,
links sideboards to the ends,
and staples the corners together.
he turns the cradle over
and screws the skirt to the base from the top,
beginning at the corners
and continuing along the entire border.
he uses rounded maple corners for the end frames
to eliminate sharp angles.
he sprays a generous amount of glue
on the outside of the frame.
this prepares it to receive a laminated composite material.
he coats the back of the laminate with glue...
♪♪
...and wraps the laminate around the end frame,
which adds a different aesthetic.
then he sands the rims
so that it sits evenly on the base of the cradle.
he glues the end frame to the cradle...
reinforces the glued seams with staples...
and joins the sides of the cradle to the end piece,
which fit together perfectly.
♪♪
another technician sands the wood until it's silky smooth.
then a stain is sprayed on the sides of the cradle
and the skirting.
the stain enhances the grain of the maple
and adds a depth of color.
♪♪
he sprays on lacquer, which seals the stain
and gives the wood a glossy finish.
he adds wooden inlays for visual interest.
next, the cradle is sprayed with glue.
a technician applies the carpet
to the glued areas.
the carpet will absorb the impact of pucks
that fall off the board.
with the second end plate
installed and the legs attached,
the cradle is ready
for the playfield to be mounted.
the playfield is so heavy,
it takes two people to lower it
into the cradle.
this shuffleboard table is now complete.
even though it's taken three days to build,
this shuffleboard is worth every bit of hard work.
♪♪
narrator: the hallmark of a quality knife
is a cutting edge that remains sharp
despite repeated use over time.
one of the most advanced knife-making methods
is friction forging --
a technique applied specifically
to the knife's cutting edge
to produce sharpness and durability.
friction-forged blades
are used primarily in hunting and fishing
but also work just as well in the kitchen.
the blades are made of high-carbon steel.
a laser cutter slices out rectangular bars,
each of which will yield two to five blades.
the bars are wrapped in foil and put in an oven
at 1,850 degrees fahrenheit for several hours.
the heat hardens the steel.
♪♪
the bars are removed from the oven and cooled.
then they're put back in the oven
and heated to 700 degrees fahrenheit
for several more hours.
this second round of heat treating
tempers the steel,
drawing down its hardness
to between 38 and 42 on the rockwell scale.
the bars are placed on a large electromagnet.
the magnet holds them securely,
while the bars rotate under a grinding stone.
a steady flow of coolant
prevents the heat the friction generates
from changing the hardness of the steel.
the grinder removes carbon deposits
caused by the heat treatment,
along with any surface imperfections.
a craftsman uses a rockwell hardness tester
to measure the bar's hardness.
the machine's needle bears down
until it indents the steel.
a measurement of 41 is right on target
and within the range of ultra-tough spring steel.
the bar is now ready to be friction forged.
the forging machine's specialized tool
applies immense pressure,
combined with rotational movement called "stirring,"
to a specific area of the bar.
the stirring action creates friction,
which plasticizes the steel,
reducing its microscopic grain structures to levels
no other forging or heat-treating method
can achieve,
50 to 75 times smaller
than that of the steel typically
used in a high-quality knife.
the finer the grain size, the stronger the steel,
the sharper and less brittle the blades
the unforged zone becomes the blade's main body.
this area is the tough spring steel,
with a rockwell hardness between 38 and 42.
the friction-forged zone becomes
the blade's cutting edge --
65 to 70 on the rockwell scale.
a computer-guided grinding machine shapes the blade.
this is what the blade looks like before grinding...
and after.
the blade is shotblasted with fine ceramic beads
to remove all surface imperfections.
the forged zone is now clearly distinguishable.
a craftswoman assembles the knife's handle.
she places a stainless steel bolster over the blade
and inserts two pins made of nickel silver.
she trims the pins,
then flattens them with a hammer
to lock in the bolster.
♪♪
here is the blade before...
and after this assembly.
a laser engraves the model and brand name
in the unforged area.
♪♪
the craftsman applies glue on both halves of the handles,
then presses them together.
this model is made of desert ironwood
held together with glue and brass nickel pins.
once the glue dries,
a craftswoman runs the handle against a sanding belt
to shape the wood to the steel.
she polishes the wood to bring out the beauty of the grain.
♪♪
then the blade is hand-sharpened
on a belt grinder.
first, the main cut.
then the edge.
which stays sharp 10 to 50 times longer
than a traditionally heat-treated blade.
finally, the knife is run through a test
for edge sharpness.
if the reading indicates the sharpness of a razor blade,
the friction-forged knife passes the test.
♪♪