>> narrator: digital technology
is revolutionizing dental
treatment.
3-d cameras and computers can
now be used to produce crowns
and other prosthetic
restorations on site,
eliminating the need to send the
work to an outside lab.
for the patient, it means one
appointment instead of two and
less time in the dentist's
chair.
with computer-driven tools,
custom restorations take shape
in a matter of minutes while the
patient waits.
after donning dark safety
glasses, the patient is ready
for her close-up.
the dental assistant inserts a
small video camera in her mouth
to examine the problem area.
she then inserts a strip of
carbon paper between the
patient's teeth and instructs
her to clench her teeth.
this leaves markings that
indicate her bite profile.
the dentist meets the patient
and reviews her case.
they agree to replace the silver
filling with a ceramic inlay
that will strengthen the tooth
for much longer than a regular
filling would.
he anesthetizes the tooth and
the gums that surround it.
he then stretches a rubber dam
across her mouth and exposes the
area to be treated through a
slit.
this keeps filling fragments out
of the patient's mouth as he
drills.
he switches to a smaller drill
bit to excavate the remaining
filling particles and to remove
decay.
each cavity must be completely
clear before the restorative
work can begin.
the dental assistant then scrubs
an antimicrobial solution into
the tooth.
then she brushes an acidic
conditioner into the cavity.
the dentist activates the
conditioner with a halogen
light.
he points a high-resolution
l.e.d. camera at the tooth and
downloads the image onto a
computer, which converts it to
3-d.
next, the dentist fills the
cavity with the silicone putty.
when her teeth come together,
they leave an impression in the
putty that indicates her bite
profile.
once the putty hardens, the
dentist and his assistant chip
off the excess.
he downloads the image of the
bite impression and then
superimposes the images as he
designs a custom dental inlay
digitally.
the dental assistant selects a
glass ceramic block of the
appropriate size and color.
she anchors the block in a
milling chamber and shuts the
lid.
two computerized drills now
sculpt the block into the dental
inlay, guided by the digitally
produced design.
this process takes less than 10
minutes.
the dentist then pulls the
ceramic inlay from the base.
this leaves a small nub that he
then grinds away.
next, using rubber wheels and
diamond-impregnated brushes, he
polishes the entire restoration
to a high gloss.
he conditions the inlay with
hydrofluoric acid to prepare it
for adhesion to the tooth.
he dips the filling in water,
and the hardened solution flakes
off.
he then thoroughly dries the
inlay.
next, he adds a drop of silane
that will promote the bonding of
the inlay to the tooth.
the dentist injects
tooth-colored resin cement into
the cavity.
he presses the digitally
designed and milled inlay into
the cement, then scrapes away
the overflow.
halogen light on the dental work
hardens the cement.
he takes another impression of
the patient's bite to confirm
the new inlay is perfect.
finally, the dentist polishes
the contours of the ceramic
inlay.
and it's time for the reveal.
he uses the camera to magnify
the new dental work for the
patient's scrutiny.
it's taken just an hour and a
quarter for her custom
restoration to be designed,
milled, and installed, all
thanks to digital dentistry.
>> narrator: the nail clipper
was invented in 1896 in the
united states, and soon it was
at everyone's fingertips.
by 1902 it, ads marketed it as
the "gem," and it was sold by
the dozen for $2.
as an alternative to scissors,
it was the idea that just
clicked.
more than a century after its
invention, the nail clipper is
still behind many a well-groomed
hand.
its popularity numbers in the
millions, and no manicure set
would be complete without one.
production begins with this
elaborate dye.
it's about a yard in length and
has 12 different-shaped
openings.
hydraulic machinery repeatedly
forces a steel sheet through the
various openings as the sheet
moves forward.
with each stroke, the parts look
more like nail-clipper jaws.
the clipping edge starts out
straight and blunt and gradually
becomes concave.
the machinery also cuts and
shapes the holes for assembling
the nail clippers.
in just one minute, a total of
80 strokes generate a dozen
nail-clipper jaws.
here, the clipper jaws vibrate
with abrasive stones and organic
acid for up to 20 hours.
this gentle polishing makes the
parts gleam, but doesn't ruin
the edges and contours.
at the next station, a worker
aligns pairs of clipper jaws for
assembly.
using a mechanical press, he
drives a rivet into the hole at
the gripping end of the jaws.
he flips the assembled clipper
jaws over, inserts the other
half of the rivet, and then
presses the two tightly
together.
the rivet locks the gripping end
of the nail clippers together so
that the two jaws can't be
twisted apart.
next, a worker smoothes the
edges of the clipper's gripping
end against an abrasive wheel.
this grinding evens out any
irregularities and makes the two
clipper jaws appear as one at
the gripping end.
attention now turns to the
cutting end of the clippers.
after locking them in a device,
a worker grinds the concave
edges until they match up.
these nail-clipper jaws are now
ready for the lever, but the
lever itself still needs some
work.
using a little press, they make
a whole and an indentation
between its two prongs, allowing
the lever to sit more
comfortably on the clipper.
levers are then fed one at a
time to a set of drills that
carve little holes into the
prongs of the fork.
the holes are just big enough
for a pin that's 0.05 of an inch
in diameter.
here's the view from the side
before and after drilling.
a worker now inserts a bolt in
the cutting end of the clipper
jaws.
this bolt has a little hole in
the end of it.
he presses the jaws together,
and it's now time to attach the
lever.
he inserts the pin in the holes
in the lever and the bolt.
he pinches the pin with pliers
to secure it, and the lever now
pivots freely on the cutting
jaws.
all the pieces of the nail
clipper have come together, but
the assembly processes have left
oil and other residues on this
tool.
it's time for a cleaning in a
special tub.
sound waves keep the water
moving to distribute the soap
and scrub them clean.
once they dry, a worker uses a
combination of acid and positive
electrodes to etch the company
name and item number onto the
nail clipper.
the next employee sands the
cutting edges to sharpen them.
it takes skill and practice to
get them just right.
he holds the nail clipper to a
light and scrutinizes the
alignment of the jaws as he
opens and closes them.
this cardboard test confirms
that these nail clippers are up
to the job.
from a blunt clipper on the left
to a really sharp tool on the
right, what a difference the
sanding has made.
the lever swivels for various
clipping angles and then folds
down neatly when not in use.
it takes 11 people to
manufacture 100 of these
clippers an hour, and that means
they've been working at a very
fast clip.
>> narrator: long before the
internet and electronic media,
the poster was an important
means of communication.
these lithographed notices were
used to sell everything from
soap to political propaganda.
today they're being
painstakingly restored to
preserve both the artistry and
history behind them.
these are the signs of a
different time.
and decades later, the bold
artistry of these poster
lithographs is still an
attention grabber.
some vintage posters can be
worth tens of thousands of
dollars, which makes them worth
restoring and preserving.
posters often become brittle and
break along the fold lines.
so first, this restoration
specialist reassembles the torn
sections and examines them to
determine if this poster can be
saved.
he decides to proceed.
he loosens old tape with solvent
and carefully peels it away.
next, he separates the poster
sections with plastic mesh -- to
keep them from sticking
together -- in a bleach bath.
the bleach gently removes dirt
and mildew to reveal the vintage
poster's original colors.
he presses out air pockets
between the layers to maximize
its effect.
while the pieces of this poster
dry, he prepares a paste of
water, wheat, and calcium.
the calcium will counteract the
acid in the vintage paper,
preventing further
deterioration.
he rolls the wheat paste onto a
big sheet of acid-free paper.
and he spreads more paste on a
piece of linen-textured cotton.
he then presses the paper to the
fabric, and they adhere.
he now has a big piece of
fabric-backed paper.
he rolls out the air bubbles and
excess paste for a more even
surface.
he now reconstructs the poster
on the fabric-backed paper,
which is now saturated with
glue.
he works carefully and quickly
to put the pieces together
before the glue dries.
one false move and he could make
a real mess of things.
but experience pays off.
he aligns the four sections
perfectly.
the glue dries, giving the
vintage poster a solid backing.
he flips through a collection of
paper scraps in search of one
that's similar in texture and
thickness to the posters.
he'll now use it to repair the
poster's ripped corner.
he traces the outline of the
tear onto transparent paper.
he cuts the scrap paper along
the traced line, producing a new
corner for the poster -- one
with exactly the right profile.
he sands the edge a bit to give
it a more gradual slope.
he brushes vegetable-based glue
onto the cutout.
he aligns it with the torn edge
and glues it in place, then
flattens the new corner to make
it level with the rest of the
poster.
it's now time to complete the
picture by repairing the torn
images.
the tricky part is mixing the
paint to match the poster's
vintage colors.
it sometimes takes a few tries
to get it right and make the
repair blend in.
even the white on the border has
to match.
no detail is overlooked as he
restores the corner of this
poster to its original
condition.
he touches up the rest of the
artwork with watercolor pencils,
applying color heavily or
lightly where needed.
and with a practiced hand, he
makes all the flaws and fold
lines disappear.
by the time he's done, the
vintage poster will look good
enough to frame.
with all the details now
covered, he trims the poster on
all sides and examines his work
for imperfections.
the repairs have to both look
and feel real.
from a tattered relic of the
past to one that looks fresh off
the press, a restored vintage
poster is an important piece of
history, now preserved for
future generations.
>> narrator: canola oil is a
commonly used type of cooking
oil.
it's derived from the seed of
the canola plant, which
north american farmers have been
growing for about 30 years now.
the plant blooms in the summer,
producing bright yellow flowers.
farmers harvest the seeds from
pods which form after those
flowers die off.
canola oil is one of the
healthiest cooking oils.
compared to olive, sunflower,
and soybean oils, it has the
lowest level of saturated fat --
7%.
it also contains more healthy
omega-3 fatty acids and is high
in monounsaturated fat, which
lowers cholesterol.
when the canola seed arrives at
the processing factory, it
contains foreign material --
mostly plant pieces.
so the first step is to clean
the seeds in a vibrating sieve.
the seeds -- smaller than the
openings in the sieve's mesh --
fall through to a conveyor
below.
the foreign material remains on
top.
a conveyor moves it to a storage
bin, where it's collected for
sale as cattle feed.
the seeds pass by a magnet.
it removes any metal that may
have fallen in during the
journey from field to factory.
next, the seeds enter a roller
mill.
they pass between two steel
rollers, which crush them into
thin flakes.
a conveyor then feeds the flakes
into a screw press.
it has a large revolving
screw-shaped shaft enclosed
within a slotted cage.
as the shaft turns, its threads
squeeze the flakes with high
pressure, forcing out the oil,
which then drains out through
the slots.
42% of canola seed is oil.
this group press extracts nearly
3/4 of that.
the remainder is still trapped
in the pressed flakes, now
referred to as canola cake.
the cake exits the other end of
the press and moves on to a
second extraction, this one a
70-minute wash with a solvent.
this chemical-extraction process
removes all but a trace of oil.
the factory then grinds the cake
into protein-rich meal that it
sells as animal feed.
the extracted oil, stored in
large tanks, now enters the
refining phase.
first, they wash the oil for 20
minutes with sodium hydroxide.
during this wash cycle, they
spin the oil at high speed so
that the centrifugal force
separates the natural
impurities, which the factory
later sells to soap
manufacturers.
after this cleaning process, the
canola oil is visibly clearer.
however, it still contains
natural waxes, which makes it
look cloudy.
so the next step is to cool the
oil to 41 degrees fahrenheit.
this thickens those waxes so
that they can be filtered out.
the waxes don't go to waste,
either.
the factory uses them to produce
vegetable shortening.
in the factory's lab,
technicians recreate production
on a small scale to ensure
performance and quality.
meanwhile, back in the factory,
after washing and filtering the
oil, they bleach it to lighten
the color, then use a
steam-injection heating process
to remove the canola odor.
the oil is now fully refined and
ready for bottling.
the equipment first turns the
plastic bottles upside down and
injects filtered pressurized air
to blow out any dust or dirt
inside.
then it turns the bottles right
side up again to position for
filling.
just before a nozzle starts
filling, it applies a vacuum.
if there's no suction,
indicating a leak in the bottle,
the machine automatically ejects
that bottle from the line.
each bottling machine in the
factory fills 22,000 bottles per
hour.
the labeling machines work
at the same speed.
they spread glue on the back of
each label, then apply the
label's edge to the bottle.
the bottle spins, wrapping the
rest of the label around itself.
as the bottles come off the
labeler, a robot separates them
into groups of 12.
then it picks up and deposits
each dozen in a shipping box --
from field to factory to your
pantry, where, once opened,
canola oil has a shelf life of
about a year.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications