-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
>> narrator: filigree glass is a
highly advanced form of
glassmaking.
the artists first produce
threads of colored glass, then
weave these threads together in
intricate patterns, encasing
them within clear crystal.
then they use complex
glassmaking techniques to shape
these patterned rods into
breathtaking works of art.
the filigree glass technique was
invented in the 1500s by master
glassmakers in murano, italy.
their then-secret process
incorporated ancient methods
from mesopotamia, the birthplace
of glassmaking some 2,000 years
earlier.
it all begins with a blend of
mostly silica sand, soda ash,
and lime.
they heat the mix to almost
2,400 degrees fahrenheit,
melting it over several hours
into lead-free liquid crystal.
with a steel rod called a punty,
the glassmakers roll some molten
crystal on a metal table as it
cools and solidifies --
a shaping technique known as
marvering.
then they use the post they've
shaped to pick up a piece of
densely colored glass called a
color bar.
they melt the color on the end
of the crystal post.
at the same time, they heat
another color bar into molten a
state.
then they perform a process
called overlaying.
they push the molten colored
glass over the other color bar,
then marver until the colored
glass symmetrically encases it.
they encase the color in clear
crystal and reheat some more,
then prepare a new bit of clear
crystal on another punty.
they use it to grab the free end
of the color overlay.
the glassmakers pull, stretching
the crystal like taffy into
what's known as overlaid cane, a
thin rod of crystal with a
thread rod of colored glass
inside.
it takes tremendous expertise to
stretch the rapidly cooling
glass to a consistent diameter
without twisting or breaking it
in the process.
they snip the long cane into
manageable lengths.
next, they cut the colored rods
into the size required...
lay out the rods in a precise
configuration, heat, then roll
them onto a precisely sized
piece of molten clear crystal.
now they repeat the pulling
process, but this time, to
create the internal pattern they
want, they twist both punties.
they use an electric drill to
ensure steady, uniform
revolutions.
the rod this creates is called a
complex cane.
after it cools and stabilizes
overnight, they cut it into the
lengths they need to create the
filigree glass piece.
the colors and pattern inside a
complex cane are determined by
the choice and layout of the
overlaid cane rods rolled onto
the molten crystal.
the filigree pattern is now
determined by the way in which
they lay out the complex cane
rods.
after fusing the laid-out rods,
they wrap them around a collar
of hot crystal at the end of a
blow pipe.
while rolling the piece on a
glass blowing bench, they use a
scissor-like tool called jacks
to close off the end.
they snip off the excess with
shears.
then, they roll the hot glass on
a wet wood block to smooth and
round the bubble.
they blow in some air to produce
the shape of a pear, stick a
punty to the bottom of the pear,
then use cold tweezers to shock
the hot glass into breaking
along the separation line
and transfer off the blow pipe.
now they take some hot crystal
from the furnace and roll it in
fine, granulated colored glass.
they reheat to melt the color
into the crystal...
then attach a bit of glass to
the top of the pear to form it
into a stem.
they smooth the cutoff edge with
a small torch.
they take another bit of molten
colored crystal to shape a leaf.
this crimping tool imprints the
veins.
every filigree piece these
canadian master glassmakers
create is signed by way of a
piece of cane bearing their
initials.
they fuse it to the piece in a
discreet location.
now the finishing touches --
reheating, then some
shape-tweaking with tools and
wet newspaper.
with the artist's work done,
it's time to enjoy the
spectacular fruits of their
labor.
>> narrator: flake foods for
aquarium fish were invented in
the middle of the last century,
and what a difference this
invention has made.
before they came along, pet fish
were fed live food from rivers
and streams -- a food source
that wasn't always accessible.
the invention of flake and
other dried foods made life in a
fish tank a whole lot easier.
just a few sprinkles and dinner
is served.
it's not much like the live
water fleas or bloodworms the
fish would feed on in their
natural environment, but it
contains the nutrients and
vitamins they need.
these dried tidbits can be
supersized to appeal to larger
fish that prefer to chow down on
something more substantial.
each formulation consists of up
to 40 different ingredients.
the main components are fish
meal...
wheat flour...
soy and paprika oils.
they also add food colorant
because fish are drawn to
certain colors.
they follow a precise recipe and
measure the ingredients
carefully.
they blend the smaller
components together first.
they include lecithin -- a
blending and thickening agent
also found in foods humans
consume -- and calcium for bone
strength.
the main ingredients -- the fish
meal, flours, and oils -- are
piped from silos into big tanks
and mixed with hot water.
they add the smaller premix and
blend everything together to
produce a thick slurry.
they spray the slurry onto the
surface of a series of rolling
heated drums.
as it flows over these drums,
the slurry cooks and dries into
a thin film that's like a paper
sheet.
as the sheet rolls off, a long
rotating blade chops it up to
produce big flakes.
they're pretty chunky at this
point and will need to be broken
up into bite-sized versions.
next, they fall down a chute and
into a plastic bag.
a worker transfers them by the
bagful to the next conveyer.
the various colors represent the
different formulations.
the green are veggie flakes,
while the red are protein-based.
they all head into a spiraling
device known as the tumbler.
it spins to toss the flakes
around.
this mixes then breaks them
into smaller flakes.
after several minutes in the
tumbler, the flakes fall onto a
series of screens to grade them
by size -- small, medium, and
large.
they land in separate bins, now
mixed and sorted by size.
meanwhile, the production of
fish-food sticks is underway.
machinery presses a food mash
through the small holes of an
extruder plate to create
spaghetti-like strings.
as the strings exit, rotating
knives cut them into sticks.
the sticks dry and solidify.
a worker routinely examines them
for size and form.
the next worker wheels a hopper
full of flakes above a chute and
removes the trap door.
the mix falls down one floor
onto the packaging line.
at the same time, a column of
empty cans heads toward the
flakes.
the fish food flakes fall
through special openings that
funnel them into the cans.
machinery cuts out aluminum foil
caps and slaps them on the tops
of the containers.
hot circular irons then seal the
caps to the cans.
this conveyor belt is also a
computerized scale which keeps
track of the amount of product
in the cans.
then, devices spin by to twist
plastic lids onto the threaded
rims of the cans.
as the cans pass by on a
carousel, applicators press
glue-backed product labels onto
them.
and these fish food flakes are
done.
in its various formulations,
dried fish food offers a range
of feeding options.
some contain additives that
enhance the growth and color of
the fish.
others are geared to a fish's
specific tastes, because even
pet fish can be discriminating
diners.
>> narrator: a motor home is a
fully equipped house on wheels.
the class "a" types are shaped
like a bus, the largest models
more than 40 feet long and
spacious enough to sleep up to
six people.
when parked, the exterior room
walls slide outward, expanding
the width by more than a yard.
motor homes have driver and
passenger seats at the front,
and in the back, the essentials
of a small house -- kitchen,
bedroom, living room, bathroom.
the factory buys a ready-made
standard-length steel chassis
from an automotive supplier with
motor and other components
already installed.
they then lengthen the chassis
by cutting each side and welding
on an extension piece.
they also extend the
pre-installed exhaust system and
electrical wiring.
then, they weld on steel plates
to reinforce the splices in the
chassis.
next, they lower the steel
basement frame, which has
compartments for the water
supply, waste collection, and
storage.
before installing the frame,
they attach three pairs of
sliding hydraulic cylinders
called rams.
each pair operates a slideout
room at the push of a button.
after bolting the frame to the
chassis, they spray each welded
joint with an anti-rust coating.
then, they test the rams to make
sure they slide in and out
properly.
they lower the preassembled
steel cab structure onto the
basement frame and weld it to
the chassis.
the motor home's front end is
made of fiberglass with a bumper
and headlights built in.
workers connect the headlights
to the electrical system, then
attach the front end to the cab
structure.
then, they install the hood and
make any necessary adjustments.
next, they load up the
compartments in the basement
structure, starting with the
freshwater tank made of durable
white plastic.
water runs from this tank
through flexible plastic water
lines to the sinks, shower, and
toilets.
next, the drainage line for
sewer waste.
it runs to a plastic tank that's
gray to differentiate it from
the water tank.
now they run a line of
heavy-duty adhesive along the
steel grid of the basement
structure and set down the
motor home's floor.
the floor construction is like a
sandwich -- aluminum on the
bottom, plywood on top, with a
high-density hard foam in the
middle to muffle noise and
absorb road vibration.
after securing the glued floor
with screws, they staple carpet
underpadding onto the plywood...
except in the kitchen and
bathroom areas, where they lay
down vinyl or ceramic tile
flooring and cut holes in it for
heat registers and drains.
then they install carpet over
the underpadding.
the pieces are precut to the
motor home's layout -- large
pieces for the main areas, small
ones for closets and the cab.
now, workers hook up what
they've built so far to a chain
mechanism that tows down an
assembly line.
first, overhead lifts lower the
motor home's three slideout
rooms -- dinette, living room,
bedroom -- onto their respective
rams.
workers bolt the rooms to the
rams, then test them.
next, workers install the
bathroom cabinetry, plumbing,
and wiring.
then the motor home gets its
three remaining walls.
they're fiberglass on the
outside, decorative paneling on
the inside, with foam and an
aluminum structural frame in
between.
the back wall has a luggage
compartment accessible from the
outside of the vehicle.
like the headlights on the front
end, the vehicle's taillights
are integrated.
the roof structure is the same
as the walls.
it has electrical wiring built
in and cut-outs for ceiling
lights and air-conditioning
vents.
the inner structural frames of
the roof and walls interlock.
a line of screws running the
length of the roof secures the
connection.
a generous application of
sealant, then on goes the roof
cap with built-in clearance
lights to finish off the front
end.
>> narrator: at this point, the
outside of the motor home is
almost complete.
however, there's still much
interior work to come.
everything on the inside is
designed to maximize living
space and storage space.
and even though the motor home
has just one bedroom, pullout
beds in other areas add
additional sleep space.
one of the last jobs remaining
on the outside is to install the
door.
it fits perfectly because they
constructed it using the piece
they cut out of the side wall to
make the door opening.
next, some decorative detailing
on the vehicle body, including
an adhesive vinyl decal bearing
the model name.
on the inside, workers are busy
applying the finishing touches.
they hang cabinet doors...
install under-cabinet
lighting...
and hook up the kitchen
appliances.
the stove is a special compact
size manufactured specifically
for recreational vehicles.
customers buying motor homes
have a choice of window
coverings.
this order calls for double-duty
roller shades -- one setting
filters daylight, the other
blacks it out.
the installer uses a gauge to
adjust the blinds to the correct
drawing tension.
then, she installs decorative
valances to hide the edges and
pull cords.
in the cab, workers bolt the
base of the driver and passenger
seats to the basement frame.
then, they bolt a seat-belt
receiver to each seat base.
the seats, upholstered in
high-end synthetic leather,
attach into their respective
bases.
workers install the dinette,
which sits in one of the
slideout rooms.
the bench seats have a storage
area underneath, and the seats
and table convert into an extra
bed.
at the rear of the motor home is
the bedroom, which is the second
slideout room.
the bed has storage space
underneath for blankets and
pillows.
regulations designate certain
seats safe to sit in while the
vehicle is moving.
those seats are equipped with
safety belts.
the couch in the living room,
the third slideout room, has a
few hidden features -- an air
mattress which inflates and
deflates at the push of a button
for an extra bed, and a drawer
underneath for storing pillows
and blankets.
the bathroom has a toilet...
sink...
shower stall...
and lots of cabinet space.
back on the outside, workers
install a rear-view camera on
each side wall.
when the driver activates the
right turn signal, the right
side camera automatically turns
on.
the left turn signal, the left
camera.
the cameras transmit the image
to a dashboard monitor.
every motor home this factory
produces undergoes extensive
water-infiltration testing.
hundreds of sprayers shoot
several straight minutes of
simulated heavy rainfall from
all angles, including
underneath -- with the slideout
rooms both extended and
retracted.
inspectors check everywhere,
even inside cabinets.
if they find any leaks, they
seal them and run the water test
again.
and finally, one last mechanical
verification of the slideout
rooms, now that they bear the
additional weight of the
furnishings.
this expansion feature is the
secret to the motor home's
spacious feel, as it increases
the floor-space width by nearly
five feet.
the slideouts operate only while
the motor home is parked.
with smart design and ingenious
use of limited space, a motor
home lets you hit the road
without leaving the comforts of
home behind.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...