>> narrator: the story of tequila begins many centuries
fermented the juice of the agave plant to produce a low-alcohol
when the spanish conquistadors arrived, they added distillation    to th
stronger drink, and tequila was born. tequila is t
champagne is to france. tequila is only made in this
has claimed exclusive rights to the word "tequila."  for
jimadores have grown and harvested the agave plant for
it takes seven years, on average, for a species called
and even today, it's harvested entirely by hand. using
tool, the jimadores chop away the greenery until all that's
the pia. filing the round blade frequently keeps it  raz
allowing them to remove most of the bitter-tasting leaves from
the tequila distilled from this crop will be a premium
juice. the jimadores routinely remove a   small pi
starch content of the crop. only if it's deemed to be
sent to the distillery. workers wield special hatchets
quarters. they're a more manageable size
they transfer the chopped pia to a brick oven, where it's
this thorough cooking converts the agave starch to sugar.
softens and the color turns from white to reddish brown. the
into a shredder that rotates to tear the fruit into long, thin
the fibers exit onto a conveyor. the shredded pia lands in a pit, where a worker forks it
and moves it into the path of a huge stone wheel called a ta
operated mechanically, the tahona wheel turns to crush the   fibers and
precious agave nectar. it takes two hours of crushing
they pipe the juicy mash into wooden tanks and add yeast. the yeast causesferment
process by which sugar is transformed into alcohol. after 72 hours of ferme
the alcohol content reaches 5%. the fermented pulp and juices have an earthy, acidic
and the aroma fills the air. they transfer the fermented mash to small cop
inside the stills, the alcohol is boiled off and the vapor
liquid. this is called distillation.
they have tequila. a technician measures the al
after straining out the pulp, they transfer the tequila to
they add purified well water to dilute the alcohol content
this tequila is now ready to drink, so it's over to the b
with the bottles upside down on a revolving carousel, they spray the inside with real tequila
a quick rinse. the grippers flip them  ri
filled with 100% agave tequila. this automated system keeps the   fill level
an employee corks the bottles and then sends them down the
the next worker presses adhesive-backed transparent
the see-through labels showcase the clarity of this fresh,
for a drink with a little more complexity, they age the tequila in oak cas
more, depending on the grade. during aging, the tequila takes  on a woody
warm shade of amber. the master distiller personally  approves
he checks the color, inhales the aroma, and puts his observations down on
he also takes a little sip. no longer a rough swill for
uptown and evolved into a more sophisticated drink.
>> narrator: waterbeds have come a long way since the ancient
goat skins. hitting the market in the  l
pretty wavy and made some people seasick. but innovative changes in d
make today's waterbeds as stable as a traditional mattress.
displaces. that's why a waterbed mattress shapes to your body, giving
equal support everywhere with no pressure points. a washable quilted cover sits
top of the mattress to provide extra cushioning and absorb
the mattress is made of high-durability vinyl.   i
factory in giant rolls which workers feed into a conditioning    machi
at a speed of one yard per minute, the machine heats the vinyl to 100 degrees  fah
this preshrinks the material, ensuring the mattress won't
next, computer-guided machines cut out the mattress's top and
die cutters stamp out the smaller and simpler corner and
then, workers lay the top piece on a wooden pattern mold. applying this pattern makes
vinyl more flexible, enabling the mattress to better follow
the company won't reveal exactly how this caged device molds the pattern into
now, with a die, workers cut a hole in the top piece for the
after fitting the valve and cap to a piece of vinyl printed with product information, they lay
the top piece, then fuse the vinyl with a high-frequency w
it emits high-frequency electromagnetic waves that heat   and cause
interact, blending the two pieces seamlessly into one.
mattress. this is the most complex part of the process because it
making a very particular angle. after fusing the folds with the high-frequency welder, they
each corner onto a rounded form, then close off the tip by  w
this makes a rounded corner, which is far more durable than a  pointed on
whereas regular mattresses are foam-filled, waterbed mattresses  contain
bed waveless. mattresses come in various
the more layers of fiber inside, the less the mattress moves. once they've inserted the f
workers perform a final round of high-frequency welding to close    up the m
first, they position an aluminum stick under the area they have
a static laser line shows workers where to position the
welder. once the mattress is welded all  around, the
through the valve hole, then flatten the mattress,  dis
within it. the final operation is qua
they put the mattress in a press and, with a vacuum hose, extract  all the a
then, they set the mattress aside for six hours to ensure
would indicate a leak. elsewhere in the factory, they construct the frame in which
mattress sits. the lower part is made of pvc plastic extruded into a
shape. workers fuse the frame parts
then pressing together the edges to bond them.  this fa
mass-produce. every single waterbed is made to   order from
choices. the customer who ordered this
upholstered in black faux leather.  the mattr
melamine base. they slide it into the frame,
the upper sides of the frame are made of upholstered foam, designed to be soft against
back of your legs when you sit on the side of the bed. waterbed mattresses are
empty. the installer fills it with
leaving enough space inside for the water to displace under p
is open, water doesn't spill out, even when someone's lying
>> narrator: they may not be the fanciest of footwear, but flip-flops, also called
are inexpensive and comfortable. it's believed these flat sandals   with the
modeled after traditional japanese sandals that have a
woven from plant fibers. the anatomy of a flip-flop is
y-shaped straps called uppers. the sole is constructed from the top and bott
they make the bottom out of either heat-moldable plastic or rubber.
an injection-molding machine shoots the molten material into passing mold
two fans positioned over the injector kick-start the cooling    process
then, a continuous water-cooling system takes over. 3 1/2
the material is solid. they make the top soles from
a hydraulic press forces a sole-shaped die through the
slicing through dough. the die also cuts a hole and two slits for attaching the
some flip-flops have decorations on the top soles.  the d
pair manually using a standard screen-printing process.  t
for each color of the design. the screen is kind of like a
shape of the design, and the rest of the mesh is blocked. workers load a pair of soles
each station of a rotary-screen printing machine.  then,
they close the first screen over the pair of soles, then, with
the screen surface. the ink passes through the open   mesh, appl
they move the soles to the next screen and do the same with the second color of ink, and so
now for the uppers. for this flip-flop style, they
once they've correctly positioned the ribbon, they
then, they connect the left-side and right-side straps with m
add a toe piece... then stitch everything together. for aesthetics, they sew a c
piece over the toe piece. uppers give flip-flops their
materials, colors, thicknesses, and embellishments.  the
endless. now to connect the uppers to the  top sole, w
toe piece into the toe hole and a strap end into each slit.
trim the ends... then insert a last -- a foot form in the required shoe s
they pull the straps tightly against it.  next, th
the top sole and the top of the bottom sole with glue.  th
oven activates the adhesive. workers then place the bottom sole on a positioning guide
stick the top sole onto it, locking the strap ends in
this is instant-contact glue, so they have just one chance to get  the alignme
a 4-second bonding experience in a press, and they're  "so
however, the former bottom sole is slightly larger than the
so, with a high speed sander, workers trim off the excess,
smooth. after a manual sanding touch-up,   if nece
quality-control inspection, the flip-flops are ready for
workers stuff a pad of paper under the uppers to prop them up   should the
during transport. once considered strictly
stepped it up in style to become fashionable everyday
>> narrator: not only used for jewelry or silverware, 80% of the world's silver is mined
industrial purposes. silver is the most conductive
planet. for example, it's used in  e
construction as an insulation coating on glass.   the
silver bars, the composition of which is 93% to 97% pure silver. it sells the bars to a
which further purifies them for sale to industries.  the
mine, where geologists point a niton gun at various spots in
the device detects the levels of 40 different elements, including silver.
silver in its natural state isn't silver-colored at all.
those silver-looking deposits are actually zinc and lead.
silver-rich areas the geologists pinpointed, then
after the blast, carts hall the chunks of rock, called ore, to
geologists then test ore piles and blend them as required to
silver content per kilogram of ore.   the ore fi
primary crusher. the machine's huge steel teeth
smaller pieces. those pieces then drop through
secondary crusher, which breaks them down into even smaller p
those go into vibrating cone crushers, which pulverize them
a conveyor transports the crushed ore to the ball mill.
are roughly 2/10 of an inch big. as the mill's large cylinder
around inside, grinding the ore into powder.   a wate
flushes the silver-rich powder out of the cylinder and into large tanks which keep the w
moving. to separate and dissolve the
workers pour in acid. 72 hours later, the rock waste
the solution containing dissolved silver is pumped t
the filter plates are treated with a zinc-based chemical which   attracts
as the solution passes through, the plates trap particles  c
layer of black powder called silver precipitate. this precipitate is composed
approximately 50% silver and 50% waste -- the waste being a jumble of various metals, d
and other impurities. to separate the silver from the    waste, th
precipitate in a gas furnace for a couple of hours.  in t
technicians continuously test ore samples to determine the
quantity of silver per kilogram of ore. they heat t
degrees fahrenheit for about an hour to burn off the impurities. what's l
are the silver and other metals, such as lead, zinc, copper, s
lab technicians then treat the samples with a chemical that prevents silver from burning
and put them back in the oven. when the samples come out, about  an hour la
metals have burnt off, and only silver is left.    they
compare it to the weight of the original sample in order to
the key to running a profitable mine is to ensure that the grade is consiste
parameters. back at the mill, workers put the now dried silver  pre
into an oven, along with chemicals which prevent silver
approximately four hours later,
the silver and waste have
separated and melted.
workers pour them into
bar-shaped molds.
the silver, being heavier,
settles at the bottom.
workers skim off the waste
floating on top.
in less than five minutes, the
molten silver cools and hardens,
enabling workers to extract what
is now a silver bar.
the mining company sells the
bars to a refinery for
processing into industrial-grade
silver.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like
to suggest topics for future
shows, drop us a line at...
--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications