-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: surgical instruments
have evolved
with the science of medicine.
they actually date back
thousands of years,
when primitive man
used crude implements
to cut holes in skulls
to release evil spirits.
medical science
has come a long way since then,
and today's surgical tools
are among its advancements.
in the hands
of a skilled surgeon,
the right tool
can be a lifesaver.
there are now hundreds
to choose from,
each designed for
a specific task or operation.
made of surgical-grade steel --
which is extremely
corrosion-resistant --
they can withstand frequent
cleaning and sterilizing.
one of the more useful tools
is a self-retaining retractor,
which is used to pull back
tissues or organs
during surgery.
using a circular cutter,
they round
the profile of the tool's joint.
this round joint
allows the tool to open
when the shanks are shut, the
opposite of a pair of scissors.
next, cutters carve slots
in two parts
to create the retractor's
intermeshing jaws.
these jaws will be used
to grasp and retract body tissue
so the surgeon can operate.
a technician sands the teeth
down to a precise size.
he must be accurate within
a quarter of a millimeter.
he then smoothes the jaw's teeth
against a fine-grit wheel
so they'll easily intermesh
when needed.
he rounds the tips of the teeth
to make them blunt
so they won't damage
human tissue.
he hammers back
the tips of the teeth,
giving them a claw-like profile.
with the teeth now complete,
attention returns to the round
joint of the instrument.
the carved slots
and counter-sync
allow the two sides
to fit together perfectly.
they install a part called
the rack, below the joint,
and file teeth into it.
it will be used to lock the tool
in an open position.
after heat treatment,
a worker sands
all the tool components
to smooth sharp edges.
vibrating porcelain chips
and polishing compound
scrub them clean and remove
burrs caused by machining.
next, they install the pivot
screw and trigger for the rack.
by pressing it,
the surgeon can open the prongs
to the desired width
and lock the tool in position.
production now moves
to the surgical clamp.
it's used to block the flow
of blood during operations
and has
a more scissors-like joint --
rectangular instead of round.
mechanized cutters
carve the joint and catches.
a worker forces the finger bows
against
a spinning grinding wheel
to remove surface imperfections.
precision is again critical,
as the worker grinds
each of the tool's shanks
to the correct thickness.
he measures to confirm
that the size is consistent
along the length of the part.
he then files the joints
so they mate perfectly.
he places the joint part of
one of the shanks over hot coals
to soften the metal
and make it malleable.
then he forces a spike
through a slit in the joint,
and the now-compliant steel
stretches to open the slit.
the other shank now slides
easily into the opening.
he hammers the joint
to close the opening,
and the two arms
of this surgical clamp
are now hinged together.
next he files
the teeth of the clamp
so they'll interlock
when the tool is closed.
he bends the two ends
around a tool
to form the jaws of the clamp.
these curved jaws
will come in handy
when the surgeon needs to reach
around organs or bone.
next, using a variety of tools,
he adjusts
the shanks and the finger bows
to give them
a more ergonomic feel.
this is called soft-setting
because at this point,
the metal is still
soft enough to be manipulated.
he tweaks the bend of the jaws
until he's satisfied
with the curvature.
he smoothes
the inside of the finger bows
with a fine abrasive belt.
after heat treatment
to strengthen the metal,
they blast it
with fine glass particles
to give it a satin finish.
they laser-etch the company name
and identifying numbers
onto the surgical clamp.
the numbers
will allow the tool to be traced
back to a particular
production run.
and now it's ready
to take its place
on the front lines
of healthcare.
narrator:
ketchup has a questionable past.
according to one theory,
it comes from the chinese
"kê-chiap," a type of sauce.
another theory traces it
to european pickling sauces,
and yet another
claims arabic origins.
but there's widespread agreement
on where it ends up --
on hot dogs, hamburgers,
and french fries.
tomato ketchup recipes
vary only slightly,
as consumers expect a certain
familiar tomatoey taste.
this u.s. company produces
all-natural ketchup
made entirely of certified
organic ingredients --
tomato paste, agave nectar --
a natural sweetener --
onion powder, spices,
salt, and white vinegar.
the tomato paste,
not surprisingly,
is the base ingredient.
it arrives at the plant
in huge bins,
which have been vacuum-packed
to preserve freshness.
after unsealing each bin,
the factory's
quality-control technician
scoops a sample for testing.
this is to make sure that
the thickness is just right.
if the sample gets the okay,
workers slide the bin under
a powerful air-driven pump.
then they flip a switch,
and the pump
begins moving the tomato paste
to a large holding tank,
transferring nearly 310 pounds
of this ketchup base
in less than 10 minutes.
at production time,
an intricate system of piping
transfers a specific amount
of tomato paste
from the holding tank
into a cooking kettle.
as the paste cooks,
a mixer continuously revolves
to keep it
from sticking to the sides
and to blend in the onion powder
workers add next.
this and the upcoming
ingredients
have been pre-measured
to be in correct proportion
to the batch size.
the next ingredients are salt,
then, as a sugar replacement,
nectar from the agave plant.
they pour in an initial amount,
mix a bit,
then pump in the remainder.
the last ingredient
is white vinegar.
for competitive reasons,
the company won't divulge
the mixing time, cooking time,
or cooking temperature,
all of which are key elements
of this top-secret recipe.
on the packaging line,
an alignment machine stands
the plastic bottles upright
as they make their way
to the filling machine.
the finished ketchup, meanwhile,
is passing through
an elaborate system of cooling
pipes en route to the filler.
and let the bottling begin.
the machine fills
eight bottles at a time...
...150 bottles per minute.
the factory tests every batch
of ketchup it produces
to ensure the correct
consistency in every bottle.
the next machine,
appropriately called the capper,
places a plastic flip-cap
on each bottle,
then, with spinning circular
belts, twists it on securely.
the next machine
cuts a decorative neck band
made of plastic film
and slips it over the cap.
each bottle
then passes under an air jet.
the air
blows the neck band downward
until it's positioned
under the cap.
then a quick blast of hot steam
shrinks the band to a tight fit.
the next machine presses on
two adhesive labels --
one on the front of the bottle,
the other on the back.
then it's off to
the packing-and-shipping area.
a sealed bottle of ketchup
stays fresh for at least a year
because the vinegar in it
acts as a natural preservative.
ketchup also has health benefits
because it's
chock full of tomatoes,
which are high in lycopene --
a powerful antioxidant
believed to protect
against many types of cancer.
narrator: double-decker buses
have long been a fixture
on the streets
of london, england.
a typical double-decker
carries 60% more riders
than a regular bus.
and though
quintessentially british,
nowadays you'll find
london style double-deckers
on the streets of several major
cities throughout the world.
every bus design undergoes
rigorous stability testing.
they fill the prototype
with lead weights
to simulate
a full passenger load,
then tips the bus
to a 28-degree angle,
the side wheels lifting about
shoulder height off the ground.
if the vehicle
doesn't keel over,
the design passes the test.
the bus's underframe --
the chassis --
is made of welded steel.
they construct it
in three separate modules --
front, center, and rear --
then set the three modules
in an alignment jig
to be welded together.
once that's done,
welders add a steel structure
that'll support the floors,
seats, and body panels.
then they clean the chassis and
paint it with anti-rust epoxy.
after baking on the paint,
they seal the gaps between the
welded parts with polyurethane.
this prevents water penetration,
which would cause
internal corrosion.
meanwhile, technicians bolt
the 6-cylinder,
250-horsepower engine
to the automatic transmission
and connect the hydraulic lines
and other piping.
then they wheel this engine pack
over to the assembly line
and bolt it to a bar
at the rear of the chassis.
by suspending the engine, they
shield it from impact damage
in the event
of a rear-end collision.
they also install the radiator,
battery, and other components.
at the front of the chassis,
they install
the driver's binnacle --
on which
all the controls are located.
unlike a stationary
car dashboard,
for driver comfort, the binnacle
tilts with the steering column.
after installing
the front and rear axles,
technicians mount the wheels.
each one is more than a yard in
diameter and weighs 100 pounds.
the engineering specs
require the wheel nuts to be
turned to a specific tightness.
workers also install
the driver's seat
and the vehicle's
73-gallon gas tank.
the complete chassis
goes onto a test-drive machine
which simulates
varying passenger loads
and road conditions.
a camera pointed at the binnacle
records the accuracy
of the speedometer
and whether
any warning lights illuminate.
then it's in to the body shop,
where workers mount fiberglass
boxes over the wheels.
another team
builds the inter-deck floor,
the aluminum-frame structure
that separates
the bus's two levels.
they affix the lower level's
melamine ceiling to one side
and the upper deck's
plywood floor to the other.
to make the roof,
they construct an aluminum frame
then glue an aluminum sheet
onto it.
most of the bus's body
is made of aluminum
because,
compared to other metals,
it's lightweight, durable,
and easy to repair.
next, they paint the roof
and install components
integrated within it,
such as the aerial antenna
and wires for lighting.
as this computer animation
illustrates,
step by step,
the bus is slowly taking shape.
workers insert the pegs
underneath the roof
into aluminum pillars running
the perimeter of the upper deck.
along the sides, workers
sandwich the structural frame
between inner and outer
aluminum body panels.
first,
they affix the inner ones,
then they fill
the spaces in between
with blocks of foam insulation.
finally, they glue on
the outer side panels,
pressing out the excess adhesive
with a roller
so that the panel lays flat.
the front and back of the bus
are made of molded fiberglass.
they have openings for windows,
and in the back,
a cut-out beneath the top window
for the upper-deck
air-conditioner.
as one crew glues
all the window glass into place,
others install the doors and,
inside, the upholstered seats
and a durable
non-slip floor covering.
once the bus comes back
from the paint shop,
the factory's
quality-control department
inspects the interior.
the seat fabric
is dark and patterned
to discourage graffiti.
the bus also has 12 cameras
hidden in various locations
to deter vandalism.
the typical double-decker
is 11 yards long
and nearly 15 feet high.
it carries up to 92 passengers.
narrator: when you need
something to lean on,
a walking stick can provide
the necessary support.
wooden walking sticks
have been coming in handy
since primitive times.
the first versions
were likely crude branches,
but they've evolved
into something much finer.
today's wooden walking sticks
are designed to support
the user in style.
there are rustic versions
for the outdoor adventurer
and distinguished-looking ones
for getting around town.
but, whatever the style,
a walking stick adds stability
to the human journey.
it all begins with
these 3-year-old saplings.
these are chestnut --
a lightweight and durable wood.
once the sticks
have been peeled and dried,
it's into the washing machine
to scrub off any dirt or mold
that may have accumulated.
and it's not
your usual washing machine --
this one is a long tank sized
specifically for these sticks.
a worker closes the lid tightly
so no sticks will spill out
as the tank rotates
in a trough of soapy water.
after a few minutes
of tossing about,
these sticks come out
squeaky-clean,
and they're ready
for the steamer.
the sticks are steamed
for 20 minutes,
and this makes them
soft enough to bend.
so next, he secures the stick
and activates
a spring-loaded arm.
it wraps one end around a form
to curl it into a crook.
he ties it
so it holds the crook shape
and retracts the bending arm.
this crook will serve
as the walking stick's handle.
a century ago, crooks
were formed entirely by hand,
which took brute strength.
but with the invention
of this nifty machine,
the job
became a whole lot easier.
next, it's over to a device
called the straightening horse,
because it's used
to straighten the stick's shaft.
this job
does take a bit of muscle,
as the worker
wrenches the shaft between posts
to set it straight.
with the shaft now quite linear
and the end curled into a crook
and still tied,
it's time to set
the shape of this walking stick.
and so it's in to the drying
room for a couple of days.
the temperature in here is
around 175 degrees fahrenheit.
and as the sticks dry,
the shape solidifies.
a worker then cuts the stick
to the correct length,
and he also pares down the end
to prepare it for capping later.
he also sands down
the knots in the wood,
creating a smoother surface.
from a simple sapling
to a cane shape,
it's quite a transformation.
and it's not over.
the next worker
exposes the wood to a flame,
just long enough to blacken it.
this is staining
without the chemicals,
and the finish is distinctive.
he now turns the walking stick
against a very sharp
circular blade
to carve spirals on the crook
and down the shaft.
it's a candy-cane look, and
achieving it is a bit tricky.
this is where
on-the-job experience counts.
another worker then trims
the end of the handle crook.
the cutoffs won't go to waste --
they'll help fire
the factory furnace.
next, a worker inserts the crook
in a machine that works
like a pencil sharpener,
except the blade inside
rounds the end.
this process is called
"nosing the stick."
the stick that started out
as a peeled sapling
now looks
dramatically different.
next, a dip
in water-based lacquer
gives this walking stick
a high gloss.
they hang it to drip-dry
for an hour,
after which the walking stick
is ready for the end cap,
or ferrule.
ferrules come
in a variety of styles.
there are blunt ones, for
a good grip on indoor surfaces,
and there are pointed ferrules,
for navigating
rougher, outdoor terrain.
after hammering the ferrule
onto the stick,
he drives a nail through it
to secure it.
and these walking sticks
are now complete.
all that's left
is to hang around
until the orders come in.
and those orders
are usually very specific.
customers get to choose
the length of stick that's
appropriate for their height,
as well as the style and finish
they prefer.
from a simple stick
to a dignified-looking cane,
it's been quite a journey.
the path ahead may be uncertain,
but with one of these
walking sticks in hand,
a person is well-equipped
to make his or her way
in the world.