-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
>> narrator: the clay liquor jug
is a product with an elicit
past.
in 19th-century america, this
distinct stoneware jug was used
to contain backwoods brew,
moonshine whiskey that was
produced under the cover of
night to avoid scrutiny from the
authorities so it could be sold
tax free.
today they still uncork the
little brown jug to serve up
old-time corn whiskey.
replicas like this one add an
authentic touch to the
traditional brew.
the jug starts with raw clay dug
out of the ground and crushed
into little particles.
they also break up defective and
damaged pottery and recycle it
into the process so nothing is
wasted.
next, a shaft with protruding
knives mixes the clay with water
and fortifying chemicals.
when the clay reaches a doughy
consistency, a vacuum sucks out
the air pockets, and then
machinery forces it through a
dye to form a long log.
in log form, the clay is easier
to handle.
the potter pulls off some
chunks of clay and shapes them
into patties.
he presses the patties into
molds of the top and bottom
parts of the clay liquor jug.
he inserts each mold in a
holding ring and spins it.
a wooden tool now sculpts the
jug's top section from the
inside.
clay migrates up the walls of
the mold and takes its shape.
the potter pokes a wooden dowel
in the neck of the jug to round
it out.
as tools shape the lower body of
the liquor jug, the potter
sprays water on the rim.
this makes the rim sticky, which
will allow the bottom portion of
the jug to adhere to the top.
still in the molds, he presses
the two parts of the jug
together, and the moistened clay
bonds.
once the clay is dried, the next
craftsperson pries it from the
molds, and it comes out in one
piece.
she removes any unwanted bits
and transfers the jug to the
workbench.
she levels the lip of the jug
with a stick and spins the jug
on a pottery wheel to scrape off
surplus clay at the seam.
she smooths down rough spots on
the exterior surface with a wet
sponge.
at this point, the clay is still
fairly supple and responds to
moisture.
meanwhile, jug handles are
taking shape in this tub.
steel paddles force the clay
through holes in the bottom,
producing ribbons of clay that
will now be shaped into curved
handles.
the potter moistens one end of
the clay ribbon and presses it
to the neck of the jug.
she must apply just the right
amount of pressure, or it will
fall off.
she pulls the clay ribbon into a
distinctive curve and presses
the other end to the side of the
jug.
the curvature must be similar
from jug to jug, and producing a
consistent shape every time
takes practice.
at the glazing station, an
operator tests a pump that
spurts glaze upwards, creating a
brief fountain of glaze.
with a paddle, he swishes the
solution around to keep the
glaze particles suspended.
then he immerses the top of the
jug in the liquid to give the
clay liquor jug that familiar
two-toned look.
he pumps glaze inside the jug,
giving it a leakproof lining
that will allow it to hold
liquids.
the next worker stamps product
information on the side of the
jug using ceramic inks.
next, they prepare a different
glaze.
the worker dips the bottom
portion of the jug in it, and it
appears to completely obscure
the carefully applied product
information.
but when the glaze dries, it
will become transparent, and the
stamp will be visible again.
the next worker scuffs off the
glaze on the base to keep the
jug from sticking to the shelves
in the kiln.
they fire the whiskey jugs at
around 2,200 degrees fahrenheit
for eight hours.
this hardens the clay and
deepens the glaze.
it's taken a total of 19 steps
and one week to transform a
couple of lumps of clay into a
little brown jug.
and it's sure to add a touch of
nostalgia to cocktail hour.
>> narrator: man cannot live by
bread alone.
but add a few slices of chicken
or turkey deli meat, and you've
got a meal.
poultry deli meat is a popular
alternative to corn beef or
salami, and that's because it's
less fatty any way you slice it.
when it comes to making deli
meats, it's all in the
seasoning.
from fiery southwestern turkey
to hot-sauce-marinated chicken,
they really know how to spice it
up.
they begin with plenty of
filtered water.
it will be used to disperse the
specially formulated seasonings.
there's a different blend for
every product, and they include
salt and different herbs and
spices.
they add honey because this is a
honey maple recipe.
and while that's all being
mixed, they check the
temperature of the raw poultry
to confirm it's in the safe
range.
if it's even slightly off,
there's a risk of bacterial
growth, so the whole batch would
have to be rejected.
but this poultry has been
well-chilled.
the stitch pump machine's
long steel needles repeatedly
inject seasoning solutions into
the breast meat.
excess liquid drains through the
conveyor as the chicken is
transferred to a holding area to
marinate for at least two hours.
next, numerous lumpy rollers
massage the chicken and break
down fiber to tenderize the
meat.
then, in a tumbler, metal
paddles vigorously knead the
meat.
this tenderizes it even more and
releases a natural protein that
will eventually bind several
breasts into one big piece.
meanwhile in the turkey kitchen,
workers shape and season
previously marinated meat and
apply strips of bacon to the
top.
the employee arranges them in a
crisscross pattern for full
coverage.
he dusts it with a mix of
seasonings and then wraps it in
thick plastic.
once enclosed in the plastic, he
can press the turkey breast into
a more perfect shape.
for a different flavor, they
drench some turkey breast in a
spicy southwestern marinade.
after folding the turkey meat to
the desired shape, the worker
adds salsa and seasonings to
complete the recipe.
a little more hand shaping and
it's ready for the oven.
back on the chicken line, it's
the same idea but with a
different twist.
chicken breasts are too small to
shape by hand, so they funnel
them into thermoformed plastic
molds.
as the molds move forward, a
worker sprinkles spices onto the
meat while another swabs juices
to test for pathogens as part of
a quality-control program.
equipment heat-seals the plastic
molds and then cuts them free
from the matrix.
then they're on their way to the
smoke oven.
they spend six hours smoking at
165 degrees fahrenheit.
the protein released earlier by
kneading causes the chicken
parts to adhere and take the
shape of the mold.
once they've been temperature
checked, it's on to the next
station.
here, workers peel off the
cooking mold and drain the
excess juices.
then the molded breasts go
through a fryer.
the hot canola oil browns the
outside of the chicken meat for
a more appealing and tasty
effect.
meanwhile, workers swish other
cooked chicken breasts in hot
buffalo-wing sauce to really
kick up the spice a few notches.
and after extra seasoning, the
chicken travels through a long
arc of electric heat rods.
this is a special convection
oven.
fans blow the heat from the rods
onto the meat to complete the
cooking process.
by now the turkey deli meat has
also been thoroughly cooked and
crisped.
they transfer the turkey-filled
bags to clam-like devices that
close around them.
inside, a vacuum sucks out the
air to shrink the packaging
around the turkey and keep it
fresh.
it has taken about eight hours
to produce this poultry deli
meat.
refrigerated, it should last
about 35 days, unless there's a
hungry crowd.
>> narrator: nascar, an acronym
for the national association for
stock car auto racing, is one of
the most popular spectator
sports in north america.
nascar vehicles are modeled
after certain american-made
four-door passenger cars, but
with far more powerful engines.
no overhead camshaft engines on
this track.
for tradition's sake, nascar
rules require an overhead valve
engine, an older type of
configuration also known as a
push rod engine.
designing the engine takes about
a year and a half.
it culminates in a detailed
computer model, an anatomical
rendering of the engine in full
detail, right down to every last
nut and bolt.
the computer model guides a
stereolithography machine to
produce a plastic prototype of
each engine component.
the machine repeatedly outputs
paper-thin layers of
photosensitive liquid resin,
which an ultraviolet laser
instantly solidifies.
over the course of several
hours of resin layering, their
prototype component takes shape.
technicians test it in
conjunction with other prototype
components and make any
necessary adjustments to the
design.
then, computer-controlled
machining equipment produces a
metal prototype.
when every component has gone
through this process, the engine
design gets the go-ahead to move
into production.
the factory first casts the
basic shape of certain
components in a mold, then
machines that shape to its final
form.
here, computer-guided hones
finish the engine's eight
cylinder bores, the chambers in
which the power-generating
combustion cycles will occur.
technicians take very precise
measurements to ensure the
bores' diameter and roundness
meet specifications.
then they flip the engine block
upside down, oil the crankshaft
bearings, position the
crankshaft on those bearings,
and lock it in with bolted-on
caps.
as the pistons inside the
cylinders move up and down, they
rotate the crankshaft, driving
the clutch and transmission,
which propel the racecar.
with this little black component
called a wrist pin, they join
the piston to a connecting rod.
next, they fit two rings on the
piston.
the top one seals the cylinder,
maximizing the pressure inside,
which optimizes combustion.
the bottom ring skims excess oil
off the cylinder walls between
combustion cycles, which
prevents the car from burning
oil.
after inserting a piston all the
way down into the cylinder bore,
they grease the upper portion to
prepare for measuring the
compression ratio which must
comply with nascar rules.
the compression ratio refers to
the volume of space in which the
piston compresses the gas and
fuel mixture entering the
cylinder.
to take this critical
measurement, they raise the
piston all the way to the top
dead center point, then verify
the positioning with gauges.
they seal the top of the
cylinder with a see-through
plastic plate.
then, with a syringe, inject
alcohol into the space in
between.
the markings on the syringe tell
them how many ccs -- cubic
centimeters -- filling that
space requires.
this volume measurement
indicates the compression ratio.
the higher the compression
ratio, the more horsepower the
engine produces.
they repeat this test with each
cylinder.
they flip the engine block
upside down and put each
piston's connecting rod in the
corresponding position on the
crankshaft.
then lock the piston in place
with bolted-on connection caps.
now the technician closes up the
bottom of the engine.
meanwhile, a device called a
profilometer inspects the
camshaft.
the camshaft moves the intake
and exhaust valves at the top of
each cylinder, allowing the fuel
and air mixture in and the
combustion gases out.
this testing ensures the
camshaft is straight and that
its surface is slightly rough so
that lubricating oil will cling
to it.
the engine build is now about
halfway there.
>> narrator: in a push rod
engine, the camshaft is located,
as we've just seen, above the
crankshaft.
it opens and closes the valves
with a system of lifters, rods,
and rocker arms.
in the more modern overhead
camshaft configuration, the
camshaft sits on top of the
cylinders, moving the valves
directly.
building the nascar engine
continues with the installation
of this aluminum motor plate by
which mechanics will mount the
engine in the car.
next, the timing belt, which
links the camshaft to the
crankshaft, ensuring they turn
in sync and maintain the correct
timing.
at the core of the belt is a
woven material that's five times
stronger than steel.
other technicians use a gauge to
measure how much force it takes
to compress the valve springs.
this quality-control check
ensures that spring tension is
within a specific range.
each cylinder has an intake
valve and an exhaust valve.
technicians use a compression
tool to squeeze a spring over
each one.
then they secure the spring with
a locking clip.
the valves are located in the
top section of the engine,
called the cylinder head, that
technicians now bolt on to the
engine block.
next, they assemble the push rod
system by which the camshaft
opens and closes the valves.
first, rocker stands.
then push rods.
these insert into lifters which
connect to the camshaft.
and finally rocker arms.
one end of each arm goes on the
push rod.
the other sits on the valve.
when the camshaft turns, the
system opens and closes the
valves.
technicians close up the
cylinder head with a valve
cover.
next, they install the engine
cooling system, starting with a
water manifold.
after mounting a cover to
protect the cam belt from rocks
and other debris, they install
the water pump.
it circulates cold water through
the engine to prevent
overheating.
having absorbed the heat, the
water exits the engine via the
manifold, then travels to the
radiator which cools it back
down.
then the pump, driven by this
pulley, sends the water back
into the engine to repeat the
cycle.
next, technicians mount the
alternator.
it generates electricity to run
the engine and other components,
such as the air-conditioning,
the dashboard gauges, and fans
which cool the brakes, tires,
and rear end.
this belt drives both the
alternator and water pump
pulley.
next, technicians install the
oil pump.
it sucks hot oil out of the
engine, sends it to the oil
radiator for cooling, then pumps
it back into the engine.
now the distributor.
it sends electricity from the
alternator-charged car battery
to the spark plugs.
the spark plugs fire, igniting
the fuel and air mixture in each
cylinder, producing a mini
explosion that drives the
piston.
this component, the intake
manifold, feeds the air and fuel
mixture to the cylinder intake
valves.
the carburetor regulates the
mixture ratio by metering the
right amount of fuel to the
amount of air coming in.
technicians install the numerous
parts that make up the clutch.
next, the starter ring, which
engages with the starter to fire
up the engine.
finally, they mount the bell
housing, a cover that protects
the clutch from debris and
connects the engine to the
transmission.
the factory hooks up every
engine it produces to a testing
machine.
the machine starts up and runs
the motor, analyzing some 300
performance criteria, from
revolutions per minute to fuel
flow.
at the same time, three
remote-controlled cameras
shooting from different angles
enable technicians to zoom in
and view on a monitor anything
they need to visually inspect.
all this to ensure the engine
they've built will have a
winning track record.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...