--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
many banks and businesses
have time-delay locks
on their safes
to keep their valuables
and documents secure.
this helps deter theft
because robbers
may not want to wait around
for the safe to open.
if they do, the time delay
may keep them around long
enough
for police to make an arrest.
this lock lets you select
delays
ranging from 1 to 30 minutes.
the timer starts
after you insert the key.
most of the lock's components
are made of zinc.
this semi-automated
casting machine
heats zinc bars
to about 800 degrees.
the molten metal is then fed
into an injection system,
which shoots the zinc
into a part-shaped mold.
the machine automatically
refills the zinc bars
as the metal is used.
as soon as the machine injects
molten zinc into the mold,
surrounding tubes
spray cold water
to quickly cool
and solidify the metal.
then the mold opens
and ejects the part.
the parts have rough edges,
so they go into a vibrating
tub.
inside, they run against
ceramic
stones and an abrasive
compound
to smooth the edges
and polish the surface.
the parts are cleaned
and painted on one side.
then they go into an oven
to bake on the paint.
the lock's main cam
sets the time delay
and the open window --
the amount of time before
the safe automatically
relocks.
here, they're drilling holes
for screws,
which will regulate the
lengths
of the time delay
and the open window.
once the lock's components
are prepared, assembly begins.
workers insert the lock
cylinder
into its shell
and remove the key.
then they screw
on a steel cylinder cam.
when you turn the key
in the cylinder,
a cam winds
and starts the timer.
after the set time delay,
the cam pulls a lever
that releases the lock's
latch.
to build the lock's
timing assembly,
they first attach a spring
to the timer plate.
they hold the spring in place
with a plastic retainer.
then they install
a brass timer cam.
the spring holds it
in the locked position.
a pin on the cylinder cam's
lever sits on the timer cam.
when the time delay is over,
the
pin releases the timer spring,
and the timer cam
moves to the unlocked
position.
this allows the cylinder cam
to retract the latch
and open the lock.
they screw the plate
with the spring and timer cam
to the timer,
which is gear-driven
like a mechanical clock.
they let the timer
run down all the way.
then they turn the spring
four times.
they mount the main cam,
which sets the time delay
and open window
on top of the timer cam.
now they begin calibrating
the timer.
first they install
an aluminum weight assembly
that controls the timer speed.
they run the timer
on a testing machine,
comparing it to the delay
set on the main cam.
if the timer runs too fast,
they take some tension
off the timer spring.
if the timer runs too slowly,
they trim down
the weight assembly
until they get the right
speed.
once the timer is accurate,
they
screw it into the timer cover.
the lock body contains the
lever
that retracts the lock's
latch.
it also has
a brass electrical plug
to connect
a time-delay indicator light.
after securing the latch
and lever in position
with a cover plate,
they install the timer
assembly.
the visible side
is painted black,
just like the visible side
of the cover plate.
then they insert
the cylinder assembly.
they mount the lock
on the door of the safe
and hook up
the indicator lights,
which run
on double-"a" batteries.
to open the safe, you insert,
turn, then remove the key.
the red light indicates
the timer is counting down.
when the time delay is over,
the green light comes on.
then you reinsert the key,
and the safe opens.
narrator: chocolate brownies
are irresistible.
their origins are uncertain,
but they were
definitely developed
in the united states
over a century ago.
one story is that a homemaker
from bangor, maine,
made the first brownies
accidentally
while trying to make a cake.
another story states that
they were deliberately
invented
by the chef at a chicago
hotel.
neither cake nor cookie, a
brownie is something in
between,
a moist, dense,
and chewy square.
there's no doubt it brings
something special to the
table.
to mass-produce brownies, this
factory starts with canola
oil.
they add xanthan gum,
a natural preservative
that increases moisture
retention during baking.
they blend these two
ingredients
in an industrial mixer.
then they add sugar, cocoa,
and canola
and palm oil shortening.
they reactivate the mixer,
and it blends the ingredients
into a chocolate batter.
the next ingredients
are whole eggs...
...and corn syrup.
the massive mixing arm
descends back into the bowl
and whips these ingredients
into the batter.
a worker wheels the bowl
to a hopper,
which releases
a precise amount of flour.
the flour thickens the mix.
it will give
the baked brownies structure.
after 25 minutes of mixing,
the batter is complete.
there's enough batter here
to make 6,000 brownies.
they transfer
the smooth chocolaty mixture
to a machine called a
depositor.
a sprayer mists the pans
with oil
to keep the brownies from
sticking to them during
baking.
then the pans
arrive at the depositor.
this computerized machine
releases the batter
into each pan.
it has perfect aim every time.
next, the pans
enter an 11-1/2-foot oven.
the brownies rotate through
13 tiers to bake them evenly.
after about 20 minutes,
the brownies are cooked.
they exit the oven
and head into a cooling
chamber.
like the oven,
it's multi-tiered.
the pans move through it
as fans cool the brownies.
the cooling
helps solidify the brownies.
then a robot arm
with needle-like claws
lifts them out of the pans
and transfers them
to the next conveyer.
the robots are gentle,
so the cool brownies
stay intact during the
process.
the brownies round a corner
and
transfer to another conveyer.
at the end of the line,
a worker places the brownies
in a narrow conveyer system
that takes them
to the wrapping station.
a computer sensor
detects their approach
and alerts the plastic
wrapping system ahead.
the plastic unwinds
into the wrapping machine
as the brownies enter it.
metal wheels with grooves pull
the wrapper under the
brownies,
and then heated wheels
melt the seam to close it.
a hot jaw then seals and
severs
the plastic film
between the brownies,
creating individual packets.
a robot opens a box
and sets it on a conveyer
next to the brownie line.
an employee then places
eight packets of brownies
in each carton.
they ride by a rotary device,
which automatically folds
the ends of the cartons.
then the boxes are glued shut.
finally, they travel
through a metal detector.
it uses a high-frequency
electromagnetic signal
to detect any metal fragments
in the brownies.
it takes about an hour
to make and package brownies
at this factory,
but only a fraction of that
time
to enjoy them.
narrator: pallets are used
to easily move
large quantities of goods.
they were invented
in the early 20th century
and have been a warehouse
staple
ever since.
multiple unused pallets
can cause clutter
and even be a safety hazard.
that's where pallet dispensers
come in.
before pallet dispensers,
pallets were kept
in loose stacks.
retrieving one
was potentially dangerous.
the pallet dispenser
solves this problem.
it helps keep the workplace
safe and organized.
a high-speed cnc machine
cuts out the steel parts
of the pallet dispenser.
an employee uses a press brake
to bend the components
to the required shapes.
a preset backstop
ensures that the metal piece
goes into the precise depth.
next, a worker uses a mig
welder
to quickly bond
the new parts together.
the parts hang from chains,
which are charged
with a negative current.
painters then spray positively
charged paint on them.
the parts are baked in an oven
for 20 minutes to dry the
paint.
the traveler frame
moves up and down
with the pallets
inside the dispenser.
a worker
installs 12 cam followers.
a team positions
the linear track assembly.
its vertical bars
guide the cam followers,
keeping the traveler frame
on track.
once this sub-assembly
is complete,
workers install it
inside the main side frames.
together, these components
form the main base assembly.
the dispenser's
self-contained hydraulic
system
doesn't require power
to control the traveler frame.
this is one
of two hydraulic cylinders.
they're designed to easily
hold
a heavy stack of pallets.
the worker
installs four brake arms.
they hold a set of
spring-loaded latches in place
to keep the pallets
suspended in position.
next, he positions
the sprockets.
the pallet dispenser
requires four sprockets
to support two chains.
these chains
connect the traveler frame
to a massive
steel counterweight.
as it gets fuller, the
traveler
frame lowers to the ground.
after the pallets
touch the floor,
the counterweight
lifts the frame.
the pallets are stored in a
tall
column called a pallet
magazine.
two employees work together
to install it.
the magazines
come in two standard heights
--
4 feet and 8 feet.
not all pallet magazines
are red.
customers can select
from a wide variety of colors.
the interior panels
protect the dispenser's
mechanism from being damaged.
they're also the access panels
to the product's
precision engineering.
a trained professional
should always handle
the machine's maintenance
and repair.
making the panels
relatively inaccessible
decreases the chances of
tampering, injury, or
accidents
by an amateur.
next, a worker
runs a quality-control test.
he uses a walkie rider
to raise a stack of pallets
and remove the bottom one.
when he's done,
the hydraulic system
lowers the stack
back into position.
here, one worker uses a
forklift
to raise the top section of
the
pallet magazine into position
while the other worker
guides the magazine into
place.
graphics and decals
have already been added,
so all that's left
is for the worker
to securely bolt
the two sections together.
with about 2 billion pallets
in the u.s. alone,
things can really start
to pile up.
pallet stackers make life
easier
for manufacturers and shippers
all over the world.
some refer to these devices
as giant pez dispensers.
in a way,
that's exactly what they are,
and they're just as safe.
narrator: once reserved
for palaces and castles,
today's chandeliers can be
found
in even the most modest homes.
they function as more
than just a light source.
chandeliers can be
the illuminating centerpieces
of traditional rooms or give
modern rooms an eclectic
twists.
either way, a crystal
chandelier
is always elegant and
timeless.
this chandelier
is quite a showstopper.
it stretches
more than 3 feet high and wide
with 24 elegant arms.
it's decorated
with clear and red crystal
and a gilded hurricane shade
over each light.
to make the crystal, they melt
silica sand in a furnace,
along with lead, hot ash,
and several other ingredients.
the materials combine
to make crystal heavier
and more sparkling than glass.
to make each chandelier arm,
a crystal blower
gathers some molten crystal
on the end of his blowpipe,
then shapes the arm with
a series of blocks and molds.
he makes a channel
down the middle
for the arm's electrical
wiring.
next, two master crystal
blowers
work together
to pull and twist the crystal
into the arm's rope-like
design.
this maneuver
requires tremendous expertise.
to achieve the correct
diameter,
these craftsmen must stretch
the crystal exactly right.
next, they put it
in a chandelier arm mold
and snip off the excess
on both ends.
they blow cold air
to solidify the crystal.
another craftsman
inspects the chandelier arm,
checking the shape,
measurements,
and channel
for the electrical wiring.
next, a pair of craftsmen
make the bowl-shaped bottom
of the chandelier.
using traditional techniques,
they place molten crystal
in a mold,
then place the mold in a
press.
the crystal chandelier parts
are cooled down in an oven.
the gradual decrease
in temperature
slowly releases tension
in the crystal.
this prevents cracking.
straight out of the furnace,
the crystal is 2,280 degrees.
it continues to be pliable
until
it reaches about 1,202
degrees.
it cools rapidly,
so as the craftsmen work,
they must regularly reheat the
crystal in a smaller furnace.
the freshly molded crystal
tends to have a rough surface,
so they use heat from
a blowtorch to smooth it out.
these holders support the
hurricane shades on the arms.
this company produces its
signature shade of red crystal
by adding 24-karat gold powder
to the raw materials
in the furnace.
the color emerges
after the molded piece
is reheated in an oven
to just over 1,000 degrees.
a crystal blower
makes the hurricane shades.
first, he rolls a starting
shape
at the end of his blowpipe.
then, with pliers,
he narrows and stretches one
end
to form a neck.
by now, the crystal has
cooled,
so he reheats it
before continuing.
next, he inserts the crystal
into a foot-pedal-operated
mold
installed in the floor.
he then turns the pipe
and blows through it
to expand the crystal
to the mold shape.
once the hurricane shade
has cooled,
artisans apply an elaborate
24-karat gold decal.
with a paintbrush, they
also apply raised gilding
and 24-karat gold paste.
they heat the shade
to fuse the gold to the
crystal,
then polish the gold
with an agate stone.
every part of the crystal
chandelier is handmade,
and the entire chandelier
is manually assembled.
however,
some of the crystal parts
require prep work
before assembly.
the arms have a light socket
at one end
wired to a connector
at the other.
all 24 arms
mount to a round tray.
beneath it, the connectors
link to the main wires
running down the center
of the chandelier.
the chandelier's ornate bottom
hides it all.
the electrical sockets
that hold the light bulbs
are hidden inside metal
sleeves
painted white
to look like candles.
the gilded hurricane shades
go over the candles
and sit snugly in the holders.
this stunning crystal
chandelier
casts sparkling light,
easily making it
the focal point of the room.
weighing in at over 150
pounds,
this grand chandelier makes
a big, bold design statement.