--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: a channel sign is
made
of individual letters
that are fixed
to a building or backdrop.
the letters have internal
channels that house either
neon
or led lights.
at night, the channel letters
light up
and make a bold statement.
channel letters
are three-dimensional
and really stand out
from the rest.
the illuminated signs
grab people's attention
and convert them
into potential customers.
channel letters
are made from acrylic.
the factory uses colored vinyl
to tint them.
an employee peels the liner
from the vinyl,
exposing the adhesive backing.
he uses a roller
to apply the vinyl to one side
of the clear acrylic.
the other side
of the acrylic sheet
is covered with a paper liner.
a computerized router cuts
the letters out on that side.
the font style and size
are custom-made for the
client.
after the letters are cut out,
they remove the paper backing.
the employees use nails
to hold the letters in place
as they work.
the worker
unrolls plastic trim cap
and cuts it
to fit around the letter.
he lines the letter with trim
and hammers in more nails,
to keep everything in place.
he makes cuts to the trim
to form neat corners.
the trim cap gives the letter
a finished look.
it also creates a surface
for attaching
the back letter enclosure,
called the letter can.
he seals the trim
around the entire length
with high-strength glue.
once it dries,
he removes the nails.
now, it's ready
for the letter can.
to make the sides
of the letter can,
they feed a wide strip
of aluminum
into a computerized machine.
it bends the aluminum
to match the face of the
letter.
it also forms a lip
at the bottom,
to attach the can
to the back wall.
the side of each channel
letter
is called the return.
it attaches the letter face
to the back wall.
the return also
creates the channel
which holds the lighting
and directs the illumination.
these are the dies
that cut and shape the
aluminum.
using a computerized machine,
it takes the worker
a few minutes to create
the channel letter return.
it would take four times
longer
to make the letter return
by hand.
here is a completed
channel letter return
with the ends welded together.
an employee slides the side
structure over the back wall
to form the letter can.
he checks the fit, then
clinches the back to the
return.
this completes
the channel letter can.
they run led lights
throughout the can.
in recent years, led lights
have replaced neon tubes
because they are more
energy-efficient.
an employee paints the
aluminum
can to match the vinyl
on the letter's acrylic front.
they test the lights.
if they work, the technicians
mount the letter can
to the sign backdrop.
the installer attaches
the translucent acrylic face
to the can.
it takes about an hour
to make one channel letter
and a couple of days
to make an entire channel
sign.
the final product
is sure to be noticed.
the wetsuit was invented
in the mid-20th century.
however,
it wasn't an immediate hit.
made of a synthetic rubber
called neoprene,
the early wetsuits
were hard to put on
and irritated the skin.
but recent neoprene
improvements
have made the wetsuit
a popular choice for
protection
against the elements.
when the surf is up, but
the water temperature is down,
a neoprene wetsuit
is a practical swimwear
choice.
even when wet,
it keeps the body warm.
wetsuits fit like a second
skin,
so many surfers and divers
have theirs custom-made.
the tailor measures the client
from the neck to the ankles.
the suit allows
a small amount of water
to seep between it and the
skin.
body heat warms the water,
insulating the swimmer.
using the measurements, a team
cuts out cardboard patterns.
then, a worker uses the
patters
to cut the neoprene pieces.
they use neoprene
because its cellular structure
is a good insulator.
the number of pieces
in each suit varies,
according to the style
and size.
each suit has at least 15
pieces
and can have as much as 30.
fabric for the wetsuits comes
in a variety of colors.
some fabric will be used
for accent panels,
while others
create the structural
elements.
the pieces fit together
like a jigsaw puzzle.
a worker heats one of the
panels
with a hot press.
this slightly expands
the neoprene.
he places a decal of the
company
logo on the panel.
he lowers the press again
to fuse the logo to the panel.
as the neoprene cools,
it shrinks to its original
size,
making the lettering
less likely to crack.
next, a worker applies
waterproof rubberized glue
to the edges
of the neoprene panels.
this is one of the most
important parts
of the wetsuit's construction.
too little glue could affect
both the adhesion of the
panels
and the waterproofing
of the seams.
but if he applies too much
glue,
it could bleed
into the colored panels.
he pushes the glued panels
together at the seams.
the panels adhere instantly,
and the wetsuit
comes together quickly.
it takes him about 45 minutes
to put a wetsuit together.
he inserts paper in the bottom
half of the wetsuit.
this prevents the front
of the suit
from sticking to the back
as he joins the top assembly
to the bottom.
he lets the glue dry
for a few minutes.
then, a seamstress
turns the suit inside out
and stitches the seams.
she uses a curved needle,
so it doesn't go all the way
through the fabric.
this is called blind
stitching.
it doesn't puncture the
fabric.
it also creates flat seams.
using a hot roller,
she applies nylon tape
to the back of the seams
for extra waterproofing.
a nozzle blows hot air to melt
the adhesive onto the fabric.
she sews a plastic zipper
onto the back of the wetsuit
and attaches a hook-and-loop
stopper, to prevent unzipping.
another team member brushes
rubberized glue
around the zipper.
he presses the edges
of a neoprene panel
to the glued area,
creating a waterproof barrier
around the zipper.
he trims the end of the panel.
this custom neoprene wetsuit
is complete.
from start to finish,
the process takes 5 to 6
hours.
he tests the zipper and
closely
scrutinizes the workmanship.
after passing
an initial inspection,
this wetsuit
is ready for a fitting.
a good fit is crucial
to its performance.
if the wetsuit
doesn't fit properly,
cold water will pass through
it
and the suit will fail
to keep the surfer warm.
it meets expectations,
so she's ready to test the
water
with this custom
neoprene wetsuit.
airplanes need to be durable,
to withstand the wear and tear
of frequent flying
and the dangers of landing
on rugged airstrips.
most small airplanes
are made with aluminum
because it's both sturdy
and lightweight.
some aluminum aircraft
are twin engines,
meaning they have a propeller
on each wing.
single-engine models,
like this one,
have one propeller,
typically on the nose.
this airplane
also has a pressurized cabin,
so it can reach an altitude
of about 30,000 feet.
it also has a deicing system
for the wings, tail,
and propeller blades,
so it can fly safely
in cold, wet conditions.
the aluminum is delivered
to the factory in long rolls.
they unwind each roll
and feed the aluminum
through a series of heavy
rollers, to press out the
curl.
a blade at the end
of the machine
automatically slices the flat
aluminum into smaller pieces.
the thickness
of the aluminum varies,
depending on the part
they're making.
they use a 3-millimeter
sheet of aluminum
to make the cockpit
instrument panel.
a computer-guided mill
cuts the profile,
drills screw holes
for installation,
and cuts all the openings
for the instrumentation.
the sheet goes from this
to this.
a computer-guided router cuts
out most of the wing
components.
workers feed it
between machine rollers
that slowly bend it
to a specific angle.
once the bend is complete,
they use templates
to check both sides
and make sure
it meets specifications.
during production, residue
from the factory machines
contaminate the aluminum
pieces,
so, once all the parts
are created,
they are thoroughly cleaned.
the machine washes them
in soapy water twice
and then rinses them off.
once the parts are clean,
the machine submerges them
in an acid bath.
this preps the surface
for a coat of protective
primer.
once it's primed, workers
clean the surface with
solvent.
then, they lay the part
on a sheet of epoxy adhesive
and cut along the perimeter,
to create an adhesive backing.
later, they'll activate the
adhesive with heat and
pressure.
once all the parts
have their custom-cut
adhesive,
workers assemble them
on a bonding fixture.
metal clamps hold the parts
in position.
this assembly is
the internal structure
of the wing's leading edge.
the long pieces
are called stringers.
they're clamped
to oval access panels
that enable maintenance
technicians
to get inside the wing.
next, workers position
and clamp the skin
of the leading edge on top
of the internal wing
structure.
they heat the entire assembly
in an oven
for 2 hours
at 275 fahrenheit.
this activates the adhesive
and bonds all the assembled
parts together.
meanwhile, another team
assembles the aluminum frame
of the airplane's
fuselage section.
they load the parts
onto an assembly fixture
and rivet them together.
when we return,
they'll apply an aluminum
cover to the frame.
the aluminum skin of an
airplane
consists of numerous panels,
so the body is easier to
repair.
technicians simply remove
the damaged panel,
instead of replacing
the entire section.
workers start by applying
an airtight sealant
to close any gaps
between the skin and the
frame.
the fuselage must be sealed,
so the cabin can be
pressurized.
a pressurized cabin
allows passengers to breathe
comfortably at higher
altitudes.
once the sealing is complete,
they attach the corresponding
aluminum skin panel.
it has already been
primed for paint.
they apply cleko fasteners,
to properly align the panel
until it's riveted to the
frame.
then, they select the rivets.
they'll need rivets
of various sizes and strengths
for the different parts
of the plane.
they begin riveting the holes
that don't have
cleko fasteners in them.
then, they remove the clekos
and rivet those holes as well.
the fuselage is built
in six sections.
the front section houses
the engine compartment.
all the sections
have attachment panels
that fit in between the frame
and skin of the adjacent part.
workers rivet
the sections together.
once the back sections
are installed,
they rivet the completed
fuselage to the main spar
that connects the wings.
they install the retractable
landing gear,
the tail-section rudder,
and stabilizers.
they also install the moving
flaps and ailerons.
workers weld together
steel tubes
to create the engine mount.
the mount will be installed
in the engine compartment
in the front of the fuselage.
this section also houses
the nose landing gear.
they prime and paint
the steel engine mount,
to prevent corrosion.
this plane has a
500-horsepower
turbine engine.
workers bolt it
to the engine mount.
then, they bolt the engine
mount
to the airplane's
engine compartment.
the engine rotates a shaft
which spins the propeller.
meanwhile, all the airplane's
electrical wiring
is mapped out
on an assembly board.
each wire has a number.
the wires are arranged
in a specific configuration.
then, workers group the wires
by
their location in the airplane
and tie them
in a wiring harness.
these wires are for the back
of the instrument panel.
the circuit breakers
are located
on either side
of the flight display panel.
with the push of a button,
the pilot can customize
the information displayed
on the center screen.
technicians thoroughly test
all the electronic functions,
as well as
the autopilot system.
one pilot
can operate this plane,
but it comes with an extra
yoke,
to accommodate a copilot.
workers install the interior
and the windows.
then, mechanics verify
the flight control surfaces,
the moving parts
on the wings and tail
that change altitude
or direction.
here, they're checking
the ailerons.
a mechanic in the cockpit
turns the yoke
while another uses
a rigging board
to measure
how the aileron responds.
if the angle's off,
he makes an adjustment.
they check the landing gear,
to make sure it drops down
from the wing
and engine compartment.
then, they mask the windows
and
apply a second coat of primer,
for extra protection
against corrosion.
when the primer dries,
they paint the plane
to the customer's
specifications.
then, they paint the plane's
registration number
on both sides,
as required by law.
the airplane's deicing system
heats the propeller blades
to melt ice buildup.
it also uses inflatable
rubber bladders
attached to the wing
and tail.
the pilot throws a switch
to inflate the bladders
and break any ice,
ensuring a smooth, safe ride,
even in poor weather
conditions.