--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: mines and quarries
use crushers
to break down raw material.
those raw materials go through
a vibrating screen to separate
the particles by size.
the vibrations cause the
smaller
pieces to fall through
the screen while the larger
pieces remain on top.
this limestone quarry uses
a vibrating screen
with three decks.
the top deck filters out the
largest stones,
which will be
used to make concrete.
the second deck collects
half-inch rocks.
they'll be used to make
asphalt.
the final deck
gathers the smallest materials
to product limestone sand.
the screen mesh
is made from steel wire.
this steel contains carbon,
making it more durable
than regular steel.
a pair of wheel dyes
crimp it into a wave pattern.
the diameter of the wire
and crimp pattern
determine the shape and size
of the screen mesh openings.
workers can change the dyes
to crimp different patterns.
the machine cuts the crimped
wire to a specific length.
then, workers take the pieces
over to a loom.
it weaves screens the same way
a textile loom weaves cloth.
they lay the crimped wires
vertically,
playing one in between each
of the loom's heddles.
they line up the crimped wire
so that the bottom of one
crimp
faces the top of the next.
then they weave a straight
wire
horizontally across
the vertically crimped wires.
they continue to feed
straight wires across.
then use the loom
to secure each one in
position.
the vertical
and horizontal wires interlock
to form the mesh.
once they've woven a section
to the required length,
a sheer cuts it off the loom.
another sheet cuts the section
to the customer's
requested dimensions.
this is the final size
of the screen mesh section.
next, workers insert one set
of the screen
into an electromagnetic
induction heater.
the device evenly generates
heat
inside the steel.
this is critical because
heating
unevenly can weaken the steel.
they inset the heated edge
in a steel strip
mounted in a press.
the press clamps the strip
over the edge then
vents it into a hook strip.
they repeat the process
on the opposite site side.
the two hook strips
attach the mesh section
to the vibrating screen.
the loom can weave many
different types of screen
mesh.
this one is made of finer wire
that's crimped
in a different pattern.
the openings of the screen
mesh
are larger and more
rectangular.
it's designed for a less
precise
sorting process.
for both screens,
the weaving and cutting
processes are the same.
they even use the same
technique
to attach the hook strips.
the only thing that changes
is the crimping pattern.
next, they connect the hook
strips to the vibrating
screen.
installers lay the sections
end-to-end
on each of the machine's
decks.
then they fashion
the hook strips to the machine
with tension rails
and secure those rails
with large bolts.
when the mine or quarry needs
to
change the screening
parameters,
they simply replace these
screens with different ones.
narrator: whoopie pies are not
pies at all.
this all-american treat is
made
of vanilla cream frosting
sandwiched between two pieces
of round chocolate cake.
the whoopie pie
was invented in new england.
and today, it is the official
state treat of maine.
this company adds a modern
twist
to the classic
whoopie pie recipe.
in addition to traditional
chocolate and vanilla,
the company makes four other
all-natural flavors.
the ingredients
are certified vegan,
non-gmo, gluten-free, kosher
and free
of many common food allergens.
workers begin by making
the chocolate cakes.
the first ingredient is water
followed by apple cider
vinegar.
then, they add either canola
or sunflower oil.
they mix the liquid
ingredients
in a large bowl.
then they add the dry
ingredients,
starting with tapioca starch,
bean flour, and sorghum,
a gluten-free grain.
next, they mix in cocoa
powder,
granulated cane sugar,
and light brown sugar.
they run the mixer
at a very high speed
to incorporate air
in the batter.
this will make the cake
lighter
and fluffier.
after about 4 minutes of
mixing,
the batter is ready.
they test a sample
using a viscometer,
a device
that measures the thickness.
if the batter
is the right consistency,
they pump it through a hopper
into a multi-head depositer.
each of its five nozzles
shoot one ounce of batter
onto a moving baking sheet.
a finished sheet
contains seven rows of batter.
workers load multiple sheets
of batter into an oven.
the sheets rotate for 15
minutes
at 75 degree fahrenheit,
evenly baking the cakes.
the precise combination
of ingredients allows the
acids
in the apple cider vinegar
to react with the cocoa
powder.
the result is a perfect
little chocolate cake
that's rich in flavor
and moist in texture.
the main ingredient
for the filling is shortening.
it's made
from sustainable palm oil.
this means the palm tress
were responsibly harvested.
they mix the shortening well,
incorporating enough air
to make it light and fluffy.
then they add
powdered cane sugar
and organic rice milk
as a dairy-free substitute.
the rice milk
makes the frosting creamy.
for vanilla frosting, they
simply add pure vanilla
extract.
this is a batch
of raspberry frosting,
so they add
pure raspberry extract
and beet juice
for color.
when they make mint frosting,
they use pure mint extract
and alfalfa extract
for green color.
lemon frosting is made
from pure lemon extract
and turmeric for color.
they check the shade
against a color chart
to ensure the correct flavor.
the multi-head depositer drops
frosting on the baking sheets
in the same configuration
as the batter.
then they assemble
the final pie.
workers start by placing a
piece
of cake on top of the
frosting.
they press down hard enough
to spread the frosting
just shy of the cake's edge.
they cover the top
with a sheet of parchment
paper
then place a baking sheet on
top
and flip it over.
they remove the top baking
sheet
and the parchment paper.
then, they carefully place the
second cake onto the frosting.
workers roll the trays
of whoopie pies into a cooler
where the desserts chill
for about 15 minutes.
this hardens them so they
won't
get squished during packaging.
workers place the whoopie pies
on a conveyer belt
that leads to an automated
wrapping machine.
it wraps double-printed
packaging around each pie
and seals them underneath.
then the machine cuts the film
between each pie.
the next machine packages
four sealed whoopie pies
per retail box.
there are zero preservatives
in these whoopie pies.
they're shipped frozen
to the grocery store
and sold in the freezer
section.
when it's time for a treat,
simply let them thaw
to room temperature and enjoy.
narrator: wooden utility poles
are a constant presence
in our lives.
they were originally built
in the mid-19th century
to suspend telegraph lines.
now, they hold up power
and phone lines
as well as fiber-optic
and coaxial cables
for television
and computer networking.
builders use many different
types of pine or fir trees
to make utility poles.
in the us, southern yellow
pine
is the most popular choice.
foresters select trees that
are
10 to 20 inches in diameter
and at least 30 feet high.
they look for a straight,
healthy trunk with few limbs.
the foresters mark the
selected
tress with spray paint.
then, the tree harvester
saws them down at the base.
after the loggers saw off
the limbs and cut the trees
to a specified length,
a log truck
delivers the poles to the
mill.
there, a truck scale
weighs the load.
then, workers ticket it
with a tracking number.
the truck enters the yard
and the poles
are unloaded into piles.
a loader feeds the poles
to a debarking machine.
the machine's razor-sharp
cutters shave of the bark
and the layer of tissue
beneath
the bark called the cambium.
next, a saw trims one inch
off the bottom of the log
to make it square.
at the same time,
nozzles spray lines
of red food coloring
at set intervals along the
pole.
these mark
indicate different lengths.
another worker
inspects the quality
and measures the
circumference.
this assessment
determines the wood's class.
he marks the length and class
on the bottom of the pole.
the bark and shavings
removed from the poles
don't go to waste --
a grinding mill
reduces them to small fibers.
the factory uses those fibers
to power the boiler.
the fire
in the boiler will product
heat,
which dries the poles.
after the poles have been
sorted
by length and class,
loaders
stack them on large trams.
they place spacer sticks
in between each pole to allow
air to flow around them.
then, the loaders push the
trams
into a large kiln.
the steam from the boiler
flows through the trams,
heating the inside of the kiln
to 200 degree fahrenheit.
large fans blow the hot air
around the poles for 3 days
until the wood is dry.
when the poles
come out of the kiln,
workers brand them
with product information.
next, they cut a flat surface
on one side of the pole.
then, they drill holes
to attach a crossarm.
after they drill the holes,
they stack the poles
in another tram.
this one takes them to
a 125-foot-long
treatment cylinder.
they lock the door
and vacuum all the air
out of the cylinder.
they fill the cylinder
with a liquid that's 98% water
and 2% chemical preservative.
the preservative is a mixture
of chrome, copper and arsenic.
once the cylinder is full,
the pumps start running
to pressurize the liquid,
infusing the wood
with the chemical solution.
the 2-hour process
leaves the wood resistant
to rot, fungus and termites.
next, inspectors
bore 3-inch holes into each
pole
to collect a sample.
the inspectors check to make
sure the preservative
saturated the wood
to the target depth.
then, they send the samples
to the on-site laboratory,
where they're dried in
a microwave oven and ground
up.
they also put the sample
in an x-ray machine
to analyze the chrome, copper
and arsenic levels.
these quality control steps
ensure that every utility pole
contains the right amount
of chemical preservatives.
these finished poles will
assist
for at least 45 to 60 years.
narrator: humans have been
using roller conveyors
for thousands of years.
the ancient egyptians
used wood rollers
to move the large stones
needed to build the pyramids.
today's conveyors
are more complex.
but the basic concept
is still the same.
many factories use roller
conveyors to transfer
materials
from one station
to another during assembly.
they can move heavy loads
up to 65 feet in a minute.
to make the conveyer rollers,
this factory
starts with hollow steel
tubes.
they deliver to the factory
in batches.
after they arrive, a band saw
cuts the tubes to length.
the diameter can vary from
batch
to batch.
so an employee
obtains the exact
measurements.
he inputs the measurements
into a computer
that controls this laser.
the laser etches the company
logo onto a sheet of thick
steel
and cuts out support disks
for the roller axles.
the support disks fit
perfectly
into the hollow rollers.
an employee feeds a flat sheet
of steel
to a computerized break press.
it bends the sheet
into a vertical rail
for the conveyer frame.
here's the steel
before and after bending.
a worker joins two
vertical rails
with steel supports
called crossmembers.
he welds them where they meet.
this creates the frame
for the roller conveyer.
then, they paint the frame.
the paint isn't just
for decoration.
it also protects against rust.
next, they install
the chain-driven axle
that will spin the roller.
an employee measures it
and confirms its dimensions.
another worker slides three
support disks on to the axle.
he welds the disks in place.
the disks on the end
fit snugly to the roller rims.
this is why premeasuring
is so important.
he welds the disks
to the ends of the tubes.
he slides roller chain
sprockets
onto the end of the axle
and welds them in place.
he uses a dial indicator
to measure the circumference
of the roller
and confirm
that it's sufficiently round.
using a forklift, the team
lifts the motor and places it
in the conveyer frame.
they slide the motor's
threaded rods
into holes drilled in the
frame.
an employee places metal
washers
on the threaded rods.
then he screws nuts to them,
securing the motor to the
frame.
he installs a bearing
on the end of the roller axle.
next, workers arrange the
rollers on the conveyer frame.
they place the bearings
on the flange
of one of the vertical rails.
they attach the bearings
to the rail with socket
screws.
one of the workers
attaches the welded steel
chain
to the teeth of sprocket
wheels.
he joins the sections
of the roller chain with
links.
then he drops the ends
of the chains down to the
motor.
the worker loops the chains
around the motor sprockets...
and connects the ends
with the joiner plate
and retaining clip.
now, they're ready
to put this roller conveyer
to the test.
an employee measures the
rotational speed of the
rollers
with an instrument
called a tachometer.
he also tests the conveyor's
ability to move heavy objects.
once approved,
the roller conveyer will be
shipped to another factory,
where it will be
an important part
of the manufacturing process.