--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: champagne toasts are common at weddings,
birthdays, and many other special occasions,
but if the cork isn't secured properly,
it can pop off at the wrong moment.
so champagne manufacturers
have developed hoods and foils
to keep the bottles
closed until the right moment.
the foil covering
that protects the cork is part
of the iconic champagne look.
unwrapping it is like opening a special present.
underneath the foil is a wire hood and disk
that keeps everything in place.
the flat disks
begin as thin sheets of steel.
a suctioning device transfers the sheets
to a printing machine.
the machine slices the sheets into strips.
then, the suctioning device moves the strips
to the next step in the production line.
it positions the strips on a machine
that quickly punches out the round disk components.
the wire hoods are made out of galvanized steel.
a series of large bobbins feed the steel
into a multiphase machine.
the wire is coated with colored lacquer
for increased protection and aesthetic appeal.
on a rotating carousel,
the machine twists two horizontal strands of wire.
it leaves enough room for a vertical loop
between each set of twists.
next, the device twists the vertical loop.
a blade cuts the wire in between each newly formed cross.
then, a mechanism removes the crosses
and transfers them to the next stage of production.
a machine shapes the bottom
of the crosses in three steps.
first, it pinches the wire
together at the four extremities.
then, it forms a bend.
and finally, it folds them over to create a hook.
a device folds the feet up
and hooks them onto a wire circle called a belt.
the wire structures
are ready for the disk insert.
a press forces the disks into a die
to create rounded caps.
finally, the machine inserts the newly formed caps
into the wire structure.
the champagne wire hoods
are now complete and ready for their bottles.
it takes 15 steps to build a wire hood.
incredibly,
the machine can build each hood in under 2 seconds.
the wire hood holds the cork in place,
but the polylaminate foil wrapper
protects it from the elements.
this specially made foil is composed of polythene film
sandwiched between two sheets of aluminum.
a high-speed cutter trims the edges.
then, the polylaminate rolls through a bath of varnish.
the polythene film is made out of granules.
they dye the polylaminate gold
using
a high-speed printing process.
the polylaminate foil is coated with specially formulated ink
that dries instantly under ultraviolet light.
the foil transfers to a perforation machine.
this allows customers to easily unwrap the champagne bottle.
a hot stamping machine
adds decorative elements and the brand name to the foil.
another device adds a strip of glue to one edge.
a machine cuts the foil,
then a device equipped with cylindrical rods,
called mandrels, wraps the foil into cones.
the glue strip holds the cone together.
a machine places a disk on top of the cones.
they crimp the ends to increase the cone's rigidity.
then, a vacuum sucks the completed cones
off the mandrels.
no bottle of bubbly is complete without a hood and foil.
this factory quickly pr
or color the winery requests.
the factory's speed and versatility allows them
to produce wire hoods and foils
for 50% of the sparkling wines
made in france.
narrator: pneumatic tubes
were originally used to transfer
money and sensitive documents.
today, these systems have a different purpose.
hospitals use them to quickly transport blood samples
to their labs.
for patients who need a quick diagnosis,
these pipelines are a lifeline.
many hospitals have a series
of pneumatic pipes running behind their walls.
health care workers seal medical samples in capsules
and put them in the system.
these pipelines can be several miles long.
a computer allows users to monitor the capsule's movement.
compressed air instantly pushes the capsules through the tubing.
they arrive at the lab in seconds.
the building process starts with the send-and-receive unit.
a worker glues tubes to a plate.
both are made of plastic to reduce static.
he slides the tubes through holes in the top
of the unit's metal housing.
he places more tubing inside the housing,
then installs the track.
the tubing slides back and forth on the track to shift
between send and receive mode.
he screws a bracket to the box.
it contains a motor for the sliding mechanism.
then, he places the unit in an upright position.
he connects the motor to a power source to test it.
he confirms that the motor moves the plastic chutes
back and forth smoothly.
the worker connects an air source to the system
to verify that the seals and vents work properly.
at the next station,
a technician removes the temporary door.
then, he wires the motor to the electrical power source.
he bundles the wires and trims the plastic ties.
he screws the computerized control panel to the door.
then, he reattaches the door.
the technician wires the control panel
and verifies that it works.
then, he connects the computer
in the send-and-receive unit to one in a diverter unit.
he confirms that the two computers communicate.
each pneumatic delivery system has several diverters.
they allow the medical capsules to turn a corner
or change direction to reach their final destination.
he installs a gear and motor.
then, he tests the movement of the pipe
from one outlet to the next.
if everything works properly, he screws the back panel on.
then, they connect the diverter and other transfer units
to tubing in the walls of the hospital.
next, they make the delivery capsules.
a worker places the plastic body in a machine.
he activates it,
and the machine spins a cap onto the body.
the spinning also generates heat, which fuses the two parts.
he slides the capsule onto a post to keep it in place.
then, he hooks one end of a spring to the lid framework
and the other end to the sliding lid.
he screws the sliding lid to the framework.
now, the lid easily snaps open and shut.
he places a rubber casing onto the end
and stretches a rubber gasket around the rim.
he wraps fabric bands around both ends.
this helps buffer the capsule during the journey
through the pipeline.
he tucks the bands into the rims using a screwdriver.
he installs plastic bumpers inside.
they help cushion any blows to the capsule
and its contents during the ride through the pipeline.
this capsule is now ready for a test run.
the technician inserts it in the shoot and programs the path.
he opens the door to monitor its progress.
the tubes slide over to collect the capsule
and then slide back to drop it into the main pipeline.
compressed air blows it through the system.
it zips through the pipes
and arrives safely at its final destination.
narrator: in the 1880s,
italians developed special machines to make espresso.
as the name implies,
this coffee drink can be produced in seconds.
soon, the appeal of this quick brew expanded beyond italy,
and today, espresso
is enjoyed all over the world.
making good espresso is as much a science as it is an art.
professional machines balance
temperature and steam pressure
to produce espresso with kick and crema.
professional espresso machines
are made of high-carbon steel sheets.
computer programmed tools carve different shapes
out of the steel.
these parts will be the framework
for the espresso machine.
the tools also cut holes for screws, bolts,
and components like the steam tap.
an employee places a freshly cut control panel
into a hydraulic press machine.
the press bends the panel to the correct shape
and creates tabs for assembly.
this is the panel before and after bending.
after bending the other panels, they assemble the framework.
the worker attaches a receptacle to capture excess water.
he installs meters to control the flow of water.
they release different amounts for long or short espressos.
he turns the base right side
up and screws the side framework to it.
he attaches the front panel to the sides.
the espresso machine's framework is now in place.
next, they make the group heads.
these parts will shoot hot, pressurized water
through the packed ground coffee.
the worker installs valves
that will regulate the water flow.
the valves allows release built-up pressure
so that the filter holders can be removed after brewing.
the group heads fit into slots
in the front of the framework.
he secures them with nuts at the back.
he places a large copper-and-brass boiler
in the espresso machine chassis and connects the water lines.
the tank will generate steam
to froth milk for cappuccinos.
it will also supply hot water for tea.
heat exchangers
run through the boiler to supply the hot water for brewing.
he connects copper pipes
to the heat exchanger outlets on the boiler.
then, he links them to the group heads.
the pipes have been pre-bent
in order to easily fit into the group heads.
he tightens the fitting for the hot water tap.
next, he installs the pump that pressurizes the water.
he screws it to one side of the framework.
a worker then wires the electronics
to the front of the machine.
the employee fits the control panel to the front framework.
he slips rubber molding around the protruding seam.
then, he screws knobs onto the levers.
he tucks a heating coil into
the upper part of the machine.
the top of the machine works as a cup warmer.
the espresso stays hot longer when served in heated cups.
a worker then encases the steel espresso machine
in polycarbonate molded panels.
the plastic parts are slightly rounded to make
the espresso machine look less boxy.
he seats a steel drip tray under the group heads.
and he places the cup tray over the heating element.
the espresso machine is ready
for the filter basket holders.
they're equipped with winglets that hook into the group heads.
the worker tests the espresso machine to confirm
that there are no leaks in the hydraulic circuitry.
the machine appears to be in good, working order.
now, it's time for a coffee break.
narrator: the best-tasting pizzas
are made in traditional wood-fired pizza ovens.
they're constructed primarily of natural clay bricks
that can withstand high temperatures and retain heat.
if a chef prefers to not use a wood-burning oven,
a more convenient gas version is available, as well.
this italian company has been handcrafting classic pizza ovens
since 1892.
while the tile or paint options change over time,
the construction of the oven
itself has remained the same for four generations.
it begins with the oven's rounded top.
they lay clay bricks
on a dome form, working inward from a steel edge.
these bricks are made in house.
they can withstand temperatures of over 900 degrees fahrenheit.
that's fast enough to bake
a traditional neapolitan pizza
in just 60 seconds.
they combine sand,
soil, concrete, clay and water in a mixer.
they pour this mixture
into a steel mold for the base of the oven.
once they fill the mold to the top,
they place a circular template in the exact center of the mold.
then, they begin constructing
the oven's combustion chamber.
this is where the pizza is baked.
the carefully place clay bricks
along the template's inner perimeter.
then, they remove the template and add more bricks.
they work from the outside in, towards the center.
the oven floor
serves as the cooking surface.
it's comprised of four pie-shape pieces
made of the same heat-resistant clay as the bricks.
each piece is 2 inches thick.
they slide the floor in temporarily
so they can correctly
position the bricks around it.
they remove the floor pieces and begin mortaring the bricks.
once complete, this oven will weigh over 5,000 pounds.
the company makes even larger models
that can weigh more than 3 tons.
they lay a second row of bricks on top of the first.
then, they fill the middle with clay.
the team covers the clay with soil.
they pack down the soil
as they go to create a hard, stable surface.
now, they can permanently install the oven floor.
next, they position the oven's cast iron mouth.
they lay bricks in a circle around the mouth
to form the wall of the combustion chamber.
they lay most of the bricks
vertically to fit in as many as possible.
more bricks will provide better insulation in the chamber.
the team pours water on the top edge of the wall.
they remove the oven mouth and apply the mortar.
then, they lower the dome onto the wall
to enclose the combustion chamber.
a worker repositions the mouth and mortars it in place.
he installs the over mouth,
a cast iron plate bearing the manufacturer's name.
he levels it, then fills the gap between the mouth and oven floor
with plaster.
they also use plaster to create a smooth surface
on top of the mouth.
now, the smoke will rise through the hood
toward the chimney instead of being trapped in the oven.
they position steel side plates and weld them to the over mouth.
then, they wield
on a curved steel front plate.
next, they construct
a funnel-shaped stainless steel hood.
they fill the hood with the same mixture
they used for the oven's base.
they cover the dome with wire mesh to compact the mix.
then, they apply a final coat of the mixture.
a worker lays a cast iron plate on the base,
directly in front of the mouth.
he spreads a smooth finishing layer of concrete
on both the dome and the base.
then, they paint the steel
and cast iron parts with anti-corrosion paint.
they install marble on the base
and apply paint or tile to the dome.
they mount the oven steel door last.
they fire up the oven for 9 days to dry all the natural
construction materials.
then, this oven is complete.