captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator:
people have been crafting
religious statues for years.
but time can take a toll
on these sacred works of art.
that's where restoration
experts
come in.
these professionals work
small miracles to return
statues
to their former glory.
this is a wooden sculpture
of the christian messiah.
it was originally crafted
in the 15th century.
but today, it's riddled
with termites and broken.
a major restoration
has been its salvation.
now, this historic work of art
is once again on display
in an italian church.
like the messiah statue,
this 18th century madonna
is damaged.
the plaster
on her face is chipped.
her fingers are broken,
and her robes are crumbling.
first, the restorer dusts
off some of the surface dirt.
he uses a soft brush
and gentle movements
to avoid further destruction.
then, he prepares
a cleaning solution.
he mixes a low-acid,
perfume-free soap with water.
he uses mild soap because
it's gentle on old plaster.
he heats up the mixture
to melt the soap.
then, he starts cleaning
the statue.
he applies the cleanser
to the madonna's face and
body.
he lets it soak into the
plaster
for 7 to 15 minutes.
he makes sure the statue
doesn't absorb too much water
because that would cause
more deterioration.
next, the restorer
wipes the statue
down with a damp sea sponge.
centuries of dirt
and grime come off.
for serious stains,
he combines alcohol and
ammonia.
he applies the cleansing
mixture
using a cotton swab.
he lightly scrubs off
the deep stains.
the alcohol evaporates quickly
so it's not on the surface
of the statue long enough
to do any more damage.
this madonna statue is
starting
to look like her old self.
the restorer uses rabbit glue
for the next step.
it's a strong
and flexible adhesive
that won't chip or crack.
he dissolves some glue
in distilled water.
he applies it to the cloth
exposed underneath
the broken plaster.
then, he mixes a special
plaster
called gesso
with the rabbit glue.
the mixture is 80%
plaster and 20% glue.
he dabs the plaster mixture
onto the glued sections
to fill in the gaps
in the madonna's robes.
he repairs her chipped nose
using a thicker version
of the plaster solution.
he applies it
with a small spatula.
after the first coat of
plaster
on the robes dries,
the restorer
adds another thicker coat.
he adds more layers until he
has
enough material to work with.
then, he sculpts
the robe's contours
using a surgical scalpel.
he blends the repair
into the original plaster
and sands it
until it looks seamless.
he mixes water-based paint
to match the original colors.
then, he carefully
covers the repaired sections,
blending the old with the new.
he mends the brocade
by pressing gold leaf
onto the border of the robes.
the gold leaf sticks
to the glue applied earlier,
matching the original pattern.
he seals the paint
with carnuba wax --
it gives the surface
of the statue
a hard and resilient finish.
it can take up to 4 months
to restore a damaged statue.
a sculpture
that's hundreds of years old
can look as good
as new in just a few months.
then, churchgoers can enjoy it
for centuries to come.
narrator: humans have been
making three-legged objects
for thousands of years.
the third leg gives these
structures extra stability.
some of the earliest
photographs
were taken
with cameras mounted on
tripods.
in fact, the tripod
has been called the most
important photographic
accessory
ever invented.
early tripods were made
out of wood.
they were heavy and
cumbersome.
their design and materials
have improved over time
to meet the needs
of both hobbyists
and professionals alike.
today's state-of-the-art
tripod
is lightweight,
collapsible and equipped
with precision adjustments.
contemporary tripods are made
from aluminum tubes that have
four different diameters.
the tubes are electrowelded
and anodized for precision,
hardness and durability.
a machine cuts the tubes
to the required lengths.
a press expands one end
of the d-shaped tubes to keep
the smaller diameters in
place.
here are two of the
different-sized diameter
tubes.
a worker inserts a tube
into this machine.
it uses a high-precision laser
to etch the company's name
into the aluminum.
the laser process
turns the etched aluminum
white.
they coat aluminum castings
with powdered paint.
the casting is part
of a component called a
spider.
it connects the tripod's legs.
once painted, the components
are taken to a cnc machine.
the machine shapes
the parts to the designer's
exact specifications.
a worker puts foam sleeves
called leg warmers on
two of the tripod's three
legs.
the sleeves allow
photographers
to easily handle the legs
in extreme temperatures.
the worker uses a pressurized
air device to open the sleeve,
then she inserts the leg.
she uses a specialized machine
to add the top hinge collar
to the upper leg section.
the parts were designed
to work together
and click neatly into place.
next, she applies
the locking collars.
when a photographer
adjusts the legs,
the locking collars
will hold them in place.
she threads a bolt
through the collar ends
and adds a quick-release lever
to the assembly.
then, she fastens
all the components in place.
the levers
are ergonomically designed
and can be opened with one
hand.
she presses bushings into
place
on the upper collar
to complete the leg assembly.
now, the tripod
is ready for the next phase.
but first, the worker performs
a quick quality control check.
she makes sure the legs slide
in and out correctly.
then, she checks
the locking collars.
next, she brings the legs
together to form the tripod.
she positions the bottom
of the spider component
on a specially-designed
support mechanism.
she installs the legs and caps
them with the top of the
spider,
then she bolts everything
in place.
next, a worker
assembles the tripod head.
this state-of-the-art
component
can be adjusted
in three directions.
she places plastic rings
between the three main parts
to ensure smooth
and accurate adjustments.
she installs leveling bubbles
to help photographers
accurately position
their cameras.
she adds the upper plate
and the adjustment knobs.
the plate screws
into the camera,
which conveniently
mounts onto the tripod.
the knobs also adjust
for easy storage and
transport.
she labels a knob to indicate
the scale of friction
intensity.
once the entire head
assembly is complete,
a worker carefully threads it
onto the tripod column.
the final step
in the assembly process
is to slide the column and
head
down through the spreader.
a worker checks to ensure
the mechanism
is working correctly,
then tightens the locking
knob.
the finished tripod
is lightweight,
compact and durable.
this tripod is ideal
for both professionals
and hobbyists.
it'll keep the camera
steady for anyone
who wants to take portraits,
profile architectural
features,
or capture
panoramic landscapes.
narrator: polish sausage isn't
necessarily made in poland.
also called kielbasa,
the term refers to
the style of sausage
rather than its location.
it's usually made
entirely of pork,
or a mix of pork and veal.
the meat is seasoned
with salt, pepper, and garlic.
these sausages
might be made in canada,
but there as polish as warsaw.
this kielbasa is 100% pork,
traditionally seasoned
and cooked
by natural wood smoking.
this company uses
the hind leg meat
leftover from
the hams they sell.
each sausage recipe
calls for specific portions
of lean, medium, and fat meat.
workers fill
three separate meat carts
with the required quantity
of each.
they grind the contents
of each cart separately.
the three types of meat
are ground to different sizes.
the lean meat
will be the largest,
and the fat meat
will be the smallest.
the small chunks of fat meat
will fill the gaps
between the large, lean
chunks.
they also add whole
garlic cloves to the grinder
with the fat meat.
then, they prepare a spice mix
that includes garlic powder,
white pepper,
coarsely-ground white,
red, and black peppercorns,
and a proprietary blend
of dried herbs and spices.
they also add pickling salt
as a preservative.
they blend the spices,
pork, and cold water in a
mixer.
the mixer also vacuums air
out of the meat.
this helps the seasoning
thoroughly saturate the pork.
it also makes the sausage
denser
and concentrates the flavor.
they mix the ingredients
for 15 minutes,
then let it rest
and marinate for several
hours.
after marinating,
the meat is ready to be put
into sausage casings.
the casing is made
out of hog intestine.
the filling specialist
controls the fill speed
with a knee-operated lever.
he applies the right amount
of pressure with his fingers
to stuff the fragile casing
without tearing it.
no two hog intestines
are identical,
so this process
can't be automated.
the filling specialist
constantly adjusts the speed
and pressure as he works.
the filling specialist
takes the finished casing
and gently loops it
over his arm.
then, he puts the loops
on the rack of
a smokehouse trolley.
a fully-loaded trolley
holds about 550 pounds
of raw sausages.
they roll the trolley
into the smokehouse chamber,
shut the door...
and light the fire.
they feed maple and hickory
logs
into a 10-foot fire pit
located
directly below the chamber.
they monitor each sausage
while it's smoking
and adjust the heat exposure
as needed.
the smoking period
lasts for 6 to 8 hours.
the meat cooks
at about 160 degrees
to kill off all the bacteria.
the smoke infuses it
with additional flavor,
naturally curing the sausages.
after the sausages
leave the smokehouse,
they're cleaned with hot
water.
then, the sausages
are rinsed in cold water
and sent to a blast fridge.
this minimizes the amount
of time
the sausages are warm enough
for bacteria to grow.
the rapid cooling procedure
eliminates the need
for additional chemical
preservatives.
a worker cuts the sausage
into 4 1/2-pound portions.
he places each portion
in the bottom tray
of the plastic package.
before sealing the tray,
a machine sucks out the air
and replaces it with a mix
of 80% nitrogen
and 20% carbon dioxide.
this extends shelf life
because mold and yeast
can't live without oxygen.
the carbon dioxide
also inhibits bacterial
growth.
the nitrogen fills the package
to protect the sausage
during transport.
every sealed package
passes through a metal
detector.
then, a scale weighs each
package and prints out a label
indicating the weight
and the sell-by date.
a sealed and refrigerated
package of sausage
can stay fresh
for up to 35 days.
once opened, these sausages
taste best
if eaten within 7 days --
and even better
with a little sauerkraut.
welding guns are regulars
on "how it's made."
they're used in many factories
all over the world.
they have copper claws that
hold
parts together with high
force,
then weld items together.
the guns are designed to do
precision work at a steady
pace.
a welding gun is designed
to make the same weld
over and over again.
they're programmed
to accomplish a repetitive
task
with pinpoint accuracy.
production starts
with the gun's electrode caps,
which are made
out of copper rod.
the rod uncoils
and travels to a forming
machine
with a series of punches
and dies.
mechanical fingers move the
rod
from one die to the next.
the punches drive the rod
into the die cavities
to shape it into electrode
caps.
the electrodes come in
thousands
of different shapes
and are made
it many different ways.
the make this electrode,
automated tools taper a thick
copper rod at one end.
then, a drill bores a hole in
the other end for cooling
water.
smaller electrodes are made
of partially-hollowed blanks.
they shave down the blank
so that it will be able
to weld in small areas.
they also shape it
so that the electrode cap
will fit on top.
they use another drill to make
an entrance for cooling water.
the entrance intersects with
the hollowed part
of the cylinder.
then, another machine
bends the electrode into
its final shape.
next,
they make the shunt adapter.
a worker uses a hydraulic
machine to bend a copper bar
around a die.
he measures it to confirm
that the dimensions are
correct.
a high-pressure water jet
carves
through a thick copper plate
to create the welding arms.
the water jet
can precisely cut out the part
without scorching the copper.
at the next station,
computerized tools shape a
solid
block of steel into a mount
for the welding machine's
motor.
it's a substantial
transformation.
an employee bolts steel plates
to the end of the copper arm.
he places a washer
over the plates
and then tightens the bolts.
he inserts the electrode
in the other end of the arm.
then, he places the cap
on and hammers it in place.
the worker uses a crane to
move
the second weld arm into
place.
he aligns the holes
and joins the arms
with the temporary metal pin.
the transformer delivers
electricity to the electrodes.
a worker attaches the robot
welding arms to it.
he replaces the temporary pin
with a permanent one.
then, he bolts the arms
to the transformer.
now, the welding gun
is ready for the motor.
he joins the motor to the arms
and tightens the bolts
on each side.
the mechanics of this robot
welding gun are complete.
now they need to add
the plumbing.
an employee cuts plastic
tubing
and connects it
to the welding gun.
the tubes will supply a
constant
flow of water to the gun.
without it,
the gun would overheat
and the electrode tips
could melt.
he bundles some of the hoses
and ties them together
for neater installation.
they test every
robot welding gun
to confirm that it's
fully operational.
this gun is a slightly
different
version that the one
that was just assembled.
the technician also
confirms that the tips
have sufficient force
for a good weld.
too much force
could damage the tips.
too little force
would result in a poor weld.
it takes about an hour
to assemble a robot welding
gun.
this gun is ready
to leave the factory
and be part of the action
at another one.