--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: exercise bikes can provide a great cardio workout.
their tension settings
are equivalent to the gears on a road bike.
cyclists can adjust the tension to control the intensity
of their workout, all while staying in one place.
riding an exercise bike can help burn calories,
increase strength, and reach fitness goals.
they start by making the bike frame,
which includes the handlebars, saddle post,
and flywheel housing.
an employee places all the parts in a welding fixture.
the welding system is computerized.
the fixture moves the parts into position
and a robot accurately
welds the joints of the frame.
it takes 20 welds to link all the parts of the bike frame.
at the next station, a machine shapes the handlebars
and saddle post to the correct profile.
then, a worker polishes the welds with a wire brush.
next, they apply a black plastic finish to the metal.
this process is called powder coating.
an employee applies a metallic decal of the company name
to the powder-coated frame.
he inserts the bearing for the pedal crank axle
and gently taps it into place with a hammer.
he attaches a circuit board to the base.
it will control the resistance of the flywheel.
he threads the wiring through the hollow frame
and out the handlebar post.
he drills holes in the saddle-bar tubing,
then, he installs the post and adjustable locking screw.
he installs a temporary clamping lever on the flywheel framework,
which will be used to tension the transmission build.
he installs the bike saddle.
then, he uses a hydraulic system to press an axle and bearing
into the center of the flywheel.
he places a product-name decal on the flywheel.
the cast-iron flywheel is the heart of the bike.
at about 40 pounds, it's heavy enough to stabilize the bike
during the stationary ride.
he loops the transmission belt around the flywheel axle,
then mounts the flywheel to the framework.
he installs magnetic brakes and
wires them to a bike computer.
the brakes allow the rider to control the resistance
during the ride.
he connects the pulley disk to the front of the bike.
then, he loops the other end of the transmission belt
around the pulley disk.
he uses a clamping lever to pull the belt tight.
he strums it and measures the sound
to confirm the tension is right.
the next worker removes the clamp
and places the bike in a test station.
it spins the flywheel and applies resistance.
a computer analyzes the bike's performance.
another employee wires the switches
for increasing and decreasing resistance.
she tucks the wiring inside the handlebars.
she attaches switches to the outside
for easy access during the ride.
she folds the lower half of the resistance wiring up
and installs the wiring sleeve in between the handlebars.
she screws the bracket to the handlebar housing,
then, she connects the wires to the ride computer
and attaches it to the bracket.
she opens the computer
and plugs the main power cable into the back.
then, she reinstalls the computer's back panel.
this completes the handlebar assembly.
the next worker encases the transmission belt
and electrical parts in a plastic housing.
he attaches the pedals to the axle.
then, he places plastic caps on the ends
and hammers them into place.
he packages the bike and
handlebar assembly separately.
this exercise bike is now ready to ride.
it may be stationary,
but, when it comes to fitness,
this bike should help riders go the distance.
a pasty is a common british meal consisting of
meat and vegetables wrapped in a pastry.
historically, the cornish pasty was served as a convenient meal
for miners in the cornwall area of the united kingdom.
the crimped edge served as a handle,
allowing workers to enjoy their food
without contaminating it with their dirty hands.
the cornish pasty is the national dish
of cornwall in the uk.
its signature crimped edge,
along with other characteristics,
are culturally and commercially protected.
under european union regulations,
only pasties made the traditional way in cornwall
can be sold as cornish pasties.
the traditional recipe begins with pastry dough.
workers combine lard and margarine
with salt and flour.
they mix these ingredients at low speeds
so they don't overheat the fats.
the solid fats break up gradually
and combine with the flour and salt
to form a bread-crumb-like texture.
after about five minutes, they add water.
then, they resume mixing, until the dough
reaches the right consistency.
they let the dough rest for about an hour.
this relaxes the gluten in the flour,
preventing the dough from shrinking when it bakes.
they put it in an extruder,
which feeds it down an automated forming line.
at the first station, the dough passes through several rollers,
which progressively flatten it into a sheet.
they add flour to the dough, so it doesn't stick to the rollers.
the flattened dough finally exits the first station.
the next station uses revolving cutters to slice the dough
into 5-ounce disks.
the excess dough is collected
and reworked into the next batch.
flattening and cutting the dough heats it up,
so they put it in a refrigerator
for about an hour, to restore its elasticity.
meanwhile, they prepare the pasties' vegetable filling.
workers load washed potatoes into an industrial peeler.
it spins them inside an abrasive metal drum to remove the skins.
then, the potatoes go through a dicer,
which cuts them to a specific size.
the dicer deposits the potatoes in water,
to remove any excess starch.
workers combine the potatoes
with diced rutabaga and onion in a vegetable mixer.
they add melted butter,
to help caramelize the onions.
they also add salt, pepper, and a blend of other seasonings.
they run the mixer for about two minutes.
then, the vegetable filling
joins the other components on the production line.
workers place the dough on a moving belt
with the front edge of each disk on a white line.
this position ensures that the depositor's nozzles
drop the filling onto the right spot.
next, workers place fresh, lean skirt steak
on top of the vegetables.
the steak is cut from
the forequarter of prime beef.
according to european union regulations,
12.5% of a cornish pasty must be beef.
this company's pasties exceed that, containing at least 17.5%.
highly skilled workers
close the cornish pasty with the signature crimped edge.
they fold the dough in half,
form 19 to 22 even crimps along the back of the pasty,
then, neatly tuck the end.
this must be done
with both precision and speed.
it takes these expert crimpers about 20 seconds per pasty.
workers collect the pasties and make a small incision,
to vent some moisture as the bake.
the remaining juices will infuse the vegetables,
producing a flavorful gravy.
the factory immediately cools the finished cornish pasties
to about 65 fahrenheit.
this keeps the raw ingredients fresh during packaging.
pasties are stored and shipped frozen,
then glazed and baked onsite.
after 45 to 50 minutes in the oven,
these traditional cornish pasties are ready to serve.
fresh pasta is made from a moist egg and flour dough
that's mixed, kneaded, and rolled into a sheet.
then, the dough is cut into soft noodles, ravioli,
or other shapes, using a pasta maker.
this italian-made industrial pasta maker
is designed for restaurants and smaller pasta suppliers.
the machine is only five feet wide,
but it's still capable of mixing the dough
and pressing it into a variety of pasta shapes.
the machine can turn dough
into ravioli or assorted types of long and short pasta.
the machine's three stations --
the extruder, the ravioli maker, and the pasta cutter --
are constructed from stainless-steel parts.
a computer-guided punch press
makes the required holes and slots.
workers insert pieces into a press
to bend them to the required shape.
this is a cover for one of the machine's components.
once all the pieces are ready, workers weld them together.
the machine's pasta cutter uses stainless-steel cutting rollers
to slice the pasta.
each roller starts out as a stainless-steal rod.
a computer-guided mill carves grooves into it.
the groove width determines the width of the pasta.
the pasta cutter contains four pairs of rollers
that cut the pasta to different widths:
2-millimeter-wide taglionlini,
4-millimeter-wide fettuccine,
8-millimeter-wide tagliatelle,
and 12-millimeter-wide pappardelle.
rollers are available in additional sizes.
workers install four corresponding pairs
of steel combs underneath the rollers.
the combs gently scrape the dough out of the grooves
to eject the cut pasta.
next, workers install the gears that turn the rollers.
the gears engage one another,
so that the rollers revolve at the same speed.
this ensures that the cutter
operates smoothly and quietly.
the motor turns the larger main gear, which moves the others.
they mount protective covers.
this critical safety feature
prevents users' fingers from
getting caught in the rollers.
at the base of the cutter,
they mount a smooth laminating roller.
this roller thins the dough sheet
before the cutting rollers slice it.
they install the electrically powered motor
that turns the main gear.
then, the handle that moves the laminating roller.
here, they've removed the protective covers
to demonstrate how the cutting rollers operate.
next, they build the extruder.
they mount a blade in the dough mixer
and connect it to an electric motor.
the extrusion tube is located directly below the dough mixer.
the dough is pushed through a bronze die
in the extrusion tube.
the dies can be changed to make different types of pasta.
one die makes a flat sheet of dough,
for cutting long pasta or making ravioli.
other dies can be used to make short pasta,
such as fusilli or rotini.
the machine's third station is the motorized ravioli maker.
it also has interchangeable dies,
to make different shapes of ravioli.
now, this machine is ready to make pasta.
first, they pour in the dough ingredients
and mix for 15 minutes.
then, they pull a lever to feed the dough through the extruder.
this is the die that makes a dough sheet
for the long pasta cutter or ravioli maker.
they cut the dough off the extruder
and put it through the cutter's laminating roller to thin it.
then, they feed it through the rollers
in one of the cutting slots.
to make ravioli,
they extrude two narrow sheets
and put them through the ravioli maker.
a tube injects the filling between the sheets
before the die crimps them together.
a cooling system built into the extruder
prevents the dough from heating up
as it's forced through the die.
this keeps the pasta fresh for a long time.
slate was originally used to make roof shingles,
as well as floor and wall tiles,
but, now, this metamorphic rock is used all over the house.
artisans are using slate to create everyday items,
including tableware, address plaques,
and garden accessories.
these cornish slate products use
traditional building materials
in nontraditional ways.
in cornwall,
they have been mining slate for hundreds of years.
some of the craftsman's slate is old roof
or floor tile retrieved from the demolition sites.
other projects require new slate, fresh from the quarry.
the craftsman selects
and older piece from a cheese board.
he evaluates the color, as well as the thickness and shape.
older slate is weathered and has more colors running through it.
he scrapes the loose slate off the surface,
working carefully to avoid
fracturing the stone's thin layers.
he sweeps off the scrapings.
he scrubs the slate tile with a chemical cleaning solution
and rinses off the residue.
the slate dries in minutes.
as the water evaporates,
the color changes dramatically
from dark gray to light gray with a bluish hue.
he measures the slate for cutting
and scores it lightly with a sharp tool.
he places a template for the handle
within the scored boundaries and marks it for drilling.
then, he cuts the slate with a slate guillotine.
it's a double-bladed tool similar to a paper cutter.
he leaves a margin for trimming.
he breaks off the margin
by tapping it with a special slater's tool
and checks the edges, to confirm that they're neat.
then, he redefines the markings for the handle holds.
the craftsman drills holes through the slate
for the handles.
then, he changes the drill bit
to cut a sloped profile into the holes.
this will allow the screws to sit flush against the slate.
he brushes the edges, to get rid of loose chips,
and refines the ends with a razor blade.
the craftsman washes the slate one more time.
the glues four small silicone knobs onto the base.
the knobs act as legs,
so the cheese plate can be set on any surface.
he applies two coats of
food-safe sealer to the slate.
each coat takes a day to dry.
then, he installs the stainless-steel handles.
this slate cheese board is now ready to hold a few snacks.
from an old roof tile to a nice piece of tableware.
it's quite a transformation.
next, the craftsman slices
a block of new slate with a wet saw.
new slate comes in thicker chunks.
it can be used to make signage.
he uses eight different grades of diamond abrasive pads
to polish the surface until it's completely flat.
then, he uses a computerized graphic cutter
to make a stencil out of vinyl.
he places the stencil over the slate
and sandblasts it with a special compound.
the process creates rough grooves in the slate.
the grooves will allow paint to adhere to the stone.
another employee uses the stencil
to apply paint to the slate.
she allows each coat of the paint to dry
before brushing on the next.
she applies four coats in total.
when she's finished, she peels off the vinyl.
this custom slate sign is ready of face the street.
it takes four days to craft, seal, and paint the sign.
now that it's complete,
the sign is sure to make a rock-solid impression.