--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: the word champagne
is often used to describe sparkling white wines.
but true champagne can only come from the champagne region
of france.
it must meet a long list of special requirements
before receiving the coveted label.
the champagne industry is heavily regulated.
the grapes must be locally grown in the champagne region
of france.
they can only use three types of grapes, black pinot noir,
pinot meunier,
or white chardonnay, to produce champagne.
additional rules regulate how the grapes
can be pruned, picked, pressed, fermented and aged.
workers harvest the grapes in mid-september.
they use aerated crates to transfer the crops
to a grape press.
they crush the grapes
and immediately filter the juice.
the grape skins and pulp can alter the juice's flavor,
so they have to be removed quickly.
vintage champagne is fermented in old oak barrels.
they use a sulfur disk to disinfect the barrels
between uses.
first, a worker lights the disk and inserts
it through a hole on the side.
the flame goes out once
it's sealed inside the barrel.
the sulfur smoke fills the barrel
and kills off any bacteria.
non-vintage champagnes
are produced in these stainless steel tanks.
they start the fermentation process by adding yeast
to the grape juice.
in about 10 days, the yeast
turns the sugar into alcohol and carbon dioxide gas.
the alcohol level of the wine is now about 10 1/2 percent.
there are no bubbles yet
because the co2 escaped through the top of the tank.
each fermentation barrel and tank
is labeled based on where the juice inside originated.
the grape juices from each village have distinctive tastes,
caused by differences in soil composition and sun exposure.
blending begins after the first fermentation.
the winery's experts experiment with different combinations
until they find the taste
and aroma they're looking for.
they bottle the mixture with yeast and sugar,
and place it in a cold, damp cellar for 5 weeks.
this second fermentation raises the alcohol content
to 12 1/2 percent.
after fermentation,
they lie the bottles down horizontally
and let the champagne age for up to 10 years.
after the aging,
the bottles go into a machine that freezes the neck.
the yeast residue freezes in a small ice cube under the cork.
the carbon dioxide is invented during the second fermentation.
when workers open each bottle,
the gas pressure ejects the ice cube.
this procedure is called disgorging.
a worker turns the bottle
to minimize the amount of champagne that escapes.
then he smells it to make sure the champagne hasn't spoiled.
the winery
makes a special liqueur out of wine and cane sugar,
which they add to the champagne.
the amount of liqueur added brings the champagne to one
of three sweetness levels,
known as brut, sec,
or demi-sec.
the filling machine secures the new cork with a wire cap.
the next machine rotate the
bottles to mix in the liqueur.
then the bottles go into the cellar
for at least 3 months.
after they come out of the cellar,
the bottles go through an automated washing machine.
a worker inspects every bottle for floating cork particles
or flaws in the glass.
the labeling machine's first station places
gold foil over the neck.
the foil label bears the winery's name.
the second station fires a shot of compressed air
to mold the foil to the shape of the cork.
the third station glues on the neck label.
it's made of varnished paper.
then, the last station
applies an adhesive label to the front of the bottle.
a scanner makes sure the foil
and labels are in the correct place.
this bottle of champagne is finally ready to drink.
when you pop the cork, the gas
trapped inside gently escapes.
shaking the bottle just before opening
will cause an even more dramatic champagne explosion.
either way, it's the perfect drink to celebrate any occasion.
cheers.
narrator: before the automated teller machine,
withdrawals and deposits were made in person.
then, in the 1960s,
simple cash machines started to appear all over europe.
later, more sophisticated versions were developed.
today's atms make it easy and convenient
to bank outside of normal business hours.
atms are made of two sections.
the bottom is a steel safe that houses the cash dispenser.
the head module contains all the user features on top.
most of the atm's non-electronic parts are cut from steel sheets.
workers load the steel sheets
into a computer-guided laser cutting machine.
the laser uses focused light to generate intense heat.
the heat melts the steel to make the cuts.
the simpler parts are stamped with a die and a press.
next, a robot loads
the piece into a fully-automated
computer-guided bending press.
the press bends the part into the required shape.
a computer guided spot welder
fuses the simple parts together at set intervals.
for more complex parts,
a computer guided 3-d laser welds the entire joint.
an automated transport system
dips the steel parts in a metal primer
to prevent corrosion.
after dipping,
they dry the parts in an oven.
the housing parts are sprayed with liquid or powder paint.
then they go into an oven to bake on the color.
this is the internal structure for the atm's head module.
workers assemble all the module's internal components,
including the power unit and the atm's computer.
then, they lower the head module onto the atm's steel safe.
the safe's walls can be up to 2 inches thick.
there's a separate assembly line for the operation panel.
this panel goes on the front of the head module.
it contains everything used in an atm transaction,
from the card reader, to the key pad,
and even the speaker system.
the key pad encrypts the user's
personal identification number
inside the atm.
the machine has up to three security cameras.
they record the key pad, the cash tray and the atm user.
workers connect the monitor to the internal computer.
they also install the card reader and the receipt slot.
at the bank's request,
they can install a separate module for deposits.
however, this atm uses the cash out slot to accept deposits.
workers also install the shutter,
a computer-controlled flap on the cash out slot.
it opens when the machine accepts a deposit
or dispenses money.
next, workers mount the operation panel
to the head module.
on a separate assembly line,
they prepare the electronic mechanical unit.
it dispenses the money
and accepts cash and checks for deposits.
workers load cassettes into the unit for each cash denomination.
the bank will separate and stock the cash for their atm.
before they install the unit in the atm,
they hook it up to a test computer.
they test a few different transactions with fake bills
to make sure it dispenses the correct amount.
if the unit passes testing,
workers install it in the atm safe.
they run a couple of the finished machines
through several quality control tests.
first, a shake test
ensures the atm can withstand
a bumpy ride during transport.
next, they conduct a shower test
to ensure that rain won't damage an outdoor atm.
there's also a climate test.
they place the atm in a chamber that simulates temperature
ranging from negative 40 degrees to over 120 degrees fahrenheit.
atms designed for extreme temperatures
usually have built-in heating or cooling systems.
every atm comes with basic operating software installed.
the banks then install their custom software
or have the manufacturer do it for them.
it takes a powerful engine to move a cruise liner
or a cargo vessel.
turbochargers help make it possible.
they double the diesel engine's output
to 100,000 horsepower or more.
turbochargers also use exhaust gases to run the compressor.
in a ship's engine,
the turbocharger is
a welcome breath of fresh air.
it's capable of significantly boosting
the engine's performance.
it does this by compressing almost 200 feet
of air per second,
then thrusting that air into the engine's combustion chamber.
first, they make the turbine wheel.
it's used to extract the exhaust gases.
a long cutting tool known as a broach
carves a tree-shaped pattern around the edge of a steel disk.
the pine tree shapes
are designed to interlock with the matching blades.
next, a computer-guided saw slices a brass alloy
cylinder into small bearings.
these bearings will support the turbine shaft.
they make several bearings in a range
of sizes and materials for different turbochargers.
computerized tools mill the surface of the axial bearing.
they also drill holes to connect the turbine rotor
and the casing.
this is the completed bearing.
a worker inserts one
of the turbochargers
nickel alloy blades in a mold.
he leaves the foot of the blade sticking out.
he slides the mold directly under a spout,
which dispenses a hot liquefied tin alloy.
he fills the mold to the top.
the tin alloy solidifies, encasing the blade
just below the foot.
this structure will fit into a clamping device
in the grinding operation.
an employee
inserts the tin-encased blades
into tensioning devices in the grinding machine.
inside the tensioning device,
a clamping mechanism grips the blades.
as coolant flows,
a computerized grinder carves grooves in the feet.
they're specially designed to engage with the tree pattern
on the turbine disk.
they pull the tin alloy blocks out of the machine.
they break the tin alloy,
and remove the blade inside.
now, it's ready to be connected to the turbine wheel.
a worker slides the blade foot into place on the turbine disk.
then he bends a clip back halfway, with pliers.
he tightens the alignment with a clamp.
he hammers the clamp down further,
until it lays flat against the blade foot
and turbine wheel.
this secures the blade to the wheel.
he continues until the blades are in place.
it takes 41 blades to complete the job.
next, computerized tools mill the aluminum compressor wheel
and prepare it for cutting.
the tools carve blades
and grooves in the compressor.
the design makes the compressor more aerodynamic.
an aerodynamic compressor is important
because it allows more air to reach the ship's engine.
here's the compressor wheel
before and after the milling operation.
next, they run through compressor
through a safety test.
they lower it into a chamber
and spin it a lot faster than it would normally operate.
they confirm that the compressor can withstand a speed
of 27,000 revolutions per minute without breaking.
next, the compressor wheel receives an ultrasonic cleaning.
high frequency sound waves ripple through the water
to scrub off any grease
and contaminants.
a worker uses a blower to start drying the compressor wheel.
then, he lowers it into a dryer to get rid
of any residual moisture.
when we return,
this marine turbocharger will become seaworthy.
stay tuned.
narrator: turbochargers deliver fresh air
to big ship engines.
this enhances their combustion
and adds to their mechanical might.
turbochargers help
make these diesel engines among the most powerful in the world,
allowing them to move gigantic vessels
swiftly through the water.
a technician shines an ultraviolet light
onto the surface of the compressor wheel.
this illuminates any fine cracks
that could compromise its quality.
if no cracks are found, they start assembling the rotor.
the employee slides bearings onto the main shaft and turbine.
he uses a crane
to align the center hole of the compressor wheel
with the shaft.
he guides it into place and fits it to the bearing.
then he screws a cone-shaped cap onto the end.
the turbine wheel is connected to one end of the shaft,
and the compressor is connected to the other.
the core parts of this turbocharger are now assembled.
a technician locks the rotor in a balancing machine.
when he activates the machine, the rotor starts spinning.
sensors detect the speed
and the angular position of the rotor.
they also check for any possible imbalances.
the team uses this information to shave down the rotor
and bring it into balance.
then, the final assembly of the turbocharger begins.
the team screws the iron casing to the gas outlet.
they attach three bearings to it.
this insert is called the labyrinth cover.
it will act as a seal for the turbine disk and shaft.
the long bolts fit into holes in the bearing casing.
he moves to the other side,
and secures the protruding bolts and nuts.
he removes the compressor wheel
temporarily to slide the shaft
through the center bearing.
the turbine wheel fits perfectly over the labyrinth cover.
on the other side,
he bolts the labyrinth disk to the casing.
the labyrinth disk protects against hot turbine exhaust gas
and prevents oil leakage.
then, he re-installs the compressor wheel.
meanwhile, an employee
wraps rock wool insulation around the gas inlet casing.
it's made of cast iron
and built to withstand gases as
hot as 900 degrees fahrenheit.
they cover the part with a heat-resistant fabric jacket.
then it's ready to be mounted to the gas outlet casing.
workers use a crane to move it into position.
they align the holes in the part with the threads in the casing.
then they bolt it into place.
they install a cast iron casing around the compressor wheel
and secure it with numerous nuts and bolts.
they hoist an insert part into place
between the compressor wheel and the casing.
air will flow between the insert and the compressor
before traveling to the engine for combustion.
the turbocharger is now ready to
be installed in a ship engine.
this is done in the factory's assembly hall.
once in place,
they fire up the engine and test its performance.
they evaluate how much power the turbocharger adds to the engine.
they also assess the turbocharger's impact
on fuel efficiency.
this turbocharger meets expectations.
some cars and trucks use small turbochargers in their engines,
but these behemoths should
deliver twice the air pressure
of those models,
so the ship's captain will have all the power
he needs to navigate the high seas.