--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: the bead is the lip of the tire
that fits to a wheel rim.
high-tensile steel wires inside the bead
pull the tire tightly and uniformly to the rim.
these bead wires provide stability
so the wheels can start turning.
these bronze-coated steel wires
are the muscle in the bead of a tire.
they're a source of hidden strength
that we don't usually think about.
but without them, tires wouldn't properly grip the rim,
and riding on wheels would be dangerous.
production starts with coils of high-carbon steel.
a forklift slides the coils onto metal cones.
a worker cuts the ties around the wire.
then the cone moves into an upright position
on the carousel.
a motorized system
uncoils the wire and pulls it up through the cone.
at the top,
a guide positions the wire to enter a descaler.
the device
has a revolving sandpaper belt
which smoothes and refines the wire.
next, the wire travels
through a channel filled with powdered soap,
which acts as a dry lubricant.
then, the system pulls the wire through a series of dies,
each with progressively smaller openings.
the process is called drawing
because it draws
down the diameter of the wire,
stretching it longer and thinner.
the process reduces the wire's diameter by almost half.
a carriage lifts the thinner wire
onto a spool that winds it up.
the table the spool sits on turns
to deliver the wire to the next operation.
the spool of wire is one of 40
that now unwind simultaneously at a controlled speed.
large cones keep them separate
so they'll be ready for the next stage
of the journey --
a trip through a long oven.
it's heated to an incredible 1,800 degrees.
inside, intense heat
recrystalizes the microstructure of the wires.
this reduces brittleness.
then spools take up the wires.
the wires take a dip in a tank
filled with hot water and phosphate solution.
a floating foam blanket keeps the solution hot.
the phosphate solution and a subsequent rinse lubricate
the bead wire for the next process --
a second drawing
that squeezes the wire even longer and narrower.
the holes in a series of dies become progressively narrower
to reduce the wire's diameter even further.
after each trip through a die,
a drum winds up the wire.
each drum turns a little
faster than the one before it.
that's because longer wires
need to be wound up quicker to prevent slack in the system.
this final drawing process
brings the wire's diameter down to less than 1 millimeter.
the bead wires are now at the correct width.
next, the bead wires receive their bronze coating.
bronzing the steel wires
allows them to adhere to the tire rubber.
after the bronze solution dries,
two rollers straighten the wires.
then a spool winds up the bead wire.
they produce bead wire in different thicknesses
and metal coatings for a variety of tire sizes.
they test the wires
before they leave the factory.
if it can withstand up to 1,500 pounds of force
before it breaks,
then it's ready to be shipped to the tire factory.
once they're installed in rubber tires,
these bead wires will be
an important source of strength, doing their part
to keep your vehicle moving forward safely.
narrator: mini pepperoni makes a great portable snack.
it's made of red meat or poultry.
this protein-packed snack
can alleviate even the most serious hunger pains.
the meat sticks are fermented and dehydrated,
so they don't need to be refrigerated.
this brand of mini pepperoni is made entirely of pork.
it comes in a variety of flavors,
each made with different seasonings.
first, they prepare the raw meat.
they combine different cuts in specific proportions
to attain their target meat-to-fat ratio.
the meat comes from the pig's back, shoulder, and belly.
the butcher loads the pork into an automated grinder.
it grinds the pork
until it's the right texture for mini pepperoni.
the meat was frozen,
then partially thawed before entering the machine.
as a result, the pork grinds cleanly.
the seasoning recipe includes paprika, cayenne pepper,
dextrose, anise, and salt.
they also mix in sodium nitrate,
a preservative
that prevents bacterial growth
and gives the meat a cured flavor.
they load the ground pork into a mixer
and pour in some lactic acid bacterial culture,
which will kick-start fermentation later.
next, they add the seasoning mix
and a premeasured amount of concentrated liquid paprika.
they continue mixing for a couple of minutes,
distributing the ingredients evenly.
then they transfer the ground pork from the mixer
to a meat buggy.
they roll the meat buggy over to the filling machine...
...and empty the contents.
a worker loads a tube of sausage casing.
the casing is made of bovine collagen.
the filling machine pumps out 1.6 ounces of ground pork
then twists the casing between each one to form a link.
the machine feeds 25-link chains onto a hanging line.
the line spaces them out to preserve
their perfect sausage shape.
one casing tube makes 100 links.
next, they ferment, smoke, and dry the meat.
workers hang three dozen 25-link chains on each smokehouse rack.
then they roll the rack into the smokehouse.
first, they humidify and heat the links
to approximately 77 degrees, triggering fermentation.
the lactic acid bacterial culture
starts feeding on the dextrose in the seasoning.
the process increases the acidity in the meat,
preventing harmful bacteria from growing.
it also produces a fermented flavor.
after about 14 hours, they lower the temperature
and humidity to halt fermentation.
next, they start up the smoke generator,
which they've loaded with maple and beechwood chips.
they run several smoking cycles until the links change color
and acquire a slightly sweet and smoky taste.
then they raise the heat again to cook the meat thoroughly.
finally, they dry the links in a temperature
and humidity-controlled room for a couple of days.
workers separate the links
and put 10 into the bottom of each tray.
the trays go
into a vacuum-packing machine,
which sucks out the air then seals the top with plastic.
the pepperoni is tested by an
in-house lab before packaging.
they confirm that the moisture content is sufficiently low
and the acidity reading is sufficiently high.
if it is, the final product is considered shelf-stable,
meaning that it isn't perishable
and doesn't require refrigeration.
narrator: where mother nature fails,
a center-pivot irrigation system can succeed.
if you can't afford to wait on the rain,
these systems can water your crops.
they're essentially a huge sprinkler
on wheels that pivots around a central point
in a slow, circular path.
developed in the 20th century,
center-pivot sprinklers have become a staple on large farms.
they can be up to a half-mile in length
and sprawl across fields,
ensuring there isn't a dry spot in sight.
they custom-design each sprinkler for the field
it will be irrigating.
then, they transform flat, high-strength steel
into a water pipe for the sprinkler system.
the steel travels
between forming tools and then a series of rollers.
they curve the steel upwards, taking it from flat
to cylindrical.
more rollers squeeze the pipe to close the gap.
then an automated induction welder can fuse the joint.
a carbide blade trims excess metal from the welded seam.
the metal is collected on a spool to be recycled.
next, they douse the pipe with coolant.
a plasma torch then moves along the pipe
to cut it into 40-foot sections.
the pipes fall off the cutting line and roll
into a holding area.
after the pipes
have been inspected for flaws,
a team clamps flanges to the ends.
these flanges will be used to link the water pipes
in the field.
they weld the flanges to the pipes.
next, the welder uses a plasma torch to cut
outlets for sprinkler heads.
he welds a threaded fitting onto each outlet.
the water pipe is complete.
they'll use dozens of these pipes
for a single irrigation system.
next, a progressive die stamps hook plates from steel.
hook plates hold the spans of the sprinkler together.
they also keep the sprinkler flexible as it moves.
robots weld mounting plates and other parts to a pipe,
creating a base for the sprinkler
system's wheeled towers.
then they dip all the parts in molten zinc.
the zinc hardens as it cools to give the pipes
a glossy, rust-proof finish.
next, an employee
assembles the sprinkler heads.
she screws a weight to the plastic sprinkler body
to stabilize it.
then she snaps on a spray nozzle.
the nozzles come in various sizes
for different applications.
finally,
she adds a pressure regulator.
the next member of the team
lubricates the wheel rims with soapy water.
then he installs the rubber tires.
the tire size and tread
are selected based on expected field conditions.
these tires
should allow the sprinkler system to rotate freely.
they ship the parts of the sprinkler system
to the field.
they arrange the pipes on the ground
in the correct configuration...
...and set all the structural components beside them.
then they start assembling the immense sprinkler system,
beginning with the triangular supports for the water pipes.
they hoist the ends of two pipes onto the supports
and bolt them at the flanges.
they repeat this process until the structure
stretches across the field.
a crew member screws the sprinklers to hoses.
he connects the hoses to u-shaped fittings
screwed into the pipes.
next, they complete the electrical wiring.
then they roll the wheels to the end towers
and bolt them to the gear motor hubs.
it takes a full day to assemble a center-pivot sprinkler system
in the field.
by tapping into an underground source,
the system can pump out water through the sprinkler heads.
during a drought, this irrigation system
can provide a long, cold drink
for crops on a hot summer day.
narrator: gloves have long been a part of human history.
up until the middle ages,
most people ate with their hands.
so, ancient romans wore silk or linen gloves
to protect their hands from hot food.
today, leather gloves are
mainly used to provide warmth,
but they can also make a fashion statement.
these gloves are made of high-quality lambskin.
the tanneries process the hides to make the leather smooth,
supple, and very durable.
the gloves are then handcrafted in france.
making a fine pair of leather gloves
starts with a master glove-cutter.
cutting expertise is just as important
as the quality of leather they use.
first, he adds water to make the leather supple.
then he stretches the skin in a single direction.
this prevents the glove from stretching and losing its shape
after it's made.
he uses a rectangular template
to make indentations in the leather,
then cuts them with shears.
he produces two rectangles, one for each glove in the pair.
he stretches the leather again.
a master glove-cutter knows how to optimize
the natural stretch in the skin.
he deliberately leaves room in certain areas
for comfort and eliminates
stretch in other areas to preserve the glove's fit.
using the template again, he marks and makes his final cuts.
the rectangle is for the section of the glove
that covers the hand, called the trank.
he marks the glove size with a white pencil.
he follows the same procedure to cut pieces of leather
for the other parts of the glove.
they include the thumb,
the pieces
that go in between the fingers
called the fourchettes,
and the decorative trim.
he uses a die to cut each part.
there's a separate die for each part of every glove model.
there's also a different die for each size.
the cutter places a few pieces into a trank die.
then, he covers the leather with a resin block
to prevent damage from the press.
the press quickly cuts the pieces.
then, all the cut pieces are
sent to the sewing department.
the head seamstress makes a paper pattern.
this model has three rows of stitching
and three circular openings on the back of the hand.
she places the pattern on the leather
then uses talc to transfer the design.
she uses specialized tools to punch out the openings
and perforate the stitch holes.
then another seamstress sews the glove together.
she starts with the three rows of decorative stitching.
they form three raised lines
and stretch the round openings into ovals.
the rest of the glove is machine-sewn.
the seamstress turns the trank inside out
and stitches the fourchettes to the fingers.
then she sews on the thumb and the trim on the cuff.
she finishes off the cuff with an engraved rivet.
another seamstress
attaches a silk jersey lining to the inside of the glove.
there are also linings made of cashmere, wool,
fur, and polar fleece.
she hand stitches the lining to
the leather in each fingertip.
she turns the glove right-side out,
using a wooden tool to gently push out the fingers.
a final seamstress slips the
gloves onto heated hand forms.
she rubs the leather with a downward motion
to manually iron out all the wrinkles.
the packager wears a pair of cotton gloves to ensure
the leather remains pristine.
these leather gloves
were artisan-crafted using century-old techniques
and nothing more advanced than a simple sewing machine.
now they're ready to stylishly warm up even the coldest hands.