-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
>> narrator: the ancient greek
poet homer called olive oil
"liquid gold," and today a
little drizzle can still dazzle.
like fine wine, premium olive
oil can bring a complexity of
flavors to the table and create
a real taste sensation.
the roots of the olive tree
stretch far into the past.
for thousands of years, people
have harvested its fruit and
crushed it with stones to
extract the precious yellow oil.
in those early days, olive oil
wasn't just used in food, it
fueled lamps and was a medicinal
ointment.
today's thriving olive groves
are living proof that our
appetite for olive oil hasn't
waned.
when green olives turn a violet
red, they're ripe and ready for
harvest.
workers shake the olives off the
branches with vibrating rakes.
the olives fall onto nets spread
beneath the trees.
they funnel the harvested olives
into the factory.
they fall down a chute into a
large vat of pure water.
a hose suctions the olives and
water into a vibrating bin.
it separates out leaves and
twigs as the water drains away.
the cleaned olives now bounce
merrily on their way toward the
crusher.
a few centuries ago, the crusher
was a donkey-powered apparatus.
today, a motor drives
1,300-pound granite wheels to
grind the olives, pits and all,
into a paste.
once the paste reaches the
desired consistency, it's over
to a computerized system that
regulates the temperature of the
paste as an auger mixes it.
this separates the oil from the
paste, making it easier to
extract with this machine.
traditional extracting
techniques involve spreading the
paste on mats and then stacking
them to press out the oil.
this system is more high-tech.
rows of metal plates dip into
the paste and the oil adheres to
them.
a spin in a centrifuge separates
the residual paste from the
oil.
the result is virgin olive oil.
a sample of every batch goes to
the testing room where there's a
guy who has a nose for the job.
he inhales the olive oil's
aroma.
like a glass of fine wine, it
should have a certain bouquet
and should taste intensely
fruity.
if the olive oil makes the grade
with this tester, the entire
batch is ready for packaging.
the packaging process is
entirely automated, ensuring
it's all done hygienically.
a conveyor funnels these tins
into line for a filling.
a mechanized system then feeds
the olive oil directly from big
tanks into the tins.
a measuring device controls the
amount that goes into each one.
at the next station, equipment
spins and curls a metal disk
around the lip of the container
to put the bottom on the can.
the conveyor flips the can
around so it lands right side
up, ready to pack.
they package the premium-grade
oil in bottles.
they use dark glass to protect
the oil from the sun's
ultraviolet light, which could
cause olive oil to degrade and
lose intensity.
after an automated fill up, they
cap the threaded necks of the
bottles.
machinery press-fits and then
screws the caps on for an
airtight seal.
equipment then glues and applies
the labels to the bottles.
preserved and protected, this
olive oil is now on its way to
the store shelf and ultimately
to the table, where it's sure
to kick up the flavor factor.
>> narrator: the development of
the forklift truck in britain
early in the last century was an
uplifting event.
it was during the first world
war, and much of the country's
male workforce was on the battle
front, so the forklift literally
picked up where they left off to
keep the economy moving on the
home front.
the modern forklift has quite an
extensive reach.
that's because warehouses today
expand up rather than out to
stack more into a given space.
production starts with this
welding robot.
the robot uses computer smarts
to fuse steel parts together to
produce the truck body.
humans take over to weld
together rails for the lift
system's mainframe.
after a sleek paint job, the
truck body is ready for the
mechanics.
an emergency switch goes on the
front.
it will allow the forklift
operator to quickly cut the
engine's power.
then they assemble the lift's
hydraulic system, beginning with
the tank that holds the
hydraulic fluid.
they hook it up to the pump that
provides the required pressure.
they wire the pump so they can
later connect it to the
forklift's battery.
they nudge the pump into its
permanent position and bolt it
to the floor of the truck.
wiring for the lights, horn, and
lift sensors comes next.
then they slide a foot pedal
into place.
it both activates and brakes the
forklift truck.
at seven horsepower, this engine
may seem small, but it's enough
to move the truck and a load of
2.2 tons safely.
they check the oil and install a
bracket for the vehicle control
handle.
the handle is then connected to
a computerized system that
operates both the vehicle and
its hydraulic lift.
they slide the steering wheel
onto a shaft and make sure it's
solidly attached.
production then hits a turning
point as they power up the motor
and check the steering wheel
installation.
they flush filtered oil through
the hydraulic system that powers
the lift.
it's a cleansing process to
ensure no dirt can compromise
the hydraulics.
they test the computerized
controls for the lift and motor.
with the hydraulic cylinders
installed, they grease the
mainframe above them.
this makes it easier to slide
the inner rails onto the frame,
and later, the grease will also
improve the function of this
hydraulic lift.
they thread chains through the
mainframe and its inner rails.
these chains will work in
conjunction with lift cylinders
to elevate the load.
they roll the forklift's
carriage along grooves in the
rail system.
it's this carriage to which the
forks and other attachments will
be mounted.
a special machine now maneuvers
the lift into an upright
position.
then they wheel in the completed
truck.
they call this a marriage
because the truck and lift are
getting hitched.
they bolt the two subassemblies
together from the inside of the
empty battery compartment.
they then temporarily connect
the forklift to a battery in
order to move it down the line.
it's time for the forklift to
undergo a little corporate
branding with these company
decals.
they engrave a serial number
onto a metal plate.
it identifies the forklift for
warranty purposes.
they put a cover on the truck,
and this forklift is ready to go
to work.
the forks and the battery will
be installed on the worksite
because they're often specific
to the job.
but one thing's for certain --
this forklift is sure to carry a
lot of weight in the workplace.
>> narrator: seamless rolled
rings keep a lot of things
running in our world, so we
thought it was time to recognize
their contribution.
these wheels of steel are
essential components of engines,
power generators, and industrial
machinery, to name just a few
things.
and you could say they keep
things operating seamlessly.
seamless rolled rings are at the
center of the action in a lot of
machinery such as bearings,
gears, and connectors.
a seamless rolled ring starts
with one of these solid steel
billets.
a powerful magnet moves them
into a queue for production.
a saw with carbide-tipped teeth
cuts the billet into smaller
chunks.
a hydraulically powered claw
then takes the cut piece to a
furnace fired to 2,300 degrees
fahrenheit.
that's hot enough to soften the
steel for forging, but below its
melting point.
the steel turns bright yellow,
which indicates that it's ready
to be removed.
the operator places it in a
chamber where chains batter the
ends to break off scale formed
by the searing heat of the
furnace.
the claw then transfers it to an
1,100-ton press.
it squashes the steel slightly,
causing the scale on the sides
to crack and break off.
then it's over to a die.
a worker places a bit of coal in
the center of the hot steel
chunk.
the coal catches, generating a
powder that lubricates the
action of a 2,800-ton punch.
the punch pierces the center of
the steel and pushes it against
the walls of the die,
transforming the steel chunk
into a doughnut.
30 feet away, the operator
controls the gripper to lift out
the doughnut.
he then reactivates the punch to
knock out the last bit of metal
in the center hole.
by now, the steel has cooled
down quite a bit, so it's into
another furnace to bring it back
to forging temperature.
once it's yellow hot, this steel
doughnut is ready to be
transformed into a ring.
a mandrel pokes up through the
center.
it stabilizes the doughnut as a
conveyor slides it into position
for ring rolling.
the doughnut rotates, and
rollers press against it to
shape it into a thin, wide ring.
cone-shaped tools above and
below also spin against it to
establish the desired height.
the hot steel is easily
manipulated by the tools and
stretches like putty.
this process turns the doughnut
into a ring, and that's why they
call this ring rolling.
the change is truly dramatic.
a worker stamps a serial number
onto the rim.
next, a tool drags the ring
onto a conveyor which takes it
to a stacking device.
the rings cool from yellow to
orange.
soon, they'll be completely
cooled and ready to head into
another furnace, this time for
heat treating.
this tempering process relieves
the stresses in the steel caused
by all that rolling and
forging.
this makes the steel stronger
and more resilient.
once this ring has been cooled
and hardened, they position it
on a turntable, relying on a
special gauge to let them know
it's on the mark.
the ring revolves as a tool
peels off that sooty-looking
crust to reveal the glossy
substructure.
and they give the interior of
some rings the same treatment.
now these steel rings are ready
to take their place as
components in heavy equipment,
power plants, and even train
wheels because when it comes to
their capabilities, they're
definitely well-rounded.
>> narrator: in a sport with
steep challenges, proper
footwear is a must.
early ski boots were made of
leather, but when molded plastic
boots came along in the late
1960s, they offered a big
advantage -- stiffness.
stiffer boots meant better
control, and when you're heading
downhill fast, control is
definitely a good thing.
the modern ski boot transfers
the body's movements effectively
to the skis, and a little high
tech can't hurt when you're
trying to take your skiing
skills to new heights.
transforming these plastic chips
into a high-tech ski boot takes
some planning.
they design the boot on a
computer and simulate the
process of the chips being
melted and molded into the
shape.
like in the computer model, it
will take just seconds to turn
the chips into the outer shell
of the ski boot.
machinery lowers boot forms into
molds which clamp together with
a force of up to 550 tons.
pumps then inject the melted
chips into the space between the
molds and the forms.
the plastic hardens instantly,
and robotic arms pull the new
ski-boot shells off the forms.
two different plastics have been
used to give these shells
specific performance
characteristics.
equipment now stamps the brand
name and graphics onto the
shell.
the assembler rivets rubber
protectors to the sole of the
boot.
they'll interface with the ski's
bindings.
they'll also provide tread to
make the boot safer to walk
around in during those ski
breaks.
this ski-boot shell is now ready
for some buckles.
their location has been mapped
out during molding with little
indentations.
the indentations guide the
assembler as she rivets the
buckles to the boots.
meanwhile, another worker
focuses on the boot's plastic
cuff.
it's fresh out of the mold, so
he trims the edges to ensure
they're perfectly smooth.
he installs a reflector on the
inside to locate the skier in
the event of an avalanche.
this feature is found on
high-end models.
he attaches a long strap to the
back.
it's for adjusting the boot's
fit around the skier's calf and
shin.
now they're ready to attach the
cuff to the shell.
the fastener is adjustable to
align the cuff with the shape of
the skier's leg.
this adjustment is called
canting.
with the outer boot now
complete, production moves to
the liner.
a technician loads the patterns
into a computerized fabric
cutter, arranging them to
minimize waste.
the computer-guided blade goes
to work and cuts out the shapes.
they use a combination of
synthetic fabrics to help the
boot liner insulate the skier's
foot against cold and humidity.
after sewing the outer part
together, they glue two layers
to it.
the outside fabric and inner
padding are polyurethane
material and the inner layer is
polyester.
this special device presses the
glued fabrics together and
shapes them.
then it's over to the sewing
department where the glued seams
are stitched.
they add the sole and finish it
off with a waterproof fabric.
it has a special weave that
keeps the liner from sliding
around in the boot.
mechanical arms now hold open
the boot as the assembler slides
a liner into it.
once the liner is installed,
this ski boot is on its way to
the sporting-goods store, and,
inevitably, to higher ground.
the manufacturing process has
taken about an hour.
and these boots should be good
for years of plunging through
powder and mogul maneuvering.
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...