narrator: if you've ever
looked inside a wind-up watch
or a car's transmission,
you've seen a system of gears.
a gear is a wheel with teeth
that meshes with the teeth
of another gear
to transmit power
on a continuous basis.
combining gears
of different diameters
affects rotation speed
and force.
this factory makes gears
that go into transmissions
for industrial machines.
production begins with a large,
round bar of high-grade steel,
which contains
a certain amount of carbon
to make it even stronger.
an automated band saw
slices off a piece
that's the right thickness
for the size of gear
they're making.
this piece is called
a gear blank.
they mount the blank
on a computer-controlled blade.
as it spins,
a turret carrying a series
of carbide tools moves in.
one tool after another takes
its turn machining the blank
to a specific shape.
a shower of coolant
prevents overheating
when the jumbo drill
has its turn.
it bores a hole right through
the middle of the blank.
the last tool carves a groove
on the front of the blank.
this final bit of metal removal
lessens the gear's weight.
now the blank goes into
a computer-controlled mill.
the mill drills holes through
which lubrication will flow
when the gear is operating.
these holes also lighten
the gear's weight.
when the blank
comes off the mill,
they stamp it with the company
name and part number.
now for the gear's teeth.
a machine called a gear shaper
carves out the inner teeth --
the ones
lining the center hole --
with its titanium-coated cutter.
the machine's other components
keep the cutter's movement
correctly timed.
the number of teeth and tooth
size vary from gear to gear,
so for each model, the factory
has to fit the gear shaper
with a specific cutter.
now for the outside gear teeth.
the computer-controlled machine
that cuts them
is called a gear hobber.
the gear turns against it
as it cuts.
if the hobber would cut the full
depth of the teeth in one shot,
the cutter would chip,
so the gear keeps turning
around and around again
as the hobber cuts
a bit more with each pass,
until the teeth
are the right depth.
then the gear undergoes
a computerized inspection.
a probe scans the entire
surface, including every tooth.
it sends data to a computer,
which then analyzes
the dimensions
and ensures they meet
the engineering specifications.
gears that pass
this quality-control inspection
go into a furnace
for heat treatment.
this strengthens the steel.
when the furnace
reaches a certain temperature,
they inject carbon inside.
the gears absorb it, and the
steel strengthens even further.
a soaking in oil afterward
hardens the metal.
heat treatment, however,
distorts steel somewhat,
so each gear now goes to
a computer-controlled grinder.
it restores them
to very precise specifications
for bearings to fit properly.
this factory manufactures gears
in various sizes,
and not only in steel.
it also makes gears in material
such as nylon, aluminum,
brass, and stainless steel.
some gears have straight teeth,
others angled teeth,
which makes less noise
when turning.
gears are an essential component
in everything from watches
to heavy mining equipment,
keeping machinery going
at every turn.
narrator:
when it comes to wristwatches,
there's nothing quite like
a band made of genuine leather.
it has a classic look
that's versatile,
working with both casual
and formal attire.
and a leather watchband
is always comfortable
against the skin
because, unlike synthetics,
leather breathes.
these premium watchbands
are made of alligator,
a leather with an unmistakable
texture and shine.
the tannery dyes the
croc leathers in classic shades,
as well as in the latest
high-fashion colors and styles.
nearly all the production steps
are manual,
beginning with
cutting leather pieces
for the band's two straps.
every watchband model
requires a steel cutter
for each strap in every size.
now they coat the back side
of each piece with glue.
later, when it's almost dry,
they center a watchband core
onto it.
this flexible form
is made of synthetic material
reinforced with fiberglass.
using a machine
with a fine blade,
they make small cuts at the ends
to let the leather fold smoothly
over the form.
one side of each strap
attaches to the watch face
with a spring-loaded bar.
they mark exactly
where the bar goes,
then punch a tiny hole
for its tiny base.
next, they apply
super-strength glue
and fold the leather over
to encase the bar.
the glue dries instantly.
they now coat the rest
of the form with glue,
then lay it in a mold
that pushes the leather
against the edge tightly
so they can neatly
fold over the remainder.
now they run the open end
through a machine
that cuts a beveled edge.
next, they run a tiny sander
over the leather
on the back side.
this roughens the surface,
which will help
the leather backing adhere.
to make the loops
which go on the buckle strap,
they bevel the ends
of small leather strips.
they glue and fold them
into a loop,
making sure they're large enough
to fit around both straps.
one loop sits
directly below the buckle.
a glued-over flap of leather
locks it in position.
they press it flat with pliers
to ensure a good bond.
they machine-stitch each strap
with strong,
polyethylene-based thread.
to prevent unraveling, they melt
them right into the leather.
on the buckle end, they pierce
two holes for stitches
that reinforce
the locked-in first loop.
then they punch two holes
in the back of the second loop
for stitching to reinforce
its glued-together ends.
this loop has to be movable,
so they don't stitch it
to the band.
they heat the edge
of each strap.
the iron's rounded tip molds
an attractive, rounded edge.
using a heated tool again,
they widen the channel through
which the buckle will pass.
now they insert the buckle end
into a stamping press.
it cuts a slot
for the buckle's tongue.
a heat press burns the company's
name into the leather lining.
that same strap
then goes into a press,
which punches the sizing holes.
from here, both straps go off
to the buckle department.
random samples are subjected
to rigorous
quality-control testing.
this machine pulls
the ends of the strap
in opposite directions, with up
to nearly 50 pounds of tension,
far more than anyone would ever
apply to the watchband
when they pull to buckle it.
narrator:
vitrelle is a super-durable
dinnerware material
invented in the united states
in the early 1970s.
it's made of three layers
of glass, fused together.
vitrelle dishes
are thin and lightweight,
yet they're stronger
and far more break-resistant
than ordinary dinnerware.
in a perfect union
of form, function, and food,
this company serves up
vitrelle dinnerware
in several striking designs.
the dishes are made
of 65% recycled glass
from earlier production runs.
to make the other 35%
that's new glass,
the factory combines
several raw materials --
sand...
salt...
limestone...
feldspar...
and two more types of salt.
the exact proportions
are a closely guarded secret.
the ingredients
go into a furnace,
where a fiery
2,500 degrees fahrenheit
melts them into liquid glass.
it exits the furnace.
an extruder shapes it
into a three-ply sheet
that lands in a mold --
in this case, a plate mold.
a trimmer cuts off the excess,
while compressed air
blows down from above
to cool and solidify the glass.
a vacuum arm
then extracts each dish,
and the leftovers are recycled.
the dishes now undergo
what's called fire polishing.
each one passes through
a gas-oxygen flame,
which seals
the three layers of glass.
it also melts the outer rim,
smoothing and rounding out
the rough edge
created by the trimming.
oval dishes go on
a different fire polisher,
designed for an oval rim
rather than a round one.
now the conveyor system flips
each dish over for backstamping.
the bottom
of every vitrelle dish
has the trade name
and other information.
a silk-screen machine
applies the lettering.
then a gas-air flame
bakes the ink into the glass.
once that's done,
the conveyor system flips
the dishes right side up again.
to decorate the dishes,
a machine silk-screens
the design onto membranes.
robotic arms position a membrane
above each dish.
then a press head pushes the
membrane down onto the surface,
transferring the paint.
robotic arms
then move the dishes
back onto a conveyor belt.
certain dishes have a design
on the outside.
an automated silk-screen machine
applies the paint
directly to the surface.
the decorated dishes
now travel through a tunnel oven
for 5 1/2 minutes.
the nearly
1,500-degree fahrenheit heat
cures the enamel paint.
at the end of the ride,
a tempering process
that makes the glass stronger.
then, nozzles spray the dishes
in a soy-based silicone.
this wash-off coating prevents
scratches during packaging.
the factory subjects a sample
from each production run
to a 6 1/2-foot-drop test
and a rim-impact test.
the sample mustn't break, chip,
or crack...
...all to ensure
this stylish dinnerware
will withstand whatever
your household can dish out.
narrator: shears are typically
larger than scissors,
for heavier-duty cutting.
and you can insert
up to three fingers
in the handle's finger ring.
using more fingers
gives you a stronger grasp,
which translates into more
control and more cutting force.
these high-end shears
effortlessly
slice through produce,
snip fresh herbs,
and open packaging.
outside the kitchen,
they easily cut many materials,
including thin aluminum
and galvanized steel.
the secret to their strength?
blades made of stainless steel,
which contains
a minute amount of carbon.
to make them,
workers feed a bar of this
high-carbon stainless steel
into a press.
it stamps out blade shapes
called blanks.
stainless steel
can be heat-treated
to make it more durable
and corrosion-resistant.
but first, a furnace softens the
blanks for the forging process
that transforms them
into blades.
each blank
goes onto a forging dye
that has two
blade-shaped cavities.
one strike in each,
and the blank is a blade.
once it cools,
a trimming press
cuts off all the excess metal
around the perimeter.
heating and forging
tend to warp steel,
so another press makes the blade
perfectly flat
and straight again.
trimming the excess metal
leaves some rough areas,
so the next step is to smooth
the surface with a sanding belt.
to make the hole for the bolt
on which the blades pivot,
they drill a round hole
partway through...
then pierce a rectangular hole
through the rest.
you'll see why later on.
now the blades
undergo heat treatment --
first, to harden them, a slow
heating and rapid cooling,
then, to make them
tough and durable,
a reheat and slow cooling.
a grinder shapes the round area
next to the tang,
the term for the metal core
of the handle.
with a sanding belt,
they smooth out and blend
the adjacent corners.
here, two polishing wheels
give the surface
an upscale satin finish.
then an etching machine uses
electrically activated chemicals
to imprint the company's name
into the thumb-operated blade.
just one final step
before the blades are finished.
a computer-operated grinder
serrates the inside edge
of the thumb-operated blade.
workers now load
six blades at a time
into an injection-molding
machine.
the machine shoots molten
plastic into the cavities,
then rapidly cools the material
until it solidifies.
each blade exits the machine
with a molded handle
firmly encasing the tang.
now for the final assembly --
first they drive a bolt
with a rectangular head
into the pivot hole
of the finger-operated blade.
then they add
the thumb-operated blade
and press the bolt again
into its final position.
a self-locking, hexagonal nut
secures the bolt
from underneath.
an automatic tightener
does the initial fastening.
then workers do the final
tension adjustment manually.
the final step
is to grind the excess plastic
off the handle stops.
this enables the blade to close
fully and in perfect alignment.
so, why the rectangular bolt?
watch closely.
it allows you,
with just one simple twist,
to separate the blades
for cleaning
and then reassemble them.
now, that's cutting-edge design.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications