narrator: the need to hammer things
goes back to prehistoric times
when early man used stones as tools.
the modern hammer evolved
from those first crude implements.
but with its forged-steel design
and user-friendly handle,
the hammer of today is strikingly different.
no one-hit wonder,
the modern hammer is made to endure.
it maintains its structural integrity
despite repeated pounding and pulling.
it starts with a thick steel bar.
an automated system loads it into an induction furnace
set at more than 1,800 degrees fahrenheit.
the fierce heat makes the steel malleable.
this forge-hammer pounds the hot steel
into a series of hammer-shaped compressions.
then it's into a punch cutter
which trims the ragged edges of the forged steel.
the cutoffs go into a bin for recycling.
a worker sandwiches the newly trimmed shape
in a press that fine-tunes the shape.
the hammer is cooled down on this revolving rack.
then they load the hammers into a tumbler,
along with tiny bits of steel --
so tiny, they're hard to see.
but their impact will be very noticeable.
as they toss about,
the bits rub off scale and debris on the hammers,
for an impressive cleanup.
they then clamp the hammer in a device
that spins it against abrasive belts
to contour the striking head.
these belts also bevel the hammer's head.
it's a safety feature.
the sloped edge is less likely to chip nails on impact.
now this jagged cutting wheel
carves ridges into the hammer's head.
the device repositions the hammer
so the wheel can cut it in a different direction
to create a grid.
this surface is less likely to slip off nails on impact.
next comes the tempering process.
the hammers plunge into a very hot bath.
then they dip them in quenching oil,
which cools the metal so quickly, it hardens.
now it's time for another polish.
this one makes the steal gleam.
it's the finishing touch.
next, they assemble leather rings in a tray --
25 to each one.
they place plastic rings at each end
to break up the look
and buttress it with a pronged metal disk.
they slide the tray into a compartment
and insert the end of the hammer
in the rings.
a hydraulic tool rams it through them,
encasing the handle in a neat wrap
that's comfortable to grasp.
they secure the end of the hammer in a clamp,
and then a spinning tool flattens the prongs
that protrude from the metal plate,
riveting it to the leather wrap.
then, using a series of sanding belts,
they smooth the rough leather for a seamless finish.
this is a tank of heavy lacquer
in which they immerse the hammers repeatedly.
when it dries,
the lacquer will give the leather wrap
a tough, sleek finish,
and the leather will look like one textured piece
instead of many.
for a different kind of handle,
they pour liquid vinyl on the hammer shaft
that's encased in a mold.
the vinyl adheres to the hammer
as it hardens.
the mold leaves a dimpling impression
that will make the hammer easier to grip.
they grind off the hardened vinyl spillover
and contour the handle.
these handles are preferred by some tradesmen
because the vinyl is an antishock material.
they stamp the model number onto it.
paint guns mist the steel with lacquer
for a little rustproofing.
the hammers then travel through an oven,
which cures the lacquer.
after they stamp
the company logo onto the vinyl,
each hammer is visually inspected.
only then does it get a seal of approval.
it takes about a day to make a hammer,
and with the different handle wraps and sizes,
they've really nailed it.
narrator: the swiss call this cheese "fromage d'alpage,"
which means "cheese from the high-mountain pastures."
master cheesemakers retreat to their chalets
high in the swiss alps to make this special cheese.
these individuals follow a tradition of cheesemaking
that goes back to the middle ages.
fromage d'alpage is produced by cheesemakers
who bring their cows high
into the alps for five months --
to this region of gstaad, switzerland.
in the morning, they milk their
cows for about seven minutes
using an automatic milking machine.
each cow produces around 2 1/2 gallons of milk,
which contains water, protein, and fat.
12 hours later, he removes the fat,
which rises to the surface.
he adds a starter culture,
which helps preserve the milk.
a wood fire then heats the milk
for 20 minutes
at a constant 86 degrees fahrenheit.
he then adds an enzyme called rennet
and more starter culture to the milk.
after about 40 minutes, these active ingredients
coagulate the milk into cheese curd.
he cuts the solidifying curd into smaller pieces.
to maintain an even heat,
he keeps blending the curd and the liquid together.
he continues mixing and cutting the curd
until the active ingredients
separate the curd from the liquid,
called whey.
to make cheese,
he will use only the grains of curd.
an electric mixer then completes the separation.
he washes his arms and hands thoroughly,
because any impurities in the cheese would ruin it.
after heating the mixture for 20 minutes again,
the curd is now the perfect texture
for making cheese.
using cheesecloth,
they remove the grains of curd.
what started out as 80 gallons of milk
will end up producing only 66 pounds of cheese.
the cheesemaker stuffs the sack
of curd into a mold
and works out some of the whey.
he then puts three molds filled with curd
into a wooden press.
and using a wooden block
that distributes the pressure evenly,
he squeezes out more of the whey.
to get all the excess liquid out of the curd,
he turns each 22-pound piece of cheese over
so he can press it again.
too much liquid in the cheese
would affect its shape and quality,
so he does this a few times,
then leaves them in the press overnight.
the next morning, he trims off the excess cheese
created around the edge by the pressing mold.
like every step in this cheesemaking process,
this work is also done by hand.
he soaks the cheese in salt water for 24 hours
to conserve, harden, and intensify its taste.
the cheese then goes through a salting and maturing process
that lasts six months.
during this time, they flip each piece of cheese often
so it ages evenly.
after a final surface cleaning,
they put the 22-pound pieces on their sides to air-dry.
they'll remain edible for at least 10 years.
but, of course, you don't have to live in the alps
to enjoy the taste of swiss cheese.
narrator: when roller skates were invented by the dutch
in the 18th century,
they put a whole new spin on skating.
before that, people could only skate on iced surfaces,
so the sport had definite seasonal limitations.
the wheels of those first roller skates
were wooden spools.
but today's manufacturers
have come up with some better tricks to make them.
roller skates have improved by leaps and bounds.
the wheels are made of strong, lightweight polyurethane,
so there's nothing to hold you back.
they start with the shoes.
a die press punches out leather patterns,
called quarters --
four per shoe.
they place one quarter under a foil strip,
and a hot die stamps it
with the manufacturer's trademark.
then, using a template,
they mark the locations
where components are to be sewn...
...such as these racing stripes.
they stitch them onto the leather quarters
in two rows.
the four leather quarters have been partially pieced together.
here, the operator finishes the job,
sewing the shoe's outer layer to the liner.
she then stitches the rest of the liner to the shoe,
while a little blade on the machine
trims the excess leather.
now the roller-skate shoe really takes shape,
as she folds the leather in two
and sews the toe.
this machine punches holes
and inserts eyelets for the shoelaces.
this machine, called a laster,
glues the shoe to an insole.
they insert a shoe and insole together
into the laster.
its nozzles coat the toe of the insole with cement
while pinchers pull the leather around it.
then automated arms press the leather onto the insole,
bonding them together.
another machine then nails
the rest of the shoe around the insole,
and a worker pounds them in further.
a final laster
folds the edge of the shoe around the heel
and then drives nails into it.
the hot lights of this machine activate cement
that's been applied
to an outsole and the shoe body.
this allows the two to adhere.
as the cement dries,
this hydraulic machine presses the outsole to the shoe
to aid the adhesion.
they stitch the outsole to the shoe for reinforcement.
after all, roller-skate shoes
have to hold up to the rigors of the sport.
they insert nails into holes
of this heel-attaching machine...
then position a fiberboard and leather heel on it,
followed by the roller-skate shoe.
mechanical drivers thrust the nails up into the shoe,
firmly attaching the heel.
an operator then forces the rubber sole
against a circular cutter
to remove the excess material.
next, they screw a polyurethane toe stop
into a skate frame.
they drill through holes in the frame
to make corresponding holes in the shoe.
they push bolts into the holes.
then, using a pneumatic socket wrench,
they bolt the skate frame to the shoe.
the bolts are too long, so they cut them down to size
with a special breakoff tool.
they slide polyurethane cushions
onto kingpins,
then install bearings in the hub of each wheel.
a carousel conveyor delivers the wheel and bearings
to a tool that presses them together.
with the wheels now linked by axles,
these skates are almost ready to roll.
they mount each wheel assembly on a kingpin,
then install a second cushion ring.
these cushions can be adjusted by the skater
to change the feel of the skate.
a tweak to the axle
confirms the wheels spin freely.
it takes about four days
for the experts to make a pair of roller skates.
that's somewhat less time than it takes
for the average person to master using them.
narrator: colored pencils come in basic color packages
for schoolchildren,
upgraded sets for architects and other professionals,
and elaborate collections of shades
for the serious artist.
it isn't so much the color variety
that determines the quality,
but the pigment concentration in the lead.
the core of a colored pencil
doesn't actually contain any lead.
it's composed of pigments, minerals, and binding agents.
this company invented
a unique type of colored pencil.
the lead composition is such that it allows you
to brush on a bit of water after you draw
to create the effect of watercolor paints.
colored pencils start with a combination of pigments.
every shade has a specific pigment recipe.
they produce a large quantity of one shade at a time.
following that color's recipe,
they meticulously weigh
the different portions of ingredients.
then they boil a specific quantity of water and additives
and add binding agents --
a secret blend of gums, resins, or waxes.
the ingredients expand in hot water,
forming a paste.
workers then mix the pigments into this paste.
the next machine processes the paste into fine chunks,
intensifying the color.
the chunks move by conveyor belt
with a cylinder that compresses them,
then feeds them into an extrusion machine.
the extruder squeezes the paste
in a continuous stream
that's the diameter of the pencil lead.
in a top-secret process,
the next machine chops this long lead
into pencil-length leads.
but the leads can't write just yet.
they're bathed in a vat
filled with a mixture of chemical waxes.
these waxes coat and impregnate the leads --
in this case, red ones.
wax is a color-delivery vehicle.
as you write, it rubs off and adheres to the paper,
taking pigment with it.
with the leads now finished,
the factory subjects random samples
to quality control testing,
including a break test and a durability test
in which each lead
must yield 100 yards of writing.
this company makes its pencil bodies
from cedar wood.
this machine carves grooves for the leads,
then coats the surface with a thin layer of glue.
the planks pass under a wheel that places the leads...
...then through another machine
that slips a second grooved plank on top.
the next machine carves the hexagonal shape,
then slices the pencils apart.
one at a time,
the pencils shoot through a vat
of colored varnish.
their exterior is now the same color as the lead inside.
once the varnish dries,
a heat stamp burns the company name
and color number into the wood,
filling the lettering with colored film.
then the pencils roll across an abrasive wheel,
sharpening as they go.
the unsharpened end gets a cap of varnish,
either in white
or the same shade as the pencil lead.
the factory's equipment feeds the appropriate colors
to the packaging area.
as the pencils slide into their grooved tray,
workers visually inspect each and every one.
from pigments and planks to an artistic medium,
the story behind the making of colored pencils
is hardly black and white.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...