-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: in the 21st century,
there's more than one way
to chase down a perpetrator.
the electric stand-up vehicle
goes where traditional police
and security cars can't --
sidewalks, parks,
shopping malls, even airports.
the officer stands
for better visibility.
for a suspect,
there may be nowhere to run.
this electric three-wheeler
is the latest thing
on the police beat.
not only can it travel in areas
that are inaccessible to cars,
but its environmental footprint
is lighter
than a regular police cruiser.
it's energy efficient
and it generates
no local pollutants.
production starts
with the vehicle's frame.
an employee assembles
the tube steel parts
and welds them together.
the next worker attaches
the vehicle's
control-board panel
to the welded frame.
he inserts the steering shaft
into the column
and slides a plastic collar
onto the bottom of the shaft.
he secures the collar
with screws
and tightens
the adjustment mechanism.
he installs the second collar
on the upper part
of the steering shaft.
the two collars
will stabilize the shaft
to keep the front wheel
of the vehicle straight.
he plugs
the electric motor cable
into the control panel.
next, another member of the team
sprays a uniform layer
of a gel coat
onto a two-part mold
of the vehicle chassis.
the gel will act
as a release agent
for the finished chassis.
they make the chassis
from fiberglass.
he sprays it evenly
into the crevices of the molds.
he presses out air bubbles
using a rubber roller.
the fiberglass dries
and solidifies,
taking the shape of the mold.
the surface is smooth,
but there are some ragged bits
around the edges.
those are sanded.
he cuts out a slot
in the upper part of the chassis
for a police warning light.
finally, the chassis gets a coat
of automotive-grade white paint.
he paints the wheel wells black,
and with that,
the outer chassis is complete.
there's an interior panel
and it's made
of fiberglass, too.
a member of the team mounts it
to the inside
of the steel-frame assembly.
he then secures the outer panel
to the vehicle frame.
this electric
three-wheel vehicle is ready
for the rear-wheel hubs
and brake rotors.
he clamps brake calipers
to the rotors.
the wheels are next.
the rear ones
are motorcycle wheels.
for the front,
they use a golf-cart wheel.
he equips the wheel
with a pulley system
to transfer energy
from the motor.
he installs
the 1-horsepower motor
and attaches the pulley to it.
the motor is the size
of a lunch bucket,
but can pull up to 450 pounds
and reach 20 miles per hour.
he hooks up the front wheel to
testing equipment and powers up.
it evaluates
the motor speed and noise.
it also detects any undue strain
or wheel wobbling.
satisfied
with the front-wheel assembly,
he installs it on the vehicle.
he wires, and then attaches
the throttle and brake control
to the handlebar.
they carpet the floor
with non-slip rubberized foam
and then slide
the two rechargeable batteries
into their respective
compartments.
the charge time
is three to four hours.
next, this grab handle
gives the driver
something extra to hang on to.
they equip the vehicle
with warning lights
and a high-beam headlight.
this electric patrol vehicle
has been six hours
in the making,
and it's now ready for a spin.
narrator:
nowadays, you don't have to wait
for your favorite fruit
to be in season.
you can buy it year-round
in the freezer section
of your local supermarket.
frozen fruit
is useful to have on hand
for baking,
for making fruit salads
or smoothies,
to use as a topping,
or to eat as a healthy snack.
timing is everything.
for example, strawberries,
when sold fresh,
are picked
well before they're ripe
so they won't spoil
before reaching store shelves
as much as a week later.
but if the berries
are for the freezer section,
they're harvested
when fully ripe.
that state of perfection
will be frozen in time
within 36 hours.
farm workers
pick the berries by hand
and trim them
right in the field
with one swipe over
a sharp stainless-steel blade.
within 90 minutes of harvesting,
the strawberries
are on their way
by refrigerated truck
to the nearby processing plant
for cleaning, sorting,
and quick freezing.
first stop
on the processing line,
a bath in fresh water
to remove field dirt.
this wheel gently submerges
every last strawberry.
then, a shower
of clean rinse water.
followed by a spray rinse
with highly-chlorinated water
to sanitize the berries.
next, eagle-eyed workers
pick out and discard
any bruised
or under-ripe berries.
the rest receive a final rinse
en route to the freezing tunnel.
temperature --
-34 degrees fahrenheit.
the cooling coils
contain liquid ammonia --
a refrigerant commonly used
for industrial-scale freezing.
inside the tunnel,
where the frigid air circulates
at high speed,
the berries freeze
in about 20 minutes.
upon exiting, they ride through
a sorting machine.
the smaller berries
drop through narrower gaps
between the rollers
near the top,
the medium-size ones
through wider gaps partway down,
while the larger ones
continue to the bottom.
these peaches,
also handpicked when ripe,
go through the same cleaning
process as the strawberries.
first a bath, then a shower.
then a sanitizing rinse
with chlorinated water.
after workers
pick out leaves, twigs,
and any less-than-perfect fruit,
a sorting machine sorts
the peaches by size --
small, medium, and large --
sending each size
to a separate conveyor belt.
each belt
leads to a different line
of stainless-steel
pitting machines,
adjusted for the size
of the incoming fruit.
first, the machine
places the peaches stem-down.
next, a knife cuts the peach
in half along its natural line.
then mechanical jaws
grab the stone inside
and dislodge it by twisting
the two halves of the peach
in opposite directions.
each machine can pit
90 peaches per minute,
so the only way to see
that action is in slow motion.
all the peach halves and stones
coming out of the pitters
tumble
onto a vibrating conveyor.
the stones
fall through the holes
while the peaches,
larger than the holes,
continue on.
a conveyor flips them
cut-side up
so that workers can inspect
and remove any stone fragments.
the next conveyor gradually
lines them up in single file
to enter the slicing machines.
the slicer blades cut each half
into four to six pieces,
depending on what format
the customer ordered.
then the slices
go into the freezing tunnel.
peach slices
take slightly longer
than strawberries to freeze --
about 25 minutes.
to prevent the frozen fruit
from defrosting,
the air temperature
in the packaging area
is a frigid
39 degrees fahrenheit.
an automated scales weighs out
the per-package quantity,
then drops the berries
into a retail bag.
the machine
then heat seals the bag
and deposits it
on the final conveyor,
which goes
to the pre-shipping freezer.
only 15 minutes have passed
since the fruit was frozen,
and just 24 hours
since it was field picked.
narrator: liquid refreshment
can leave its mark on the table.
coasters come between
the glass and that.
but two centuries ago,
coasters were mainly placed
on the rim of the glass
to keep out flies.
made of felt,
they unfortunately spread germs,
so the cardboard coaster
was invented
to improve hygiene
on the pub scene.
beverage coasters
protect the table
and are also a marketing tool.
raise the glass, and you'll see
advertising catchphrases
and promotional graphics.
in fact, some bar hoppers
consider coasters pub art
and accumulate vast collections.
production
at this facility in germany
starts with spruce wood.
in this case, it's from
the black forest nearby.
they spray the wood with water
to moisten the bark.
then it's into a tumbler
that tosses the wood logs.
as they knock against
each other, the bark peels off.
the de-barked wood
exits onto a conveyor with slots
to correctly orient it for entry
into a massive grinder.
inside,
chains press the wood logs
against the grinding stone,
shredding them into chips.
water flows
over the grinding stone
to cool it
and carry away the chips,
which are then mixed into a mash
that has a porridge-like
consistency.
it's pure wood pulp.
they now add leftover product
from previous beer-coaster
production to the pulp.
this will be used to make
the middle layer
of the beer coasters.
finally, they mix residual paper
from the manufacturer
of magazines and envelopes
with water.
this creates
a lighter-colored pulp.
it will be used
for the printable surfaces
of the beer coaster.
they spray the pulp onto a mesh
that drains water from it.
the fibrous wood core
goes between the layers
of the lighter pulp.
spigots apply a mix
of wheat starch and water
that acts as a glue
between the layers.
off the mesh conveyors now,
the pulp board
travels between cylinders
that squeeze out the moisture.
more heated cylinders dry it.
knives now cut the board
into large rectangles
sized for the coaster-printing
and cutting machinery.
this specialty cardboard
is known as wood-pulp board.
it's lightweight
yet highly absorbent.
next it's over
to the printing department
to put the beer-coaster artwork
on the wood-pulp board.
they use offset printing --
a process that involves
more revolving cylinders.
color cylinders pick up ink
and transfer it
to the printing cylinders.
from there, the image goes
to a rubber-wrapped cylinder
that then prints it
onto the sheets.
a print specialist scrutinizes
the print job close up
with a magnifying glass.
he checks the color and clarity
of the images
and confirms that they're
correctly positioned
on the sheet.
the borders of the images
must line up
with the grid of blades
on the die-cutting machinery.
if the alignment
is even slightly off,
every coaster on the sheet
would be ruined
as the die cutter
punches out the coasters,
dozens of them in one swoop.
the coasters end up
over little chutes,
and pushers give them a nudge.
they fall down the chutes
and land neatly
on a pallet below.
the coasters stack up,
and when there are 100 or so
in each pile,
they're ready for packaging.
machinery shrink wraps
the stacks,
and they're ready
for the thirsty masses.
this factory
can produce and package
10 million offset-printed
beer coasters every day,
so there should be no shortage
at cocktail hour.
they also print coasters
using a centuries-old technology
known as letterpress.
blank coasters drop down
into the machine.
a rolling wheel presses each
coaster against an ink plate.
it's a system
that both prints the image
and embosses it
on the cardboard.
it's a difference
you can both see and feel.
letterpress production
is lower volume than offset,
generating
100,000 coasters per day.
for coasters, the design
possibilities are endless.
just raise a glass and enjoy.
narrator: a door handle
is a decorative detail
that delivers tremendous bang
for the buck.
it's quite inexpensive,
yet through its design,
material, and finish,
contributes immensely
to defining the style
of a space,
from traditional
to ultra modern.
these hand-forged iron handles
open the door to a rustic
english country decor.
while the handle itself is iron,
the backplate behind it
is steel.
a computer-guided water machine
cuts the backplate
out of a 3-millimeter-thick
steel sheet.
the machine
slices through the steel
not with a blade or saw,
but with a concentrated
high-pressure jet of water.
the water contains a tiny amount
of a super-fine abrasive
and cuts through the steel
with 2,000 times the pressure
of a car tire.
the jet cuts the contour
of the backplate,
then holes for the key,
the mechanism, and the screws,
which affix the plate
to the door.
next, with a beveling machine,
they cut a neat angle
on all four sides
of the backplate.
this smooths the sharp edges
and gives the backplate
a finished look.
meanwhile,
on a computer-guided lave,
a knife progressively shapes
a round steel bar
into the main component
of the door-handle mechanism --
the inner barrel.
the next tool bores a hole in it
to receive the spindle --
a bolt
that runs through the door,
connecting the handles
on either side.
to make the handle,
a blacksmith heats up
an iron bar
in the 1,600-degree heat
of a forge
and hammers it
to a tapered point.
then he repeatedly reheats
and works the iron,
hammering it some more
and bending it
against a steel forming jig.
with each bend,
the handle comes closer
to the final shape.
once the blacksmith
has completed his work
and the iron handle has cooled,
they drill a hole
to receive the mechanism.
then with another tool,
they angle the edges
of the hole.
this increases the surface area
to which they now weld
the mechanism's inner barrel.
the larger the welded area,
the stronger the weld.
the welder places
both components
in a positioning jig
to get the proper alignment,
then welds them together.
he removes the assembly
from the jig,
flips it,
and welds from the other side.
they grind the weld lines flat,
rendering them unnoticeable.
if the handle is supposed to
have a hammered finish,
this is when they create
that texture
with, you guessed it, a hammer.
now they heat
the handle assembly
and the steel backplate
in the forge,
then dip them
in a vat of beeswax.
this protects against rust
when used indoors.
with the main components
now ready,
final assembly can begin,
starting with the mechanism.
they slip a nylon washer,
then a steel spring
over the inner barrel.
next, they grease the outer
barrel made of forged iron
and place it
over the inner barrel.
the washer in between
the barrels eliminates friction
when they move
against each other.
this prevents the barrel
from wearing out and squeaking.
they install a tab washer
made of nickel-plated steel.
this tab restricts
the barrel's rotation
so that it doesn't
simply spin around and around.
this high-strength
steel locking clip holds
the inner and outer barrels
and that important tab washer
in place.
now that the handle
and mechanism are complete,
all that remains is to align
backplate to handle
and secure it in position
with screws.
each retail package contains
two handles
and two backplates --
one for each side of the door.
also in the box,
the steel spindle
that goes through the door,
connecting the barrels
so that the handles turn
in unison
to retract the latch
and open the door.
while their mechanics
are hidden from view,
these hand-forged handles are
certainly a sight to be seen.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...