narrator: when it comes to construction,
whether you're a seasoned pro or a do-it-yourselfer,
having the right tools makes the job easier.
sawhorses support the piece of wood you're cutting,
and a toolbox keeps your implements
organized and portable.
sawhorses are always sold in pairs
because you need two under a piece of wood
to stabilize it for cutting.
by pulling the hinged tray upward,
the sawhorse collapses flat for transport and storage.
this model is made from pellets
of an exceptionally strong
type of polypropylene plastic.
a vacuum system draws the pellets into
an injection-molding machine.
the machine melts them
then shoots the liquid into a mold.
it takes about a minute for the liquid to solidify,
at which point the mold automatically opens,
and an articulated robotic arm removes the parts --
for each sawhorse, two halves, the legs, and two panels
which form the collapsible hinged tray
that holds those legs open.
the robot drops those parts
at the first assembly station,
where a worker joins each panel to a sawhorse half
and applies non-slip footpads.
these pads help keep the sawhorse stable
and protect the floor from scratches.
the worker lays out the parts
for both sides of the sawhorse
in a positioning fixture
then activates the press a couple of times
to snap the parts together.
at the next station, a worker inserts ribbed rubber pads
into molded holes on top of each sawhorse half.
these anti-slip pads help hold
large pieces of wood steady on the sawhorse.
next, he lays both sawhorse halves on the work table
and with a tool called a stamping arm,
snaps the two panels together.
this forms a strong hinge,
which opens and collapses the tray.
the sawhorse is now finished
and heads to the packaging station.
there, a worker stacks two sawhorses,
then, with a foot pedal, activates a machine
which binds them with a plastic strap.
then she tapes on a wrap-around label.
have tools, will travel.
this two-piece toolbox
consists of a large storage tub on the bottom
and a spacious toolbox on top.
like a rolling suitcase,
it has two large polypropylene wheels
with molded-on rubber treads
and a collapsible pull handle.
a toolbox doesn't have to withstand pressure
bearing down on it, so it's made of standard,
rather than high-strength, polypropylene.
the injection-molding process is the same.
the storage tub, the toolbox bottom,
and the toolbox lid are each molded separately.
in the assembly area,
workers apply an adhesive label on the front of the toolbox
then install the latches for locking the lid.
the latches slide into molded slots.
after inserting a removable tray,
workers install the lid
with a few strikes of
a non-marring urethane hammer.
both lid and latches snap in easily
because the polypropylene is still hot and flexible.
once it cools and becomes rigid,
the lid and latches can't dislodge.
to assemble each wheel,
workers position a star nut
and steel axle into the wheel,
then, with an assembly ram,
press the axle into the star nut to lock the parts together.
they snap a wheel onto each side
of the tub portion of the toolbox,
then, with a press, force the wheels
into their final locked position.
once the toolbox and tub portions
are each separately assembled,
workers hang a parts tray on the rim of the tub
then sit the toolbox on the tray
and lock it in place with two large side hinges.
and that completes construction of this workshop on wheels.
narrator: traditionally, sorbets have been dished up
between courses to refresh the palate,
but served in a squeezed-up pop,
a sorbet becomes a snack you can grab anytime --
no need for scoops, spoons, or dishes.
just squeeze the sorbet out of the paper sleeve.
now that's refreshing.
a long favorite of foodies, fruit sorbet has gone mainstream
with these squeeze-up pops.
more fun than a few scoops in a dish,
sorbet pops are also lower in calories
than a lot of other snacks.
they start with freeze-dried rice syrup.
they pour it into a mixing vat
that's a mega version of a home blender.
they add strawberry puree.
this is the main ingredient of the sorbet pops.
the berries were pulped within 12 hours of harvest.
the next ingredient is cane sugar.
it's followed by strawberry essence --
compounds extracted from the berries
for more intense flavor.
they turn on the tap for the final ingredient --
water.
it's time to close the lid
and power up this industrial blender.
the mixer has four blades that turn at a high velocity.
they whip up the sorbet ingredients
to the consistency of a fruit smoothie.
the sorbet mixture then flows into refrigerated pipes
that chill the mixture to 40 degrees fahrenheit.
the pipes wind around the factory
and finally deliver it to holding tanks.
inside, an agitator swirls the chilled mixture
to maintain
the smoothie-like consistency.
once a tank is full,
a technician tests the acidity
and the level of suspended sugars in the mixture.
if the levels are right,
they transfer the mixture into a continuous freezer.
it pumps air into the sorbet mix,
and it churns and scraps it
against the freezing-cold walls of the machine.
cool water runs through the motor
to keep it from overheating as it freezes the sorbet.
this is only a partial freezing to keep the sorbet
soft enough to be pumped into the paper squeeze tubes.
a device with little robotic fingers
pries the papers tubes from a stack
and deposits them in slots in a moving tray.
the tubes are in position to receive
the partially frozen sorbet,
and because the sorbet is only partially frozen,
it is able to now flow through conduits.
frozen solid, it couldn't make the journey
to the squeeze tubes.
as the sorbet is pumped into the paper sleeves,
its temperature is critical.
it is precisely 37.8 degrees fahrenheit.
one degree cooler
and it would be too thick to pump.
a degree warmer, and ice crystals would form
during the final freezing.
the next machine collects foil lids from a pack,
using rubber heads with tiny magnets in the center.
it deposits the lids onto the sorbet-filled tubes.
the foil lids stick to the glue-coated rims.
this line fills 280 paper sleeves
with fruit sorbet per minute.
that's just under 17,000 per hour.
an iron applies heat to the lids to further melt the glue
and provide a water-tight seal.
it happens fast
so the sorbet doesn't have time to start melting.
sealed and partially frozen,
the sorbet pops cascade into crates.
each one holds about 100 pops,
so they don't need to keep count.
and then it's into the blast freezer,
also know as the shock freezer.
fans circulate the cold air
to rapidly lower the temperature of the sorbet pops,
bringing it down to -24 degrees fahrenheit.
this fast freezing prevents
the formation of large ice crystals
that would damage
the consistency and flavor of the sorbet pops.
out of the freezer,
a mechanized arm grabs and opens cardboard boxes.
a pusher shoves the sorbet pops into the boxes.
and they're ready to grab and squeeze.
narrator: the big yellow school bus
on the road to an education.
it all started in the 19th century
with horse-drawn trucks known as kid hacks.
the word "hack" was short for hackney carriage.
in the 20th century, they were motorized
and became known as school buses.
every school day,
children across north america wait for the school bus.
appearance-wise, it's hard to miss.
big and yellow, it is deliberately conspicuous,
designed to stand out in traffic
so other drivers slow down and take notice.
manufacturing starts with a support structure --
the steel underframe.
they arrange several short rails
down the top of two long frame rails.
these cross rails will link the long rails
and provide strategic support.
using the lift, they raise the long rails,
and the cross rails slide into position
just under the rims of the long ones.
now, in a fixture that pins the rails together,
workers bolt them together.
with the school-bus underframe assembled, they roll in
two enormous wheel axles complete with brakes.
overhead cables lift the bus frame
and workers guide it into place on the axles.
they attach the axles to the frame
with metal brackets, shackles, and spacers where needed.
the chassis is ready for the engine.
they lower it onto the front of the frame
and secure it with bolts.
the school-bus engine packs a lot of power.
it's diesel-fueled with six cylinders.
next up is the front cal assembly,
which includes the instrument panel
and steering column.
a workers wires the steering wheel
to the controls in the column and slides it into place.
they mount the tires and rims --
four on the back axle to handle the heavier passenger load
and two on the front.
using a multi-pronged tool,
the worker tightens numerous nuts
to fasten the wheels to the axles.
they now encase the engine with a fiberglass hood.
the hood has been pre-painted
and equipped with cross-view mirrors and headlights.
they bolt it to the vehicle frame,
and after adding antifreeze and coolant,
the bus is technically drivable.
they roll it over to a test station
to check the brakes.
the wheels turn on rollers so the bus runs in one spot.
a computer monitors the performance
of both the front and back brakes
as a driver applies them.
they now move on to build the school-bus body.
the body starts with the floor.
they unwind double-sided galvanized steel
into a machine that slices it into panels.
it also cuts holes to be used for assembly.
a forming machine folds the sides
to create support beams.
two more steel beams will really stiffen the floor panel.
a worker positions those beams on the panel,
and an automated machine welds them to it.
it feeds the floor panel to the welder incrementally
so it can spot weld down the length of the beams.
it takes dozens of welds to solidly secure
the steel supports.
and with those reinforcements, the floor panel is complete.
it's ready for assembly.
workers arrange several panels upside down
in a precise configuration.
then it's into a second automated welder
that joins them to make one school-bus floor.
after manually welding pockets for wheels,
a machine called the floor flip picks up the bus floor
and turns it rightside up.
they're now ready to build the passenger compartment,
so stay tuned.
narrator: a school bus transports precious cargo --
children.
to hold the average bus together,
they use an incredible 6,100 rivets, bolts, and screws
and make a total of 840 welds.
for the maker of school buses,
there's strength in those numbers.
to build the frame
for the school-bus walls and ceiling,
they bend steel beams into bow shapes.
a hydraulic machine with pushers does the job in seconds,
achieving an exact radius.
the bows will serve as ribs for the school-bus body.
they make several bows for each bus.
the precise number depends on the bus size and capacity.
workers plug the ends of the bows
into holes in steel rails and secure them with bolts.
they weld lateral supports higher up,
and the cage-like skeleton
of the school bus takes shape.
they're now ready to build on this framework.
they attach
the metal windshield surround.
the team then moves
the steel side sheets and skirting into place.
they secure these panels with super-strong adhesive
and numerous rivets.
using cables and nylon straps,
they pull steel sheets to the roof structure
to make them conform to the contours.
the steel is 20-gage --
a grade that's flexible enough to be easily bent.
the cables hold the steel panels tightly to the roof structure
while the workers rivet them to it.
the number of rivets
and the strength of the joints
are among many government safety standards
the school bus must meet.
working from the inside,
they glue fiberglass insulation into the pockets of the cage
to keep the bus warm in winter and cool in summer.
the insulation will also muffle road noise
and absorb some of the student chatter
for a quieter ride.
the team installs steel panels on the ceiling.
these panels have tiny perforations
to allow sound to escape into the insulation.
they tape up the windows and doors
and sand some areas
as they now prepare to paint the exterior of the bus.
the paint, national bus yellow,
takes the metal from dull to bold.
this shade was developed specifically for school buses
and can be noticed even with peripheral vision.
with the paint now dry, they open the doors
and lay a plywood subfloor inside.
it too will absorb noise.
an employee drives the chassis
over to the school-bus-body production line,
and parks it.
using cables, they lift the bus body
over to the chassis.
at over three and a half tons, it's hefty.
they gently lower it onto the frame rails
and mate the front to the hood.
they tie the body to the frame with heavy-duty clips.
they arrange the seating
to surround the passengers with cushioning.
this creates compartments around the occupants
to protect them in a collision.
outside, a worker applies school-bus lettering.
another worker presses
an adhesive-backed manufacturer's emblem
to the hood.
they equip the bus
with the flashing lights and stop signs
to get the attention of other drivers
when children are loading and unloading.
they also install a crossing gate to keep children
within the bus driver's sight line.
they test all of the warning lights
and safety devices.
and satisfied that everything is operational,
the bus rolls off the production line.
it's taken a day and a half to build it,
and when it comes to an education,
it's ready to deliver.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...
--  captions by vitac  --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications