--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: most experts
will tell you that the key
to the perfect paint job
or wood-refinishing job
is to prep the surface properly
before applying the paint
or wood stain.
that requires sanding
to remove old finishes
and to level uneven areas.
the easiest way to do that
is with a motorized sander.
professional-caliber sanders
are typically pneumatic,
meaning you plug them
into an air compressor.
air-driven tools are more
powerful than tools
than run on electricity.
this type of sander is called
a straight line,
because the pad
to which you attach sandpaper
moves in a straight line
back and forth.
many of the tool's components
are made of powdered metal,
then machined
to exact dimensions
on a computer-guided lathe.
powdered metal is iron powder
that's compacted
with high pressure
and heated in a furnace to bond
the particles into a solid
part.
sometimes they further
strengthen the powdered metal
by infusing it with copper
in the furnace.
using an induction welder,
which heats the metal
with an electric current,
they fuse a powdered-metal gear
to each end of a steel shaft
by melting on silver.
this constructs the sander's
timing driveshaft,
the regulating component
that makes each stroke
of the sanding pad
just under an inch long.
heating the metal softens it,
so they now cool the timing
driveshaft in oil.
this quenching hardens
the component.
meanwhile, they coat
a sheet of aluminum rectangles
with industrial-strength
contact adhesive.
each rectangle is a base
for a rubber sanding pad.
the rectangular pad, which they
coat with the same adhesive,
is 6 1/2 millimeters thick,
the same dimensions as the base
with identical holes
for the mounting screws.
once the adhesive becomes
tacky,
they mate the base to the pad.
using a small pneumatic press,
they force out trapped air
to ensure a thorough bond.
elsewhere in the factory,
they paint
the recessed lettering
of the polished aluminum
plates,
two per sander,
which bear
the manufacturer's name.
once all the remaining
components are prepared,
technicians begin the assembly.
first, the motor's piston.
they place the piston rack
in an arbor press
and push a plastic piece
onto each end.
then, on each end piece,
they mount a piston ring
made of a proprietary
wear-resistant material.
they insert
the now-assembled piston
into the sander's
aluminum motor block.
the ring creates a tight seal
to prevent air leakage.
next, a technician installs
the timing driveshaft
and the idler gear shaft,
pressing the gears of both
into the piston rack's teeth.
the powdered-metal
counterweight
goes on each side
to balance the piston rack,
then guides made of that
proprietary material
to align and lubricate
the counterweights.
a second set of anti-wear
guides
goes in the lower part
of the motor block.
these help balance
the sanding pad.
then the start
of the valve system,
which controls the entry of
compressed air into the sander.
at the front of the motor
block,
they install a paper gasket
to prevent air leakage,
then seal it
with an aluminum end plate.
continuing with
the valve system,
they install the components,
which control the timing of the
pistons' back-and-forth motion.
after sealing the top
with a cap,
they install the air-valve
block, then the handle,
which contains the inlet
to which the air compressor
connects.
the handle squeeze trigger
is mounted to the cap
above the handle.
they install the counterweight
for the pad.
here, you can see the two
shafts
the piston rack rotates.
workers connect them
to an aluminum drive shoe,
which will move back and forth.
a pair of side rails holds
the drive shoe in place.
where the air exits the tool,
they install a muffler made
of porous plastic.
finally, when the technician
screws the base
to the drive shoe,
the chain is complete.
compressed air moves the
piston,
which rotates the shafts,
which moves the drive shoe
holding the rubber pad
with sandpaper.
this pneumatic sander
is ready to level
and smooth a surface
in seconds flat.
narrator: a solid terrain
model,
"stm" for short,
is an exact, three-dimensional,
miniature replica
of a geographic area.
stms are indispensable tools
for museums, visitor centers,
and for planning everything
from industrial projects
to military operations.
to create a solid terrain
model,
the first step is to gather
data
via satellites and aircraft.
two types of data --
color photographs of the
surface
showing the precise location
of vegetation, rock, buildings,
and so on,
and elevation measurements,
taken with lasers
and other equipment.
a cartographer digitally merges
the black and white elevation
diagrams with the color photos
and adds artwork for roads
and place names.
he produces a 3-d computer
model
of the area.
this model will guide
the machines
that manufacture
the physical model
out of a block
of polyurethane foam.
foam is a durable material
and lightweight,
making the model easy
to transport.
a computer-guided cutting
machine first shapes a ledge
around the block's perimeter.
this is for mounting
the model on a frame.
then the machine reads the
computer model's elevation
files
and carves a miniature replica
of those elevations into foam.
the machine first does
a rough cut.
then --
and this takes much longer --
it carves the fine details.
depending on the complexity
of the terrain,
cutting the elevations
into the foam
can take just a few hours
or several days.
when the cutting's finished,
the technician cleans off
the foam dust
with compressed air and a
brush.
the foam goes into a spray
booth
where it first receives
a coat of primer
to seal the porous surface,
then multiple layers
of special coatings
to make images printed on
the surface sharp and vibrant.
once the coating's dry --
that takes about a day --
technicians put the model into
a
custom-designed inkjet printer,
which reads the computer
model's
photograph file.
just like an ordinary printer,
this printer produces
a multitude of shades
from just four basic colors --
black, yellow, magenta,
and cyan.
the jets pass just a few
millimeters above the model,
emitting one microscopic drop
of ink at a time
at precisely
the correct location.
the end result
is a miniature replica
of what the surface looks like
in real life.
other workers, meanwhile,
construct a sturdy frame
for the model
by gluing, clamping,
and nailing together
four lengths of oak.
this frame will protect
the model from damage
and make it easier
to lift and move.
once the glue dries, they
remove
the clamps, and with a saw,
trim each corner
to a 45-degree angle.
then they round the edges
with a sander.
they complete the frame
by protecting the wood
with a coat
of clear polyurethane.
when that dries,
they spread glue
onto the frame's inside edge.
then they position the model
so that the ledge
along its perimeter
sits on top of the frame.
after printing,
they spray the model
with clear polyurethane
or lacquer.
the protective finish
allows people
to now touch the model
without damaging it.
sometimes, an area
they're modeling has buildings,
bridges, or other structures.
when that's the case,
an engineer designs a computer
model of the object.
then, guided by this model,
a 3-d printer produces
a physical model out of
plastic,
building the miniature replica
from the bottom up
one thin layer at a time.
these mountaintop castles
in portugal
are the finishing touch
on this model
that's set to go on display
at the local tourist center.
solid terrain models are
a creative and valuable tool
for educating people
young and old.
by translating complicated
technical data
into a unique and
scientifically sound visual
aid,
a solid terrain model delivers
a fascinating bird's-eye view
from the ground.
narrator: stucco is one
of the oldest construction
materials on the planet.
the earliest formulations
date back to ancient greece
and mayan mexico.
stucco has stuck around,
and as an exterior siding,
it's come a long way.
modern stucco is more
attractive
and offers better protection.
whether cement-
or acrylic-based,
stucco always starts out
as a sticky paste,
and that's the great thing
about stucco.
in this wet and gooey form,
it can be worked
as it's applied to the exterior
of a building
to achieve a variety
of textures.
it hardens to provide
a tough exterior
that shields the building
against the elements.
to mass-produce cement stucco,
they start with tons
of silica sand.
they unload it into a conveyor
and elevator system,
which delivers the sand to
silos
for storage until needed.
they select sand with various
grades of coarseness
for different stucco finishes.
they mix it with cement, lime,
and other ingredients
to create the stucco base.
a technician demonstrates how
the ingredients come together
using this research lab mixer.
she blends
all the ingredients dry,
achieving a consistency that's
similar to cake mix from a box.
cement stucco
is sold in dry form.
water will be added to liquefy
the ingredients on the job
site.
in this demonstration,
she also adds pigment.
with the stucco pre-colored,
there's no need to paint
the building.
to mass-produce cement stucco,
they use this mega-mixer.
the operator adds three or four
different pigments
to create a custom color
in the dry stucco batch.
large paddle blades
spiral vigorously.
usually,
this is a closed operation,
but they've opened it up
for our camera.
after three minutes of mixing,
the dry stucco mix is ready
for scrutiny.
an employee takes a sample
and sends it to the quality
control lab for evaluation.
at the lab, the technician
weighs the stucco mixture
and adds water.
he keeps an eye on the scale
to ensure that the amounts
are proportionate.
he mixes them
and visually checks to confirm
that the pigment and raw
materials are well dispersed.
acrylic stucco,
on the other hand,
calls for
an entirely different recipe.
they use calcium carbonate
instead of silica send
and acrylic as a binder
instead of cement.
they mix it with water
and sell it wet in a bucket
instead of dry.
to color it, they use
a computerized tint machine,
similar to what you find
in a paint store.
they load the machine
with liquid pigments
and enter a color formula
into the computer.
it mixes the pigments
to produce the exact color.
and it releases
the precise amount needed.
they blend the color
into the acrylic stucco,
and the batch ends up
looking like blue mud.
it's now ready to apply
to a home.
no prep required.
they also sell acrylic stucco
with no color at all.
it's called tint base.
the pigments will be added
on the job site,
where they can be adjusted
if needed.
an airtight seal keeps
the stucco in its viscous
state.
acrylic stucco dries quickly,
like paint,
while cement stucco
takes 28 days to totally cure
into a more durable finish.
over on the cement stucco line,
a rotating machine
handles all the packaging.
a suctioning device pulls
a paper bag into position
under a spout,
which then fills it up.
it takes just 8 seconds
to fill a 90-pound bag.
that works out
to over 1,300 bags per hour,
enough material for 30 houses.
the machine transfers the bag
to the conveyor belt.
this stucco is now ready
to provide a strong finish
to building projects.
applied to
a building's exterior,
stucco can be textured to suit
the homeowner's taste,
and it will harden to provide
the building with a tough skin.
that's why stucco continues to
be part of the urban landscape.
narrator: an industrial
roll-up door opens and closes
at least three times as fast
as your average
residential garage door.
that means machines and
products
can be moved in and out
quickly.
these heavy-duty rubber doors
are also engineered for a good
seal, so they're weathertight.
in many workplaces, doors
are always opening and closing.
a high-speed roll-up door
is designed for heavy traffic.
coal mines, parking garages,
and large food freezer rooms
are just a few of the places
you will find them in action.
they start with rubber panels.
their number and size depends
on the width of the door
being manufactured.
workers brush high-strength
epoxy onto the edges
to bind the panels together.
the epoxy will take
a couple of hours to cure,
so there's time to smooth out
the air bubbles
by applying pressure to
the seams with a heavy roller.
after the epoxy cures, they map
out areas with masking tape
to contain glue
for the application
of extruded rubber strips.
the horizontal one
is a stiffener,
and the vertical strips
at the sides are wind blocks.
they'll secure the curtain
to the building
even in bad weather.
the employee also applies
synthetic fabric to both sides
to prevent wear.
he adds reflective yellow
strips
to the front and back
to make the black rubber door
visible at night.
a machine now drills holes
in a steel tube.
this tube is the header
that the rubber curtain
will be rolled up on to.
the holes will be used
to attach the curtain to it.
he tack-welds axles
onto both ends of the tube.
the axles will be attached
to mounting plates,
so these are critical welds.
he measures the axles to
confirm
that the assembly is level
and won't wobble.
satisfied, he welds them
permanently to the steel tube.
next, he assembles
and welds the side frame
for the rubber curtain.
he assembles a hinge cover
to the front of the frame,
creating a compartment
for the curtain
that can be opened when needed.
then it's on to the paint
booth.
here, an employee primes
the frame components
to protect them from rust and
then gives them a coat of
paint.
a worker assembles
the bottom beam now.
he bolts an aluminum track
for the rubber edging
to a heavy steel frame.
he screws the box
for the wireless transmitter
that opens and closes the door
to the beam.
two workers now pull
the rubber edging
through the aluminum track.
the edging is equipped
with an electric safety wire
to detect movement
and abort a door closing.
this will keep the door
from hitting anyone
who walks under it.
it's now time to pull
everything together.
the team screws the rubber
curtain to the steel tube,
making use
of those pre-drilled holes.
they move down and position
the bottom beam on the curtain.
they attach it to the curtain
with numerous nuts and bolts.
they roll up the rubber curtain
to prepare for assembly
to the mounting brackets.
with the attachments,
the curtain now weighs
over 1,100 pounds.
a crane transfers it
to the end mounting plates
and holds it steady
while workers slide
the end brackets onto the
axles.
they build a steel support
structure around the brackets
and the rolled-up curtain.
they attach the motor
to one of the axles.
this roll-up door is now ready
for delivery.
two days in the making,
it's ready
for whatever comes its way.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...