-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: carbon fiber is an engineer's dream --
lightweight yet incredibly strong.
it's a string with thousands of parallel filaments.
multiple strings can be twisted into yarns,
woven into fabrics, or molded with resin
to produce materials called carbon-fiber composites.
carbon fiber is five times stronger than steel
yet less than half the weight.
to make it, they take a plastic fiber
composed of thousands of filaments
far thinner than human hair.
they then chemically alter it
to form a perfect chain of carbon atoms
for the final product.
this mammoth machine lines up dozens of those fibers
which then travel through an oxidation oven
for a couple of minutes.
the oven temperature, about 480 degrees fahrenheit,
prompts the fibers to pick up oxygen molecules from the air.
this rearranges the fibers' atomic structure,
rendering them resistant to high heat.
as the fibers oxidize,
they change color to eventually turn black.
they're now primed for the next
process, carbonization.
furnaces heat the fibers in an oxygen-free gas mixture.
this expels the non-carbon atoms
and transforms the remaining carbon atoms
into tightly bonded crystals
running parallel to the length of the fiber.
this gives the fiber its strength.
the exiting fibers travel
through a bath of electrically charged water
that etches the fibers' surface
so they'll better absorb resin.
the next station applies a light
preliminary coat of resin.
this will strengthen the fibers' chemical bond
to the molding resin.
a spooling machine winds each fiber,
now referred to as a carbon-fiber tow,
onto a bobbin
which buyers either weave into a carbon-fiber fabric
or mix with resin to mold a product.
another form of carbon fiber is prepreg --
sheets of resin-impregnated carbon fiber ready for molding.
it's like ready-to-bake cake mix.
the resin is a formula of epoxy
and various powdered hardeners and accelerators.
workers pour the resin into a filming machine
which spreads it
in a thin, wet layer onto paper.
the paper is pre-treated with a release agent
to prevent the final product from sticking,
like spraying a baking pan with non-stick coating.
another machine, meanwhile,
groups 200 to 300 carbon-fiber tows
into a giant band of fibers called a web.
the width and thickness of the web
determines the width and thickness of the prepreg sheet.
workers mount two rolls of resin-coated paper
onto the resin-impregnation machine.
a heating element warms up the web as it enters
to facilitate resin absorption.
then the heated carbon-fiber web
is sandwiched between two sheets
of resin-coated paper.
high-pressure heated rollers thin out the resin
so it penetrates the millions of carbon-fiber filaments.
cooling plates then turn the liquid resin to gel
so that the next station can remove the paper,
which pulls off easily thanks to the release agent.
the next station covers the top
of the prepreg sheet
with polyester film.
this prevents the prepreg sheet
from sticking to itself at the end of the line
when it's wound into a roll like a fruit roll-up.
in the factory's lab,
technicians run quality control
tests on prepreg samples.
first they weigh the sample.
then they wash off the resin with chemicals
and weigh the sample again.
this verifies whether the ratio
of carbon fiber to resin
is correct.
the lab also analyzes samples of composite --
carbon-fiber reinforced resin --
in this tensile strength test.
the computer measures how much strain the sample withstands
before breaking.
such testing ensures the carbon fiber
delivers optimum strength,
durability, and heat resistance,
whether it's used to make an auto part,
a wind-turbine blade, or a golf club.
narrator: antique gilded frames
have spent many years
protecting paintings and enhancing them.
but over time, grime can obscure
the gold-leaf shine
and the frame can suffer damage
and deterioration.
but these frames are highly collectible,
and restoring them preserves their value.
with elaborate cast ornamentation
and gold-leaf work,
this 19th-century gilded frame is itself a work of art.
but it's in need of renewal.
restoration work
done many years ago has cracked,
and gold leaf is deteriorating elsewhere on the frame.
the technician carefully
pries the cracked acorn casting
loose
and removes it from the frame.
he'll make a new one from scratch.
it will need to completely fill
the empty space
and look exactly like the others
on the frame.
he starts by making a mold with dental impression rubber.
he kneads the two putty-like components together
to activate the ingredients.
when the color's uniform and there are no streaks,
the rubber is ready for molding.
he must act quickly
because in just three minutes the rubber will cure.
he presses it around the acorn ornament on the frame
to capture the detail.
he now has a mold he can use
to cast a new ornament for the frame.
he'll use this wood epoxy for that.
like the dental impression rubber,
it must be mixed thoroughly to activate it.
he presses the epoxy into the contours of the mold,
pushing it from one end to the other.
this will prevent air from becoming trapped in the casting
and compromising its integrity.
after a 10-minute cure, the epoxy casting is ready,
and he extracts it from the mold.
he examines the detail
and confirms that it is an exact reproduction.
then, using a scoop chisel,
he sculpts the edges and the inside of the casting
to shape it to the picture frame.
in this comparison shot,
the shaped part is the one on the left.
he places the cast epoxy ornament on the frame
and nails it down.
the epoxy is still soft enough
that he can drive the nail into it without breaking it.
he fills the gap between the casting and the frame
with more epoxy,
providing a seamless transition
from new to old.
after the epoxy solidifies,
he brushes something called bole
onto it.
bole is a mix of clay and rabbit-skin glue.
it provides a surface that the gold can adhere to,
and the rabbit-skin glue will give it flex
as the wood expands and contracts.
he then transfers the 23-karat gold leaf to the casting.
before he lays each piece of gold leaf,
he wets the surface of the ornament
with a gilder's liqueur --
a mix of water, alcohol, and rabbit-skin glue.
this causes the gold leaf
to conform to the contours of the ornament and adhere.
after the golf leaf sets for an hour or two,
he burnishes it to a very high shine
using a tool made from agate,
a very hard, semiprecious stone.
hundreds of years ago,
craftsman used dogs' teeth for this job.
he rubs the shiny, new gold surface
with very fine-grade steel wool.
this removes some of the gold to simulate natural wear
so that it matches the patina of the rest of the frame.
and what a transformation
this plain epoxy casting has undergone.
newly gilded, and it looks like
it's always been part of the antique frame.
other sections of the frame require regilding.
he rubs alcohol onto those areas
to get rid of atmospheric residue
that would prevent the adhesion
of the new gold.
and after applying gilder's liqueur,
he lays sheets of the new gold leaf over the old,
working with a steady rhythm to
give the area complete coverage.
he's aiming for more of a matte finish on this section,
so he doesn't polish it.
he brushes a protective coat of shellac onto it.
he's used a combination of old materials and new
to restore this antique gilt frame,
and it's picture-perfect.
narrator: pushing and pulling railcars at the train yard
is the job of a large motorized vehicle
appropriately called a railcar mover.
it switches the cars from one track to another,
shuttles them in and out of the cargo loading area,
and positions them in line behind the locomotive.
a railcar mover has to drive
both on and off the train track,
so it has two types of wheels --
four steel rail wheels for guiding it on the track
and four wheels with rubber tires
for driving on the ground.
when building a railcar mover, they start with the frame.
a computer-guided plasma cutter
cuts out all the frame parts
from a 4-inch-thick steel plate.
once all the frame parts are ready,
workers begin welding them together.
they position the deck plate, the mover's floor, upside down
and weld on the frame rails.
these will hold the axles for the rubber wheels.
then, to those frame rails, they weld the rail arm mounts.
these will hold the rail arms which hold the rail wheels.
after welding several additional
components to the frame,
workers bolt the axles for the rubber wheels
to the frame rails...
...then the rail arms to the rail mounts.
now the frame goes to the paint shop
for a coat of primer followed by a coat of automotive paint.
workers also roll on a textured floor coating
to create a non-slip surface
for the driver to safely walk to and from the cab.
when the paint dries, the frame
returns to the assembly line
where workers begin mounting
the 4.5-foot-wide rail wheels onto the rail arms.
after mounting each wheel on the spindle,
they install a bearing, then a large nut.
they must tighten the nut to the correct torque
yet not over-tighten it, or the wheel won't turn freely.
once they've got just the correct torque,
they secure the nut with a retaining lock nut.
they finish off this installation
with the rail-wheel equivalent of a hubcap.
this steel cover holds in the grease
that lubricates the wheel and bearing
while keeping out dust and dirt.
next they mount the four rubber wheels,
securing each one with a dozen bolts.
these steel wheels with rubber tires
are about 6 1/2 feet in diameter.
workers mount several other components,
including a pair of air tanks with gauges
for the railcar's pneumatic brake system.
these are the brakes the driver uses
when the mover is coupled to railcars.
when it's not,
the mover has its own separate hydraulic brake system,
the components of which workers
also install at this stage.
they attach a hydraulic cylinder
to the steer axle.
this controls the steering of the rubber wheels
when the mover is off the train track.
the rail wheels, of course, don't require any steering,
as they simply follow the track.
now workers install the 300-horsepower diesel engine.
it's already bolted to the transmission.
then they hook up the electrical wiring,
which connects the engine and transmission
to the computer controlling them.
they lower the hood over the engine and transmission.
the hood has three components already installed --
the engine air intake, air cleaner, and muffler.
finally, they install the cab.
it has a steering wheel for driving off-rail
and a control console that rotates 180 degrees
to let the driver operate at whichever side of the cab
provides the best view
of all the railcars
the mover is pulling or pushing.
the finished railcar mover doesn't leave the factory
before a burn-in period in the test pit.
the test is so intense,
the rubber tires have to be cooled with water.
pulling as many as 40 railcars at a time
is no job for a lightweight.
that's why a railcar mover weighs in at up to 45 tons.
narrator: at first, hood ornaments were used
to beautify external temperature
gauges and radiator caps.
they then evolved into signature pieces
that embodied the car brand.
and when the radiator caps were moved under the hood,
the ornaments stayed on top.
a hood ornament is a little piece of automotive art.
popular mainly on luxury cars now,
these ornaments symbolize the spirit of the car
and can make quite a statement on the street.
each ornament starts
with an aluminum mold that consists of many parts
in order to achieve a complex shape.
an injector pumps specially formulated wax
into the mold cavity.
the wax solidifies quickly.
the operator dismantles the mold
and removes the cast wax model.
the detail is impressive.
he examines it for flaws.
he cools the model in water until the wax firms.
this wax model will be used to make a mold
to cast the metal ornament
using a technique that dates back thousands of years.
he attaches numerous cast models
to a wax riser
by melting the wax a little so they adhere.
the next worker then dips the models and riser
into specially formulated ceramic slurry.
he makes sure that the liquid covers every detail.
still wet, the models then go into the rain sander,
so named because it actually rains grit.
the grit sticks to the models for a stucco effect.
he repeats the ceramic dip and grit process three times
to build up substantial shells around the wax models.
these shells will serve as molds
to cast the hood ornament.
in this case, the casting material is steel.
they melt rejected
hood ornaments with steel chunks
to transform them into a white-hot liquid.
the ceramic models have by now been cured
and the wax melted out.
workers ladle the molten steel into the riser feeder cup.
the steel flows into all of the ceramic molds.
they top it off with a manganese mixture
that catches fire
and keeps the steel hot and liquid a little longer,
ensuring that it feeds into all of the molds.
the steel cools for several hours and solidifies.
an employee then breaks open the network of molds
to reveal the cast hood ornaments.
he inserts a pneumatic hammer into the feeder cup,
and it shakes off most
of the remaining ceramic shards.
this machine blasts off the rest
using very fine stainless-steel particles.
they're ready to cut the cast ornaments
free from the main base.
with the riser on its side,
the worker slices off one hood ornament at a time
using an aluminum-oxide cutting wheel.
at this angle, he can't make a clean cut.
he leaves a fairly thick chunk on the base.
he grinds off that chunk using an abrasive belt.
the base of the hood ornament is now smooth and level.
next he refines the shape of the hood ornament.
he grinds away excess material
to improve the profile of the piece
and generally clean it up.
this process also adds shine to the stainless steel.
to give the hood ornaments a real polish,
they plunge them into a sulfuric-acid solution.
the solution eats away
impurities to expose the nickel.
a worker buffs each hood ornament
against a cloth wheel until it gleams.
he examines his work under a magnifying glass.
defects won't be tolerated,
and even at this stage, the statuette could be rejected
and melted into a new one.
it passes inspection.
made of steel, silver, or gold,
a hood ornament on a luxury car
is a great way to say you've arrived.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...