-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications, inc.
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
...holograms --
projections for the future...
...package printing --
how to make an impression...
...skin culture --
it definitely grows on you...
...and canned corn --
we hope you're all ears.
holograms aren't just
beautiful and fascinating.
they have a certain
high-tech mystique about them.
well, stay tuned
to have the mystery revealed.
holograms are simply layered
variations of an image,
each one causing light
to reflect in a different way.
a hologram is
a 3-dimensional photograph
produced by the interference
of two laser beams.
a laser emits light --
this light ray.
the color of the light varies
according to the wavelength.
a shutter, when activated,
either blocks the light ray
or lets it pass through.
here the beam splits in two
at a 90-degree angle.
the interference
of the two beams
is clearly visible
on this screen.
it has very defined fringes.
the beams need great stability
because the pattern
of interference
projected on the screen
is extremely sensitive
to minute vibrations.
a light tap on the table
can easily spoil it completely.
the team will create a hologram
from this sculpture
made of modeling clay.
the sculpture is positioned
on a support
with a magnetic base that
adheres to the metallic table.
then they place a glass
in front of the object.
here's the exact point
where the light beam passes.
the table
has to be perfectly stable,
so it's made of
a 2.4-ton block of steel,
which rests on 18 air tubes.
the table and laser
are thus well-insulated
from all vibrations.
the beam splitter
separates the beam in two,
directing one behind the object
and the other in front of it.
one part of the beam
heads toward
the front of the sculpture.
the beam first passes through
an objective lens
that diffuses the light.
then it's reflected
by a parabolic mirror,
which prevents it from losing
too much of its intensity.
as in photography,
film is required.
this holographic film
is attached to a glass plate
with adhesive tape.
then another glass plate
is added
so that the film will not move.
a vibration of 1/10 of the
laser's wavelength is tolerable.
the laser is turned on.
the intensity of its light ray
reaches about 250 milliwatts.
the normal exposure time
of the model to the beam
is about one second,
but some holograms made
with a pulsed laser
are exposed to the light
for 12 nanoseconds,
an infinitely short
period of time.
here we see the reference beam
coming from
the parabolic mirror.
and here we see it
from another angle.
as in photography,
the film has to be developed.
these trays contain
different chemical solutions
and the developer.
first the film is soaked in
the developer for two minutes.
this solution blackens
the silver salts
that have reacted to the light.
then the film is soaked
in a solution called bleach
to completely eliminate the
silver salts that blackened it.
now the film is rinsed.
this step is used to eliminate
the acids in the emulsion
and so as not to contaminate
the next solution.
the film
gently becomes transparent.
it's then rinsed in clear water.
and it's soaked for one minute
in a wetting agent
which eliminates
all water spots.
the film is then dried,
and it reveals its secrets,
and here's the hologram
created from the sculpture.
a hologram really creates
a 3-dimensional illusion.
some holograms can be animated.
they are generated from
a series of still holograms.
depending on the complexity
of the project,
a hologram can be produced
from between one and five hours.
narrator:
your average product packaging
is crammed
with so much information,
it's hard to see the artistry
behind the instructions
and ingredients.
an incredible amount of thought
goes into making
packaging that's unique,
instantly identifiable,
and attractive to the consumer.
all consumer products
are packaged,
and the making of these packages
starts with the burning of
an aluminum plate like this one.
this animation illustrates
the burning process --
the transfer of an image
onto an aluminum plate.
the plate is placed
onto a cylinder,
and, using a laser,
the burning begins.
the image appears
in six minutes.
this plate will make
the printing impressions
on packages.
the laser that did the burning
has to be perfectly calibrated
using this test plate.
the plate is now ready
to make impressions
via the offset method.
printing involves ink,
and it requires selecting
the right one.
if the desired color
does not exist,
it has to be made up from
a mix of various other colors.
an ink trial
is done with a spatula,
and, using this small manual
press, color ink tests are done.
the ink is spread onto paper
and the color compared with the
one called for by the customer.
if the two match,
the presses can be started up.
this is a 6-color
offset process printing press
with a 28x43-inch capacity.
the press is fed by
a suction and friction process
devouring 8,000 sheets an hour.
now the printing plate is placed
onto the press cylinder.
this plate will contact inking
rollers of the ink reservoir.
to prevent it from drying,
ink viscosity is maintained
with this oscillator.
the press starts up
and reaches a production rate
of 8,000 impressions
in 60 minutes.
the press comprises
individual color printing units.
the paper sheet passes
from one unit to another,
receiving a new color
at each step.
here they register the colors --
that is, the quality
of the superimposition
of the different colors.
the final step is the folding
and gluing of the boxes.
this grooved plate
makes folding-point marks
on the carton.
and this machine does
the cutting, the embossing,
and stripping of the sheets
at a rate of 6,000 an hour.
the cutting die
cuts the carton sheets
and, together with the grooved
plate, makes the folding joints.
this sheet is slid
behind the cutting die
to equalize the cutting
of the sheets.
this enormous pile of 3,000
sheets is ready to be cut.
the embossing press feeder
handles between
6,000 and 8,000 sheets an hour.
rollers guide the sheets
in the direction of the press.
and here the sheets are embossed
by the machine.
the precision of the embossing
is then verified.
next comes the cutting
of the sheets.
they cut 8,000 an hour.
the cutting unit strips and
removes the unnecessary pieces,
and the carton scraps are sucked
up for eventual recycling.
the scraps can also be cut away
manually using a hammer.
the carton end pieces
are sent off for recycling.
all that remains is
the assembly of the packages.
this high-speed gluing unit
can make up to 30,000 to 40,000
per hour.
gluing begins with
the folding of sheets
following the folding marks.
the sides of the formed box
are then glued together.
an average of between
five to eight steps are needed
to fabricate a packaging box.
every day this plant produces
between 1 and 2 million boxes,
requiring almost 4,000 tons
of cardboard annually.
narrator: for people
who've suffered severe burns
there's hope.
they can be treated
with skin grafts
using human skin
that's been cultured in a lab.
patients
who receive these grafts
tend to develop less scarring
and usually heal
in a fraction of the time.
culturing of skin
allows us to save many lives.
to grow skin, epidermis cells
have to be isolated
and made to multiply.
it all begins with the removal
of a small skin sample.
the 10 million cells
in this piece
are enough to make a culture.
the skin soaks
in a medium containing
penicillin and gentamicin,
antibiotics which protect it
from bacterial infection.
now a piece of skin is cut
and delicately sectioned
on a petri dish with a scalpel.
the fat is gently detached
from the dermis
since it will not be needed
in the culturing.
the skin is cut into thin strips
because thermolysin,
the enzyme that separates
the dermis from the epidermis,
acts more efficiently
on the small surfaces.
then an enzyme
destroys the links
uniting the dermis
and the epidermis cells.
this procedure is carried out in
this incubator over three hours
at a temperature
of 98.6 degrees,
or body temperature.
once incubation is over,
the petri dish is removed
from the incubator.
only the epidermis cells,
also called "keratinocytes,"
are retained.
the epidermis is detached from
the dermis with great precision.
now the strips are placed
in a trypsination unit.
trypsin, an enzyme,
will destroy the links
uniting the epidermis cells
in order to isolate them.
this operation
signals the cells to multiply
now that they're
in a favorable medium.
in order to increase
the effectiveness of trypsin,
the trypsination unit
is placed on an agitator.
the cells do not have to remain
in extended contact
with the trypsin.
they're inhibited with
a medium containing serum.
then the liquid containing
the cells in suspension
is drawn off.
now the liquid is centrifuged
to obtain two fractions.
the base fraction containing
the desired cells
is at the bottom of the tube,
while the upper floating
fraction containing the trypsin
has to be removed.
this upper fraction is drawn off
with a vacuum system.
in order to eliminate
all traces of trypsin,
the culture medium is added
to the base fraction,
and the whole is put back
into suspension.
now the cells from the small
skin sample have to be counted
before being centrifuged
a second time.
the cells are counted
by hand using a microscope
or with this apparatus.
the exact number of cells
obtained during the extraction
via a biopsy is determined
as well as the number of cells
that will have to be seeded
for maximum growth.
the bottom portion
of keratinocytes
is divided in these flasks
containing a culture medium
whose composition
resembles that of blood.
the cells will multiply
over a week in these flasks,
placed in an oven at
98.6 degrees and at 8% oxygen.
the medium in which
the cells are immersed
is changed every two days.
in less than a week,
the cells have almost covered
the entire surface of the flask.
they can now be trypsinated anew
and thus reseed some 50 flasks,
which in turn will be placed
in the oven for about one week.
skin strips carpet
the inner surface of the flask.
they are then detached
with a spatula.
the flasks are cut in two
with a heating unit
resembling a soldering iron.
to make handling easier, gauze
is placed on the skin strips,
whose thickness is less than
1/10 of a millimeter.
the graft is placed
on the wound.
clamps and the gauze will be
removed after 10 days.
a patient can be skin-grafted
in less than two weeks.
narrator:
when it comes to vegetables,
there's nothing like
fresh corn on the cob.
but when that's not available,
corn is also great
right out of the can,
and anyone with an appetite
for feats of engineering
will appreciate the whirlwind
journey from cob to can.
throughout man's history,
food preserving has included
smoking, freezing,
drying, and salting.
in the early 19th century,
nicolas appert built a factory
to preserve foods in
hermetically sealed glass jars
and to sterilize them
by boiling.
but glass was breakable,
and so in 1810,
an englishman named durand
invented the tin can,
first used by the military,
and soldiers, it seems, first
developed a handy can opener.
the corn that's canned
is harvested
from mid-august
until mid-october.
canning is done very quickly.
less than four hours pass
between harvesting
and canning procedures
so as to conserve
much of the nutritional value
of the product to be sold.
the unloading of many trucks
of this size will be needed
for the 150,000 tons of corn
that are canned here annually.
the cobs are transported
into the plant on this conveyor.
they will first have to pass
through a kernel remover.
equipped with several
counter-rotating cylinders,
this unit removes the leaves and
the silk which surround the cob.
with only a few seconds,
the cob is completely stripped
of its covering.
once cleaned,
the cobs fall into this chute
en route to the next
processing step.
here they're lined up,
ready to be handled
by the kernel remover.
the kernels are removed
from the cobs
by going through the machine
where knives remove the kernels
in a fraction of a second.
each of these units remove
1.5 tons of kernels per hour.
twice a day the machines are
stopped to inspect the blades,
to clean, and sharpen them.
the corn kernels
fall into the middle
while the cobs themselves
are moved to the sides.
both kernels and cobs move along
on their separate ways
in the process.
the kernels are entered into
this rotating drum,
which removes any particles
larger than the kernels.
nothing is wasted
in the processing.
corn residues, leaves, and cobs
will all be used later
as animal feed.
now the kernels fall into
a mix composed of water
and of a fluid that's obtained
when cutting the corn kernels.
this liquid mix allows for
the transporting of the kernels
without damaging them.
next the kernels
flow along this belt
and are placed on this conveyor
toward the following
processing step.
bleaching is done
in this huge cylinder.
a worm screw brings the
bleached kernels to the surface.
a visual inspection verifies
the quality of the kernels.
all that remains is to pack them
into these leakproof cans.
thousands of cans of every size
are carried
to the filling department.
filling the cans is done from
this rotating filling machine.
this filling machine can handle
300 to 450 cans a minute.
the kernels
that fall to the side
are gathered up later
in this cylinder
and returned
to the filling line.
here a brine solution
composed of water, salt,
and sugar is added.
covers are securely attached
onto the containers,
but the canning
is not yet finished
because they have to proceed
with some very important tests.
they perform tests
in this laboratory
that assure the quality
of the product.
first they check the
watertightness of the cans.
they also control
the filling weight
and the quality of the kernels.
meanwhile,
cans continue winding their way
through the plant.
one step remains --
sterilization.
sterilization takes place
in this oven
at 250 degrees
and lasts
between 4 to 6 minutes.
this is a crucial step
because it guarantees
that the product is reliable
and that it will remain so
for 18 months.
now they taste
samples of the product
to determine that it conforms
to quality standards.
cans are labeled
as customers' orders are filled.
in this facility,
they produce an amazing total
of 43 million cans of corn.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...