-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery
communications, inc.
narrator:
today on "how it's made"...
steel --
the original heavy metal...
apple juice --
from the tree to the glass...
aircraft landing gear --
what you really need
to score a touchdown,
and cosmetics --
we'll tour a factory where they
make it up as they go along.
they call superman
"the man of steel"
because, flying
and x-ray vision aside,
he could bend solid steel
with his bare hands.
thanks to its
legendary strength,
steel is used for everything
from bridges and skyscrapers
to household appliances.
steelmaking usually begins
with a pile of scrap metal.
using this 11-ton electromagnet,
scrap iron --
composed of crushed car bodies,
electric appliances, cans,
and other steel scraps --
is gathered up.
this powerful magnet is able
to lift 5 1/2 tons of metal.
about 83% of this scrap will be
transformed into bars of steel.
this metal is then dumped
into a basket
which, by itself,
weighs 35 tons.
the basket can hold
up to 65 tons of metal.
and now they're going
to melt the metal.
this furnace reaches
a temperature
of 3,000 degrees,
hot enough to liquefy the metal.
it is heated by three electrodes
and by four natural-gas burners.
the contents of the basket
are dumped into the furnace.
here, the pieces of metal
come into contact
with liquefied steel,
which always remains
at the bottom of the furnace.
there's a reaction,
and an aeration system draws out
the smoke that's produced.
at this high heat,
the 66 tons of metal
will melt in about 60 minutes.
then the cover is placed
on the furnace.
this liquid is composed
of impurities
that rise to the surface
when the metal becomes molten.
at this stage, a workman
draws a sample of steel
to determine
its chemical makeup.
and now they make use
of a supersonic oxygen lance.
this lance blows oxygen
into the molten steel.
this reduces
its carbon content,
homogenizes the mix, and speeds
up the melting process.
a ladle is positioned
beneath the furnace.
the molten steel
will be transferred
from the furnace
into this ladle.
the molten steel easily pours
into the ladle.
the ladle weighs 60 tons and
holds 127 tons of molten steel.
an overhead crane capable
of lifting 200 tons
carries the ladle
filled with steel.
additives are introduced
in order to obtain
the correct steel tone.
here, the electrodes are taken
out of the furnace ladle.
a workman now opens the pouring
nozzles of the distributor.
it is equipped
with four pouring holes.
the molten steel
runs into molds.
it cools very quickly
and begins to harden.
steel billets are produced
in lengths varying
from 15 to 35 feet.
the billets are then cut
to the desired length
with a natural-gas torch.
a pouring identification number
is marked on them
with a wax crayon.
the difference between
a steel billet
and the nearly finished
flattened product is clear.
flattening of the billets
remains to be done.
before flattening begins,
billets are placed
in the furnace to be reheated
for 2 hours at 2,000 degrees.
water jets
cool the billet ejector.
the billets are placed
on the flattener,
where powerful rollers
compress them.
this operation gives the billets
the required shape and size.
water-cooled rollers
crush the billets.
some billets go from a thickness
of 5 inches down to 1/2 an inch,
while other reduce from 6 inches
down to 3/4 of an inch.
at the end of production,
bars move along at a speed
reaching 22 miles per hour.
once they reach
their required dimensions,
the bars must be cooled.
this cooling bed allows the
steel bars to cool uniformly.
a total of 440,000 tons
of steel bars
are made at this plant
each year.
narrator: dump thousands
of apples into a giant press,
apply several tons of pressure,
and what do you get?
apple juice, of course.
and good thing it's made
on such an enormous scale,
when you consider
how many people
drink gallons of this
popular juice every year.
here at rougemeau,
they make apple juice
mainly from mcintosh apples.
some 90% of juice production
is done at harvesttime
in october.
a conveyor transports apples
to an inspection location.
apples tumble in the reverse
direction of the conveyor belt
so that wet leaves
and undesirable materials
adhere to the belt.
the apples are stored in silos
for several hours.
so the apples don't get
too bruised in their descent,
they're slowed down
in this stepped chute.
juice making can now begin.
now they wash the apples.
since they use some apples
that have already fallen
to the ground,
this first water bath must
eliminate pebbles.
a shower of cool water
completes the washing process.
the apples are cut into little
pieces in this grinder
and produce gratings.
enzymes are added,
which break down
the cellular structure
of the fruit,
allowing for maximum
juice extraction.
next, the gratings
are transferred
into maceration reservoirs,
where they'll stay
for 60 to 90 minutes.
then they extract the juice.
the gratings are pumped
into a powerful hydraulic press.
inside the press, filter sleeves
hold back the skins,
seeds, and stems of the apples.
quality control is strict.
at each stage of the process,
they draw off samples of juice
to evaluate its quality
and to make sure
that fabrication parameters
are well adhered to.
the juice is filtered
a first time.
the very smallest
undesirable particles
are held back by this sieve.
the fabrication process
continues.
juice flows
from one stage to another
via these immense reservoirs.
the next step
will be pasteurization.
juice enters this exchanger
at 72 degrees
and is heated up to 190 degrees,
then cooled back down
to 122 degrees.
enzymes are then added
to hydrate the pectin
and facilitate
the second filtration.
this is
the ultra-filtration process,
where filter membranes
with microscopic pores
retain the smallest
of particles.
the apple juice
is now perfectly filtered.
its clarity is verified,
as well as its flavor,
color, and natural
fruit-sugar content.
since juice
is produced in october,
it has to be conserved
throughout the year.
a portion of the production
is stored
in this sterile warehouse area
to await being bottled
during the year.
each reservoir can hold 29,000
gallons of filtered juice.
no preserving agent is added.
now we move to the next stage,
the filling of containers.
these little drinking containers
are filled
at the rate of 100 a minute.
the containers
are then hermetically sealed.
two little sprays of hot glue
are applied to the containers.
this secures the straws
to their sides.
another automated production
line fills bottles with juice.
they circulate in a row
on this conveyor.
bottles are washed
and disinfected
with hydrogen peroxide
in this white, sterile room.
then they're rinsed
with sterile water
before being carried
to the filling location.
each minute,
120 bottles are filled
with pasteurized apple juice
and sealed with a cap
in a sterile environment.
bottles are then labeled
and sent to shipping.
between 20,000 and 40,000 tons
of apples
are transformed
into juice yearly.
thanks to its perfect
preservation,
consumers can enjoy this juice
at any time of the year.
narrator: what goes up,
they say, must come down,
and when what's up
is an airplane,
you need dependable landing gear
to get you back down safely.
this critical piece
of aircraft equipment
is the product
of expert mechanics
combined with sophisticated
technology.
this heavy piece of steel
is the undercarriage
of a kc-135r airplane.
a landing gear comprises
a central shaft
to which an axle and wheels
are attached.
they begin machining the shaft.
this digital lathe machines the
exterior surface of the part.
sprays of water and oil
cool the part,
which heats up due to friction.
they're now going to pierce
the shaft.
this drill head will ream out
the inside of the shaft.
alignment of the head
must be perfect,
so they're cautious
with their work.
the perforating gets under way.
turnings from the cutting
are saved,
and these will be sold
to foundries,
where they'll be recycled.
we see here the cutting tool
used to pierce the holes
in the landing gear.
to perforate the part, very
sharp cutting tools are used.
here, they complete
an attachment hole.
the hole is enlarged
on its sides,
as required
by this machine tool.
the part is cooled with a mix
of water and oil.
cutting is completed,
and the hole is now cleaned out
with compressed air
so that they can proceed
with a visual inspection.
here, three pieces are rough-cut
at the same time
by this machine.
because they'll be used
in aviation,
these pieces have to be machined
to perfection.
the machining of the shaft
is now almost completed.
this deburring unit polishes
the machine's surfaces
with a compressed-air tool
and sandpaper discs.
and now they have to verify
the dimensions of the parts.
this digitally controlled
machine has three axes
and does the verification
with extreme precision.
here, another unit allows
for the machining of parts
with greater dimensions.
this facility also reconditions
used landing gears,
such as this one
from a boeing 707.
they strip off the paint
with a sandblaster
to verify the condition of
the parts with great precision.
and here are those parts
stripped clean.
but a visual inspection
is not enough.
they can detect cracks by
magnetic-particle concentration.
they magnetize the part,
and any cracks will become
visible under ultraviolet light.
now it's time
for the shot-metal procedure,
where they spray steel balls
onto the metal's surface
to increase its resistance
to fatigue.
before repainting the part,
they first plate it.
the part is immersed
for 10 minutes in cadmium,
which forms
a protective coating on it
that will resist corrosion.
then the part is quickly soaked
in a weak concentration
of chromic acid.
water, agitated by air jets,
cleans away the chromic acid,
and the part is rinsed
with water another time.
the part is now baked
at 375 degrees over 23 hours
to remove hydrogen induced
during the plating process.
then the part is immersed in
liquid nitrogen at -200 degrees
before it's inserted
in order to reduce its size.
this collar is easily pushed
on with a hydraulic jack.
reheating the collar makes it
return to its normal size.
now the different components
and the leakproof joints
are inserted into the piston.
the shock-absorber tube
goes into the piston.
this part absorbs the shock
stresses when an aircraft lands.
the piston is now slid
into the cylinder,
and they verify that
the shock absorber is leakproof.
fabrication finishes with paint
baked in an oven.
some six to eight months
are required
to make a new landing gear
and between six to eight weeks
to recondition a used one.
narrator: perfume, eye shadow,
foundation, lipstick --
they're all products
of a huge industry
driven by our desire for beauty.
well, "how it's made"
is about to show you
how they manufacture cosmetics,
and we assure you,
we're not making this up.
during archaeological
excavations,
mummies were discovered
wearing makeup,
the egyptian technique
of enhancing eye contours
with antimony, lead,
and metal oxides --
all toxic, lethal substances.
greek women also
adorned their cheeks
with a dye made from lead oxide.
in 1910, florence nightingale,
under the name elizabeth arden,
would change
the whole makeup picture,
launching the vogue for
cosmetics without toxic agents.
cosmetics have been in existence
since the dawn of time.
there are many ingredients
that make up a cosmetic formula.
the industry heavily uses
iron oxides
to color its products in
a multitude of attractive tones.
before moving into fabrication,
each ingredient
must be carefully
and accurately weighed.
these raw materials
are often dry, such as powder,
but can also be liquid
and even oil or wax.
every ingredient
will have first been approved
by the quality-control
laboratory.
a single formula may contain
over 50 ingredients.
the other essential ingredient
is water.
the water used
in making cosmetics
is first purified
by an inverse-osmosis system.
when it meets strict
company standards,
it is put
into a stainless-steel tank.
depending on the complexity
of the recipe,
between 4 and 10 hours of work
are needed to make up a product.
let's begin
with a bubble-bath recipe.
a part of the recipe is prepared
in an adjoining container
to make certain ingredients
more soluble.
a stainless-steel
screw propeller
mixes all the ingredients
thoroughly.
all along
its fabrication processing,
the product will be subjected
to many tests.
here, an acid-based
neutralization-reaction test
is performed
with a color indicator.
the bubble bath
has to be colored.
a fragrance
and a color are added,
for in this recipe,
the final product will be mauve.
before the filling process,
the quality-control
and microbiology laboratories
make sure that the product meets
strict quality standards.
now it's on to the next step.
this filler
can simultaneously fill
up to 12 700-milliliter bottles
at a steady pace
of 50 per minute.
the fill level
is adjusted electronically.
capping remains to be done.
this capper positions and
tightens the caps automatically.
urethane rollers apply
the precise tightening force.
the bottles now pass beneath
a sealer via induction,
which generates
a magnetic field,
heating the metal piece
placed in the cap.
when hot enough, it welds itself
onto the neck of the bottle.
another product made here
is the peeling mask.
the mask is poured
into this funnel,
whose end is attached
to the tube-filler pipe.
the product descends
via gravity.
the filler pours the peeling
mask into 50 tubes each minute.
then, with heat and crimping,
the tube end is sealed,
and the tube
heads for packaging.
other products made here --
cologne and perfume.
the liquid is drawn
into the bottle by suction.
this rotating filler operates
with intermittent vacuum
to fill 50 bottles a minute.
bottles are positioned beneath
the 16 filling spouts
that seal their opening to allow
for the creation of a vacuum,
which draws in the product.
now atomizer pumps are inserted.
handling two bottles
simultaneously,
this machine seals the pump,
securing it around the neck
of the bottle.
we see the white sleeve
aligning the pump,
while the gray one
tightens the pump.
then there are the sprayers.
this machine
applies the spray stoppers
and, with a hammer, presses them
onto the pumps of the bottles,
which are now finished.
and one final product --
roll-on deodorants.
this machine
fills 115 bottles a minute,
handling 8 bottles at a time.
a filling stem pours the product
into the bottle,
and here they place the roller
ball at 115 per minute.
then the ball is lightly pressed
into the cavity
in which it turns freely.
this plant makes
over 1,200 different products
and yearly sells 32 million
items per year.
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...