[ beeping ]
♪♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
narrator: today on
"how it's made" --
pétanque balls...
♪♪
biologic medicines...
asphalt pavers...
♪♪
...and basque espadrilles.
[ sign squeaks ]
the french game of pétanque
is somewhat similar
to the italian game of bocce
and the british game
of lawn bowling.
it's played with
hollow steel balls
called boules
on a dirt or gravel surface.
the object of the game
is to toss the balls
as close as possible
to a small wooden ball.
the first pétanque players
carved their balls from wood.
by the late 1800s,
players hammered in nails
to make their balls heftier
and less likely to crack
when hitting other balls.
then came brass balls
and later the hollow
steel balls used today.
♪♪
manufacturing begins
with long bars of carbon
or stainless steel,
about 1 1/2 inches in diameter.
this is stainless steel.
an automated saw cuts pieces
about 1 3/4 inch long.
workers place the pieces
on a conveyer,
which moves them
into an induction oven.
the oven heats them
to between 1,650
and 2,190 degrees fahrenheit,
softening the steel.
as soon as a piece
comes out of the oven,
the forging press
strikes it three times,
first flattening it into a disk.
next, thinning the disk,
then stamping the disk
into a half sphere.
♪♪
workers mill the forged
half sphere
on a lathe to refine the shape
and to create a gap they later
fill with metal wire
when they weld this half to
another half to form the ball.
a worker drops the milled halves
down two separate chutes
and deliver two halves at a time
to an automated welding machine.
the machine clamps
the halves together
and welds them to each other.
a robot removes the ball
from the welding machine
and transfers it to a
computer-guided milling machine.
as the machine's lathe spins
the ball, a knife shaves off
thin layers of steel
to smooth the ball
and make the weld invisible.
this also puts the ball
within a specific diameter
and weight range in accordance
with international rules
governing the sport.
the machine also engraves
a pattern to help identify
whose balls are whose.
♪♪
international pétanque rules
require a ball
to have four items
engraved into its surface --
the brand name,
the pattern name,
the weight of the ball,
and a serial number
for the set to which
it belongs.
once the brand, pattern
and weight are engraved,
the balls move along a conveyor
toward the tempering station.
cutting, heating, forging,
and machining steel
makes it brittle and weak.
tempering is the process
of hardening it
to restore its strength.
after heating the ball
to between 1,470
and 1,830 degrees fahrenheit,
they immediately cool it in
water that's about 104 degrees,
a process known as quenching.
after tempering the steel,
manufacturers polish the ball
with an automated sander.
the finished balls
do vary slightly,
so this last automated machine
weighs each one
and sorts it in rows
of identical weight.
♪♪
then, equal weight balls
are grouped in sets of three
and are engraved with
the same serial number.
these pétanque balls
are made of carbon steel.
to prevent oxidation
and corrosion,
the factory electroplates
its carbon steel balls
with a protective
layer of chromium.
it submerges the balls
in a series of chemical baths
and water baths
to prep the surface
for the final dip
in an electroplating tank
in which an electrical current
draws chromium particles
through the water and deposits
them onto the ball's surface.
the chromium treatment
leaves a white film.
this brushing machine removes it
and restores the shiny finish.
international rules require
pétanque balls to be 2 3/4
to just over
3 inches in diameter
and weigh between 1 1/2
to 1 3/4 pounds.
the retail box contains
three identical balls
engraved with the same
serial number,
along with
the wood target ball,
a cleaning cloth,
and a warranty card.
the goal of the game
is to toss the balls as close
as possible to the target ball
while knocking the opponents'
balls away from it.
and the player's feet must
remain planted inside
a small circle when tossing.
you can play pétanque indoors
in a venue
known as a boulodrome
or boule bar,
or you can play outdoors
anywhere there's a patch
of relatively flat ground.
♪♪
narrator: biologic medicines
are proteins
produced inside living cells,
which are mini factories
generating
the genetically engineered
protein treatments.
it's a different approach
from traditional drugs,
which are manufactured
using chemical synthesis.
biologics offer hope where
other therapies have failed.
♪♪
to mass-produce
these biologic medicines,
scientists use the molecular
machinery inside living cells.
the process starts with the
insertion of genetic material
into chinese hamster
ovarian cells.
they're known as cho cells.
they keep them frozen in liquid
nitrogen until the next step.
in the seed lab, a technician
thaws the cells in warm water.
♪♪
he transfers them
to a glass flask
that contains growth media.
the growth media is comprised
of hundreds of nutrients,
including vitamins and minerals.
it's a recipe to help
the cells multiply.
♪♪
a worker transfers the flask
that contains the cells
to the production side
of the plant.
the team injects the mixture
into a 5-gallon-capacity
bioreactor.
inside, a propeller agitates
the mixture to stimulate growth.
over a 3-week period,
the number of cells
increases exponentially.
each new cell is programmed
to produce the target
biologic protein.
a worker sterilizes this
21-gallon-capacity bioreactor
to prepare it to receive
the cell mixture.
under precisely controlled
conditions in the bioreactor,
the cells multiply
substantially.
over several weeks, the team
transfers the cells
to progressively
larger bioreactors.
the cells grow until
there are trillions,
each producing
the target protein.
next, a technician measures
salts and other dry ingredients.
he's preparing a recipe
for purifying the protein liquid
once it's been separated
from the cells.
he labels the bag and records
the information
separately as required
by government regulations.
he adds the ingredients to
purified water in a mixing tank.
an automated system keeps tabs
on the condition
of the purification solution.
♪♪
after separating
cellular material
from the protein mixture,
the team pumps it through
steel and glass columns.
here, the purification solution
works with resin beads
to separate the protein
from the impurities.
♪♪
the purified protein
is stored in steel tanks
at -4 degrees fahrenheit.
it keeps the biologic medicine
in a stable state.
meanwhile,
in the quality control lab,
a technician injects a sample
into glass capsules.
she places the capsules into
a robotic analytical instrument.
this sophisticated equipment
measures the potency and purity
of the biologic medicine.
♪♪
once the biologic medicine
passes the tests,
they prepare glass vials
to receive it.
that means
an intensive cleaning.
♪♪
the automated system loads
the vials into individual slots,
and sprayers rinse them.
the system then transports
the vials through a heat tunnel
that sterilizes them to remove
any potentially harmful toxins.
moving through an isolated
sterile zone,
the vials funnel
into a fill station.
nozzles dispense a specific
dose of biologic medicine
into the vials.
here, plungers insert
stoppers in the vials.
a camera then takes a picture,
and a computer
instantly analyzes it
to confirm that the stoppers
have been correctly installed.
the system then caps the
stoppers to completely seal them
from contaminants.
this machinery hygienically
fills and caps
over 100 vials per minute.
a worker visually
inspects each vial.
he carefully swirls the contents
as he looks for impurities.
if he sees any, the vial
of medicine will be rejected.
♪♪
finally, this technician takes
a sample and conducts a test
to ensure the medicine
is sterile.
grown in living cells,
these biologic medicines
are now on their way
to potentially making
a difference in people's lives.
♪♪
narrator: the development
of the asphalt paver
in the early part
of the 20th century
changed the way roads
were built.
the paving machine took over
from large crews
who paved surfaces manually
using picks and shovels.
this invention has made it
a lot easier to pave the way.
♪♪
the asphalt paver transforms
rough roads into smooth ones.
this paving machine distributes
asphalt, levels it,
and also provides
the initial compaction.
♪♪
making one starts with
a computerized plasma cutter.
the operator programs it
to cut out all the parts of
the paver structure
from heavy-gauge steel plates.
it also configures the cutting
to minimize waste.
the plasma tooling also cuts
and threads holes
for bolting the parts together.
once the parts have been cut,
a crane transfers them
to a welding fixture.
♪♪
the fixture holds the parts
for the paver frame
in tight alignment
while a welder tacks
them together.
♪♪
he also tack welds smaller parts
like engine mounts
to the structure.
once the tack welds are done,
he does full welds throughout,
creating strong, thick seams.
♪♪
a team loads more steel into
a computerized press break.
it clamps the steel plate
between
a matching punch and die.
then, using hydraulic power,
the press break makes
precise bends
to shape the steel into
a section of the paver hopper.
with the first bend done,
one of the workers measures
the angle with a digital level
to confirm that
it's exactly right.
♪♪
the team then moves the steel
plate into position
for the next bends.
they make a total of three
in the hopper part.
those three bends must be
perfectly angled
and positioned to fit
the rest of the hopper.
♪♪
it's why precision is critical.
they do a final check of the
three bends using a template.
next, a welder joins
a side panel to the hopper part
with the three bends.
these two parts form
the left side of the hopper.
♪♪
after an acid wash, it's into
the paint booth to coat
the steel with an epoxy primer
and urethane paint.
♪♪
the parts then spend time
in an oven
to accelerate the paint cure.
then it's over to
the assembly line,
where construction of the paver
tractor is already underway.
a worker bolts gear systems
to the sides.
these gears will drive
the paver wheels.
♪♪
with the help of a crane,
the team guides
the engine into position.
the engine's mounting structure
mates to bushings
in four locations.
♪♪
they now assemble the hopper to
the front of the paving machine.
♪♪
hinge tubes on the hopper part
intermesh with tubes
on the center
conveyor framework.
they'll run a long pin
through these hinge tubes
to complete the assembly.
with everything in good
working order,
they're ready to build
the screed,
beginning with the base plate.
the screed is a critical
apparatus.
its system of vibrating
extenders both levels
and compacts the asphalt
once it's deposited on the road.
they're also equipped
with heating elements
to keep the asphalt workable.
they run a battery of tests
on all these components
to confirm that the screed
is fully operational.
♪♪
the screed is now ready to be
mated to the paver tractor.
they put the tractor in reverse
and back it up to the screed
until brackets on both meet
in perfect alignment.
♪♪
once the brackets have been
bolted together,
the asphalt paver
is ready for work.
the road ahead will be long
and potentially winding,
but it should be pretty smooth,
thanks to this asphalt paver.
♪♪
narrator: espadrilles
have been a popular style
of casual footwear
for decades now,
yet most people
likely don't know
the origin of this
comfortable cloth shoe.
europeans have been wearing
espadrilles since the 1300s.
the basque region in northern
spain is still famous for them.
espadrilles are fashion forward
and a step back in time.
the people of the basque region
have been making these cloth
and jute shoes
for hundreds of years.
they began reinforcing the soles
with rubber in the early 1900s.
jute is a plant fiber that's
spun into strong, coarse twine.
for traditional basque
espadrilles,
they use twine that's about
1/10th of an inch thick.
large jute spools feed
an automated braiding machine.
its five bobbins move
in a circular pattern
that produces a neat
braid measuring
roughly 3/4ths
of an inch wide
by a quarter of an inch thick.
♪♪
right after exiting
the braiding machine,
the braid enters
a calibration machine
which applies tension
to make the dimensions uniform.
each espadrille sole
is hand-crafted by an artisan.
he winds the braid on a form
that's more than a century old.
the positioning of the metal
pegs in the holes
correspond to the size
of the shoe he's making.
the closer the pegs
are to each other,
the smaller the shoe size.
after nine rotations for this
shoe size, he cuts the braid,
then, using a large needle,
ties off the end.
♪♪
he places the wound braid
into a press
which, as we see here
in slow motion,
compresses it into
the shape of the sole.
♪♪
in real time, this step takes
just a couple of seconds.
then he picks up the sole
with a comb
and feeds it into
an automated sewing machine.
♪♪
two large needles, one above,
one below, simultaneously stitch
all the way through the sole
with thick jute thread,
binding the wound jute braid.
♪♪
this machine sews more than
100 pairs of soles per hour.
♪♪
by now, the espadrilles'
signature jute sole
is formed and sewn,
but it's not quite finished yet.
to prevent it from wearing out,
it needs a protective layer
of rubber.
♪♪
the artisan now opens a mold
for the corresponding shoe size
and fills
the sole-shaped cavities
with a pre-measured quantity
of colorless rubber granules.
♪♪
then, he places
the jute soles on top.
♪♪
he closes the mold and places it
in a press for 6 minutes.
the press heats the mold
to 300 degrees fahrenheit,
melting the rubber granules.
the liquid rubber spreads
throughout the cavities,
penetrates the jute fibers
and vulcanizes,
meaning it hardens and cures.
this produces
a rubber outer sole
about 1/6th of an inch thick
that protects
the jute inner sole.
the espadrilles' uppers are made
of 100-percent-cotton canvas.
the artisan stacks
about 20 pieces
and cuts them simultaneously
with a razor-like blade.
each upper is comprised of a
front piece and a back piece.
a seamstress sews the upper
entirely by hand.
she wears a glove that has a
copper cup built into the palm,
which she uses to force
the giant needle
through the tough jute.
after stitching the front
and back pieces to the sole,
she sews them to each other
along the sides.
♪♪
she closes and reinforces the
toe with three rows of stitches.
♪♪
all this with strong, thick
thread made of braided cotton.
♪♪
this maker of basque espadrilles
prides itself in using
only natural materials,
even in the paper packaging.
the rubber used for the soles
contains no colorants
but is infused with citronella,
a fragrant plant oil believed
to help repel mosquitoes.
♪♪