♪♪
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: thermoplastic fire helmets are lightweight,
but that doesn't mean they aren't tough.
because of their chemical composition,
these plastic helmets
remain sturdy, even when exposed to temperatures
of over 500 degrees fahrenheit.
developed in the 1970s,
the helmets have become standard issue
at many fire stations.
♪♪
there are few situations more dangerous than entering
a burning building.
thermoplastic fire helmets weigh substantially less
than other alternatives.
these helmets are one piece of equipment
that won't slow down the rescue mission.
production starts with a special
blend of thermoplastic pellets.
a vacuum pulls the pellets into a hopper.
the pellets then flow into an injection-molding machine.
it melts and molds the pellets
into the shape of a fire helmet.
a robot retrieves the helmet
and transfers it to a cooling station.
♪♪
a worker then clips off plastic that solidified
as it flowed through a channel and into the mold.
this unwanted bit is called sprue.
she wipes off fingerprints and inspects the condition
of the helmet shell.
♪♪
the next worker trims the brim to remove excess plastic
that formed when the mold closed.
for this process, he uses a blade with a curved edge.
next, he applies reflective strips
that will allow the firefighter
to be seen in the dark.
♪♪
he drills holes for attaching either goggles or face shields.
and the worker adds a last reflective strip.
he screws a support plate for the i.d. shield
to the front of the helmet shell.
he uses plastic screws rather than metal
because metal is electrically conductive
and would put the firefighter at risk
in the event of electrical sparking during a fire.
♪♪
another worker now applies labels
to the inside of the helmet shell.
♪♪
the labels indicate that this model of fire helmet
is in compliance with the safety requirements.
the worker inserts high-density foam padding
in the helmet shell.
the padded cap will cushion the wearer
from the force of an impact.
this web of straps will serve as a suspension liner
and will also support the helmet
on the wearer's head.
♪♪
another worker installs a ratchet system for adjusting
the fit of the liner to the firefighter's head.
positioned at the nape of the neck,
the firefighter can turn the knob
to pull the suspension web tighter.
attachments on the suspension liner fit into sockets
on the helmet to lock it in place.
♪♪
he fastens the chin strap to the helmet
by wrapping the ends around molded struts
on both sides of the shell.
the chin strap has a quick-release button
in the event that the firefighter
has to remove the helmet fast.
♪♪
another worker now folds up flame-resistant earflaps.
the flaps are equipped with hooked
and looped fastening strips that fit to the helmet.
he sets the earflaps aside while he inserts snaps
for goggles into brackets on the helmet.
♪♪
he screws the snaps snugly to the helmet.
the worker then wraps the fire-and-fog-resistant goggles
around the helmet and snaps them to it.
♪♪
he tucks the maintenance instructions into the helmet,
followed by the folded earflaps.
this thermoplastic fire helmet is now complete,
but there's still one last bit of official business.
the worker screws the large leather i.d. shield
to the support plate.
the shield bears the name of the fire department
and a symbol that denotes rank.
♪♪
this fire helmet is now ready for duty.
it will be one of
the first things the firefighter
reaches for when he or she gets an emergency call.
♪♪
narrator: contemporary artists are challenging
our perception of basketry.
focusing on form rather than function,
artisans are weaving grasses
and other fibers into sculptural art.
these basketry sculptures
usually aren't meant to contain anything.
instead, they're meant to capture and hold our attention.
♪♪
is it art, or is it a basket?
a basketry sculpture is both.
it celebrates the tradition of the craft
while elevating basketry to an art form.
materials for a basketry sculpture
can include a mix of thing, from natural fibers,
to metallic pieces, wire, and beads.
soaking fibers like palm-tree strands
in hot water will soften them
and make the fibers flexible enough for weaving,
but they won't lose their interesting crinkly texture.
♪♪
about two hours in,
the artist checks the suppleness
of the fibers.
they can now be bent without breaking,
but they need a bit more softening up.
so she covers the fibers with plastic and leaves them
to soak a little longer.
she turns her attention to the sculpture's centerpiece,
which will be made of copper.
she draws a design
onto the copper's protective plastic liner.
using metal shears, she cuts out the shape.
♪♪
the artist peels off the plastic liner
that has protected the copper,
revealing the glossy, untarnished surface.
♪♪
she now places the copper above
a bag full of small pellets
and pounds it using a nylon mallet.
this process gives the copper an aged, hammered texture.
she gives some areas on the other side the same treatment.
the hammering also bowls out the profile of the piece.
using a marker, the artist draws a line
about 1/3 of an inch in from the edge.
♪♪
she marks dots onto this newly defined border,
spacing them evenly apart.
♪♪
she then punches holes through all the dots,
using a lever-operated drill press.
♪♪
she cuts out the space between the holes,
and this process creates separate tabs for each hole.
the artisan now bends back the tabs,
following the marked line.
the application of a clear
powder coat prevents tarnishing.
after a few hours, the palm strands
are now sufficiently softened.
she retrieves the strands from the hot-water soak
and sets them aside.
the artist returns to the copper centerpiece
and begins to weave, starting with rattan reeds
that have also soaked to make them more pliable.
she pulls the reeds through the tabs and intercrosses them
so that they fan out in two directions.
she then braids cotton string against the centerpiece.
this creates a neat and sturdy border all the way around.
♪♪
she clips clothespins to the rattan
to hold the braided border
in place against the centerpiece.
she then trims the ends of the strings.
♪♪
next, the artist weaves rattan reeds
parallel to the cotton braid,
entwining them with the reeds that extend outward.
she creates one row of these rigid fibers for structure.
she's now ready for the palm strands.
after the soaking, the strands
remain soft and pliable for many hours,
so she doesn't have to rush the work.
♪♪
as she continues, she alternates rows of palm
and rattan fibers.
the different textures add visual interest
to the basketry sculpture.
it will take two months to complete this work.
♪♪
when the basketry work is done,
the artist takes the piece outside
and airbrushes them with acrylic paint.
♪♪
she sometimes relies on a metal template
to more evenly define the paint border.
it's the finishing touch to the basketry sculpture,
and now it's up to the public to understand the story
that the artist has woven.
♪♪
narrator: the earliest tools for
roasting coffee beans were pans
you would hold over hot coals or an open fire,
but, today, coffee roasting
is a far more sophisticated process,
using large, often fully automated machines
with built-in gas burners
that heat air to roast the beans.
this coffee roaster is both programmable
and manually adjustable by touch panel.
the roast master can tailor the temperature
and roasting time to influence flavor,
acidity, and other characteristics of coffee.
to shape the roast chamber, workers feed a sheet
of stainless steel through a sheet-metal roll.
the roast chamber is the drum in which the beans roast
by convection heat.
the next step is to weld the rolled sheet into a cylinder.
then workers grind and polish the welds until they're flat,
smooth, and shiny.
another worker makes the cooling
tray in a similar way,
but with a support band welded to the top.
the cooling tray is the drum into which the hot beans drop
when they exit the roast chamber.
stirring arms circulate the beans as a fan draws air
through the tray to cool the hot beans.
certain parts of the roaster
are cut from a stainless-steel sheet.
stainless steel is the ideal material
not only because it's stylish,
but also because it's durable and corrosion-resistant.
this computer-guided laser cutter
is slicing out a safety component
called the heat shield, which prevents the roast master
from accidentally touching a hot surface.
♪♪
the heat shield, like many other parts
cut from stainless-steel sheets,
has to be formed to a very precise shape.
a worker bends angles and curves into the metal
with a press brake.
another component, the trier, lets you draw a sample
of beans during roasting.
a craftsman constructs the trier
by welding various smaller parts
to a piece of stainless-steel tube,
then meticulously grinding
and polishing the welds until they're smooth.
this high-pressure water-jet cutter also cuts parts
from stainless-steel sheets.
this component is one of six flights,
which is part of the paddle that lifts
and mixes the beans inside the roast chamber
so that they roast evenly.
to form the flights to the required shape,
a worker curves them one at a time in a press.
♪♪
next, the welder places all the paddle components
into a specialized fixture,
which positions them correctly.
first, he aligns the spokes to the paddle shaft.
then he welds the parts in place.
♪♪
he positions the flights, clamps them securely,
and welds them on.
♪♪
the combination of inner and outer flights
lifts the beans into the airflow,
ensuring the beans roast evenly.
♪♪
a custom-designed grinding machine hones
the flights to produce a small clearance
of around 1/10 of an inch between the edge of the paddle
and the wall of the roast chamber.
this design ensures the paddle is wide enough to pick up
every last coffee bean
without touching the wall while rotating.
♪♪
once they install the paddle, a worker closes up
the roast chamber with a faceplate.
♪♪
alignment pins ensure the faceplate