♪♪
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
♪♪
narrator: the metal bistro set
is a fixture in
european-style cafés
and small restaurants.
the set consists of a small
dining table and two chairs.
a bistro set is also popular in
homes with limited outdoor space
as there's usually
enough room for one
on a balcony or small patio.
the small restaurant bar
known as the bistro
originated
in 19th century france.
its iconic dining sets
are still being produced today
in both traditional
and modern styles.
this french factory makes them
out of strips of flat steel
with rounded edges.
the first step is
to flatten the strip
with pressure-applying rollers.
the steel then enters a press
which does three operations
simultaneously.
it cuts pieces to
the required length,
rounds their ends, and punches
out holes where required.
these are parts
for the table legs.
meanwhile,
this computer-guided machine
bends a 1/2-inch steel rod
into a circle to form a ring
that will support the tabletop.
♪♪
this table is collapsible,
allowing it to fold flat
for storage.
therefore, two of the legs
are hinged.
a pin and notch lock them
in the open position.
after putting together
the folding legs,
a worker positions all
the parts for the base
on an assembly fixture.
then he operates
a welding robot,
which welds all the crossbars,
reinforcing the legs
and the legs to the ring.
it only takes about 2 minutes
to weld all these parts
into a folding table base.
the manufacturers
make the tabletop
from a square piece
of sheet steel.
this machine first sheers
off the corners,
transforming the square
into a circle.