-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications, inc.
narrator: today on "how it's made"...
engine blocks...
...jawbreakers...
...drum shells...
...and drums.
the engine block is the largest
single piece of metal in a car
and also one of the most intricate.
it houses and links all the engine components,
such as the cylinders and pistons,
and it contains passages for circulating coolant.
the engine block is where combustion converts
into mechanical energy that drives the transmission,
propelling the car.
engine blocks used to be made of iron.
today, most are made of lightweight aluminum alloy
for fuel efficiency.
an engine block is a one-piece component
cast from a sand mold.
to make the mold, the factory mixes glue...
and a hardener...
with zircon sand.
this combination of materials
can withstand the intense heat of molten metal,
but only for one casting.
each mold is made up of sections called cores
that fit together.
to make each core,
a machine blows the sand-and-glue mixture
into a master mold made of iron.
it injects a gas that activates the hardener,
which solidifies the mixture.
this is the base core to which other cores will attach.
the base core travels down an assembly line
to receive the other cores.
the next core molds
the engine-block cylinder bores,
which will house the motor's pistons.
a robot inserts iron liners into six holes in the core.
they prevent the aluminum walls
of the bores
from wearing out from abrasion.
the base core receives 17 other cores.
the ones for engine-block areas
through which oil will flow
are coated with talcum powder.
this keeps sand particles from sticking to the aluminum
and getting into the oil.
the machines glue certain cores
so they'll stay intact when
the robots flip them upside down
and attach them to the rest.
these are the last two cores.
the mold is now fully assembled
and ready for casting.
workers load aluminum ingots
into a device called an elevator bucket.
it positions them above the jet melter --
a gas-fired furnace.
the bucket drops the ingots
into the fire
that's 1,500 degrees fahrenheit,
liquefying the aluminum.
just before casting,
they heat the cylinder-bore liners
using high-frequency electric current.
aluminum will bond better to hot metal.
they fill the molds from the bottom
to avoid contaminating the metal
with aluminum oxide.
oxide forms when molten aluminum
comes into contact with the air.
pouring into the top of the mold
would expose the metal to oxygen,
and the pouring action itself would mix in the oxide.
after the casting,
the mold spends six hours in what's called
a thermal sand reclaim oven.
that breaks down the glue so the sand falls away.
the heat also strengthens the metal.
the cast aluminum engine blocks emerge,
needing just some minor finishing.
robots turn them upside down to spill out loose sand.
machines saw off the risers --
extra metal that fed the mold cavity
to compensate for the 7% shrinkage that occurs
when liquid aluminum solidifies.
finally, computer-guided tooling equipment
performs a rough machining of the metal.
this brings the engine blocks to a near-finished state.
the engine plant that buys them
does the final machining before
installing the engine parts.
every engine block this factory produces
passes through an automated vision system
that inspects the engine block
to ensure they have no defects whatsoever.
narrator: jawbreakers, also known as gobstoppers,
have preoccupied candy lovers for decades.
you pop one in
and slowly suck or chew through up to 10 layers
of colors and flavors.
sometimes there's bubble gum in the middle
for an even longer-lasting finish.
the larger ones are just for show.
most jawbreakers are about the size of a golf ball.
to make their bubble gum centers,
a worker blends synthetic rubber
with powdered resin,
which will dissolve the rubber.
he adds a thickener, a preservative,
and an oil called soya palm stearin
so the candy won't stick to your teeth.
after mixing and steaming at 300 degrees fahrenheit
for four hours,
the batter pours into trays to cool.
sugar, coloring, and flavoring would deteriorate in the heat,
so workers add those later.
there's enough of this base to make gum centers
for 450,000 small jawbreakers.
after 24 hours, the batter is hard.
workers chop it up and blend it with corn syrup
to make it softer and sweeter.
they add just under 100 pounds of finished gum
that didn't make it into jawbreakers before
because it wasn't the right shape.
now they add natural and artificial flavors,
which can include lemon, orange,
strawberry, grape,
even tutti-frutti.
then they add icing sugar.
it makes the gum smoother to chew than regular sugar would.
workers dump the batch into an extruder
that shapes two continuous streams of batter, called rope.
another extruder divides
each rope into six hollow tubes.
the cavity inside will become pockets of air
inside the gum centers.
the next machine slices the tubes
into segments that are three feet, three inches long.
a mechanical arm pushes the segments
into the channel of a forming machine.
steel rolls then slice through the tubes
and shape them into balls.
the balls range in diameter,
depending on the size of the jawbreakers being produced.
air blows through perforations in a cooling tunnel
to cool and firm the centers.
then they fall into another forming machine,
which restores their round shape.
other jawbreakers have hard candy in the center.
the machine that makes them works like
the presses drug companies use to make pills.
it feeds candy powder into dies,
then applies up to five tons of force
to compress the powder into a solid candy.
now for the rest of the jawbreaker.
first, they dump the candy centers
into what's called a coating pan.
they add a hot mixture of water,
corn syrup, and food coloring...
...then dextrose, a type of powdered sugar.
the pan rotates for 20 minutes
as warm air dries the ingredients over the centers.
the factory repeats this step 10 times for each layer.
talk about a sweet ordeal --
making a jawbreaker takes four days.
workers give this batch special treatment.
they speckle these jawbreakers with different colors,
giving them what this company calls the psychedelic look.
after letting the candies dry for 24 hours,
a worker adds pinches of powdered carnauba wax.
this gives the jawbreakers a shiny finish.
sliced open,
you can see these jawbreakers have 10 layers
of flavors and sugar surrounding either hard candy
or bubble gum cores.
they measure 2 1/4 inches in diameter --
as big as a billiard ball.
and if you're counting calories,
forget it.
a jawbreaker is 90% sugar.
narrator: almost every culture has used drums in some way.
drums have been a part of different civilizations
for thousands of years.
the earliest drum shells were hollowed-out logs or gourds.
different sizes created different sounds.
today, drum shells are more sophisticated and consistent.
to make drum shells,
they slice an enormous rock maple log
into several boards.
maple is ideal for making drum shells
because its hardness allows sound to resonate fully.
each of these maple boards
will be transformed into one drum shell.
workers feed the boards to a ripsaw,
which cuts them to the correct width.
this varies depending on
the size of the drum being made.
then each board goes into a planer,
which shaves it thinner.
a worker aligns the board with markings on a saw table.
this positions the board
to be cut to the correct length.
a radial arm saw does the job neatly.
now he sizes up each board in preparation for tapering.
he places a board on an angle in a jig
and then moves the end against a router cutter to taper it.
it takes a few passes to get it
just right.
the taper needs to be about six inches long.
he thins the other end of
the board to the same dimension.
these tapered ends will make it
easier to bend the wood
into a drum shape later.
they'll also act as scarf joints
which will fasten the ends of the board together
when it's bent round.
but first this board needs some softening up.
an hour in the steam box does the trick.
it's pliable enough to wind around a hot cylindrical form.
steel banding secures the board
to the bending form,
where it will spend 10 to 15 minutes.
a worker pries apart the ends...
...and applies a generous amount
of glue
between the tapered tips.
then he removes the shim that was holding the ends apart,
so that they stick together.
he places a wooden guard over the glued joint.
this nylon mesh band is a clamp.
he wraps it around the drum shell
and turns a screw to pull the band tightly around the wood
until it reaches 14 inches in diameter.
then he fastens over a dozen steel clamps onto the joint.
all these clamps will prevent any gaps
from occurring in the joint as the glue sets overnight.
with the joint sealed,
the drum shell now spins while a cutter shaves down the edges
to make it a true round shell.
then they bring in another cutter.
it bores into the shell,
making a smooth edge and rounding the inside.
he turns the drum shell around to cut it from another angle.
as the shell spins,
a high-speed cutter shaves the outside from top to bottom.
this makes the surface very smooth.
it takes about a week to make a drum shell from solid wood,
and it will be able to stand up
to some loud playing.
narrator: there's more than one way to beat a drum,
and there's more than one way to make one.
earlier, we showed you how they create a drum shell
from a maple plank.
but a newer technique involves
layering multiple plies of wood.
this process is called laminating,
and you can hear the difference.
the laminated drum is an instrument of change.
its sound is crisper
than a drum crafted from a single piece of wood.
to make one, they layer 11 sheets of maple.
here, a worker glues on the final ply
using a special adhesive.
this outer layer is a luxurious bird's-eye maple.
rollers press all the layers together
to ensure they stick without any gaps.
then they cut through the overlap
to create a perfect seam.
a robotic drill now takes over.
it drills holes of various diameters.
the small ones will hold hardware.
this larger one is an air vent.
a computerized router then cuts
the bearing edges
to a 45-degree angle,
and a worker sands it smooth.
he uses a level surface
to ensure that all the edges are perfect.
if they're not, the drumheads won't fit properly.
he applies an adhesive to the air hole
and inserts a plastic vent.
next, he inserts brackets, called lugs,
into the other holes and screws them in.
there are 10 lugs, spaced 36 degrees apart.
they'll hold the rods
that will attach the heads to the drum shell
and also enable the drummer
to adjust the tension on the heads.
here he attaches a lever to control wires, called snares,
that are to be strung across the bottom head.
it's called a snare strainer.
then he fits a plastic drumhead
over the bottom of the shell.
the counter hoop goes on next.
it has little tabs which he aligns with each lug.
he slides tension rods into the holes in the tabs.
using a drum key,
he tightens the head to an even tension across the shell.
now he blasts it with a heat gun
to shrink the plastic and remove any wrinkles.
now he places another plastic head on the top bearing edge.
since this head is the one that gets played,
it's twice as thick as the bottom one.
he places the chrome rim on it and tightens the tension rods.
these brass brackets will hold the snare wires.
he slides them under the snares
that are stretched tightly across a jig,
putting one at each end.
he measures the length,
then solders the snare wires to the brackets.
he snips the wires on both ends...
...and unlocks each wire from the holding device.
when he removes the snares,
they're held together by the brackets.
he slides a nylon strap into one of the brackets,
then attaches the strap to a fixture
just above the bottom head.
the other end of the snare is attached to the strainer --
the lever that will apply tension and release it,
controlling its distinctive buzz.
for a bigger sound, there's the bass drum.
it's made with wooden hoops.
they attach the hoops to the drum shell with steel claws.
as they screw the claws to the hoop,
the drumhead is pulled just tightly enough
to produce that low-pitched bass drum sound.
now it's off to be played.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...