--  captions by vitac  --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
>> narrator: the latest
taxidermy trend is motion.
centers feature wildlife
models
that move. these rob
lifelike that hunters use them
as decoys and game wardens set
the act.
activated by remote control,
the robotic deco
its tail wags.
more elaborate models have
the decoys can be set up
directly on the ground or  i
which moves it along as though
it is walking.
at the decoy factory, they b
by waxing a two-part
fiberglass
body mold. this one'
waxing the mold cavity will
make
it easy to extract the
casting.  next, the
reinforcement bars in the
legs.
the bars stick out the bottom
of
the hoofs as stakes to prop
decoy on the ground.
they apply the other half of
perimeter to hold the two
parts
together.  they prep
deer's head the same way, then
pour in a bit of liquid
casting    materia
they pour about three quarts
of it into the body mold...
this casting material is
expanding polyurethane foam.
and within two minutes reaches
full expansion, transforming
solid.
over the next hour and a half,
inflexible state, at which
point they remove the clamps
some foam seeped out between
the two halves of the molds
and  between whe
the body, producing seams
which
workers now sand flat.  us
make one-inch sockets for
eyes.
then, with a miniature router
they glue a glass eye into
each
socket with a bit of wet clay.
when the clay dries, the eye
set securely in place.
no faux fur for these decoys.
flesh off a real deer hide,
then wash the hide and apply
then they slip the hide over
the foam deer.
they fit the fur to the form
snugly using a combination of
once the deer is fully
dressed,
it is put aside for four to
six weeks.
this gives the preservative
ample time to penetrate and do
harden the hide.
this is essential to ward off
from decomposing.
the taxidermy phase of   p
now off with his head...
because it is time to install
the head move.
the first step is to drill out
this creates a pocket in which
to install the plastic housing
components.
the first of those components
it drives this hard plastic
gear.   next, the
remote control...
then a aa battery pack that
the receiver.
all this goes into the neck p
they drill out a cavity in the
head and install a gear and s
the final step is to mount the
head on to the body, inserting
of the motor.
so now when the motor runs, it
the shaft, which moves the
decoy's head.    each
the identical mechanics, its
receiver corresponding to a d
control.
the remote works for more
you can even program it to put
the decoy through a pre-set m
>> narrator: often considered
to be a veggie, the tomato is
it is developed from the ovary
of the plant and it has seeds.
it is also the most popular
on the planet.
mechanization of canning in t
possible, ensuring that
tomatoes
are preserved when they are
ripe   and ready.
all you need is a can opener
to
unlock the juicy flavor of the
there are more than 2,000
varieties.
for canning purposes, they
a type with a thick skin and
firm consistency so machinery
damaging the flesh.
rotating clippers cut the
vines  as the har
the crop.
once cut, the plants ride
the harvester.
inside the harvester, metal
to free them from the vines.
an electronic color sorter r
a conveyor transfers the red,
ripe tomatoes to a trailer t
harvester.
once they have a load of 24
tons, they deliver the
to the canning factory.
here they fill the trailer
with
water to float the tomatoes
through a door at the side.
the tomatoes land on a slatted
the water, dirty from residual
soil, drains away through the
the tomatoes land in a clean,
water-filled channel, and here
and are removed.
the tomatoes float on into a
big  tank where
water for more gentle
cleansing
action.  the tomato
a sorting line.
they travel over metal bars
and  smaller tom
the gaps.
they will be used to make  t
the others fly forward past 60
tiny cameras that detect pale
pneumatic fingers knock those
tomatoes out of the batch.
a second.
looking for a damaged or
broken  fruit now,
tomatoes.
they send any rejects to
another part of th
to make juice.
the rest take the plunge into
this scalds the tomatoes and
loosens the skins.   the
a moving bed of rubber disks,
and this gently pulls the
skins away from t
a spray of water washes away
the skins and they fall
through
the rubber disks so there is
mess to clean up after
peeling.
the now-peeled tomatoes wash
up  on to anothe
sprayers give them another
rinse.
this conveyor controls the
of peeled tomatoes into the
processing room by metering
the produce as it moves
ahead, the dicer awaits.
it has three sets of  cro
serious slicing action.
the tomatoes tumble down a
shoot into the di
chopped into small cubes.
the diced tomatoes ride by
workers who pick out pieces
aren't perfectly red.
they also remove any core pi
exiting a cleaning station,
the cans cue up for a fill-up.
into metal pockets.
this portions them out for
the pockets rotate forward to
meet the cans now moving in
sync below.
the bottoms of the pockets
open
to release the contents into
and it all happens with
perfect
timing.  they add h
flavorings...
and lids advance towards th
they land on top and a machine
crimps the lids to the cans,
a complete seal.
now in airtight cans, the  t
for a quick cook.
this sterilizes them,   el
preservatives.
the cans are now ready for
they spin across wheels that
apply glue to the sides.
they roll over paper labels
adhere to the glue-covered
cans.
here is the labeling action
the label contains brand and
nutritional information as
well
as the exact time of  pro
this means it can be traced if
there is ever a quality issue.
for these field tomatoes to be
harvested, canned, and
labeled,  preservin
to be enjoyed year-round.
>> narrator: in every sport,
fans need to know the score.
in the early days,  scor
climbed ladders to scrawl
numbers on a chalkboard.
the score might have changed,
and it was time to start
again.   modern sc
the numbers in an instant.
today's digital scoreboards
game change, delivering
results
fast and leaving fans cheering
they start with the front of
the board.    a comp
a plasma torch to cut out
precisely-sized slots in  a
the slots will house the
illuminated numerals and in
a worker then feeds narrower
strips of steel to a press
that bends back t
tabs.
these strips will serve as the
the tabs will be used to
install
them.   using a sp
air tool, a worker clinches
the tabs to the back of the
this tool punches and
stretches
the steel to interlock it,
joining the parts without u
screws, rivets, or welds.
he fastens four strips to th
he then attaches the
plasma-cut
front panel to complete the
the scoreboard.
the next worker sprays a
the entire scoreboard.
then it is into a giant
14 minutes to cure the
powder paint.  the res
powder-paint skin that will
make
it possible for the scoreboard
they are now ready for working
parts like l.e.d.
light-studded
digit boards, a data  tra
and receiver.
he connects the receiver to
it inside the cabinet.
he pulls the antenna through
a hole so it protrudes from
front, and he bends it out of
the way for now.
there are several light
digit plates on a scoreboard.
each can flash any number.
interconnecting them in what's
known as a daisy-chain con
he also plugs in a
ribbon-style
cable to link the digits to
module.
he inserts the digits in the
them with a sheet of
transparent
polycarbonate.   he sc
around each digit assembly
to secure it. he confi
good and that all the numbers
light up.    he conn
computer processing module
to the numbers and also wires
it   to a power
he mounts the module to a
panel
that will then be installed t
scoreboard cabinet.
an evening inkjet printer
on adhesive-backed paper
followed by some
fierce-looking team gr
later, a weatherproof coating
will be applied to the paper
they also use vinyl decals.
the worker peels away the  u
the lettering.
this is called weeding.  af
to applicator tape called the
pre-mask, she carefully
the front of the scoreboard.
satisfied that it's in the
the top.
she then peels off the
backing,  and the l
pre-mask.
using a squeegee, she presses
smoothing any messy-looking
bubbles or buckles. she r
then lifts the pre-mask very
carefully so as not to lift
any  of the deca
with all the lettering now in
place, the numbers on the
board   will mean
crowds in the stands.
they equip the scoreboard
with a
speaker and horn that will s
off in the event of a
touchdown.
and no need to run cable from
the scoreboard to the   k
it is operated by remote
control.
using that system, a worker
tests all the functions of the
scoreboard.
this test is thorough and t
about 20 minutes.
when it is done, he declares
action.
today's sports scoreboards
come   in any sha
customer desires.
when it comes to drumming up
scoreboard can be a
game-changer.
>> narrator: a lasso, also
called a lariat, is a classic
catching running cattle.
on one end, there is a moving
animal's head.
this loop tightens around the
the animal in its tracks.
working a lasso requires
so much so that rodeos
typically
hold roping contests and
feature  performan
maneuvers.
the ropemaker starts by
looping   five nyl
bushing mounted on a traveling
box. he ties the
of three spinning eyes...
then runs the five threads
second spinning eye, then back
to the bushing.  he the
drives the traveling box to
another traveling box, pulling
a length of 15 yards.
he transfers the threads from
the bushing to a spinning eye
this second traveling box...
then pulls the threads back to
make the other half of the r
when he arrives at the
starting
point, he loops the threads
then he pulls all the threads
to equal tension, cuts them
from
their spools, and ties them
this completes what's known
as the stringing process.
next comes the twisting
a motor turns the three
spinning
eyes, twisting the 10 threads
the three strands together
into
a lasso rope that's around
2/10th's of an inch in   d
the twisting force pulls the
two boxes toward each other.
amount of weight in each box.
that determines the stiffness
from extra soft to medium
hard.
a rope this length takes about
the ropemaker now wraps the
end
with electrical tape so that
the
rope won't unravel when he
it loose.
he pulls the rope at the
center   to releas
then just beyond the taped end
snips the strands free.  he
ends with a hot blade that
slices the nylon threads
he lays the rope in piping-hot
wax.   it seeps i
crannies, permeating the
threads
deep inside, setting the
twist.
after suspending the rope for
a
while to let the excess wax
drip
off, he connects it to a
mechanism inside a heated
room,
or, in summertime, outdoors
stretching for a couple of
days
pulls out any waves, ensuring
straight.
next, he cuts off the knot and
unravels just enough rope to
a knot for what's called a
hondo.
that's the eye in the rope w
lets him build the loop that
catches the animal.   on
different type of knot, one
which will keep the rope
using pliers and a vice, he
pulls both knots tight... sl
blade of the rope cutter...
then burns the ends with a
now, he ties the hondo.
the hondo slides along the
rope,  loosening
loop.
he hangs the hondo on a hook
and, using a specially
wheel, pulls it tight.
then he sews a piece of
rawhide   into the
this piece of leather is
called
the burner.
it prevents the eye from
through, meaning wearing out,
as the rope slides through it.
he bangs it with a hammer to
seat it in the rope grooves...
then stamps the company name
on it and marks the rope's
stiffness.
lassos come in various degrees
of stiffness for different
types
of animals and purposes, such
as
roping cattle by the head or
by
the heels.
if you have any comments about
the show or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future
shows,
drop us a line at...