>> narrator: with commercially
cultivated grass, you could have
the perfect lawn in minutes.
it comes in pre-grown sheets,
fresh from the turf farm, ready
to transplant.
first produced in the middle of
the last century, commercially
grown grass continues to change
the landscape and make the
neighbors green with envy.
don't feel like sitting around,
watching the grass grow?
with commercially cultivated
turf, there's no need.
upon delivery, workers simply
unroll it and trim it.
it's like installing carpeting,
and this is, in fact, a living
carpet.
with regular watering, it will
start to put down roots.
it should take about three weeks
to become established, and then
it's time to rev up the
lawn mower.
it starts with a seed variety
appropriate to the climate.
this farm is in the
american midwest, and that calls
for a cool-season species,
kentucky bluegrass.
they compost grass clippings and
leftover turf in a big pile and
use it to enrich the farm's
soil.
next, using an aerator, they
punch holes in the soil.
this loosens it, allowing
nutrients and oxygen to
infiltrate.
aerating also breaks up the
rootstock left from the previous
crop.
since grass is a perennial, a
new crop will grow from these
leftovers, and they'll only need
to plant seed every three or
four crops.
after about five weeks, the
grass has begun to sprout.
a sprinkler system helps spur
the growth.
it's a central-pivot irrigation
system, a wheeled tower that is
1,200 feet long, with numerous
sprayers.
it slowly circles the turfgrass
field to give it a thorough
soaking.
next up is the fertilizer.
it will give the grass the
energy it needs to flourish.
the big three ingredients are
nitrogen, phosphorus, and
potassium.
but the mix also contains
micronutrients, like iron, zinc,
and magnesium, for an extra
boost.
they fertilize the field four to
five times a year, using a
supersized version of a home
rotary spreader.
pulled by a tractor, it flings
fertilizer out the back to cover
a lot of terrain very fast.
an application of herbicide
keeps the weeds at bay as the
grass grows and the blades
become denser.
once it's thick enough, it
should resist weed invasion.
they mow it three to four times
a week, never cutting more than
a third of the total leaf.
anything more would cause the
grass to focus on repairing
top growth at the expense of
establishing a substantial root
system.
when an ordinary lawn tractor
can't keep up, they bring out a
mega version.
it has three mower decks, each
with three blades.
it can mow an area the size of
10 american football fields in
one hour.
they leave the clippings behind
for added fertilizer.
it takes about 18 months for the
roots to fully develop and form
a thick mass.
that means the turfgrass can now
be harvested without falling
apart.
as the harvester moves forward,
rollers at the front compress
the grass.
behind the rollers, a wide blade
cuts the turf at the roots,
removing just 2/10 inch of
topsoil.
at the sides, spatula-like
mechanisms lift the turf onto a
conveyor.
once there, another blade cuts
it into strips.
the strips head up to a device
that rolls them up like one
would roll a sleeping bag.
the conveyor transfers the rolls
to a platform where a robotic
arm with spears retrieves them
and stacks them on a pallet,
five at a time.
when the stack is big enough,
the harvester lowers the pallet
of grass rolls onto the field.
it moves on to continue
harvesting.
a forklift collects the rolled
turf for shipment.
this turf has been cut to order
for same-day delivery.
they'll install it fresh from
the farm so it doesn't have time
to dry out and turn yellow.
this grass has been a year and a
half in the making.
it's now ready to transform a
dusty yard into a lush, green
one for instant curb appeal.
>> narrator: if you're craving a
snack that's portable and packs
a good dose of protein, then
some beef jerky might just hit
the spot.
eating dried, cured strips of
meat dates back to the ancient
cultures of south america.
jerky may be an english
mispronunciation of a native
word for burnt meat.
beef jerky is no longer a means
of sustenance but rather a
popular snack food that comes in
a variety of flavors.
this premium brand is
hand-crafted in small batches.
the process starts with bee
rounds -- a lean cut from the
muscular hindquarter of the cow.
there's just a bit of fat --
enough to give the meat good
flavor.
workers put the beef rounds
through a slicer, which cuts
them into thin strips of
identical width so that the
jerky pieces come out as uniform
as possible.
the direction in which the
slicer cuts, as well as the
thickness of the slices --
2/10 inch -- are calculated to
maximize flavor and tenderness.
the next step, marinating, will
further tenderize the meat.
many large producers inject the
marinade prior to slicing.
this company marinates after
slicing so that the marinade is
sure to tenderize and flavor
every single slice of beef.
after loading a small batch of
meat into a rotating drum,
workers add the marinade
ingredients -- a secret recipe
consisting of both dry and
liquid seasonings.
the meat and marinade spin
together for more than an hour.
by the time the strips come out
of the drum, they're drenched in
marinade.
after marinating for another
24 hours, they're ready to go
into the smokehouse.
workers lay the marinated beef
strips on stainless-steel rods.
they space them well apart to
enable the hot air to penetrate
each and every one from all
angles.
once they fill a rod, they hang
it on a rolling rack.
a rack holds 100 rods -- roughly
240 pounds of beef strips.
each rack goes into its own
individual smokehouse, inside
which two simultaneous processes
occur.
water-soaked hardwood chips
burn, slow-smoking the meat.
the jerky also cooks slowly at
low heat, no higher than
180 degrees fahrenheit, to
maximize the flavor.
the variety of beef jerky
dictates the type of hardwood
they use.
for sweeter flavors, such as
honey barbecue or teriyaki, they
smoke with hickory or applewood,
whereas for more savory or spicy
flavors, they use mesquite wood.
over the course of 5 to 7 hours
in the smokehouse, the
circulated warm air gradually
dries out and cures the meat,
and the smoke from the wood
infuses it.
quality-control technicians take
samples from each fully-smoked
batch and measure to make sure
it's the required thickness of
just over 1/10 inch.
after workers cut the strips to
between 2 and 3 inches long, the
jerky enters an automated scale,
which weighs out the quantity
per package.
meanwhile, an automated
packaging machine heat-seals the
bottom and sides of printed
plastic film, forming a pouch,
then inserts a resealable zipper
and prints on the lot number and
best-by date.
the machine then cuts apart each
individual pouch and flushes the
inside with nitrogen.
this forces out fresh food's
worst enemy, oxygen.
then, the machine drops in
additional ammunition -- a tiny
oxygen-absorbing packet.
now the pouch is ready to
receive its allotment of
beef jerky.
in the smokehouse, the raw beef
loses about three-quarters of
its weight as the moisture
inside evaporates and the fat
cooks off.
so one pound of raw beef yields
only about 3 1/2 ounces of
beef jerky.
a conveyor belt transports the
now-sealed pouches to the boxing
and shipping area.
every 5 minutes, quality-control
technicians take a sealed pouch
off the line to measure the
nitrogen and oxygen levels
inside.
earlier on, they tested samples
from every single batch coming
out of the smokehouse to make
sure the slow-cooking process
killed off all the bacteria in
the beef and dried it
sufficiently to ensure this
meaty treat has a minimum
shelf life of 14 months.
>> narrator: the wood chipper
was invented in germany in 1884.
today's commercial-size chippers
devour wood debris and even
entire trees in mere seconds,
spitting out chips that can be
used as garden mulch.
that's why the wood chipper is
one fierce recycler.
whether it's a fallen tree or
just a few broken limbs, a
wood chipper will sink its teeth
into the problem and transform
it into something useful.
there are different kinds of
chippers.
this one is drum-style.
it has a feed wheel with
serrated edges that pushes wood
into the revolving drum.
inside, knives tear into the
wood to chop it into little
pieces.
it's the forestry equivalent of
a paper shredder.
to make the chipping drum,
rollers curl a rectangular sheet
of steel to transform it into a
cylinder.
the gap between the rollers
determine the cylinder's
diameter.
it takes a few passes through
the rollers before one end of
the rectangle meets the other
and it becomes round.
at the next station, a worker
cuts four large rectangular
holes into the cylinder, using a
plasma torch.
he staggers the location of the
holes.
each hole will be equipped with
a blade and a deep pocket for
catching the wood chips.
he now inserts those pockets
into the slots and welds them to
the drum.
the staggered location of the
blade pockets means that
no matter where the tree branch
ends up in the drum, it will
come into contact with the
chipper blades.
those blades will be installed
later.
next, he welds the ends to the
chipper drum.
the ends have holes for a shaft
and for accessing the inside of
the drum.
then, the drum spins, and
sensors pick up vibrations,
which would indicate an
imbalance.
a computer analyzes the data and
determines how much weight needs
to be added to the drum and
where.
the technician locates the spot
on the drum, using this gauge.
once he finds it, he marks it
with a piece of soapstone.
he then places a metal weight on
the mark and welds it there.
like the tires on a vehicle, a
wood-chipper drum needs to be
balanced in order to run
smoothly.
four super-sharp blades are
installed horizontally above the
blade pockets.
he bolts them down tightly to
withstand a spinning speed of
1,200 rotations per minute.
once the drum has been equipped
with a shaft and a fan for
moving the wood chips out, they
lower the drum onto the base.
a crane does the heavy lifting
as a worker guides the shaft
bearings into the mounts.
he adds some upper housing to
protect the bearings from
debris.
these bearings will need to be
replaced after extensive use.
the hood is next.
it's equipped with a chute for
ejecting the wood chips.
they attach the hood to the
base, and this encapsulates the
wood-chipper drum to keep the
chipping action under wraps.
moving to the other side now,
they install the feed rollers
and another chute.
they activate the feed rollers
manually and check the distance
between them and the chipper
drum to confirm that there's
adequate clearance.
with a crane again bearing the
load, workers now steer the
diesel engine towards the
chipper and lower it into
position.
they thread a drive belt around
the engine pulley and link it to
one that's been attached to the
drum's side bearings.
they complete that installation
and install the tires.
they mask the tires with plastic
to protect them as they now
prime and paint the entire
wood chipper.
they use a polyurethane paint
developed for american military
vehicles.
this tough finish will resist
scratching as tree trunks and
branches are dragged through it.
they paint the wood chipper a
brilliant orange so it will
stand out on the work site.
once the paint is cured, they
shield the drive belt with a
metal cover, painted to match
the rest of the machine.
they transfer a vinyl decal onto
the side.
it conveys the make and model of
the wood chipper.
after nine days of work, the
wood chipper is ready for
action.
ripping big trees to shreds
should be no trouble at all.
>> narrator: here's a somewhat
striking statistic.
an estimated 95 million people
worldwide partake in the sport
of bowling.
one of the most popular
variations is 10-pin bowling, in
which you roll a big, heavy ball
down a lane, aiming to knock
down 10 large pins.
the sport's international
governing body dictates very
strict and precise
specifications for pin
manufacturing to ensure pins
worldwide react uniformly to the
ball.
as required, this bowling-pin
factory uses hard maplewood with
a moisture level within
regulation range.
workers weigh the slabs and
calculate which ones they'll
group together to produce a
regulation-weight pin.
they glue together three slabs
to form a starting block for a
single pin.
then, they stack several blocks
in a vise and clamp them tightly
until the glue dries -- about
15 minutes.
a few light taps with a rubber
mallet separates any
stuck-together blocks.
next, a custom-designed machine
drills three holes in each
block, hollowing out what will
be the center of the bowling
pin.
this removes some weight and
leaves space for the wood to
expand and contract with
humidity levels.
one hole is at the bottom of the
block for the base ring they'll
later attach underneath the pin.
they lay the block in a carousel
vise and glue a small slab of
wood to each side.
after 12 to 15 minutes under
pressure, the glue sets and the
now-wider block comes off the
vise.
they transfer to another
carousel, which runs it through
a planer.
this removes gobs of dried,
excess glue and levels the top
and bottom surfaces.
now on to another carousel, to
receive wood slabs on the two
remaining sides.
after the glue fully cures for
24 hours, those sides also go
through the planer.
the block is now ready to
acquire the bowling-pin shape.
workers mount the block on a
lathe, via the hole on the
bottom for the base ring.
as the lathe spins, cutters
gradually shave away wood,
forming the pin shape.
this whole operation takes about
45 seconds.
the next machine saws off excess
wood from the top and bottom,
then drills and cuts those
surfaces smooth.
the machine inserts a nylon ring
into the hole in the pin's base.
next stop, an injection-molding
machine.
it coats the entire pin surface
in liquefied nylon, then quickly
cools the nylon solid.
this protects the wooden pin
with a hard, durable covering.
now a weigh-in to make sure it
falls within regulation range --
between 53 and 56 ounces.
in the final operation, a
printing machine spins the pin
under an inkpad to apply
decorative stripes.
then, another pad prints the
manufacturer's logo.
the ink dries to the touch in
just 5 minutes and fully cures
in 24 hours.
crafted from wood slabs in about
40 minutes, plus ink-curing
time, these bowling pins are
alley-ready.
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...