narrator:
having a multi-tool on hand
is like having
a toolbox in your pocket.
it contains anywhere from
5 to 21 basic implements,
from screwdrivers and scissors
to can openers and pliers.
they all fold in and out
of the handles, forming a case
that's compact enough
to be carried in your pocket.
this multi-tool
contains 14 different tools,
including scissors, a knife,
wire cutters,
two types of pliers,
three different screwdrivers,
and much more.
most of these tools
and the handle into
which they conveniently fold
are made of stainless steel.
the strip of stainless steel
winds off a reel
and moves through
a 300-ton punch press.
it works
like a giant cookie cutter,
striking a series of dies
against the passing metal,
progressively stamping out,
in this case,
one part of the multi-tool's
two-part handle.
17 strikes later,
it's fully formed
and ready to go through
a heat-treatment process
to strengthen
the stainless steel.
next, a polishing robot runs the
handle against a grinding wheel.
it does so with specific
programmed movements
which produce a delicate lined
pattern on the metal surface.
certain tools,
like knife blades,
are made of premium steel
that is too hard for the press
to punch through,
so they have to be cut out
by a computer-guided laser.
the laser's heat literally
melts through the metal.
the knife blades go into
a polishing machine,
where they vibrate among ceramic
stones for several hours.
this smoothes out
the rough edges by abrasion.
a magnet then removes the blades
from the machine.
the knife blades,
still dull at this point,
go onto a motorized table
that runs them back and forth
under a grinding wheel.
this finalizes the dimensions.
the two jaws
that form the plier head
are cast in steel.
workers assemble them
with a spring...
...a pin...
...and a rivet.
then a robot
performs a two-stage polishing,
first against a grinding belt
with the rough grit,
then against
one with a finer grit.
the plier head is at last
ready to be assembled
to the multi-tool's
two-part handle.
they align the holes
of the handle
with holes of the plier head,
slipping a spacer in between.
they put a pin
and screw fastener
through the aligned holes
to connect handle to head.
back to the knife blade now.
until this point, the blade's
cutting edge has been dull.
now a robot sharpens it
against two grinding wheels.
this is what the knife blade
looks like before...
and after.
with the handle and all 14 tools
formed, heat treated,
and polished, and the pliers
connected to the handles,
final assembly can begin --
the remaining tools stacked
together inside the two handles
with the stainless-steel ring
to fill up the excess width.
the assemblers thread a rod
all the way through
the holes of the base
of the handle and tools
to hold the alignment
until they secure the setup
with the stainless-steel pin
and rivet.
they repeat this process
in the other handle
with the remaining tools,
except for the knife blade
and scissors,
which go in later.
they apply a few drops
of thread lock
to immobilize the pins
in each handle.
a bronze washer makes the handle
housing the knife blade
open smoothly to prevent injury.
they install a safety cover
on that same handle
to shield the sharp knife
when it's not in use.
now the knife blade itself.
they rivet the scissors
to the other handle,
and the assembly is finished.
this multi-tool, with its
14 different implements,
is ready to be folded up
and tucked in a pocket
or unfolded, offering up
the right tool for the task.
narrator: jojoba oil
isn't actually an oil.
it's a liquid wax from
the seed of the jojoba plant,
native to the sonoran desert
areas in arizona,
california, and mexico.
jojoba oil is
a common ingredient in soaps,
shampoos, moisturizers,
eye makeup, lip products,
and color cosmetics.
cosmetics manufacturers
buy refined jojoba oil
from a processing facility.
jojoba in its natural state
is golden
and has a slightly nutty odor.
once refined, it can be rendered
colorless and odorless.
the jojoba farm
takes selected cuttings
from mature jojoba shrubs,
roots and grows them
for 18 months to 2 years
in a greenhouse,
then transplants them
into the fields.
the wind carries pollen
from the male plants
to fertilize female plants,
after which the female seed
starts developing.
each seed is housed
inside a hull
that gradually dries out
and separates,
dropping the seed to the ground.
the fallen seeds
are mature for harvest.
the mechanical harvester works
like a giant vacuum cleaner,
sucking the seeds
off the ground,
along with a lot of sand,
twigs, and rocks.
the harvester then dumps its
collection into a large hopper
that feeds an elaborate
seed-cleaning machine.
in it, the seeds and debris
move from conveyor to conveyor
through a series
of vibrating screens,
each made
of increasingly smaller mesh.
the process gradually sifts out
smaller and smaller bits
of debris...
...until only the seeds
are left.
they go into
huge polyethylene bags,
then off to the processing plant
where workers empty the bags
into a holding area
called a seed pit.
from here, conveyors
take the seeds to the presses.
the liquid wax is contained
within the hard, white flesh,
called the cotyledon.
they expel the liquid wax with
conventional expeller press.
a long screw conveyor
feeds the seeds into the press,
then crushes them
against a shaft.
this forces out the liquid wax
that makes up
about half a seed's weight.
the mashed seed-solids, called
cake, are put to good use.
some are used for compost.
some will be processed
into exfoliates --
abrasives used
in face and body products
to remove dead skin cells.
meanwhile,
a second screw conveyor
moves the expelled liquid wax
into a holding container,
and from there, a pump pushes it
through a filter press.
this press consists
of several plates and frames,
each one covered
with a filter cloth.
as the liquid wax
passes through,
the cloth catches
the last remaining solids.
this buildup of seed particles
and other minute debris
is biodegradable waste.
to make exfoliates, machines
grind the cake into particles,
then vibrating sifters divide
the particles by size.
what's too big or small goes
back to the farm for compost.
the extracted liquid wax
isn't yet fully refined.
it's still cloudy and yellowish,
so workers
add natural powdered absorbents,
then filter them out.
this clarifies the jojoba oil
to its finished state.
the company lab runs extensive
quality tests on every batch.
technicians
analyze several criteria,
including color, odor,
and chemical composition,
ensuring the oil meets
strict product specifications.
as the jojoba oil
flows from storage tanks
into shipping drums,
it passes through a final
ultra-sensitive cartridge filter
that removes
any minute particles
that might have slipped
through the filter press.
this processor
makes two varieties
of refined jojoba oil --
one golden,
with a mild, nutty aroma,
the other,
colorless and odorless.
the texture and consistency
are identical.
manufacturers
buy whichever variety
better suits their product.
narrator: string puppets,
also known as marionettes,
are an ancient form
of performance.
it's not known exactly
when or where
the first string puppets
made an appearance,
but it was
thousands of years ago.
today, they've still got
what it takes
to entertain audiences
worldwide.
[ circus music plays ]
digitized characters
may rule in the movies,
but onstage, there's no doubt
that string-animated ones
can still dazzle audiences.
a few movements
of the puppeteer's hands,
and some fantastical characters
are brought to life.
behind the scenes,
making these marionettes
is a major production.
each one is painstakingly
hand-crafted
in a process that takes weeks.
it all starts with an idea.
the puppet maker draws several
sketches of the character,
tweaking the features
until he's satisfied.
he then draws a full-scale
version of the marionette.
referring to
that scaled drawing,
he sculpts the head in clay,
building it into a wooden
framework known as the armature.
the clay is oil-based.
it doesn't dry out
as fast as the water-based kind,
so there's time to tweak
the sculpture and perfect it.
lines drawn for reference
make it easier to position
the nose, eyes, and mouth.
he defines the mouth
a little more
to give it
a petulant expression.
he smoothes
the top of the clay head,
using a looped sculpting tool
and his thumb.
with a caliper tool,
he constantly compares
the dimensions of the sketch
to the sculpture
to ensure the head won't end up
too large or too small.
once the lips and other features
have been smoothed out,
he prepares to make
a plaster mold of the sculpture.
he divides the head
into four sections,
and he outlines a trap door
at the back of the head
for easy access later.
he now inserts metal
shims along the dividing lines.
he's essentially building walls
to contain molding plaster.
the shims will also ensure
that the plaster, once hardened,
can be removed from the clay
sculpture in four intact pieces.
the plaster has been mixed to
the consistency of cake batter.
he scoops a generous amount
into a walled-in section
of the clay sculpture.
the plaster generates heat
as it hardens and sets.
it then cools
for about half an hour.
he removes
the shims that surround it.
he then uses those shims
to wall-in the next section.
he adds more plaster to build up
this part of the mold.
when all four sections
are complete,
he gently chisels them
at the seams to separate them.
he opens the mold
and removes the sculpture.
its image has been transferred
to the inside of the mold.
the sculpture
is no longer needed,
and he's ready to cast
the puppet head, using the mold.
for that, he uses
plastic-infused cloth squares,
softened by solvent.
he transfers the squares
to the mold sections
and layers them
papier-mâché style.
a release agent
applied to the mold
keeps the squares
from sticking to it
as they begin to adhere to
each other, and, in the process,
conform to the mold's
curves and crevices.
with squares now applied
to all four sections,
he puts the mold back together
and joins them at the seams.
after 10 hours,
it's time for the big reveal.
all those little squares are
now one solid marionette head.
the casting looks pretty rough
at this point,
so he covers the entire surface
with plastic wood.
what a difference
sanding the plastic wood makes.
he then paints the head
and cuts holes
for the eyes and mouth.
from the inside of the puppet
head, he attaches springs
to enable the mouth and eyes
to open and close.
over in the paint department,
with every stroke of the brush,
the puppet becomes
a more colorful character.
coming up next, the marionette
gets its moving parts,
and, of course,
they come with strings attached.
narrator: with
their string-operated limbs,
marionettes can imitate almost
every human or animal gesture.
the more joints and strings
the puppet has,
the wider the range of movement
and the more lifelike
the character becomes.
before the head
of the penguin puppet
can be attached to the body,
it just needs
a few more dramatic touches,
like curly fur.
yes, in the fantasy world
of puppetry,
anything is possible --
even fur on a penguin.
he traces the pattern on the
reverse side of the furry fabric
and cuts it out
from that side, too,
to prevent any snipping
of the fur on the front.
he stitches the darts together
to conform to the shape
of the penguin head.
this process must be repeated
for each fur-covered part.
he checks out the fit
and confirms that it achieves
the desired effect.
satisfied with the results,
he moves on to the eyelashes.
he traces the pattern onto
rubber and cuts the lashes out.
to accentuate the eyes,
the lashes are substantial.
he inserts a pair of lashes into
slits in each wooden eyeball.
from head to toe,
no detail is overlooked.
here, he glues rhinestones
to shoes
for some serious onstage bling.
he's now ready to build
the torso and limbs
of the marionette.
he traces the pattern of those
parts onto blocks of poplar wood
and then carefully cuts them out
with a band saw.
this particular part is a hand
for the penguin character.
the initial cut
is rough and needs fine-tuning,
so he chisels away at it
to remove excess wood
and define the shape.
he files it with a rasp
to round the profile.
it takes about five hours
to produce just one puppet hand.
the other parts receive
an equal amount of attention,
because with
ball-and-socket-style joints,
each limb must fit smoothly
to the next.
he attaches the two
limb segments with a hinge
made from
a kind of fiber board --
the same material
used to make steamer trunks.
he confirms that the joints will
move freely under the costume.
when the marionette body
has all its moving parts,
it's time
to stretch those limbs.
so they suit him up
and thread the strings
from the puppet
to the correct spot
on the controls.
the control bars
are shaped like an airplane.
they're known in the world of
puppetry as an airplane control.
the thread they use is fishing
line because of its strength.
they run nine strings or more,
depending on the complexity
of the marionette.
some of these strings are
for support, some for movement,
and others for effects like
nose growing or ear wiggling.
of course, the string placement
is crucial for proper movement.
with the strings strung
and well knotted,
the marionette body
comes to life.
and now the defining moment.
they attach the head
to the body.
it's a good fit.
this new character is almost
ready to meet his audience.
all that's left
is to run the strings
for controlling his head
and facial expressions.
and a little accessorizing.
they now manipulate the strings
to check his limb dexterity
and the movement of his mouth,
eyes, and eyebrows.
this marionette
is now ready for the stage.
between shows, he reclines.
after all,
you can't always be on.
incredibly,
it takes up to 1,500 hours
to create
each one of these marionettes.
after all that work,
they're ready to cue the talent.
[ up-tempo music plays ]
[ music stops ]
-- captions by vitac --
www.vitac.com
captions paid for by
discovery communications
if you have any comments
about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest
topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...