narrator: restaurant dinnerware
brings a lot to the table.
it's known for rugged good looks,
it holds up to heavy use
and repeated cleaning in commercial dishwashers,
and its design reflects the restaurant's theme
and adds presentation value to the food.
most people appreciate the effort
that goes into a fine meal,
but they may not give much thought to what it takes
to make the actual plate the food is served up on.
making ceramic dinnerware that's restaurant-quality
is an intensive process --
one that starts with a master die made of gypsum.
this worker then makes a production version
of the master.
to do this, he pours gypsum
into a wire-mesh frame above the master.
there's tubing attached to the mesh frame,
and he pumps air through it.
this causes the water in the gypsum
to bubble out and evaporate.
it dries and solidifies
into a mirror image of the master --
in this case, a platter shape.
the tubing inside this production die
will be used again later
to gently blow off the platter when formed,
releasing it from the die.
another worker adds the ceramic
ingredients to water.
they including a plasticizer, silica sand,
different clays, and minerals like alumina.
once the clay mix has been thoroughly blended,
they drain it onto a vibrating sieve
to screen out large mineral chunks and impurities.
the clay-based liquid flows through the screen
into a holding tank.
they pump it through this filter press.
it compresses fabric-covered plastic plates
to squeeze out moisture,
turning the clay liquid into putty-like slabs.
with this consistency, it can now be shaped.
a worker breaks up the slabs
and feeds the pieces to a pug mill.
the mill shapes the clay into a long cylinder,
and, in the process, it sucks out air
so dinnerware made from it will be less prone to cracking.
he slices the clay cylinder into small wads,
using a wire cutter.
each of these clay wads will be shaped into one plate.
they place each wad onto molds on a revolving platform.
the mold spins up to a metal tool,
which presses the clay into the
shape of the plate mold below.
the tool also forms the back
so the plate will sit evenly on a table.
a nozzle lubricates the metal tool between pressings.
a cutter at the side
trims the rims of the plates as they're formed.
unlike the platter die,
these molds don't have tubing inside to blow off the plates.
instead, the heat from the dryer
separates them from the molds.
once out of the molds, the plates spin on pedestals
past a sponge to smooth the edges.
to make coffee mugs,
the pug mill presses out a narrower cylinder,
and a knife at the exit point slices it into precise wads.
the wads fall into coffee-mug molds,
and a tool spins the clay up against the walls of the molds
to shape it into mugs.
a blade at the top trims the excess
from the lip of the mug.
they pass under a long sponge to smooth the rims.
and now for the handles.
they make them in two-part molds
and dry them under an infrared light.
the handles must have precisely
the same moisture content
as the mugs -- around 16%.
a worker dips the ends of each handle
in a clay-and-glue mixture and presses it to the mug.
the mugs go into a dryer,
and the moisture content drops to 4%.
next, they douse the mugs with glaze inside and out
and bake them in a super-hot kiln.
this will make the mugs chip-resistant
and will strengthen the bond between the handle and the mug.
they paint the dinnerware by hand, using a ceramic stain.
the stain will enable it to hold up
to repeated rigorous cleanings in restaurant dishwashers.
for a different look, they apply
decals to some dinnerware.
this artwork has been produced
using the same hard-wearing ceramic stain.
the plates then head into the oven,
and the heat fuses the decorative touches to them.
from a liquid clay mix
to tableware you can dine out on.
the process has taken about 24 hours.
it should serve you well.
narrator: air-brake tanks are part of powerful brake systems
on tractor trailers and buses.
when the driver depresses the brake pedal,
the tank releases the compressed air
to activate the brakes
so the big wheels slow down and stop turning.
the energy used to stop a big rig comes from air.
it's compressed and stored in the brake tanks
so there's always a ready supply.
they make air-brake tanks from industrial-grade steel
that's about as thick as a typical magazine.
a press forces the steel around a dome form
and shears the edges to produce the tank's end caps.
it also punches a hole in each cap for a fitting.
the cap's dome shape is critical.
it will allow it to withstand
the air pressure inside the tank.
the tank caps now ride a conveyor under sprayers
that wash away residual oil from the pressing process.
more steel sheeting feeds into another press.
it's twice as thick as the steel
used to make the end caps.
this press is punching and forming brackets
for attaching the air tank to the trailer undercarriage,
so these connecting parts have to be extra-strong.
it takes six punches
to shape the flat sheet of steel
into the curved brackets.
here's an example of the six formative stages.
machinery now flattens and cuts
bigger sheets of steel
for the tank body.
mechanized clamps grip the sheet along the edges
and position it under another punch press.
it perforates the steel where fittings are to be installed.
it also stamps the company name
and other manufacturing information onto it.
they feed the sheet to a roller
that curls it into the cylindrical tank shell.
the rolling is precise,
and the dimensions of the cylinder
don't need any adjusting.
the worker clamps it into a fixture.
a carriage moves a welding torch overhead
to join the ends and create an airtight seal.
a worker inspects the weld.
the next worker welds fittings
onto the holes punched into the tank shell earlier.
two of the fittings are for attaching valves
that control the flow of compressed air.
the third fitting will be used to connect a line
for draining water formed during air compression.
he reinforces the fittings with large collars
that help the connections
withstand any bumps on the road.
he places the brackets and end caps
in an automatic welder and activates it.
it fuses the bracket to the cap --
one for each of the air tank's end caps.
with both bracketed end caps
now installed on the cylindrical shell,
it's time to seal this air tank.
the tank turns on a welding lathe
as automated welders bond them to the shell.
the air-tank structure is now basically complete.
it's time to put it to the test.
after plugging the open fittings,
they pump highly compressed air
into the tank --
more than it would usually handle.
if it can take all the pressure,
it's deemed structurally sound.
they bring the pressure down a bit and check for leaks.
bubbles in the water around it
would indicate air is seeping out,
but in this case, there are only a few ripples
from the action of placing it in the water.
after a cleaning, the airtight tank
heads into a powder-coating station.
sprayers apply the powdered resin coating to the tanks.
the particles are positively charged,
and the tanks are negatively charged
for an instant attraction.
the black powder clings to the tanks
as they now travel through a gas-fired oven.
the heat melts and bonds the coating
to the surface of the air-brake tanks,
forming a tough skin that's rust-resistant.
after the tanks cool,
a worker inserts a long, thin paint gun
through one of the fittings
to spray a rustproof coating on the inside.
he then inserts plugs into all the fittings
to protect the threads from damage
until they're ready to make all the necessary connections.
it's taken about five hours to produce these air-brake tanks,
and it's now time to put on the brakes.
narrator: frosted cereal originated in america
in the 1950s,
and today, you'll find versions of it
on breakfast tables around the world.
it's one of the first things
some people reach for in the morning.
the sugary coating complements the flavor of the grains.
it's one way to awaken the taste buds.
this particular blend of frosted cereal
is a combination of wheat flakes, corn flakes,
and granola clusters.
half the flakes are frosted, and half aren't.
there's honey, rolled oats, and rice in the granola.
the mix of the ingredients means
there are still a few surprises
in the frosted-cereal box.
to make the corn flakes, they start with corn grits.
they measure out a specific amount
and release it into an industrial version
of a pressure cooker.
the operator locks the lid,
and the system pipes water and flavorings
directly into the cooker.
it rotates for an even distribution of heat
and an even cooking of the grains.
after about three hours,
the kernels have absorbed moisture and softened.
as the corn flows out of the cooker,
a screw-conveyor system moves it towards a dryer.
they cook a measured amount of whole-wheat kernels
in water and flavorings.
they only need an hour
in the rotating pressure cooker.
like the corn, the whole wheat
absorbs a significant amount of water during cooking.
the kernels are about 30% moisture
when they exit the cooker.
they now merge with the corn en route to the dryer.
the drying time will bring the moisture content
down to about 19%,
making the kernels the right consistency
to be transformed into flakes.
the grains now flow into a mill.
the mill has two big, heavy rollers,
similar to the kind used to pave roads.
the kernels fall between these rollers.
the rollers exert tons of pressure
to flatten each individual kernel into a flake.
in the process, the wheat flakes turn whiter
and the corn turn more yellow.
at this point, the flakes are still quite soft
and not really tasty.
a trip through a long toaster oven
will give it that crispy cereal consistency.
it's a high-temperature toasting
and reduces the moisture content
to 3%.
here, you can see the flakes before toasting...
and after.
the toasting not only makes the
corn and wheat flakes crispy --
it also enhances the color and flavor.
a ride on a conveyor cools them down.
along the way, they split into two different streams.
one stream of the mixed flakes
travel towards the sugar-coating station.
the other heads into a flavoring drum.
the drum revolves to gently toss the cereal
as a sprayer applies a granola kind of flavoring.
the other stream of wheat and corn flakes
enters the sugar-coating drum.
a sprayer disperses a sugar-and-water mixture
as the drum tosses the flakes.
then they travel through a dryer,
and this cures the frosting to the flakes.
the frosted and the flavored flakes
flow onto the same conveyor.
it bounces the flakes around to blend them together.
to boost the nutrition content,
they add honey-flavored granola.
the granola clusters flow onto a conveyor.
they'll merge with the frosted and flavored flakes.
the feeder pipe showers granola
onto the flakes.
this frosted cereal is now ready
for store shelves.
machinery dispenses specific amounts into a plastic sleeve,
and a mechanism heat-seals and severs it at both ends.
mechanical arms then pick up boxes, open them,
and deposit them on a conveyor.
push rods shove the bags of cereal into the boxes.
the "best before" date and other information
have been printed on the outside of the boxes.
nozzles apply glue to the ends,
and the boxes brush by a side barrier that closes them.
producing and packaging this frosted-cereal blend
has taken about five hours,
and if the breakfast crowd is hungry, it won't last long.
its time on the table could be short and sweet.
narrator: a fossil is a remnant
of prehistoric life
embedded in rock --
either the actual remains of an animal or plant
or an impression left by decayed remains.
most fossils are hundreds of millions of years old
and remind us that humans have been around
for a small part of the earth's existence.
fossils are made by nature
but collected and preserved by man
for display in museums, as well
as in private collections.
one of the world's richest fossil deposits
is located in the southwestern part of the state of wyoming.
50 million years ago, the area was a freshwater lake.
with climate changes, it gradually dried out,
leaving wildlife and flora
buried under layers of sediment.
over time, that sediment hardened into sheets of rock
containing fossils of those former life forms.
to find fossils in what were the shallower edges
of the prehistoric lake,
they drive thin blades about 4/10 of an inch deep
to loosen and separate sheets of rock.
in this part of the deposit,
the fossil is often split between two layers of rock,
which is why they call this particular dig area
"the split-fish quarry."
they repeat the process, excavating several layers.
they typically find fossils
of smaller herring-type fish, plants, and insects.
they carefully separate the large rock sheets
into smaller pieces so that it's easier
to transport their haul
from the quarry to the workshop.
this sedimentary rock is oil shale --
a substitute for conventional crude oil.
scratch the surface, and it smells, and it'll burn.
however, there's not enough actual oil in this deposit
to make extraction viable.
in the company's second quarry,
they blow away surface debris to
make it easier to spot fossils.
recovery is more difficult here
because this part of the deposit
was the deep center of the prehistoric lake.
wildlife was buried under far more sediment.
it takes a highly trained eye
and the low angle of morning sunlight
to see the slight shadow
which a fossil's ridges cast on the ground.
after outlining their find,
they use a saw with a diamond blade to cut around it.
they've removed the surrounding rock
to be able to slide their thin blades underneath...
...then gently extract their treasure.
this is a tricky procedure.
one wrong move, and the fossil shatters.
in the workshop, under five-times magnification
and using a variety of sharpened tools,
they carefully scrape away the surface
until the dark color of the fossil shows through.
to fully reveal a fossil this size
takes 30 to 40 hours of tedious and meticulous work.
as for the rock sheets from the split quarry,
they saw the fossils apart,
neatly framing each one within a rectangle.
layers flake off more easily from split-quarry rock
than from the harder rock of the other quarry.
once a fossil is completely exposed,
they seal and protect the surface
with a light coat of spray-on acrylic.
when exposing a fossil, it's critical
to keep sharpening the tools on a diamond file,
and, for visibility,
to repeatedly clean the work
surface with an eraser or brush.
how many layers of rock
have to be scratched off varies.
a fossil can be sitting right on the surface
or be buried a fraction of an inch or so beneath it.
this freshwater stingray, a rare find,
is about as intricate as a fossil gets.
this fellow took more than a month to prepare.
the detail of this large palm-leaf fossil is astounding.
you can actually see insect bites.
and as this leaf fossilized on the prehistoric lake bed,
so did the fish swimming around it,
producing an incredible stone snapshot
of life 50 million years ago.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...