>> narrator: long before the
plastic water bottle, there was
the hip flask, carried in a
pocket or strapped to the waist
or hip.
unlike a water bottle or earlier
canteen, the flask was used for
carrying a very different type
of thirst quencher -- several
ounces of hard liquor.
in the 18th century, it became
quite fashionable for well-to-do
europeans to carry elegant
flasks crafted from silver or
pewter.
today, flasks are typically
given as gifts, often engraved
with monograms or messages.
pewter is an ideal metal for
flask making because it's so
malleable.
they begin with a sheet of raw
pewter that's about 8/100"
thick.
with a guillotine cutter,
they slice a rectangular
starting piece called a blank.
they lay this blank onto a
copperplate, which has the flask
decorations on it in raised
form.
they feed the plate and blank
through a rolling press.
the compression stamps the
design into the malleable
pewter.
next, they place the imprinted
blank in a hydraulic press
outfitted with flask-shaped
forming dyes.
in a single strike, the press
shapes the blank into half a
flask.
they transfer it to a trim press
and clip off the excess pewter
around the perimeter.
they repeat the entire process
to produce the other half of the
flask, then solder the two parts
together.
they shape certain styles
manually.
a metalsmith heats the blank
with a gas torch to make the
pewter pliable, then wraps it
around a flask-shaped aluminum
block.
he hammers the adjoining edges
flat with a wooden mallet and
removes the block.
he fuses the edges by running a
line of pure tin solder down the
entire length of the joint.
meanwhile, on another press,
workers stamp out pewter-sheet
rectangles.
the metalsmith solders one
rectangle to the top of the
flask...
then cuts it to the right shape
with jeweler scissors.
next, he solders on a pewter
thread for the cap.
before fusing a pewter rectangle
to the bottom of the flask, he
stamps it with a maker's mark.
then he dabs the bottom of the
flask in flux, a chemical which
helps solder run smoothly
without globs.
then, just as he did with the
top, he solders on the bottom,
then contours it.
next, he puts a drill through
the cap thread and bores a hole
for filling and boring.
then, with an abrasive belt, he
grinds all the solder seams
flat, making them barely
noticeable.
workers now fill the finished
flask with water to check for
leaks and rinse out the
interior.
then they screw a pewter cap
onto each thread.
now a buffer takes over.
with a cloth wheel and pumice,
he removes any surface
imperfections, such as marks
left by the abrasive belt they
used earlier to grind down the
solder seams.
once the buffing's complete, the
flasks go through a dishwasher
cycle to clean off pumice
residue, then the finishing
touch.
a polisher shines up the pewter
until it has a reflective-mirror
finish.
they pour out whatever water's
still inside, emptying the flask
for its new vocation.
unlike the flasks used to
conceal liquor under clothing
back in the days of prohibition,
these modern-day pewter flasks
are meant to be seen and
treasured.
>> narrator: in many families, a
potato-salad recipe is a closely
guarded secret passed down
through the generations.
the family barbecue just
wouldn't be the same without it.
but when there's no time to
whip up a homemade batch,
there's always the factory-made
kind.
the appeal of potato salad knows
no boundaries.
people around the globe have
cooked up various versions of
this dish over the years.
there are so many different
recipes, they could fill an
entire cookbook.
but no matter how you toss it,
potato salad is always pure
comfort food.
of course, it's all about the
potato.
at this factory, they use
varieties with low water content
so the potato salad doesn't end
up soggy.
they arrive fresh from the field
and funnel out of the truck
trailer onto a conveyer for an
efficient and gentle unloading.
they head up to a washer to
clean off the dirt and remove
stones and pebbles.
the potatoes then bounce across
rollers covered with fine grit
abrasive.
this scrapes off the skins.
once peeled, a worker inspects
the white flesh for bruises or
other flaws.
they then tumble down a chute
towards the dicing machine.
it's equipped with these cutting
cylinders.
the blades are positioned
vertically on one, while they're
in a horizontal configuration
on another.
as they revolve in sync, they
carve the potatoes into cubes.
the blades can be adjusted to
cut the cubes larger or smaller,
depending on the recipe.
here they turn out medium chunks
for a creamy, american-style
potato salad.
workers roll trays full of
potato cubes into a big pressure
cooker to steam-cook for 6 to 10
minutes.
pressure cooking preserves the
nutrients and original flavor of
the potatoes.
while the potatoes are cooking,
they prepare the crunchy
component -- the celery.
the celery sticks first go for a
sudsy ride to scrub them clean.
along the way, an inspector
sorts out leaves and over-ripe
pieces.
they set cutting cylinders to
dice more finely than with the
potatoes.
out of the washer and thoroughly
rinsed, the celery sticks
tumble into the dicer, and it
chops them into small bits.
the minced celery exits into a
vibrating trough and tosses
about in a peroxide solution for
a second cleaning.
it's an extra precaution because
the celery won't be cooked, and
cooking kills bacteria.
after another rinse, the soaked
celery lands in a perforated
drum that fits into another
drum.
the colander rotates within the
drum to spin-dry the celery.
the next ingredient is the eggs.
they arrive at the factory
already hard-boiled and
de-shelled by the supplier, so
all that's left is the slicing
and dicing.
the egg whites cube nicely.
the yolk separates and crumbles
completely.
with so many yolk crumbs, their
favor will permeate the entire
potato salad.
they're now ready to combine
some of the ingredients.
a worker adds finely cut onion
to the egg, followed by diced
red pepper and then celery.
they weigh the mix with each new
ingredient to confirm that the
portions are right.
and now for the dressing.
they pump the ingredients out of
big storage tanks.
they include vegetable oil,
sugar, vinegar, and egg yolks.
whipped into a frothy
mayonnaise, the dressing flows
into an enormous, steel mixing
vat.
they add the
chopped-egg-and-vegetable
combination.
the now cooked potato cubes join
the other ingredients in the
vat.
blades spiral slowly for a
gentle mixing to ensure the
potato salad doesn't turn to
mush.
with the salad now ready,
suctioning devices set plastic
tubs on a track conveyer.
sensors signal their approach to
dispenser nozzles, and the tubs
stop right on cue for a fill-up
of creamy potato salad.
suctioning arms then flip the
lids onto the tubs, and once
sealed, they're on their way.
in just 40 minutes, they've
manufactured enough potato salad
at this factory to feed 500
people.
it should be quite a picnic.
>> narrator: a hydrogen fuel
cell runs vehicles and other
machines by directly converting
the chemical energy in hydrogen
gas into electrical power.
hydrogen is an abundant fuel
source.
it can be extracted from water,
enabling almost any country to
produce it domestically.
hydrogen-fuel-cell engines can
power vehicles and run backup
generators for large computer
operations.
they produce electrical power
without any emissions.
at the heart of the engine is a
stack of super-thin hydrogen
fuel cells.
the engine's blower blows in
air.
the fuel tank feeds in hydrogen
gas.
hydrogen and oxygen react and
create electricity.
each fuel cell is made of five
parts.
on each end, there's a
channelled plate made primarily
of carbon, a material which
conducts electricity.
hydrogen enters the cell through
the first plate, which channels
it through the next component --
a chemically treated paper which
conducts both gas and
electricity.
then the hydrogen enters this
membrane, where it splits into
protons and electrons.
the protons react with the
drawn-in oxygen, producing
water.
the water passes through another
paper to the cell's outer plate,
where a pump draws it away.
meanwhile, the electrons travel
to the end of the stack of fuel
cells to electrical wires.
after assembling the stack,
technicians compress the fuel
cells in a hydraulic press.
compression helps the current
flow smoothly from cell to cell.
it also presses the rubber
casket around each plate to the
adjacent one, sealing the stack
so that hydrogen can't leak out.
the technicians run a
quality-control test with
nitrogen gas to verify the seal.
before releasing the press, they
install high-strength steel rods
to bind the compressed cells
together.
for a stack this size, the rods
apply 3 1/3 tons of pressure.
with a stack now off the press,
they hook up an electric circuit
board which monitors the voltage
of each fuel cell.
after securing the connectors to
the stack with an adhesive
strip, it's just a matter of
connecting one to each fuel
cell...
and securing that connection
with a special type of epoxy
which contains silver to conduct
electricity.
next, they mount the circuit
board in a plastic cover to
protect it.
the fuel-cell stack is now fully
assembled and moves to the
factory's test area.
a technologist mounts it on a
test station and, simulating
installation in an engine, hooks
up a hydrogen line, an air line,
and a water line for cooling.
the testing machine runs a
three-hour, automated
performance test.
they mount the stack onto the
engine's structural frame, then
install the hydrogen
recirculation pump.
next, a water-recirculation
pump, which cools the fuel cell
by pumping in cool water.
then they mount the components,
which feed hydrogen stored at
high pressure in the fuel tank.
that pressure pushes the gas
through stainless-steel fuel
lines to the cell.
next, the fan that blows outside
air into the fuel cell to react
with the hydrogen.
this filter removes dust and
other contaminants from the air
the fan draws into the fuel
cell.
meanwhile, technicians have
assembled the computer that
controls the whole engine.
they now connect the wires from
the fan, the pumps, and the
other engine components to the
computer.
they hook up the fuel-cell
output wiring, the wires which
carry the current the fuel cell
creates, and sends it to
whatever vehicle or device the
engine is powering.
a tiny portion of the cell's
output runs the pumps and other
engine components.
now fully assembled, the engine
undergoes extensive performance
and safety testing.
once it passes every test,
technicians perform a final
visual inspection, then install
the sheet-metal cover.
the hydrogen-fuel-cell engine is
now ready to be shipped to the
customer and installed in the
machine it'll be powering.
whether running a vehicle like
this forklift or powering
computer servers, the only
by-product is waste heat and
water, which is why hydrogen
power is clean energy.
>> narrator: engineered wood
siding is essentially clapboard
reinvented.
with its rough grain, it
resembles natural wood.
each board contains wood strands
that are resin-bonded for
strength and durability.
they're also treated to resist
rot and termites.
engineered wood siding is a chip
off the old block -- or a lot of
chips, for that matter.
but how do they transform a
bunch of wood chips into a solid
piece of wood?
it starts with aspen and other
kinds of wood.
they transfer the logs to ponds
to maintain a consistent
moisture content and temperature
until production.
the logs land soaking-wet on a
conveyer.
grooved rollers feed them into a
debarker.
it shaves off both the tree
bark and the cambium -- the
soft, green layer beneath the
bark.
this exposes the white aspen
wood.
the logs land on the next
conveyer in a horizontal
configuration.
circular saws cut the logs into
smaller chunks, known as bolts.
the bolts head towards a machine
called the waferizer.
here's a look under the
waferizer hood.
a 10-ton steel disk holds 48
razor-sharp knives.
when the disc spins, the knives
slice the bolts into wafer-thin
chips, known as strands, in just
seconds.
the strands are the same length,
but slightly different widths.
most are roughly the size of a
business card.
they remain flat and don't curl
up because of the stability of
the aspen wood itself.
a conveyer delivers the wood
strands to big, steel bins, and
from here, they're fed at a
controlled rate to a dryer one
floor below.
heated by a furnace, the
cyllindrical dryer is superhot.
it rotates to tumble-dry the
aspen strands.
a blender coats the strands with
resin adhesive, wax for moisture
resistance, and a preservative
to ward off rot and termites.
they spray a release agent onto
the next conveyor to keep the
strands from sticking to it.
rotating disks orient the first
layer so the strands all land in
the same direction.
the next layer lands in a more
random configuration.
the third layer is again uniform
and parallel.
the result is a loosely
interwoven mat of wood.
layering the strands will
provide dimensional stability
in the finished siding boards.
a carriage now moves a large,
circular saw back and forth to
cut the mat into sections
approximately 16 feet in length.
the sections transfer to a
faster conveyor that pulls them
forward.
a steel carriage stretches a
sheet of heavy, industrial-grade
paper across the mat of wood
strands.
the paper has been coated with a
primer and saturated with a
durable adhesive that bonds with
the wood strands.
a multitiered press closes to
compact the mats and bake them.
the heat and residual moisture
activate the resins to turn wood
strands and paper into one solid
piece of engineered wood.
at the same time, the press
embosses the paper topping with
a deep, cedar-like grain.
the press opens, revealing the
cured and compacted composite
sheets.
the thickness has gone from
roughly 4" to just under 4/10"
a conveyer doubles as a scale to
confirm the content of each
sheet is exact.
saws trim the sides and slice
the sheets in two.
a pusher pushes then shoves the
smaller sheets forward, and
another saw trims the ends.
the trimmings don't go to waste.
they're ground up and used as
fuel for the dryer.
they now have a stack of 40
engineered wood sheets.
they're ready to be turned into
siding boards.
rollers push the sheets one at a
time into saws that slice them
to siding dimensions.
now separate strips, they exit
in a cluster and separate.
a paint gun coats the trimmed
edges with primer.
this seals any exposed wood from
the elements.
after a trip through the oven to
dry the primer, the engineered
siding boards head towards an
inspection station.
here, a worker scrutinizes each
board for blemishes or damage.
if he finds any, the board is
rejected.
the siding will be painted
postproduction to the
homeowner's preference, and once
installed, this engineered
wood product is sure to fit into
the neighborhood.
-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
if you have any comments about
the show, or if you'd like to
suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...