>> narrator: a wall tent is
shaped like a cabin.
it's tall enough and wide enough
to stand up in and walk around.
this type of tent is typically
used as a base camp on overnight
hunting trips.
unlike a smaller camping tent,
you usually need to transport
a wall tent by vehicle or
by horseback.
these premium wall tents are
made of sturdy canvas.
they have a zip-up screen over
the doorway and windows to keep
out insects.
they also have a vent hole in
the roof to accommodate a stove.
they can be made with
lightweight canvas for hunters
who go out in the woods on
horseback.
depending on the number of tent
orders to be filled, the
factory's expert fabric cutter
layers up to 10 sheets of canvas
on the cutting table.
following a pattern, he draws
guidelines...
then aligns them one at a time
on the track along which the
cutting knife rides.
he does the smaller cuts with
scissors.
once he's cut all the canvas
pieces for one tent, he hands
them off to a sewer.
she overlaps adjoining pieces
by less than an inch and, using
a double-needled sewing machine,
binds them with two parallel
lines of stitching.
this produces a durable,
weather-resistant seam.
next, the stove ventilation
system -- she sews what they
call the stovepipe shield to the
roof, then cuts away the canvas
underneath.
the shield is a fiberglass
fabric rectangle with a silicone
ring in the center, through
which you insert the stove's
exhaust pipe.
after neatly finishing the
edges...
she attaches a canvas flap that
zippers shut to close off the
stovepipe shield and rolls up
and ties to open it.
she also sews a canvas weather
flap that closes over the
tent's front door --
extra protection in bad
weather.
she sews a row of d-rings to
the edge of one flap...
then hooks to the corresponding
door flap.
they're both made of stainless
steel, which never rusts, even
with repeated exposure to
moisture.
these sturdy hooks and rings
keep the flap securely closed in
windy weather.
the cutter, meanwhile, traces
templates on heavy-duty
fiberglass screen, then cuts
the screens for the tent's
triangular rear window and
rectangular side window.
the sewer stitches webbing to
the window's perimeter.
webbing is a cotton seal which
keeps out rain, snow, and wind.
meanwhile, a different sewer
stitches the zipper to the door
screen.
she also sews 3-inch-wide
seatbelt material inside the
roof hem.
workers then apply pairs of
grommets roughly a yard apart
along this reinforced perimeter.
once you've pitched the tent,
you secure it by looping ropes
through these grommets and tying
them to stakes in the ground.
the tent floor is made of
vinyl.
workers join the floor pieces
using a radio-frequency welder.
it emits radio waves that melt
the material, fusing the
overlapping edges into a seam.
they construct the tent's
internal frame out of heavy-duty
galvanized steel tubing,
then connect the pieces with
stainless-steel couplers secured
with eyebolts.
as a quality-control check,
they assemble the tent before
shipping it out.
after laying out the couplers,
they insert the frame pieces to
form the roof, fit the
tent fabric over the roof
framework, and insert the legs
to prop up the structure.
then they pull down the walls,
the same way you pull a shirt
over a hanger.
after tying back the flaps,
they lay down the floor, which
simply snaps into place.
if you're two people, the
entire setup takes about
10 minutes.
then it's just a matter of
installing the wood- or
coal-burning stove,
cooking up a hearty meal, and
getting a good night's sleep.
>> narrator: long-stemmed with
an elaborately carved stone
bowl, this is a native
north-american pipe.
historically, it was reserved
for special occasions such as
the signing of peace treaties.
that's why european settlers
called it the peace pipe.
legend has it that the mystical
buffalo calf woman gave native
people the first sacred pipe.
it is believed to have spiritual
powers.
the wisps of smoke from the
stone bowl are seen as prayers
rising to the creator.
the pipemaker starts with wood
like ash or sumac.
these species are soft at the
core, so they can be easily
hollowed out with the red-hot
tip of a thick coat hanger.
he plunges the smoking hot wire
into the soft core of the wood,
and it quickly burns through
it, creating a passageway
through which tobacco smoke can
be drawn.
now, with a planer, he shaves
off the tree bark and shapes
the outside of the wood to
create a smooth, slim stem.
he carves angled swirls into
the wood with a rasp, a long
tool studded with numerous sharp
teeth.
he whittles one end of the stem
to transform it into a fitting
for attaching the pipe bowl.
he now confirms the diameter is
right by inserting the fitting
into a template.
next, sanding between the swirls
smoothes away gouges left by the
rasp.
he files a notch into the stem
just below the swirls.
then it's over to the beadwork
artist.
she wraps fringed leather around
the notch and places a
brightly colored accent piece
on top.
she strings glass beads around
the leather-wrapped notch,
working with a pattern and color
scheme in mind.
centuries ago, natives obtained
beads through trade with
european settlers and threaded
them onto pieces of animal
sinew.
their needle was a thin piece of
bone.
the colors of the beads can
really make a statement.
a string of red might signify
vibrancy and a long life, while
a mix of colors could represent
a spiritual burst of energy.
the pipe stem is now complete
and ready for the stone bowl.
for that, they mine red clay
rock called pipestone.
natives have used it for sacred
pipes for centuries.
pipestone is soft, and this
means it's easy to carve.
it's also smooth and takes a
high polish.
he splashes water onto a chunk
to make any flaws more apparent
as he evaluates it for carving.
his selection made, he now
begins to trace, following a
basic template of a pipe bowl.
he saws through the stone along
the penciled lines using a
hacksaw.
the rock is fairly easy to cut.
it's essentially compressed
clay.
he rounds the angular edges
using a rasp file.
now nicely contoured, the
stone is really starting to
look like a pipe bowl.
with a series of finer tools,
he flattens one end and then
sculpts the shape of an eagle
head onto it.
he wields a rotary tool with a
fine bit to carve eyes and
feathers.
traditionally, natives use
sharp flint or bone to engrave
details.
power tools get the job done
faster.
he now drills into the stone to
hollow out the shank and the
actual tobacco bowl.
for early natives, this job was
very laborious.
they gouged out the stone with
an arrowhead attached to a
stick.
he rinses the eagle pipe bowl
and then sands it while wet for
a smoother finish than dry
sanding.
he aims a torch at it to heat
the stone.
once hot, it readily absorbs
beeswax as he rubs it into the
pores.
beeswax gives the pipestone
bowl a satin sheen.
after a dip in cool water to
solidify the wax, he scratches
away some of it along the detail
work, including the eyes and
feathers.
this adds definition and
contrast, and after a bit of
fine-tuning, the wooden pipe
stem fits snuggly into the stone
shank.
he peers down the pipe to
confirm that the stem is
perfectly aligned with the bowl.
the sacred pipe is now ready
for any special occasion.
they've used a combination of
traditional techniques and
modern power tools to produce
this pipe, reconciling old and
new in the quest for peace.
>> narrator: shredded wheat is a
breakfast cereal made of 100%
whole wheat, shredded into a
straw-like consistency, cooked,
and shape under to a rectangle.
it was invented by an american
entrepreneur in 1893 after he
met a man who was eating boiled
wheat with cream to alleviate
digestive symptoms.
they may look like tiny bales of
hay, but they're actually a
tasty and nutritious breakfast
or snack.
shredded wheat was the first
mass-produced, ready-to-eat
cereal, invented at a time when
people typically ate a cooked
breakfast.
it all begins with whole grain
wheat.
the raw kernels are hard as
rock, so to soften them up, the
factory cooks them
simultaneously in water and with
steam for about 30 minutes.
as the wheat exits the cooker,
its moisture content is about
50%.
excess water drains away
through holes in the conveyer
belt.
the wheat then travels through
a dryer.
inside, nozzles blast the soggy
kernels with hot air.
by the time the wheat exits
about 10 minutes later, the
cooked kernels are dried.
they drop onto a conveyer belt
which transports them to the
operation that puts the shredded
in shredded wheat.
the wheat goes into several
fill tubes.
each fill tube drops kernels in
between two rollers that apply
pressure, shredding the kernels
into delicate strands.
the strands drop onto the
conveyer belt below, forming a
fairly even layer.
each pair of shredding rollers
deposits another layer of
strands on top of the previous
one, until there's a specific
number of stacked layers.
the company won't reveal how
many, nor will it let any camera
photograph the next machine --
a especially designed cutter
that divides the sheet of
layered wheat strands into
rectangular biscuits.
the sheet of shredded wheat
biscuits now travels through a
tunnel oven for approximately
10 minutes.
the specifics of what goes on
inside this oven are top secret.
all the company will reveal is
that there are two cycles,
baking and toasting.
as you can see in this
before-and-after comparison, the
bake cycle makes the biscuits
crisp, and the toast cycle
lightly browns them.
the next machine compresses the
sheets with a belt, which
breaks apart the individual
biscuits.
shredded wheat comes in two
varieties -- plain and frosted.
at this point, the plain ones
would be ready to proceed to
packaging.
however, this batch is
designated for frosting,
so the conveyer moves them
along to the coating station.
to make the frosting, they
blend and heat sugar, water, and
other ingredients.
overhead nozzles spray it onto
the passing biscuits.
the frosting takes about a
minute to dry and set.
here's what the shredded wheat
biscuits look like before
they're frosted and after.
on the packaging line, an
automated machine forms a bag
out of a continuous sheet of
plastic film, fills it with a
weighed-out portion of shredded
wheat, then seals the bag and
cuts it free.
the next station inserts the
bag into a cardboard cereal
box, printing the "best before"
date on the top flap.
the box not only shows
consumers a photo of the
contents, it also lists the
cereal's nutritional benefits --
that it's high in fiber,
low in fat and sodium, and
contains zero cholesterol and
trans fat.
>> narrator: cannons are back
on the battlefield, as history
buffs re-enact scenes from the
american civil war.
the fighting isn't real, but
these replica cannons aren't
fake.
they can do everything the
originals could do.
the attention to detail adds
authenticity to re-enactments.
on the front lines of any
civil war re-enactment, you'll
find the big guns, the cannons,
built to various scales with
all the original details,
these replicas have real
firepower.
for safety reasons, they don't
load actual cannonballs into
the muzzles, just black powder.
it's traditionally been used to
propel cannonballs, but on
its own, it still makes firing
a cannon a real blast.
production starts with wooden
molding boxes that have a cannon
shape inside.
there's a top half and a bottom
one.
together, they're known as the
pattern.
they'll fill each box with lake
sand that's been laced with
bonding chemicals.
the sand is soft and warm at
this point.
they pack it down and level it
off.
as the sand cools, the bonding
agents cause the sand to
solidify.
this sand mold will be used for
casting the actual cannon.
while they complete the other
half, they brush an
alcohol-based wash into all the
crevices of the sand mold.
but they don't just leave it to
dry.
instead, they ignite it.
the fire burns off the alcohol,
leaving a protective skin on
the mold, one that will prevent
seepage of the casting
material into the sand.
a worker then applies glue to
the border of the cannon mold.
the other half of the mold has
by now taken shape, and they
apply the same alcohol-based
treatment to it.
using a crane, the team
carefully aligns the two sand
molds.
the glue cures, and the mold is
ready to receive the casting
material -- iron.
they pour flaming, molten iron
into a large ladle.
then, suited up for protection,
they transfer the fiery liquid
to the sand mold and pour it
inside.
the iron cools in the mold for
about six hours.
the flames die down, and the
liquid metal solidifies.
then it's into the shot-blast
chamber, so named because
there's steel shot inside.
once the door is closed, the
tiny pellets bombard the sand
mold and break it up.
a vacuum sucks the sand and
steel shot out of the chamber,
leaving the solid cast iron
cannon.
a worker slices off unwanted
gating, which was formed as the
iron flowed into the mold.
one section served as a
reservoir to compensate for
shrinkage as the iron
solidified.
he removes that, too.
he then grinds the casting seam
until smooth.
at the finishing factory, a
lubricating mix of water and oil
flows from a drill bit as it
bores into the center of the
solid cannon casting.
the operator switches bits
twice for a gradual widening of
the cavity, taking it to precise
dimensions.
here's a look down the cannon's
newly bored muzzle.
with the nose of the muzzle
now protected by plastic, he
pours an epoxy adhesive into the
barrel.
he then inserts a steel liner.
the liner is a modification to
the original design --
a modern safeguard that will
enable the cannon to better
withstand the pressure of
ignition.
the cannon turns on a lathe, and
this action drives the steel
liner completely down the
barrel.
it also spreads the epoxy evenly
for a good seal.
a carbide bit moves down the
spinning cannon, to taper the
exterior.
he grinds the area between the
trunnions, which are
cylindrical protrusions used for
mounting the cannon to the
carriage.
he stamps the maker's mark into
the metal and then sprays
solvent-based primer onto the
entire cannon...
followed by three coats of
flat, black paint.
from start to finish, it's
taken about eight days to
produce this full-scale replica
of a revolutionary war cannon.
it's now ready for a little
historical re-enacting.
it's sure to be a hit with the
troops.
if you have any comments
about the show or if
you'd like to suggest topics for
future shows, drop us a line
at...