-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: a taser device fires bursts of electricity
to deliver a high-voltage, low-amp shock
that temporarily disables the subject.
invented in 1969 by
an american aerospace scientist,
the taser has become a weapon of choice
for police forces around the world.
today, when an officer reaches for his or her gun,
it's often one without bullets.
from a cartridge on the front,
the taser fires electrified darts,
which, on impact, cause muscle contractions
in the target's subject.
the subject is immobilized
but usually recovers in a few minutes.
this metal capsule contains
the propellant, pressurized gas.
a robotic arm inserts the capsule in a plastic chamber.
the next robot places a part, called the primer disc,
on the capsule.
it contains chemicals to generate a mini explosion
that will drive pins into the capsule,
releasing the gas.
another robot adds a protective screen.
that's the primer disc on the left
and the screen on the right.
they punch out a round piece of foam,
and the robot thrusts it into the chamber and tamps it down.
after welding it in place with ultrasonic vibrations,
a robot flips the unit up and into a second plastic chamber.
the placement leaves just enough space
between the inner and outer chambers
for wire bundles to be inserted later.
a robot then tucks the assembly
into the plastic cartridge.
it has slots for other components,
like insulated copper-wire bundles.
a machine winds the wire in a tight figure-eight formation.
this wire will electrify the darts as they're deployed,
and the figure-eight winding
reduces the possibility of tangling.
a worker places two bundles in the designated spaces
in the cartridge.
he tops each bundle with a piece
of strong polyester film.
it keeps the wire pack from spring apart
as he slides it off the fork and
presses it into the cartridge.
he's now ready for the barbed taser darts.
he threads the end of each wire
bundle through one and knots it.
he installs the darts in the cartridge,
using a special tool to seat them correctly.
he selects plastic wedges -- one for each wire --
and wraps the other end of the wires around it.
he attaches electrodes
to facilitate the flow of electricity
to the cartridge.
the next part is called the blast door.
it will blast apart and break in two
as the taser darts are deployed.
the robot snaps it in place on top of the cartridge.
the door is color-coded
to signify the range of the dart probes.
yellow indicates five yards.
with the compressed-air cartridge complete,
they now focus on the taser's deployment mechanisms.
a technician installs a laser system
and two l.e.d. lights in the plastic casing.
the laser is an aide for aiming the electrified darts,
and the lights will illuminate the target.
he adjusts the laser's aim
to sync it with one of the darts,
using a bull's-eye target as an alignment aide.
next, they immerse the high-voltage board
in epoxy resin and pump more directly into it.
this board is in the part of the taser gun
that generates electrical pulses
when the gun is in stun mode.
once cured,
the epoxy encapsulates this unit
to insulate the components.
the technician inserts the high-voltage board
in the gun casing.
along with the controller board --
the brains of the taser --
he also installs an information display board
and makes the necessary connections.
he plugs the assembly into a power source
and tests the laser and l.e.d. lights.
he snaps on the trigger
and confirms that it makes contact
with the plunger on the control board.
he joins the other half of the taser casing
to the one with all the working parts.
then, an ultrasonic welder fuses the casing parts
at the tongue and groove seams.
protecting the outer casing with a sheet of plastic,
the technician welds a safety switch to the trigger.
this critical part will prevent
accidental deployment.
in a test chamber now,
they activate the taser without the air cartridge.
without the cartridge and its projectile darts,
the taser works as a handheld stun gun
to zap the target directly.
once it meets the tester's approval,
this taser is ready for the police beat.
a consumer model is also approved
for use in some jurisdictions.
like the police version,
it should deliver a shocking performance.
narrator: soup is a liquid food
that is as old as cooking itself.
its appeal is quite literally biblical
because in the old testament,
a son trades his inheritance for a pot of lentil soup.
of course, today,
one doesn't have to sacrifice it all for soup
because it's usually readily available in cans.
with the invention of canning in the early 19th century,
soup soon became available on demand.
on the home front, this caused quite a stir.
no need for a long simmer.
just open the can, reheat, and soup's on.
to manufacture lentil soup, they make a hearty soup base.
they load measured amounts into a heated mixer,
beginning with purée garlic.
the mixer's walls are steam-jacketed
so the mix will cook evenly
with no scorching on the bottom.
the next ingredient is olive oil.
they activate the steam heat,
and the garlic begins to sizzle.
they add chopped onion.
the mixing blades gently toss the ingredients as they sauté.
they blend in diced celery and cook until translucent.
the next round of ingredients takes the flavor up a notch.
they include chopped carrots, sea salt, and fragrant spices.
balsamic vinegar adds a sweet tartness
to this lentil-soup base.
they're now ready to liquify the ingredients.
they open the tap, and filtered water spills in.
as the soup begins to simmer,
they add crushed and diced tomatoes.
the final ingredient
for this robust lentil-soup base
is spinach.
mixing it makes for a colorful swirl,
and, as the ingredients cook,
they become increasingly aromatic.
meanwhile, raw, peeled potatoes
ride a steep and slatted conveyor upward.
the slats keep the potatoes from rolling back
as they make the climb up to a hopper.
from the hopper, the potatoes slide down a chute
and into a revolving drum with cross-cutting blades.
the blades cut the spuds into small cubes and spit them out.
after a trip past a metal detector,
the potato cubes land in a bin.
in small-cube form, they'll cook faster later.
next, lentils, hard and dried,
surge in a steady stream onto a revolving round table.
the table has openings that lead
to little chutes with doors.
they open to funnel the lentils
into cans
moving on a conveyor below.
this ensures that a specific amount is fed into the cans.
partially cooked green beans and the raw potato cubes
now flow onto a second revolving table.
the cans with the lentils have now moved into position below.
the veggies fall through the holes and into the cans.
the cans, with mostly uncooked ingredients,
now head towards the piston filler.
it pipes the steaming hot vegetable-soup base
directly from the kettle mixer into the cans,
filling them to the brim.
immersed in the hot liquid,
the lentils, potatoes, and green beans
at the base of the can cook a little and soften up.
sensors detect the approach of the cans and cue the lids.
the lids drop one by one onto the cans below.
a device then interlocks the rims of the cans
and the lids for a hermetic seal.
the cans move into another lane
and travel past an x-ray machine.
it scans the soup inside for metal contaminants
like stray bolts or screws.
if the images are clear,
the cans of soup move on to a giant pressure cooker.
here, the contents cook under pressure for about a half hour.
pressure-cooking simulates the effect of a long simmer
in a fraction of the time.
the soup then cools for 10 minutes.
it is now thoroughly cooked and preserved.
now on their sides with glue applied,
the cans of lentil soup roll over labels,
and the labels adhere.
they produce more than 15,000 cans of lentil soup an hour
at this factory.
that's 105,000 cans in one shift.
it's enough to feed a small city.
narrator: the jaw harp and the mouth bow
are among the earliest musical instruments.
a chinese drawing from the 4th century b.c.
is believed to be the first record of a musician
playing a jaw harp,
and cave paintings in southern france
from 15,000 b.c.
depict someone playing a mouth bow.
the mouth bow is a stick of wood
with a single string the musician plucks or strums,
while altering the vibration-generated sound
by mouth.
the jaw harp is a metal instrument.
the musician plucks its flexible tongue
to produce a twanging sound, which he then modulates
with mouth positions and breathing.
this craftsman makes the jaw harp's frame
out of 1/10 of an inch thick square steel rod.
he measures and marks the
required length and bend points.
he cuts the length with a standard hacksaw...
clamps the rod in a vice...
then slips metal pipes over the ends
to prevent them from twisting as he bends them
to form the arms of the frame.
he aligns the arms,
leaving just enough space between them
to allow the tongue to vibrate without obstruction.
for the instrument to produce quality sound,
the arms must be perfectly parallel to each other --
their edges in mirror image.
he marks the tongue's position in between the arms
and files down the metal within the markings.
this creates a notch in which the tongue will sit.
the tongue is made of spring steel --
a type of steel, which when bent,
resumes its original shape.
before attaching it,
he saws a tiny undercut in each side of the notch.
then he inserts the tongue and hammers the undercut sides
to compress them over the tongue
and lock it into position.
he heats the tip of the tongue with a propane torch.
once the metal softens enough to bend,
he angles the tip to form what's called the trigger.
then he heats the end of the trigger
and bends it into a loop.
this is what the musician's finger strikes
to make the tongue vibrate.
finally, he files the tongue's edges sharp --
a last detail to improve the instrument's sound quality.
to make a mouth bow,
his first step is to find a stick
that's between roughly 1 1/2 to 6 1/2 feet long,
not too heavy,
and ideally with a "t" shape at the end.
in his workshop, he clamps it in a vice,
trims it to the required length,
and, using a rasp, files the knots flat.
he files the top end until it's
about 2/10 of an inch thick.
this forms the mouthpiece,
which you hold gently to your lips
while plucking the string.
the string vibrates the mouthpiece,
producing sounds that you alter
by changing the shape of your mouth.
he drills a hole toward the base
of the mouthpiece
for the string, then, just below that,
files a notch for the bridge that supports the string.
just below the notch, he hammers
in a steel nail called the pin.
he drills a 2/10 of an inch hole
at the "t"-shaped end of the stick.
this is where he'll insert the tuning peg,
which he constructs out of a wood knob and dow.
he makes the string from a length of piano wire.
he forms a loop at one end
by twisting it with pliers around an awl.
he feeds this end through the hole
at the base of the mouthpiece...
...and hooks the loop onto the pin.
then he threads the other end of the string
through a hole in the shaft at the tuning peg
at the bottom of the stick.
he turns the peg to tighten the string.
just as on a violin or a guitar,
the tauter the string,
the higher the note it produces.
[ creaking ]
[ creaking continues ]
the final step is to position the bridge --
a hardwood dow --
in its notch, under the tense string.
by elevating the top of the string,
the bridge prevents it from cutting into the stick.
the mouth bow and the jaw harp are played alone
or alongside other instruments
in the folk music of numerous cultures around the world.
narrator: the earliest known reference to a diving board
appears in a hieroglyphic from 480 b.c.
it depicts a man plunging headfirst into a pool of water
from a platform.
today, diving boards are standard equipment
at neighborhood and backyard swimming pools.
one end of the diving board is fixed
to give the other end the bounce required
for a big-splash cannonball or a graceful swan dive.
to make the diving-board shell,
workers load a sheet of acrylic
into a clamping machine
that transports it into an oven.
the oven heats the sheet for about 30 seconds to soften it.
then, a forming machine applies suction
to draw the softened acrylic tightly over a mold
in the shape of two diving boards.
fans blow cool air,
hardening the acrylic to this shape within seconds.
they extract the molded acrylic,
then saw it in half to separate
the two diving-board shells.
they coat the shell surface in a resin and fiberglass mixture.
this tool is called a chopper gun
because it chops and shreds the fiberglass string,
then shoots it out drenched in resin.
they roll it to compress the
fibers and push out air pockets.
any trapped air would create
a weak spot in the diving board.
after letting the resin dry and harden for 30 minutes,
they begin filling the shell cavity
with 2/10 of an inch thick fiberglass mat.
they drench the mat in resin, rolling it over
to ensure every fraction of an inch gets well-saturated.
then they lay down another fiberglass mat,
this one a bit thinner
and saturated with the existing resin.
the diving board's core is made of laminated wood,
which is several thin layers of wood glued together.
laminated wood is actually stronger
than a solid piece of wood.
after rounding the top edge,
they lay two wood-laminate cores
over the
resin-saturated fiberglass mats.
they position clamps to hold the cores in place.
but before tightening, they insert metal spacers
to ensure the cores are correctly positioned
within the shell.
once the positioning is perfect,
they tighten the clamps,
then let the resin cure at room temperature
for a half hour or so.
then the clamps come off, and workers cover the cores
with an even thicker fiberglass
mat impregnated with resin.
this is the bottom of the diving board.
they make sure the mat is centered...
then manually form it to the shape of the board,
pushing out the air pockets as they go.
they spray on some decorative paint,
then put the board in an oven for 24 hours to cure.
when it comes out,
they use a diamond blade
to saw off the excess fiberglass
around the edge.
then they do a final trimming
to make the edge neat and smooth.
they mask the sides with tape, leaving only the top exposed.
this is where they'll now apply
a rough texture --
a safe, non-slip surface.
first, they roll on a thin coat of resin.
onto that, they sprinkle a layer
of silica sand,
making sure to cover the surface
thoroughly and evenly.
the sand sticks to the resin,
which sets and cures in about 15 minutes.
after sweeping off the excess sand that didn't adhere,
they roll on a coat of laminating resin,
which bonds to the sand,
giving the surface a clean, finished look.
they pull off the tape
and apply the
manufacture's decal to the side.
the diving board is now all set
to be installed
on a stand at the edge of the deep end
to await anyone ready to take the plunge.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...