-- captions by vitac --  www.vitac.com
captions paid for by discovery communications
narrator: the garden fork was once a very prized possession --
so coveted, it was often the object of theft.
that was centuries ago,
when a family's very survival
depended on the crops they grew.
today, of course,
food is mass produced and sold in supermarkets.
but the garden fork still rules
in the backyard garden.
there are many versions of the trusty garden fork.
use one to work the garden, and you'll reap the benefits.
at this factory,
they've been forging garden forks
from a solid-steel slab for over two centuries.
using a 660-ton punch press, they cut two basic fork shapes
from this hot and malleable slab.
the tines or prongs for this particular kind of fork
are shorter than most because these are border forks
used for turning soil rather than digging deep.
with the basic shape now established,
it's back into the furnace to re-soften the stem.
a worker repeatedly feeds it to rollers
to thin and widen it substantially.
he strikes the stem with another punch press.
this one hit trims it
while cutting holes for attaching the wood shaft.
the trimmings will be remelted and recycled into new forks.
the next press slams the steel stem
into a cylindrical die
to force it into the basic shape
of a socket.
he slides the socket onto a coned form
and strikes it repeatedly to refine the socket shape.
this sizes it for a wooden shaft.
they take an entirely different approach
when making digging forks
because of their longer curved tines.
after forging a kind of spider shape,
a worker bends a prong around
a post to orient it for shaping.
this two-person team works in tandem.
one fires the spider and bends the prongs.
the other worker inserts the prong in the grooves
of two revolving dies.
this rolls the tine within the confines of the grooves
to stretch it long and thin.
with two tines now shaped,
his partner bends them out of the way
so he can work on the third tine.
rolling takes 18 months of training to perfect.
if the tine isn't precisely aligned with the grooves,
the equipment could seize and throw the worker backwards.
not only could he be injured,
but the fork and the dies would
most certainly be wrecked.
with a fourth tine now stretched
long and thin like the rest,
the other member of the team twists all four tines
around the post again,
this time to bend them all in the same general direction.
after about 10 minutes of work,
they have the rough shape of a digging fork.
they then form the socket and crop the tines.
fired to a supple state again,
a worker drives tooling between the tines
to straighten them and even the gaps between them.
he rests the fork socket against
a steel slope and lowers a ram.
it slams into the tines to push
the socket against the slope
and bend it upward --
a more effective angle for digging.
he inserts the tines in a press
one at a time.
the press closes around each tine to taper the corners.
a ram now pounds the base of the tines
against a swooped anvil to give it a gentle curve.
he plunges the hot fork into cool water,
and the shock hardens the steel.
the next worker grinds off any rough bits from the sides
and sharpens the edges.
he narrows the tips to a point,
and this will enable the fork to pierce solid earth.
a worker repairs any irregularities with his hammer.
here you can see the difference this makes.
the prongs on the left are out of alignment.
the ones on the right have been fixed.
they apply an electrostatic charge
onto the forks to attract a green powder spray.
once cured, it forms a colorful
skin that resists corrosion.
now out of the curing oven,
a worker clamps the ends to lock the fork in place
while he inserts the ash wood shaft into the socket.
he secures it with rivets.
using a belt sander,
he blends the wood to the metal
in a process known as linishing.
he also sands the rivets
to make them flush to the surface of the metal.
the bottom fork is the one that has been linished.
he dips the wood shaft and handle in varnish,
giving it a glossy stain that enhances the grain.
this garden fork is now done.
it won't look shiny and new for long,
because things are sure to get dirty very soon.
narrator: toffee is a type of candy traditionally made
of caramelized sugar or molasses and butter.
there are many different varieties --
soft and chewy or hard and brittle.
english toffee,
which is actually an american style of toffee,
is very buttery
and typically has a topping of chopped nuts.
this english toffee
is completely free of dairy ingredients
and is kosher certified, making it ideal
for toffee lovers with certain dietary restrictions.
the workers at this small american confectioner
make this special recipe entirely by hand
one small batch at a time.
they start by combining water and sugar.
they heat the mixture until the sugar dissolves.
then they add a formula so top-secret
they won't let us see it.
all they'll reveal is that it contains
a combination of vegetable oils
and shortening
which are non-dairy substitutes
for butter and beta carotene
to give the toffee that familiar golden color.
they add an emulsifier called lecithin
to stabilize all these ingredients.
as soon as the mixture reaches the boiling point,
they add salt.
this enhances the flavor
and helps produce a rapid boil
that continues for several hours
until the mixture hits
a top-secret target temperature.
by that point, most of the water
has evaporated,
producing sweet, thick, liquid toffee.
now they open a hot-water valve
that heats up a table,
then carefully pour the toffee onto the surface.
the heat keeps the toffee pliable
while they spread it out.
they spread it wider and wider
until the toffee sheet is evenly thick.
they don't actually measure.
they just eyeball it, so the thickness varies somewhat.
but that lack of uniformity
is part of the charm of handmade sweets.
they take a tool with multiple cutting wheels
spaced about two inches apart.
they run it over the toffee sheet in one direction,
then in the other.
then they shut off the hot-water valve
and open the cold-water one to cool the table surface
and harden what are now toffee squares.
within minutes, the squares are
hard enough to be broken apart.
next, the first of two ingredients
that will turn this into english toffee --
molten semi-sweet chocolate.
once this tempering machine
heats it to the right consistency,
a pump feeds it to the enrobing machine
that coats the toffee squares in two stages,
starting on the bottom.
the underside now coated,
the squares move on to a refrigerated belt.
the cold quickly hardens the chocolate.
then they move into the next station
which covers the top with chocolate.
as the now fully-coated squares
exit the enrobing machine,
the belt vibrates, shaking off the excess chocolate.
the squares move on to another refrigerated belt
and a worker manually sprinkles them
with the second ingredient
that makes this english toffee --
chopped pecans.
the squares travel through a cooling tunnel
for several minutes to set.
as they reach the end of the line,
excess nuts drop off and collect in a pan below,
ready for sprinkling onto new squares.
some english toffee recipes call
for almonds rather than pecans.
whichever variety of nut,
every recipe follows the same structure.
layering sweet and crunchy toffee,
smooth and creamy chocolate, and coarsely chopped nuts --
three different textures, tastes, and sensations
brought together in a single confection.
and just like other decadently delicious desserts,
english toffee is heaven
to anyone with a serious sweet tooth.
narrator: trying to decide on a paint color?
each card is a small sample of related shades,
allowing you to view the actual hues
without prying off the lids of paint cans.
with thousands of shades to choose from,
how do they get it all down on paper?
whether you're looking for a brilliant blue
or a marvelous mauve,
careful scrutiny of paint chip cards can help you get it right
before the paint hits the wall.
highly concentrated colorants stored in tanks
will be used to reproduce paint colors in lacquer
similar to the kind used in nail polish.
lacquer produces better results
on paper than actual paint.
they pipe the colorants to a dispenser.
at the same time,
a bucket containing lacquer heads toward it.
the dispenser has many tentacles
with nozzles at the end of each one
and each tentacle is connected to one of the colorant tanks.
a computerized mechanism grabs the nozzles
to dispense different colorants
following a specific paint-color formula.
the bucket sits on a scale
and the weight is constantly monitored by the computer
to confirm that exact amounts are being added.
a blender mixes the colorants in the lacquer.
the mixing speed and time have been preset
to avoid over or under mixing.
and now for the color test.
a technician pulls a bit of the lacquer-based paint
on a sheet of paper just under a steel bar.
using that bar, he spreads the color evenly across the paper.
then it's into a kind of moving convection oven
to dry the color.
the technician compares the color and gloss
to that of the standard.
he also does a computer analysis
and sends the formula back for tweaking when necessary.
once they perfect the hue and gloss,
production is ready to roll.
a worker pours the approved lacquer-based paints
into cylindrical tanks above the coating machine.
there are over two dozen of these tanks
because they'll be putting that many colors on paper
in one production run.
he connects plastic tubing to the tanks
to narrow the flow and aim it at the die block below.
he activates the machine
and adjusts the tension of the paper as it moves forward.
lacquer flows into a die,
coating the paper with an endless rainbow of color.
a bar overhead spreads the lacquer evenly
without actually touching the paper.
the striped paper then travels through an oven.
the solvents evaporate,
leaving a dried lacquer skin on the paper.
if regular paint had been used,
the paper would have absorbed it
and ended up wavy.
but with the lacquer paint, it remains flat.
rotary blades cut the coated paper
into sheets sized to fit printing machinery
down the line.
they land in a neat stack.
using a transparent template,
the next worker measures the width of each stripe.
he then confirms that the colors
are in the correct order
by checking each stripe against the approved proofs.
he checks the gloss with a glossmeter.
it aims light on an angle and registers the reflection
to confirm that the gloss is consistent.
with the okay from the tester,
the entire production run receives the go-ahead.
the press operator stacks them facedown
for loading into the printer.
a feeder serves up the striped sheets
to the printing line one at a time.
it's a 4-station printing press.
each cylinder is equipped
with an ink of a different color
to stand out against the various paint-card stripes.
they print the paint color names
and numbers on both sides.
they also apply varnish to the back of the sheets
so the paint chip cards won't stick to one another
when stacked.
named and numbered, the color stripes are now identifiable.
the sheets go under a guillotine blade
which slices them into paint chip cards.
powered by hydraulics and super sharp,
the blade cuts through hundreds
of paper sheets like butter.
they produce 3 1/2 million paint chip cards a day
at this factory.
with so many options,
the cards are stacked against a quick decision.
narrator: a bundt pan
is for baking a dense,
ring-shaped cake called a bundt.
it typically has a fluted or a swirl design.
it originated in europe hundreds of years ago
and quite possibly gets its name
from the german bundkuchen --
"kuchen" meaning "cake"
and "bund" meaning "a gathering of people."
bundt pans were originally ceramic,
which is fragile, or cast iron, which is heavy.
today's version is typically made of cast aluminum --
unbreakable and infinitely lighter.
it also has a nonstick coating.
at the factory, they begin the production process
by melting ingots of recycled aluminum.
the furnace heats the ingots to 1,300-degrees fahrenheit,
at which point, they liquify in about a minute.
from the melting furnace,
workers transfer the molten aluminum
to a holding furnace
which keeps it in a liquid state
until casting.
the casting process is entirely automated.
a ladle descends into the holding furnace
and scoops up just over two pounds of aluminum,
enough to make one bundt pan.
the ladle then pours the molten metal into a sleeve
which a high-speed ram immediately pushes
into a steel bundt-pan mold.
the pressure and speed combined
shoot the molten aluminum into every nook and cranny
of the mold cavity.
as the hot aluminum hits the cooler mold,
it solidifies in about 10 seconds,
then the two halves of the mold automatically separate
and a robotic arm extracts the cast pan.
between castings, a robot cleans the mold
with a blast of air, water, and lubricant.
this removes any aluminum residue,
leaving the mold surface pristine.
this is critical, because even
a tiny speck of dust left behind
would mar the next casting.
as each pan comes off the machine,
workers inspect it for any casting flaws.
when it comes time to produce a different style bundt pan,
like this one with six mini-cake forms,
they simply mount the corresponding mold
onto the casting machine.
as the machine fills the mold under pressure,
some aluminum oozes out between
the two halves of the mold.
now a worker cuts off that excess
with a single strike of a trim press.
the scrap pieces go back into the furnace to be remelted.
next, a computer-guided router working two pans at a time,
smoothes the rough edges.
then it refines the handle slots, finalizing the shape.
the aluminum surface must be pristine
for the nonstick coating to adhere properly,
so the pans now go through
an industrial washing machine --
one wash and three rinse cycles,
and then, before exiting, a drying cycle.
workers put the pans upside down
on fixtures
which travel down the exterior coasting line.
as the pan spins by, spray guns apply
a silicone-based decorative coating to the outside surface.
the pans then travel through an oven for 15 minutes
to cure the coating.
then the workers flip the pans right-side up
and place them on fixtures,
which spin them through another spray line.
this time, to coat the inside.
the interior coating
is a food-safe silicone-polyester material
designed to release the cake easily from the pan.
it's similar to a nonstick coating on a fry pan,
the difference being that the chemical composition
is designed to prevent sugar, rather than protein,
from sticking.
again, the pans go through an oven for 15 minutes
to cure the coating.
once the finished pans exit the oven,
workers inspect them thoroughly,
checking for any flaws in the coatings.
from a practical perspective, a bundt pan's ringed shape
has definite advantages over an ordinary baking pan.
the tube in the middle
funnels heat to the center of the cake batter,
helping it bake quicker and more thoroughly.
from a decorative perspective,
when you compare an ordinary pan
to an elegant bundt,
the latter certainly takes the cake.
if you have any comments about the show,
or if you'd like to suggest topics for future shows,
drop us a line at...